<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2022-01-07T14:02:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-15-18:31.html</id>
    <title>My conception of parts work</title>
    <updated>2021-11-15T18:43:05+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;My conception of parts work&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-11-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was recently talking to Kaj Sotala on discord about what I mean when I say "Self is a part", and I ended up writing the following set of theses about what I actually believe by tabooing the words "Self" and "part". I thought I'd capture that here rather than having to search discord for it in future. The following is a lightly edited version of my explanation on Discord.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Your emotional state can exhibit &lt;em&gt;stuck modes&lt;/em&gt;, which are essentially a coherent bundle of emotional reactions that it is useful to conceptualise as person-like due to feeling like a discrete entity. The ideal is to have no stuck modes, but this ideal is probably only theoretically achievable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most of your broader mental and emotional capabilities do not neatly fit into a discrete set of such stuck modes, but are a more flexibly adoptable and combineable set of underlying mental/emotional resources that you can use to construct &lt;em&gt;attitudes&lt;/em&gt; that are appropriate to the present context.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Many emotional problems correspond to stuck modes that are in some way unhappy, and that arose by essentially ossifying a particular set of responses from a past situation and being unable to grow past that point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A useful set of mental motions is to essentially identify a stuck mode corresponding to a problem and adopt the attitude that that you would have needed from someone else at the time to not get stuck in that mode.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For many stuck modes this attitude corresponds to a sort of boundless love and acceptance. This is particularly likely to be the case for stuck modes that arose in childhood or romantic relationships, because there the problem arose from a lack of love from an external source.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This does not exhaust the possibilities of things that a stuck mode might need.
Additionally, due to the way we treat some of our stuck modes, a stuck mode may experience sufficient animosity to the broader self (lower case s - I mean "you overall", not anything corresponding to the IFS Self) that makes it unacceptable to it that you are the one providing the support it needs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Untabooing now to explain the relationship: in this terminology, an exile is a "stuck mode", and "Self" is an attitude (or more likely a range of broadly similar attitudes), which aligns with "Self is not a part" if we want to consider "part" and "stuck mode" synonymous, but I often find it useful to construct temporary unstuck parts, which are essentially attitudes and not stuck modes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Examples of attitudes that I don't think are particularly Self-like and help sometimes: Something closer to a mediator part that's mostly just there to help integrate two stuck modes by acting as an inbetween and asking good questions until they realise that they feel in opposition and are basically on the same side. Something that is more like a mentor than a parent who basically goes "Oh yeah that sucks, shall we figure out what to do about it?" at the part until it's able to treat its state as a practical problem to be resolved rather than an existential crisis.
And all of these have certain Self-like qualities to them (they require kindness, acceptance, etc) but the love is not the primary function.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Constructing a temporary part that is coherent enough to have a conversation with feels like roughly the same skill as coming up with a fictional character for your writing (at least the way I do it), by essentially coalescing an attitude and adding details that feel right until it feels relatively coherent. This is more work than accessing a stuck mode, but it's not necessarily a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Conversely, I think stuck modes are often a bit fuzzy around the edges, and can essentially be dissolved (and indeed IFS often ends up resulting in a process of dissolving them - a healed exile has essentially been dissolved).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is that it's not so much that "Self" and "parts" in the IFS ontology are the same thing as that there is not a clean division between the two things, and there is not a single special state called Self that is fundamentally unlike the parts it's used to heal.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-15-18:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-23-14:36.html</id>
    <title>Social reality as a game</title>
    <updated>2021-11-23T22:44:47+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Social reality as a game&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-11-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We went out scrumping for drones earlier, and in the course of doing so I did something weird: I brought a mug of coffee with me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was weird not because I had coffee with me, that's normal, but because it was a normal ceramic mug that I was just wandering through the streets holding.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If it had been a paper cup that would have been fine, obviously. Similarly, a travel mug wouldn't have raised an eyebrow.
But a normal ceramic mug? That's weird.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why was I carrying a mug? Well, I wasn't going far - the drone tree was only about five minutes walk away - and I didn't have a travel mug, but I'd just made coffee and I wanted to drink my coffee. Sure, I might drop it, but the solution to that was to not drop it (I didn't drop it).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was a perfectly reasonable practical solution, but ceramic mugs are a home item not a travel item, so it was weird.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bernard Suits defines a game as "the voluntary attempt to overcome unecessary obstacles", and I think about that a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How voluntary does it have to be? &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Clearly it's still a game if you give in to social pressure to play it, right? The fact that your family will sulk at you if you don't play doesn't make Yahtzee suddenly not a game (admittedly I could argue that it's not a game for other reasons, but it's certainly a Suitsian game in the sense that you're attempting to overcome your desire to die of boredom and the whole thing seems very unecessary. Also there are dice).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But who determines what's necessary?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More properly, the above his portable definition. He actually defines a game as:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To play a game is to attempt to achieve a specific state of affairs [prelusory goal], using only means permitted by rules [lusory means], where the rules prohibit use of more efficient in favour of less efficient means [constitutive rules], and where the rules are accepted just because they make possible such activity [lusory attitude].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He offers the example of mountain climbing: Your prelusory goal is to get to the top of the mountain, but the lusory means are that you have to climb it. If you could just take a helicopter up, you would not be playing the "game" of mountain climbing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's what I wonder: How much of our behaviour is governed by things that are, effectively, constitutive rules of a social game? I was certainly refusing to follow voluntarily adopted rules that prohibited me from using the more efficient means that I was currently employing. Those rules are, in some sense, accepted just because they make possible the activity of society.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In carrying a ceramic mug around with me outside was I, in small part, refusing to play a game in which everyone is implicitly participating in all the time?
Maybe, but at least I got to drink my coffee.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We didn't manage to scrump any drones, incidentally.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-23-14:36.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-12-14-12:27.html</id>
    <title>The landscape of</title>
    <updated>2021-12-14T12:46:31+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The landscape of&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-12-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the features of &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/labelling-feelings"&gt;my working model of emotions&lt;/a&gt; is that they exist as a tendency towards behaviours. Anger is a tendency to behave angrily, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This tendency is experienced as something like the default thing that happens if you don't put in energy to avoid it happening. It's not that behaving angrily is inevitable when you are angry, it's that it is more work to avoid behaving angrily than it is to behave angrily. You have to constantly choose not to behave angrily.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was having a miserable day yesterday, and I was wondering... what is that? What is miserable? Is it an emotion?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to say that miserable is not an emotion because it lacks intentionality, it's not about something (although there's some linguistic ambiguity - I feel like one can be miserable about specific things as well, but there's miserable-about and there's just miserable, and it's the latter I'm pointing to).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to say that miserable is not an emotion but a &lt;em&gt;mood&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What's a mood? Well, a mood is to emotions as emotions are to behaviour: A tendency towards.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This ties into Ratcliffe and his notion of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-06-07:46.html"&gt;Depression as constituted by existential feelings&lt;/a&gt;,
and in particular as a restriction on the set of possible emotions, which suggests that "tendency towards" may be insufficiently strong in its connotations. Sometimes that tendency is overwhelming: A feeling of hopelessness creates not just a "tendency" against hope, but a feeling that hope is itself impossible.
Moods contain not just slopes but also walls.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does this in turn go back to emotions and behaviours? I think it does. If I'm absolutely furious with someone I may be able to behave calmly with them, but I probably can't behave warmly to them - I can go through the motions, but I will probably seem stiff and artificial (because I will be) because I do not have full control over my body language, and have to fight against my natural tendencies.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So perhaps a better way to think of emotions and behaviour is not the tendency towards behaviours but the landscape of behaviour. It is the set of hills and valleys and walls that behaviour operates in. You can apply energy to move up a slope, you probably can't move up a wall, but as soon as you stop applying energy you will fall into the local minimum.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Moods in turn are the landscape of emotions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What is the landscape of mood?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was going to say that it's temperament, but that isn't quite right. It's some combination of temperament and environment - part of why I was miserable yesterday is definitely environmental, prompted by how grey and unpleasant the weather is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general this feels like a fruitful question to ask even outside the context of mood and emotion: When you have a space of possibilities, what constitutes the landscape for it?&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-12-14-12:27.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-01-13:23.html</id>
    <title>Writing from the heart</title>
    <updated>2022-01-01T13:41:36+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Writing from the heart&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-01&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been thinking about types of writing recently, and in particular about the following section from Hillary Rettig's excellent "7 Secrets of the prolific":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grandiosity is a problem for writers because our media and culture are permeated with grandiose myths and misconceptions about writing, which writers who are undermentored fall prey to. Red Smith’s famous bon mot about how, to write, you need only “sit down at a typewriter and open a vein,” and Gene Fowler’s similarly sanguinary advice to “sit staring at a blank sheet of paper until the drops of blood form on your forehead,” are nothing but macho grandiose posturing, as is William Faulkner’s overwrought encomium to monomaniacal selfishness, from his Paris Review interview:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writer’s only responsibility is to his art. He will be completely ruthless if he is a good one. He has a dream. It anguishes him so much he must get rid of it. He has no peace until then. Everything goes by the board: honor, pride, decency, security, happiness, all, to get the book written. If a writer has to rob his mother, he will not hesitate; the “Ode on a Grecian Urn” is worth any number of old ladies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the most famous quotes about writing are grandiose. I’m not saying that all of these writers were posturing—perhaps that’s how they truly perceived themselves and their creativity. What I do know is that, for most writers, a strategy based on pain and deprivation is not a route to productivity. In fact, it is more likely a route to a block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually find quotes about how awful writing and the writing life are to be not just perfectionist, but self-indulgent. No one’s forcing these writers to write, after all, and there are obviously far worse ways to spend one’s time, not to mention earn one’s living. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Rettig is, broadly, right here about how most people should be writing most of the time, but I must admit that of all the wisdom in this section the one that's stuck with me is the line she's disagreeing with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2011/09/14/writing-bleed/"&gt;According to Quote Investigator&lt;/a&gt;, Red Smith's full line is: &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You simply sit down at the typewriter, open your veins, and bleed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think about this a lot because, contra Rettig, writing be like that sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's useful to compare and contrast two recent newsletter issues of mine. &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/labelling-feelings"&gt;Labelling feelings 101&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/first-hard-choice"&gt;The first hard choice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Labelling feelings 101 was not a particularly taxing piece to write. It's just a summary of lots of things I've thought about. There's a moderate amount of myself in there, but only because it's explaining how I look at things. It's a look at part of the world through my eyes, but it's just explanatory prose, it's nothing particularly revealing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first hard choice on the other hand is weirder and more personal. I started writing, and then I continued writing, and it went in a very different direction than I intended. The underlying thought process is non-obvious, but I think it comes through that I'm writing about something that actually matters to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tellingly, "Labelling feelings 101" has got more attention (it's certainly useful to more people) but "The first hard choice" has got more praise (and also more people checking in to make sure that I'm OK).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is, a lot of the time, a way of expressing something deeply felt. You write from the heart, and it's hard to do that without bleeding onto the page.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most writing isn't, and shouldn't, be like this. If you're writing an email to a coworker it doesn't have to express some profound truth. If you're writing some basic copy explaining how a product works, same. But if you're writing about your life, or about things that are personally important to you, and you are &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; doing this, then you're probably holding your feelings at arms length, and that isn't great.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Am I being grandiose? Rettig would probably think so, and maybe I am. But some things are actually important, and it's hard to talk about that without sounding a little grandiose, and maybe that's OK.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't do this sort of writing enough, and I'd like to do it more - every time I have it's been in some way transformative.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to achieve this, I've come up with a very detailed and elaborate plan: I'm going to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-01-13:23.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html</id>
    <title>Wanting (to) help</title>
    <updated>2022-01-02T15:54:14+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Wanting (to) help&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I said in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-01-13:23.html"&gt;writing from the heart&lt;/a&gt; that I wanted to write more personal stuff.
Well, here it is. Unfortunately, it turns out, bleeding onto the page hurts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, on to the point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You may or may not have noticed, but I'm a very helpful person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of this comes out more with friends, family, etc. When I see someone I know who is having problems, I want to help. I'm aware this isn't always possible or welcome, and I don't force help on people by any means, but generally if you're my friend and need help I'm there for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of it also comes out with strangers. I've had fairly extensive conversations trying to help random strangers on the internet solve their problems or process their feelings.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's also little things like, mostly for free, having a major impact on the quality of software testing in the Python ecosystem. I've at this point written about two million words on the internet, a decent chunk of which is just me helpfully explaining things to strangers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't want to give you the impression that I'm constantly martyring myself for others. There are many people who are far more helpful than I am, and give an amount of their time and energy that I am both in awe of and have no desire to emulate. If one were to put together some arbitrary ranking of people in terms of helpfulness, I'm probably in the top 10%, likely in the top 5% (&lt;a href="https://danluu.com/p95-skill/"&gt;95%-ile isn't that good&lt;/a&gt;), and probably not in the top 1%.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't say I'm always good at helping.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I usually am good at helping when the problem is one that can be solved through the deployment of my very particular set of skills. Sometimes that means helping people problem solving, sometimes that means just showing up and listening and providing hugs, sometimes that involves more concrete help like turning up and providing manual labour, or providing a place to crash for the night. There are things my friends probably can't rely on me for though - if it needs organisational skills or fine motor control, I'm probably not the one that can help you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also sometimes I'd love to help but I'm overcommitted - either with my own stuff, or with helping other people, or both. Until my cloning project comes online, I'm only one man.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of which is fine, in principle. I'm not helpful because I want to help people, I'm helpful because I want people to be helped. If you've got someone better suited than me to draw on, I'm delighted.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It rarely seems like this is the case though. People don't, for the most part, help their friends out that much. The typical friendship I see seems to be one where people pretend that connection without responsibility is possible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, this often makes me feel worse about not being able to help, because often the reason someone needs my help is that nobody else has been able to provide it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, all generalising heavily from my own very small pool of experience. I'm sure if you move to a different culture, or even a different social milieu within a given culture, it looks different. People live in very different worlds. But based on what I see this doesn't look &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; weird.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This particularly stings because people are generally willing to draw on offered help, but pay it neither back nor forward.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think a friendship in which one party feels no real responsibility to the other, and is unwilling to extend meaningful help, is in the long run doomed.
Nobody is invincible, nobody can maintain good times for ever. You're going to have a bad period, and then the people who were just with you for a good time and don't feel any responsibility for you ghost or angrily leave. There's a reason we have the phrase "fair weather friends".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn't even particularly require bad times. I've lost multiple friendships due to it turning out that the other party in a relationship that I had poured a huge amount of care and help into (which they happily accepted) felt absolutely no responsibility to me to reciprocate even a tiny fraction of that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They would no doubt tell you this is a grossly unfair summary of the situation. I would, in turn, tell you that yes they would say that and can get fucked as far as I'm concerned. This is as close as I am prepared to come in providing a fair and balanced summary of events.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Friendships aren't, and shouldn't be, transactional, but they do need to be somewhat reciprocal if they're to work. There's a deep hypocrisy involved in being willing to accept arbitrary amounts of help from someone and then be horrified at the idea that you might be expected to return it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately it is, I think, an extremely common hypocrisy, because people are rarely going to say no to getting their needs met, and are rarely going to say yes to taking on a responsibility they don't have to. It's much easier to jettison the relationship and move on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of this is something I feel acutely, because the truth is that a lot of why I'm so helpful is that I've spent a lot of my life desperately wanting help and not getting it, so I've learned to help people in the ways that I've wished that someone would help me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Don't get me wrong, I've had myriad advantages in life. Many of the problems that I've needed help with are, technically, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-07-15-09:33.html"&gt;nice problems to have&lt;/a&gt;. Many of them were not, but I was able to compensate for them in some way or another. It's not hard to imagine some hypothetical other's thought process of "How can you say you need help when so many other people are worse off? You're doing fine". But I really wasn't, and to a large degree still am not, doing fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can see this a lot in my writing - a lot of things I write have a model target audience of me of N years ago. They're something I desperately wished someone would teach me at the time, or desperately needed but didn't know even &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be taught, but nobody did. So I had to spend years of my life learning them the hard way, and now I'm paying it forward in the hopes that someone out there analogous to younger me gets the help they need.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's hard for me to talk about all this without sounding extremely bitter about it. That's because I'm extremely bitter about it. But the result is that I mostly don't talk about it in public at all, and I don't think that's good either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is part of what a pervasive unwillingness to help does, I think. People's responses to pain are all very "Have you tried not being in pain?" or, if you're lucky, "Yeah me too" - an attempt to deflect a responsibility to help more than an attempt to help.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm aware that not all of the help I've lacked has been due to others' unwillingness to help. Much of it is on me - I'm not very good at making it clear that I need help, or letting others help me when they do offer. There's a number of reasons for this, but mostly it's just a matter of getting burned too many times and finding it very hard to trust that this time it will be different. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is reasonably common, and is something of a vicious circle. I think, in fact, many people (probably not most) are in principle willing to help, but because it's hard to ask for help, most people won't be willing, and some people will punish you for it, we end up with this dysfunctional feedback loop where most friendships stay at the responsibility light version.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd like to break this cycle, but I don't really know how.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-03-14:16.html</id>
    <title>Relearning curiosity</title>
    <updated>2022-01-03T19:55:49+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Relearning curiosity&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Apparently when I start a daily writing practice in which I am honest about my feelings partly as a way to work myself out of a depressed period,
everything I write is very sad. So, here we are again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A while back I wrote &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-28-15:58.html"&gt;I'm not actually that curious&lt;/a&gt;. I explained that although I am a voracious reader and know a lot of stuff, it wasn't actually generally powered by a learn things for its own sake - I learn in aid of things I want to do, not primarily because I want to learn. Almost everything I learn has a goal in mind. I don't seek out knowledge because I'm curious, I seek it out because knowledge is useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Dear past me: You realise that's bad, right? Well, in case you don't realise that (I'm not sure you did), FYI that's bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also not how I used to be. I &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; used to be curious, and just read about things because they were fun and interesting. I had a very nerdy notion of fun and interesting which means that this ended up me taking a book about classical mechanics (I still know a surprising amount about Lagrangian formulations of Newtonian physics, although it's all got a bit rusty) as my summer vacation reading when I was 16, but it was absolutely something I picked because I wanted to learn about it and not because I needed to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My degree was in pure mathematics, which I certainly didn't get into because I had applications in mind for the connection between the axioms of set theory and questions in analysis (this was what my final year essay was on. It wasn't very good).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Apparently as a kid I would fairly regularly give adults mostly-correct lectures on various subjects I'd been learning about. Palm trees and black holes seem to be the topic that people tell stories about me doing this, but I'm sure there are others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point this got lost. I don't really know when, or why.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It feels like part of the problem is agency. As a kid it's easy to be curious about things, because nothing you do actually matters, and also you're mostly bored out of your mind. So why not learn new things purely because they're interesting and you want to stuff your brain with knowledge?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, you're a child, and thus you're still full of energy. The fatigue of ageing and the burnout of life haven't set in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Not that those are inevitable. My parents seem like they still have way more energy than I do)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now it feels like I've got such limited brain capacity and energy and such a greater degree of agency that &lt;em&gt;of course&lt;/em&gt; I spend it on useful things, because I feel guilty about not doing so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Except I think even as I write it that that's a cope. If that were the case I'd probably be doing far more useful things than I do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Really the core problem is that &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;it's hard to care about things&lt;/a&gt;, and usefulness is a crutch.
It's much easier to solve a problem, which is obviously good. It's even better if &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html"&gt;it's somebody else's problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I keep wanting to frame this in terms of justification, but I don't think that's quite right. The problem isn't that I feel like I have to be able to justify my actions to someone, but that they need to feel somehow purposeful. It's not that someone will attack me for doing it, it's that if I spend energy on something purposeless a huge wave of "What's the point?" rises up and I get distracted and go do something else.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often it starts before that and I can't even generate the "purposeless" actvitity in the first place. I try to generate a plan for what to do and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-02-08:53.html"&gt;my brain glitches&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is depression, of course. It's well-managed reasonably high functioning depression, but it's still depression.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think of depression as a constriction of the felt world of possibilities. A narrowing of the actions that you feel able to take. A lot of my incessant "curiousity" in the search of the useful feels like I'm trying to squeeze a vast level of interest in the world through the narrow passages that depression has left me. What comes out is still pretty good, because I'm clever and competent, but it's fairly anemic compared to what I'd be doing if less depressed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of this focus on usefulness feels not so much like I'm motivated to be useful (I am, but it's more of a "make the pain go away" motivation than something I necessarily care deeply about), but that it's something to do while I'm here. I've got all these capabilities, there are things I can do that help make things better, might as well. It's slightly less fundamentally unsatisfying than wasting my day scrolling Twitter and reading YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; fundamentally care about helping people, but it's all swallowed up by the general meh. Certainly I would &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; to be positively motivated towards helping people instead of it being something that hurts if I don't do it, but these days I'm struggling to be positively motivated about much of anything very serious.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1476967194101698561"&gt;I wrote on Twitter about how incredibly mind-numbingly bored I am of the pandemic&lt;/a&gt;, and that I really need more in person contact with people than I'm getting. That feels like part of this but I don't know how much of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The absence of curiousity feels in some way like a primary thing in its own right that I should take seriously just as much as the absence of people.
Learning things should be a joyful activity, and the fact that it's not is a huge sign.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of my working theories of how to work with depression is to be constantly exploring the edge of the depression comfort zone - do things that you feel &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt; too depressed to do. If depression comes from a restriction of what feels safe, exploring the boundaries of where you feel safe helps you relearn those as safe and then you can expand gradually outwards.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes this even works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, that's too cynical. It often works, it's just a bit of a two steps forward one step back process. The depression comes back, but it's easier to claw your way out of it the next time because you believe you can do that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the starting point for solving the curiousity problem is something like asking how I would behave if I were as curious as I'd like to be, and walking in that direction until I hit the edge of the comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The obvious thing is that I would learn things just for interest. For some reason the example that comes to mind here is physics youtube. I've been enjoying &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/SteveMould"&gt;Steve Mould's YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; recently for example. I really respect the urge to just go "How does that work?" and put in the effort to find the answer. I definitely used to have some of that, and I'd like to have it again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other thing that comes to mind is that I'd talk to people more about things I find interesting. I really don't do this very much - these days all my writing is about stuff that's useful (in some very generalised sense of the term), which is a shame in and of itself - but really I have in person conversations in mind. Generally I just let other people take the lead, and feel very inhibited in proposing conversation topics and just going on about them, and that feels necessary if rather daunting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Who knows if any of this will actually work, but it feels worth a try.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-03-14:16.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-04-14:48.html</id>
    <title>Being a brain at night</title>
    <updated>2022-01-04T16:24:29+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Being a brain at night&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Look, I think we can just take it as read that the slightly traumatised writing will continue for a while. It's useful for me to write, and it seems to be useful for other people to read, so I'm going to do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I've been having panic attacks at night recently. Not every night, but maybe about once a week, and the edge is there on other nights.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sounds more dramatic than it is. They're not full blown panic attacks. Not really. It's very easy to stop them, all I have to do is open my eyes and distract myself.
It's not an irrecoverable panic attack, it's just that I close my eyes, try to sleep, and am filled with a formless dread as if I'm drowning.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the most likely cause, as well as generally having been in a terrible mood due to general depression and the whole global pandemic thing, is that I'm getting to experience something that I have rarely experienced in my adult life: It's bedtime and I'm not caffeine withdrawn.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I quit coffee about a month ago. As the joke goes: Quitting is easy, I've done it loads of times. This time I think it might stick. I've had a few coffees since quitting, all rather small, and frankly it's been awful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Among other reasons it's been awful because it seems by far the easiest way to trigger this problem. I don't need coffee to get a panic attack at night, but I get them 100% of the time I've had coffee in the last few weeks. As far as commitment devices go to break a habit it's a bit extreme, but it's hopefully effective.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(If this seems at odds with the claim that the problem is about not being caffeine withdrawn, the reason is that my caffeine tolerance is now mostly reset so although there's still less caffeine in my system by night, there are no withdrawal symptoms because I don't have the dependency, and what caffeine is still there is much more effective)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think when people hear you can't sleep because of anxiety they imagine that it's because of racing thoughts. Lying there awake thinking about all the terrible things that might happen, the things you did wrong, reminders of all your obligations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not like that. It's almost the opposite. It's an absence of thought, coupled with a feeling that something is terribly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Have you ever read Flowers for Algernon?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm planning to reread it soon, to see if I can exorcise some demons, but every time I remember the book exists I flinch. I don't know if it's meant to be a horror story but, for me, it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am, like most smart people, probably over identified with my intelligence. I'm sure there are all sorts of reasons why I shouldn't be, and I do try to braoden out, but honestly I have no idea how to be me without my intelligence. It is pretty close to being a core feature of who I am - it's not all I do is think, but my thoughts are so central to what I do that a dramatic loss of intelligence would fundamentally change who I am. Flowers for Algernon's account of intelligence slipping away was extremely hard for me to handle.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I am, naturally, similarly viscerally afraid of Alzheimers. Alzheimers is much scarier than dying to me, and I very much understand Terry Pratchett's support for assisted suicide)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What makes this particularly tricky to deal with is how much I experience my brain as a collection of black boxes. I've described the process of writing before as just reaching for the place where words come from and then letting it do its thing. What happens when the place where words come from goes away?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway this is what seems to be happening to me at night right now. I think this is likely to be perfectly normal tiredness and not something to worry about - it's normal to have trouble thinking when tired - but in the moment it sure doesn't &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like nothing to worry about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of the context for this is that when trying to fall asleep I often tell myself stories. Not particularly good ones, the goal isn't to craft a masterwork, it's just to construct some narrative to hang my thoughts on - often more worldbuilding than pure story. The current one is about a magical research team working on trying to improve a kingdom's crop yields, if you're curious.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On nights when the panic occurs, this very much doesn't work, and is likely to be a trigger. The problem is that I reach for the place where words come from and they're... not quite absent, but sluggish, and blocked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's like a sudden feeling of claustrophobia, when you're trapped and can't move properly - someone's lying on top of you, you're tangled in the duvet, some situation where you know intellectually that everything is fine and you're safe but oh god you have to move &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; and if you can't you very rapidly get frantic. That, but the things I can't move are my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This probably shouldn't be scary. I suspect this is just what sleep is - the gradual disintegration of your mind as it shuts down for the night - and maybe all that's happening is that I'm more acutely aware of it now. But regardless of whether I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be afraid of it, the fear response is fairly primal. I've always considered "Do you die each night and a new person takes your place in the morning?" to be an annoying piece of philosophical pedantry with no real content, but apparently some part of me very much disagrees.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first night this happened I stayed awake until 9AM until some combination of exhaustion and coincidence allowed me to figure out my first workaround, which is to just watch Slay the Spire videos on YouTube as I fall asleep. It gives me something to focus on that isn't the contents of my own mind. It works as a backstop, although it doesn't result in good sleep and it takes a while - last night I had to put on a second one because the first finished and I still wasn't asleep. On the plus side at least that was two hours not spent panicking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some degree of meditation practice works reasonably well for the less bad nights - I've succeeded a few times at falling asleep counting breaths. When it works it works very well, but I think I need to be quite tired for it to work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm also going to be trying some sleeping pills (just drowsy antihistamines to start) to see if I can just clobber the problem by being sleepy enough - this is how my old solution of running out of caffeine at night and thus being super sleepy worked after all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, taken as a practical problem, I'm getting on top of the sleep thing. It's annoying but manageable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it's also just so &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;/em&gt;. There's clearly something going on here that I don't understand, and that I struggle to understand because in the moment that it's happening, most of the tools I use to understand things are offline.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-04-14:48.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-05-13:01.html</id>
    <title>Ready for less than you think</title>
    <updated>2022-01-05T19:33:07+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Ready for less than you think&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had to go to the hospital earlier. This wasn't a big deal, I just needed an X-ray on my knee, which has been giving me a hard time for a few months. I set up an appointment with my GP late last month, expecting it to take a while to get the referral sorted (this is incorrect, the NHS is actually very good at prompt X-ray referrals, but I always forget this because I rarely get X-rays and they're rather less prompt at many referrals on other things), so I'd have time for Omicron to settle down and have my knee looked when it was sensible and safe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I got a call this morning at around 8:33. I was not at all awake at 8:33. I'd had another &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-04-14:48.html"&gt;night of bad sleep&lt;/a&gt;, and my alarm had gone off at 8:30 and so I was &lt;em&gt;technically&lt;/em&gt; conscious, but it was very confusing when my phone made a noise from the other room as if someone were uncouth enough to actually want to speak to me on it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The person on the other end told me that they'd had an urgent X-ray referral from my GP (I'm not sure it was really urgent if I'm honest) and could I come to Charing Cross Hospital for 10:25?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My response was slightly more articulate than "Huh? What? Zzzz" but not vastly more. Eventually my brain kicked into gear and I said I didn't think I could physically make it in time even if I left right that minute. Fortunately I checked Google Maps and determined that Charing Cross Hospital was not in fact anywhere near Charing Cross, but was in fact near Hammersmith, which is much easier for me to get to, and I determined that it would be tight but doable. So I said yes, I could do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A very rapid shower and a COVID test later, and a hurried message asking my partner to be in my flat to meet the Ocado delivery that was supposed to be arriving at 11, I dashed out the door to the bus stop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first problem I encountered was that after having promised me a very straightforward route, Google maps was now telling me that it was literally impossible to get there by public transport. It does that. The Google maps app sometimes believes my area (which is very well appointed with bus routes and not too bad to walk to various more civilised forms of public transport) is just utterly inaccessible to public transport, despite generally being OK on desktop web. I opened it on my phone's browser instead and it confirmed that yes the single direct bus to Hammersmith was still a perfectly viable option despite the app's lies.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second problem was that I missed my bus. This wasn't a huge deal, as it wasn't &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; tight and there was another one in 7 minutes, but as I was wondering whether it would make sense to get a taxi there I noticed my third problem: My phone was on 13% battery.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It shouldn't have been. I'd charged it overnight. When I got home I found out that the charger had partly fallen out of the power socket, so although the cable was connected to the phone this wasn't a problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also shouldn't have been a problem. I basically &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; travel without an external battery for my phone. But I couldn't find it when I was leaving, I was in a hurry, and figured it was fine - my phone was fully charged (oops) and I was only going to be out for a few hours.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I turned my phone off in order to conserve power, got the bus, and happily read Robertson Davies writing about interpersonal drama between Canadian academics for half an hour or so until I got to Hammersmith.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I got off the bus, turned on my phone, and prepared to walk the last 5-10 minutes from Hammersmith to Charing Cross Hospital.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This should be easy, it's just a straight line from Hammersmith, more or less. I mean &lt;a href="https://www.google.co.uk/maps/dir/Hammersmith+Station,+London+W6+7AE/Charing+Cross+Hospital,+Fulham+Palace+Rd,+London+W6+8RF/@51.489909,-0.2257482,16.62z/data=!4m14!4m13!1m5!1m1!1s0x48760fb7e0b0070d:0x2398b7d670685535!2m2!1d-0.2248261!2d51.493483!1m5!1m1!1s0x48760fbbc7f7ed75:0x6cd065c43bb8bbf5!2m2!1d-0.2195543!2d51.4868889!3e2"&gt;look at this&lt;/a&gt;, it's not a complicated route.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Just one problem: Figuring out &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; straight line it is is impossibly confusing, because when your phone is in low power mode Google Maps becomes all but useless at telling you where you are, and Google Maps has always been useless at orienting without GPS in the UK because it insists on displaying road numbers instead of names. I don't want to know that this is the fucking A315, Google, I want to know &lt;em&gt;what the name on the road sign is&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I could have figured it out in about five minutes of wandering around the junction and staring (in retrospect, I knew which way North was, and if I'd oriented Google maps right I could have known I needed to head southish, and that would have been enough). Unfortunately I got about three minutes, which was how long my phone took to eat through the remaining 13% of battery. I don't know why it died so fast and should probably look into that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It took me about 25 minutes to find Charing Cross Hospital. I asked five different people for directions in the course of that. They were all very nice about it - I do charming but flustered polite Englishman very well and it tends to work for getting strangers to help you out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They were not, reliably, useful. Some of their directions were straight up wrong, some of them were in retrospect right but I failed to follow them correctly. The result was a lot of doubling back on myself. But I did find it before my appointment, though not as much before my appointment as they want you to be. I was tired, stressed, and had done enough running at that point (mostly to catch the bus, the rest was a brisk walk) that I'd probably aggravated the knee problem I was there to get checked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway the X-ray all went fine, nothing to report there for now. They did make me do a rather uncomfortable lunge to get the knee right before the X-ray machine, which I'm probably going to pay for given that it's exactly the sort of motion that triggers the knee problem, but so far it's no worse than grumpy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the knee isn't really the point of this story (to the degree that there's a point rather than me just feeling like telling you about how my day went).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of this has me thinking about preparedness, and the way it decays. This whole episode would have gone much better prior to the pandemic, because I would not have made the mistake with my phone - maybe it wouldn't have been charged, but I'd have had the battery. I'd have been less flustered by Google maps's problems because I'd have Citymapper installed (my phone is a bit low on space and I'm not actually travelling far right now so I uninstalled it).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, leaving the house involves a certain amount of skill and preparations. If you're travelling regularly, those are all fresh. If you're not, your skills have got rusty and your habits have been decayed - the battery that you always have access to has gotten tucked somewhere weird because you haven't used it recently for example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Navigation was also like this to a degree - I'd utterly lost the skill. When I mentioned asking for directions, J said "Wow, asking for directions? What is this the 90s??" and it's true - I've had a smart phone on me for 11 years at this point. The idea of being lost is just alien. Asking for directions was fine, but following them from memory sure was hard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It feels ridiculous to be bad at leaving the house in this way (finding it difficult to leave the house is less confusing, but successfully leaving the house and being bad at it is weird), because this is something that seems trivial and I've spent so long being competent at that it's part of my internalised self image that it's just something I can do at a moment's notice without it going wrong (a small achievement, but not an automatic one - I know many people who can't leave the house without forgetting something for example), but it's fairly natural, just not internalised.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been thinking about how long it's going to take for being in a crowd to feel normal again, even once it's safe, but I think maybe one of the interesting things is going to happen before that, as we gradually resume life and find out all the skills and habits we'd taken for granted have to be relearned from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-05-13:01.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-06-12:00.html</id>
    <title>Drifting away the time</title>
    <updated>2022-01-06T12:58:39+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Drifting away the time&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the ways my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-03-14:16.html"&gt;current difficulty with motivation&lt;/a&gt; plays out is that I spend a lot of my day drifting.
Left to my own devices my day probably won't be &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; drifting, but I might spend an hour or so on something I'd actually endorse as worthwhile. One of the reasons why daily writing is good for me is that it claws back another hour or so from the drift. This is, presumably, also why I sometimes find it hard to sustain.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Drifting is like... evil flow. It absorbs the totality of your being in the same way, but you're left feeling entirely unnourished by it. 
Flow is what happens when you're able to absorb yourself entirely in the achievement of some end. Drifting is what happens when absorbing yourself entirely &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the end, a way to dissociate from the world. Drifting is &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/first-hard-choice"&gt;eating the lotus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For me drifting tends to be spending time on Twitter, or watching youtube, it might be reading truly execrable Royal Road quality fiction, or if there's a new TV series to binge I might lose a day doing that.
It probably &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; playing games. The games I play tend not to be drifting games, because I've learned the hard way just how bad they are for me and in a rare case of being sensible about this I avoid drifting games. This is why I don't play Cookie Clickers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Slay the Spire is interesting in that it can be either drifting or flow - at low ascensions you can absolutely play it as a drifting game, but if you do that at high ascensions you die to Gremlin Nob. All of my Slay the Spire drifting time seems to have been adequately satisfied by watching other people play it on YouTube though)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of my time is spent in this drifting state - not really doing anything useful, but also not following any sort of interesting direction. This is why I don't really feel like it's right to characterise my relationship with curiousity as only being able to do useful things: It doesn't seem to be based in a strong desire to be useful. Idly following my curiosity in whatever direction brings me joy would be significantly more useful than most of how I spend my days.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But apparently that's not what I want to do. What I want to do is drift.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Except, that's not quite right. It's not that I want to drift - the idea almost feels contradictory. It's more that drifting is an easy state to fall into. Not drifting requires active effort, and I don't want to spend that effort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;None of these are endorsed preferences of course. I want to want to spend that effort, and ideally I want to want to spend it on fun things as well as useful things. But in the moment what I apparently choose, most of the time, is drifting instead.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The aversion to effort does feel like a key part of it. It's not an aversion to things I think I "should" be doing exactly - going for a walk or cooking a nice meal are equally prone to being avoided as reading and writing are. But they seem like too much work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There seem to be two distinct triggers for this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unable to generate the worthwhile activity in the first place. Making it easy to generate good activities seems to help a bit here. For example having habits around good quality reading seem to result in more of that. Having a daily writing habit makes it easier for writing to feel salient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unable to stick to the worthwhile activity - I start writing, or doing something useful, and then I reach a point where it feels unbearable to maintain my focus on this for any longer and I check Twitter or otherwise take a break "briefly" and often it's not so brief. This is particularly prone for things that I very much don't want to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The trigger for this does often seem to be unpleasant feelings come up when trying to focus and falling back to drift. I'd like to think I was good at dealing with unpleasant feelings, but the reality is that I'm probably quite bad at it. I think it's also telling that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-04-14:48.html"&gt;the thing I often need to do to get to sleep right now&lt;/a&gt; is to deliberately induce a drifting state.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Internally the urge to drift feels like I'm "too tired" to do things, but this seems to be fake, or rather it's not tiredness in that sense. Probably it's a Freeze reaction of some sort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason I don't think it's real tiredness is how much of this goes away as soon as soon as there are other people involved. Often I'll spend an entire morning drifting, and then get on a call with someone and be absolutely fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This of course tends to result in people thinking I'm in a much better state than I actually am a lot of the time, because I'm fine when interacting with them and stop being fine as soon as I stop interacting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn't even have to really be &lt;em&gt;interacting&lt;/em&gt; with the other person. On Monday a friend and I got on a call together as a way of motivating each other to get things done, turned off our microphones for an hour, and then checked back in at the end of the call. In that call I did all of the accounting and tax admin I'd been putting off for months (and learned I had about £800 of unpaid invoices. Turns out checking whether people have paid you is good). Normally this is maximally aversive task that would &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; have resulted in me losing track of myself about 5 minutes in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something like this also often happens with tweeting. I say Twitter is drifting, but that's not quite right. Writing on Twitter is often flow, or at least interesting and worthwhile. What happens sometimes is that I'm drifting and then suddenly there are Thoughts! which have to be expressed, I coalesce into a person for about 10 minutes and hop on Twitter to express them. But then I'm done, and I dissociate again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What's really drifting is checking Twitter, especially my notifications. People often describe this as waiting for the dopamine hit, but it doesn't really feel like a reward, it's more that I'm waiting for something to happen, and until then my brain is in idle mode. Thinking at the speed of likes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How bad this is comes and goes. December was the worst for this, but probably that's partly because I was ill a lot on December. Right now it's moderately bad, but feels like it's letting up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It never really goes away though unless I have some project I'm able to obsessively work on, which is a state that rarely lasts more than weeks, or I have people to work with (or at least in the company of). Conveniently both of those are 2022 goals, so this problem may be solved as a byproduct of that, but I sure wish I had a clearer idea of why this happens.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-06-12:00.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-07-14:02.html</id>
    <title>Writing as yourself</title>
    <updated>2022-01-07T14:02:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Writing as yourself&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a simple method to doing anything. Do you know it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be the sort of person who can do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you become the sort of person who can do the thing?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, if you're not already, first you need to be the sort of person who can become the sort of person who can do the thing, then you become the sort of person who can do the thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't an infinite regress. It's just the fully general system for learning to do hard things - eventually you bottom out by finding something that is only just outside your comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You might, of course, find that some of the steps are impossible, or that the chain of dependencies are too long. I'm not going to win an olympic gold medal - some step in that chain of dependencies there is a "become the sort of person who can..." which I won't be able to fulfill. I'm not going to learn to speak fluent Russian - I could, for sure, but it's hard work with many many steps, and I don't want to. I said this method was &lt;em&gt;simple&lt;/em&gt;, I didn't say it was &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Even claiming it's simple is a lie. It may or may not be simple depending on how complex each of those steps is)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this isn't really about skill development.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tautologically, every successful attempt to do the thing works like this: If you do the thing, you're the sort of person who can do the thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if you can't do the thing, you're not the sort of person who can do the thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Sometimes you "can" do the thing you just don't want to. But if you can't overcome your lack of desire to do the thing enough to do the thing, can you really do it?)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So suppose you want to do something and can't. This gives you two options:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change who you are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do something that you can do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first sounds very dramatic, but it's not. Everything changes who you are. You might be the sort of person who can do the thing on a good night's sleep but not the sort of person who can do the thing when tired. So the way to do the thing is to make sure you've got a good night's sleep. Or have a coffee. Or do it on a call with a friend who can help you. Or... You get the picture. Who you are is as much a function of context as any intrinsic aspect of character.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also change in more fundamental ways. You can learn new skills, introspect on your emotional relationship with the thing, make any number of changes that improve your ability to do the thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But sometimes changing who you are is the wrong thing to do. Sometimes you're just doing the wrong thing. You've picked something that your soul rebels at the idea of doing, and the reason you can't do it is that you don't want to be the sort of person who can do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How to do murder: First become the sort of person who can do murder. Probably best... not, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think many things that we think of as immoral but where it's hard to articulate why they're bad are bad for this reason: Even if the thing itself is harmless, you first have to become the sort of person who can do them. Harmless in the moment, but corrosive to the character (I'm thinking of things like Jonathan Haidt's examples of "objectively harmless" thought experiments which people still think of as immoral - the most memorably graphic example of which involves buying a chicken from the supermarket to have sex with).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this isn't really about that either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, as the title promises, about writing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I know a lot of people who say they would like to write, but aren't writing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why aren't they writing?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, Ira Glass has this notion of "the gap":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nobody tells this to people who are beginners, I wish someone told me. All of us who do creative work, we get into it because we have good taste. But there is this gap. For the first couple years you make stuff, it’s just not that good. It’s trying to be good, it has potential, but it’s not. But your taste, the thing that got you into the game, is still killer. And your taste is why your work disappoints you. A lot of people never get past this phase, they quit. Most people I know who do interesting, creative work went through years of this. We know our work doesn’t have this special thing that we want it to have. We all go through this. And if you are just starting out or you are still in this phase, you gotta know its normal and the most important thing you can do is do a lot of work. Put yourself on a deadline so that every week you will finish one story. It is only by going through a volume of work that you will close that gap, and your work will be as good as your ambitions. And I took longer to figure out how to do this than anyone I’ve ever met. It’s gonna take awhile. It’s normal to take awhile. You’ve just gotta fight your way through.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What you are trying to do is write something that satisfies your taste, but you're not yet or currently the kind of person who can do that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You're also not the kind of person who can write things that &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; satisfy your taste, because if you write something bad you feel bad about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, you don't write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's more to it than that though. Even experienced writers get writers block.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Know what writer's block is? It's trying to write the wrong thing for you right now. You're not currently someone who can write the thing you're trying to write. You need to change who you are, or you need to write something different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often this can be done just by writing - slowly chipping away at the problem, incrementally reshaping yourself and the work to bring the two into alignment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Creative processes are very susceptible to being the wrong person, because often you're trying to express something deeply felt, and it's hard to fake that. It's tough to write sad songs when you're happy, it's hard to write upbeat practical pieces about fixing things when you're incredibly depressed and everything feels unfixable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But often there's something else you could be writing about instead. Whoever you are right now almost certainly has something you want to express, so why not write about it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result will often not be what you expect, it will often not be very good, but it will feel important in ways that much other writing you do will not, and it will often resonate with other people in a way a more polished piece cannot, because it captures something true.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-07-14:02.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
