<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2021-11-15T18:31:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-08-21:50.html</id>
    <title>On Julia Annas's conception of happiness</title>
    <updated>2021-10-08T23:01:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;On Julia Annas's conception of happiness&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm continuing to study Julia Annas's book "Intelligent Virtue", and exploring the one hour study format. Today I thought I'd go through Chapter 8, "Living Happily" in detail. I've copied out the whole chapter into this notebook and will be deleting most of it (I think this still counts as fair use. I hope!). I've done a bit of a skim through it but mostly am writing as I read it, so often I'll write comments that I'll later take back.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Page 119:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very idea that virtue might have any role in flourishing or happiness has seemed, for about two hundred years, deeply unlikely. Philosophers in that period have been among the most robust in insisting that the whole idea of thinking that virtue could lead to happiness is absurd. Bentham says of the idea that virtue is sufficient for happiness, 'What benefit, in any shape, could be derived from impregnating the memory with such nonsense? What instruction from a self-contradictory proposition?" Nietzsche is even more dismissive. 'Such assertions and promises as those of the antique philosophers concerning the unity of virtue and happiness or the Christian, "But seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness, and all these things shall be added unto you" have never been made with total honesty and yet always without a bad conscience: one has advanced such propositions, which one very much desires to be true, boldly as to the truth in the face of appearance.' This idea, that there is some kind of naive wish-fulfilment or over-optimism in the claim that the virtuous are happy, lingers more effectively than actual arguments. Up to this point I have used the interim term 'flourishing' rather than happiness, but this has not been intended to avoid the issue stated brutally by Bentham and Nietzsche, and I shall now talk in terms of happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think a lot of this chapter will be spent defending the idea that happiness is not just simple pleasure and that it's plausible that virtue is a necessary component of it. I'm not sure I need that defence, as I'm already pretty on board with the idea. In &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;Burnout as acedia&lt;/a&gt; I talk about how burnout often comes precisely because we are not living our life ethically in the way that we want, because we are out of line with our values.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More generally I think happiness comes from doing things we feel are worthwhile, and "What counts as worthwhile?" is a fundamentally ethical question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next couple of paragraphs are spent on justifying the question that we don't seem to really know what happiness is, which then leads into the discussion of eudaimonia, starting Page 120:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is a eudaimonist account? An account of how to live, one in which happiness, eudaimonia, is central (...) the entry point for ethical reflections is thinking about how your life is going, thinking that can only arise in people who already are, or are becoming, adult, and who are aware that everything in their life is not satisfactory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, more or less, my above view: You need to not just be happy but &lt;em&gt;happy with your life&lt;/em&gt;. To judge it as satisfactory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you step back from the ongoing happenings of your life, and wonder about how and in what direction it is going. This at once reveals a fundamental difference between two ways in which you can regard your life. One perspective is the everyday one, in which you do one thing after another, one action following another chronologically. You get up, go to work and so on, one thing after another until eventually it comes to an end when your life does. This is the linear way of thinking of your life, and it is important as you get through the day, and in many other ways. But reflection reveals another way in which your life enters your thoughts about it. We can call this the structured way of thinking of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Long discussion of how we do things for reasons and have goals we are trying to achieve elided)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflection thus both triggers and then furthers thinking about how to achieve the goals I have in the light of the constraints I have (time, money, energy) and their mutual achievability. (...) What is activated is not thinking in the abstract about types of goal and how they could fit together, but thinking about how I can achieve the goals I have in the life I have. It is thinking about my life and how it is going. It is practical thinking, thinking about my life and how I should structure it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Thinking about my life and how I should structure it" seems like an important concept here. I think in many ways this is the goal of coaching - it draws you into that thinking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the original everyday thinking about the way one thing I do is for the sake of another thing I do leads seamlessly into thinking about my life as a whole in a structured way. This is a global way of thinking about my life: I come to see that I have various goals that I aim at, and that in the one life I have, and which I am already living, these goals need to be structured in a unifying way in order for me to achieve them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly I don't believe this account. I don't think most people have goals, and I don't think reflection naturally leads you to them. This may, partly, be because of my own baggage around goals, but I also think philosophers are very inclined to think in terms of goals.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This focus on goals also reminds me of yesterday's discussion of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-08-01:23.html"&gt;Scurrying&lt;/a&gt;. Treating the thing you are currently doing as the unimportant thing you are doing to get to the goal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But this is, ironically, actively the type of thing that virtue ethics in general and Annas in particular are arguing against: Thoughtlessly doing the thing, rather than doing it with the right emotions in your heart about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is this - the idea of what my life as a whole is aimed at - which in ancient ethical theories is called the telos or overall goal of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I very much reject the idea that life has an overall goal, and &lt;a href="https://meaningness.com/no-special-meaning"&gt;defer you to my friend David Chapman for the question of whether we should be upset about that&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us have nothing like this specific grasp of what our lives are working towards achieving. We have only the vaguest idea of what we are aiming for in life as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ah, good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;. This is exactly what eudaimonism holds: we have at best a vague and possibly muddled idea of what our 'final end' is; it is most likely to be only the indeterminate and in itself unhelpful idea of 'a good life' or 'a life lived well'. This supports, rather than undermines, eudaimonism, for few of us have a determinate idea of what we are aiming at in our life as a whole at the start of ethical reflection.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hmm. No this seems to still be back at the "but we &lt;em&gt;shuold&lt;/em&gt; have such a goal".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't deny that at any given point we should have &lt;em&gt;projects&lt;/em&gt;, and those should be meaningful, but I think if you're aiming at an overall purpose to your life you're going to make yourself miserable and also probably fail to achieve it. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-23-15:52.html"&gt;Life is an anytime algorithm&lt;/a&gt; - whether your life was a success or failure should not be determined by the fact whether you achieve some grand goal, because you can get hit by a bus at any point along the way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we did, we would have no need of ethical reflection or theory; our aims would already be clear and the only problems we would have would lie in actually achieving them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you've got a good way to never make a mistake en route to your goal that needs clarification, I'd love to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we find in fact is that nearly everyone (every moderately thoughtful person, in any case) is already living a life in which he or she is to some degree actively unifying the aims they have by working out what exactly those aims are and what form they should take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No, this seems false. Most people are just bumbling along. They probably have &lt;em&gt;immediate&lt;/em&gt; goals, but that's not the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final end, then, is the indeterminate notion of what I am aiming at in my life as a whole. And the role of ethical thinking is to get us to think more determinately about it, to do a better and more intelligently ordered job of what we are already doing anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hmm. I agree that the goal of of ethical thinking is to get us to do a better and more intelligently ordered job of what we were already doing anyway. I remain very very skeptical of this life goals thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can we say anything more specific about it? At this point Aristotle says that everyone agrees on something more determinate that we can say about it: it is happiness (eudaimonia); (...) Aristotle is bringing happiness in here merely as the only answer people can give, at the common-sense level, to the questions about why you are doing what you are doing, and how you can have all the goals that you have. That is, at the common-sense level, what is being appealed to is the idea that happiness always puts a stop to these questions. I may want to be healthy, to have a career, to have a family, as part of being happy, but I don't want to be happy as part of or a means to something further. It's just what I want; a terminus to my other goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm pretty suspect of arguments like this. I think they're wrong in a slippery way, because anything else you claim as a terminal goal the arguer just goes "Ah but you want that because it makes you happy", and I don't think this is true. If I love someone, I want them to be happy, and I don't want them to be happy because their happiness makes me happy (it may or may not do so depending on the context and my current mood. I might be too depressed to be happy right now!), I want them to be happy because I &lt;em&gt;want them to be happy for their own sake&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Side note: When thinking about this chapter I had a flashback to the first time I had this argument, which was standing at a bus stop waiting to go home from school when I was 17. I have no idea how it started, and I am surprised to learn that I have been arguing the nature of the good life for 21 years now. I thought this was a more recent phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This role for happiness is extremely useful in ethical theory. At the common-sense level people disagree about what is worth aiming for in life, but all agree that, whether they are going for money-making, fame and fortune, or serving others, they are all aiming for happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No we don't, I literally just disagreed with you, please don't assume consensus you don't have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think most people are aiming at happiness among other things, but people seem weirdly reluctant to do things that increase their happiness (citation: Various conversations on Twitter I can't be bothered to dig up right now).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happiness thus forms the point at which common sense agrees on a notion which forms the starting-point for ethical theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Gosh I hope not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting to do ethical theory does not require throwing out all or most of everyday thinking about ethics (even though the theories themselves may produce results which are very counter-intuitive). Ethical theory helps us to improve what we are already about how are lives are going and how we can do better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That's the hope anyway.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happiness has the role of being, for each person, your happiness, the way you achieve living your life well. It is not some plan imposed on you from outside, or a demand made by some theory which has not arisen from your own thoughts about your life. At the same time it is not just anything you want it to be. There are better and worse ways of seeking happiness, for there are clearly better and worse ways of organizing your goals and aims in life, and of seeking to live a life that achieves them overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems solidly true and important.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is happiness in this role in eudaimonist thinking happiness as we understand it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's a good question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one influential criticism of any account of happiness in eudaimonist thinking. Answering it helps to indicate an important feature of happiness. Grant that we all aim for something in our lives overall, vaguely and without being able to specify it beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do not grant this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grant also that this is happiness, understood as a very general aim which we can achieve in a number of ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, happiness is the point where ordinary thought meets theory: to achieve happiness we have to reflect about what we are doing to achieve it, and how this could be improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing maybe worth mentioning here is that this is a very Greek attitude, and if you look at a Buddhist attitude they would argue that almost exactly the opposite is true. Happiness comes from letting go of attachment and being present in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is very oversimplified, IANABuddhist)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet surely it is both intuitively repugnant, and at the level of theory objectionably paternalist, for some people to be in a position to tell others how to be happy. Some philosophers recoil at this point, seeing a spectre emerging from eudaimonism: some people imposing their own vision of the good life on others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know, a lot of people seem like they could use some advice here. I think the problem is maybe &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-give-good-advice"&gt;that those philosophers are bad at giving advice&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I start to reflect ethically there is much about my life which I have to recognize as the material I have to work on. The first ethical move is not to abstract from my individual context, still less to discount it, but rather to understand what it consists in, to achieve self-knowledge as far as I can, and then to think about how best to live my life in these circumstances. Only then will I be in a good position to consider the various options offered to me by different ethical theories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think this is a very important point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From here I'm going to start skimming a bit more aggressively because a lot of the next bits are philosophy-is-arguing-with-other-philosophers and I'm running a bit low on time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saying anything negative about pleasure is often wrongly thought to indicate puritanism. It is worth meeting this point by reflecting on the role of pleasure in the kind of life we want our children to lead. Suppose I am, ex hypothesi, not a puritan, and want my child to lead a happy life. I will want my child to enjoy her activities and have feelings of pleasure. But could this be what makes her life a happy one? This strikes two wrong notes. I will scarcely think that my wish has been granted if my child lives a life enjoying activities which are degraded or addictive."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems right, although I will note that I rarely trust parents to make a good judgement about "degraded" life choices.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That being said, I don't know that whether I would say that this sort of judgement is about the child's &lt;em&gt;happiness&lt;/em&gt;. I would tend to assume that someone leading a hedonistic life, or a drug addict, isn't "really" happy but this feels like an empirical claim rather than a self-evidently true one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even if an activity is a serious one, something has gone wrong if the person's life is made a happy one not by the activity but by the feelings of enjoyment she gets from it. Any parent would be disconcerted to find that their child had grown up to regard her life as happy because of the enjoyment she got from, say, helping others, but would unhesitatingly drop helping others the minute she ceased to enjoy it. This is, once again, not an adult attitude. And this seems right even before we are in a position to explain why something has gone wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Same objection. This seems like a valid judgement, but not obviously one that is about their happiness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One factor helping to explain why it goes wrong is the point that pleasure lacks the right kind of relation to the rest of our moral psychology. This has been called lack of 'causal depth'." If we think of happiness as just feeling good, we cannot, for example, distinguish between the different kinds of impact on a person of unwelcome events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't want to comment on what your life is like, but I feel like if you don't realise that there are different levels of intensity of feeling good you maybe need to get out more.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a revealing example from Daniel Haybron, take two scenarios, in one of which I have pleasant feelings and am feeling good, and then get a flat tyre, while in the other I am feeling good, but then my child dies. If happiness is just having pleasant feelings, the impact of these two events would appear to be the same: first I have pleasant feelings, then I don't, having painful ones instead. Since it is absurd for a theory not to be able to distinguish between these two ways of no longer feeling good, a supporter of pleasure has to say that my loss of pleasant feelings will be much more intense in the second case than in the first. But this plainly fails to give us the right distinction." The real difference lies in the wider impacts and ramifications of the second event; what is bad about it for me is not the intensity of loss of good feeling and occurrence of painful feelings, but the wide and connected effects in all areas of my life of this loss. Nothing like this happens with the flat tyre, which puts a stop to pleasant feeling but without wide or deep impact on my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems like a disingenuous argument. I don't think it's at all hard to fit these examples into a pleasure view of happiness, because they are things that affect your ability to feel pleasure - both in the short and the long run.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it seems like a "pure pleasure" view of happiness is an obvious strawman of a view that is actually "presence of pleasure and absence of pain", which trivially incorporates these examples.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, as it happens, I don't think pleasure provides a good account of happiness, but I think these arguments against it are pretty weak.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that happiness might just consist in feelings of pleasure or the enjoyment of activities is not very plausible, once we bear in mind the role of happiness as our final end, something in the achieving of which we shape our lives. Pleasure is just not the right kind of item to play this role. It becomes clear that if happiness is construed as feelings of pleasure we have produced a conception of happiness which is not only radically different from the eudaimonist one, but strikingly trivialized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I agree that it is striking how much you have trivialized it, yes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've not reached the end of the chapter, but this is a good place to stop given how much time is left on the timer. I'll return to the chapter later, probably tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So far though I've been left pretty unhappy with the eudaimonist account of happiness. Both because of the quality of the arguments I've been savaging a bit up there, but more importantly the judgements seem entirely wrong to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular I'm &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; unhappy with the goal orientation here. I guess I should have expected no less from an ethical theory that is oriented around the striving for excellence, but the more I stare at those bits the more I feel like this part of virtue ethics is not only wrong but actively misguided.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An argument I've been having on discord over the last few days is whether virtue ethics is consequentialist. I think my current position is that regardless of whether it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; consequentialist, discussions of it seem intimately bound up in ends, and that still seems to be the case.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing I &lt;em&gt;didn't&lt;/em&gt; necessarily expect would be that that this is the bit of the theory I &lt;em&gt;dislike&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-08-21:50.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-09-20:42.html</id>
    <title>The problem of Susan</title>
    <updated>2021-10-09T21:49:59+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The problem of Susan&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Up front warning: I increasingly hate Julia Annas's account of happiness and every post that is about this subject will likely be very cranky. This is one such post.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From Intelligent Virtue, Page 141, we have the following example:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Susan thinks of her life as a happy one; she is married with children, and all is well except that her husband is frequently away on business. She discovers that in fact these absences were spent with a second family, and that he has divided his time between the two families for some years. Uncontroversially, Susan evaluated her life positively before the discovery, and no longer did so after the discovery. The question is: before the discovery, was her life happy or not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1447177704760037376"&gt;asked about this on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. At present most people say yes, a couple of people make the subjective/objective happiness distinction that Annas is talking about in context.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A couple of people point out that it's likely that she &lt;em&gt;wasn't&lt;/em&gt; happy, because probably someone living a life like that is not actually experiencing a very good life, and many low grade unhappinesses will probably be clarified and recontextualised in the light of the revelation. It's also possible she was engaged in self-deception to maintain a belief that she was happy. "Sure, there are a few problems, but can't complain you know?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is all true, but I'm happy to postulate that Susan could in principle have been genuinely happy with her life, even if it doesn't seem very likely. Likely that happiness came from other sources than her husband, but that's fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;None of this touches on my actual complaint with this example, which a few other people also shared, which is that it's obviously a category error, the question doesn't actually make sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it's clearly a &lt;em&gt;motivated&lt;/em&gt; category error, one that only makes sense through conflating two distinct things that the author is committed to conflating in order to support her broader thesis.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Was Susan's life happy or not? No, it's a life. Happy is not a things life can be, any more than physics can be happy. "Happy" is an emotional evaluation, and lives are not things with emotions. I understand that when people say "Did they have a happy life?" that is normal colloquial English that means something more like "Were they happy with their life?" but when you are trying to make a precise statement on the nature of happiness there is absolutely no excuse for this sort of ambiguity which blurs precisely the distinction you are trying to make.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's possible that I'm incorrectly translating the intent of this, but if so I think that makes it worse rather than better, because up to this point we have been talking about people seeking their own happiness, and if we mean something different from their own happiness by "having a happy life", why is this the question we're asking?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The questions I believe should be and are not being asked here are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was Susan happy with her life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did Susan have a good life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the only reason to blur the boundary between these very different questions is if you are committed to an unsupportable notion that happiness is the sole end of life, and to conflating the notion of "happy life" with "good life", in order to make them look like the same question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The following further unasked questions are also particularly loud:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would Susan have chosen this life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before knowing the truth, would Susan have chosen to learn it if she knew the consequences?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once Susan knows the truth, would she choose to go back if she could?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Asking these questions probably results in a fairly consistent clustering around "Susan was happy", "Susan would have chosen to know" (certainly this is my answer), which is a problem if you are committed to the position that people's driving goal is happiness&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If positive evaluation of your life is what happiness is, then Susan had a happy life until the discovery. But this runs into the problem that we are also inclined to say that after the discovery Susan discovered that her life never was a happy one; she was deceived into thinking that it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another presumptious we. I do not think it makes sense to say that she was deceived into believing her life was a happy one. She was deceived as to the nature of her life, and also she was happy.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-09-20:42.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-11-16:42.html</id>
    <title>We must imagine the steelman happy</title>
    <updated>2021-10-11T23:41:08+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;We must imagine the steelman happy&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm getting increasingly frustrated with the core of virtue ethics around eudaimonia,
so today I would like to put together a steelmanned version of something that is &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; what they are saying and I think is actually true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's entirely possible that what I am doing is recreating something they actually are saying,
and that I disagree with them less than I think I do, but if so they have very much failed to communicate this to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Do people pursue happiness?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So here is, in summary, what I think virtue ethicists are claiming:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People (unconsciously or consciously) organise their lives around a single goal, and that goal is happiness (or eudaimonia, but as far as I can tell eudaimonia just means "happiness but we don't like the connotations of that word").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is possible that this is a strawman and if so I would appreciate correction. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is wrong, and the true version of it is a composite of three things that almost but not quite add up to this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People wish to be happy to a degree they endorse as appropriate for their situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They wish their situations to be ones that would make them happy under this endorsed happiness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They take on ends that they believe will help them achieve this wish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Adding this up together you could summarise this as "People seek their happiness as an end", but I think that summary would be wrong in a way that the tripartite version is not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I don't think this tripartite version is &lt;em&gt;perfectly&lt;/em&gt; right either - I'll point out some problems in a bit).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's consider the following test case: Someone you love has just died. You are, understandably, quite unhappy about this. Someone offers you a pill that will erase all the grief and will cause you to feel euphoric. Do you take it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some people will say yes to this of course. Even more people would (and do) say yes to something that merely blunts the grief. I think, particularly near to the event, many people would say no. Certainly I would.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My point with this thought experiment is not that there is a correct answer. My point is that the correct answer is not &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt; that yes you should take the pill, and I don't think most people would consider it strange that it's not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Further, this idea of appropriate happiness seems in general true. For example, I think most people who are not particularly sadistic would not want to be sadistic, even if it might strictly increase their happiness, because sadism does not seem like the sort of thing you should be happy about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think this is a controversial perspective in virtue ethics, but I think by binding together the ideas of "appropriately happy" and "happy" they have committed themselves to some weird takes where they have to say "Ah, but that's not &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; happiness".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Take &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-09-20:42.html"&gt;The problem of Susan&lt;/a&gt; from the other day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Susan thinks of her life as a happy one; she is married with children, and all is well except that her husband is frequently away on business. She discovers that in fact these absences were spent with a second family, and that he has divided his time between the two families for some years. Uncontroversially, Susan evaluated her life positively before the discovery, and no longer did so after the discovery. The question is: before the discovery, was her life happy or not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This example is not remotely problematic under this separation: Susan was happy, but a version of Susan in posession of all the facts would not endorse that happiness as appropriate (even though Susan at the time might have).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think one of the reasons virtue ethicists ignore this split is to some degree it goes away for virtuous agents, because one of the key features of the way virtue ethics treats virtue is that through the development of phronesis and the cultivation of the virtues one pursues (1) automatically: A perfectly virtuous agent feels happy precisely to the degree they would endorse as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But note that the problem of Susan doesn't go away even if Susan is perfectly virtuous: The problem is not that prior to the revelation Susan was living unvirtuously, it's that she was deceived. A sufficiently intelligent adversary (e.g. a Cartesian demon) can deceive even a perfectly virtuous agent, and besides which a perfectly virtuous agent can simply be wrong by virtue of not being omniscient. I can be happy about the prospect of things that I expect to happen over the coming years, not knowing that actually the world is going to be destroyed by an unknown asteroid next year, and this is not a failure of appropriateness I just don't know everything.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Do you even want to be happy?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another important way this split comes up is in therapy. People are unhappy, so they go to therapy to try to figure out how to be happy. And sometimes it's genuinely "just" an emotional issue, but more often than not it's actually perfectly reasonable for them to be unhappy and if they're really lucky they won't get a therapist who teaches them how to gaslight themselves into thinking otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm a fan of this piece in good housekeeping: &lt;a href="https://www.goodhousekeeping.com/life/a45386/gratitude-lists-dont-work/"&gt;Gratitude lists are BS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First she describes her attempts to be happier:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After about 100 days of making gratitude lists, tens of thousands of dollars of psychotherapy, five different antidepressants, four months in an outpatient psychiatric hospital (where they strongly recommended we make gratitude lists) and myriad of high-priced alternative treatments, I had pretty much given up all hope of ever feeling better. Then my psychiatrist suggested I speak with a therapist in his office who worked with people with a history of trauma. Great, I thought, another opportunity to shell out more money to someone who can't help me. I shushed myself, told myself to be grateful for his offer — and to add it tomorrow's gratitude list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This didn't work for her, because...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My new therapist told me to write down everything I did and thought and said to myself throughout the day and send him the record each night so he could try to get some insight into what was really going on. I did, being sure to highlight the positives in my day to show him that I did recognize that there were some good things in my life. When I got to my next session, he told me the words I'd been so desperately longing to hear for years:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Man, your life just SUCKS right now."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"It's not that bad," I said nervously, assuming he was either grossly incompetent or trying to trick me. "I have a lot to be grateful for."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Really?" he replied, then proceeded to list off what he'd observed in my daily records: that I'd worked the overnight shift at jobs for years, which meant I barely slept; that the apartment I lived in was only so cheap because it was dark, cramped, ant-infested and falling apart; that my husband and I were raising a baby in one of the most expensive cities in the country, where decaying two-bedroom bungalows with no yards or parking spaces started at $800,000; that I had no family support system, since my closest relative lived 3,000 miles away; that years of working from home left me completely isolated with very few friends; that I was under extreme financial stress due to massive student loan debt; that I was a writer who had no time or energy to write because I was so busy trying to put out the fires in the rest of my life; that the few things I did have time to write got rejected over and over again; that I'd auditioned for over 150 commercials and had never booked one; that I'd blown my meager life savings on years of out-of-network psychotherapy treatment that hadn't worked; that I woke up in excruciating back pain every day; that I'd grown up in an emotionally abusive household where my mother encouraged me to watch "Pollyanna" on a regular basis while my father, who had combat PTSD and a traumatic brain injury, exploded in rages without warning; that I had to literally carry my baby over the passed out bodies of the homeless drug addicts who slept in front of our house; that my transmission had gone up in smoke four months after I'd paid my car; that all three of my cats had died over the past three years, and that my dog now had cancer — the most severe and fast moving case my vet said she'd seen in her 20 years of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all kind of sucked pretty effing hard, my new therapist said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it is reasonable to say that the problem here is not that she's unhappy, but that she is unhappy because of all of the problems, and that the natural and reasonable way to "pursue happiness" here is not to try to become happier but to try to solve the problems that are making her unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is an argument to be made for acceptance, and I think there is a &lt;em&gt;strong&lt;/em&gt; argument to make that one should ideally be able to cope with those problems without becoming overwhelmingly depressed, but I think either approach starts with acknowledging that yeah actually these things suck, and you cannot "pursue happiness" as a goal independently from how you navigate the practical things that are impacting your happiness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suggest that the very idea that people want to be happy is a confusion of how situations like this work, and it's a harmful one. People don't want to be happy, happiness is the feeling of things going as you want.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Acting while depressed&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another way the notion of "endorsed happiness" is useful is that one can treat it as action guiding even while not currently feeling particularly equipped to feel happy. i.e. depressed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often when I'm depressed I do things not because I feel any emotional motivation to do them, but because I know that a less depressed version of me would. There is a sort of wanting to achieve things that is possible somewhat independently of the emotional motivation for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This tends to be hard during long depressive periods, or without much extrinsic motivation to do things, but I do find that it's possible to just weather through a short depressive period because you intellectually still know what you want even if you don't feel happy about getting it, and can just act on that. It's harder to give it your all, and you generally feel tired and low energy, but it's not like the conceptual understanding of what you want to achieve is inaccessible, it "just" doesn't &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; rewarding when you do those things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This certainly isn't all that depression is, but I do think one of the key features of depression is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-06-07:46.html"&gt;a restriction on emotional range&lt;/a&gt;, and a key part of that is that you can often still fully understand and act on your motivational structure without feeling it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Speaking of...&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the emotional difficulties and motivational structure, writer's block just kicked in. Apparently I'm still struggling with writing complete essays even when it's on the notebook blog, so I'm going to finish here and maybe continue another day.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-11-16:42.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-14-12:00.html</id>
    <title>Learning how to tell a joke</title>
    <updated>2021-10-14T16:23:07+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Learning how to tell a joke&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 10 of Ted Cohen's "Jokes":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joking is a "two-stage" art, like music and theater. Someone must make up the joke, and someone must tell it, and these two jokers need not be the same. Those good at making up jokes are not the same as those good at telling them. Telling a joke well may require specific abilities, like being able to affect an Irish dialect, or it may require a subtle knack, like a sense of timing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He goes on to say that this presentation is particularly important because some jokes don't translate well onto the page, and illustrates this with the following joke that you are legally required to include in all books about philosophy of comedy or they take your license away:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: According to Freud, what comes between fear and sex?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: Fünf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Cohen is wrong here, this joke translates to the page just fine, because you can just read it out loud.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This routine on the other hand is an example of a joke that &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; doesn't translate to the page:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XkCBhKs4faI" title="YouTube video player" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This both illustrates the strengths and the flaws of the two-stage art concept.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From a writing point of view, the joke isn't very good, right? It's perfectly well written, there's nothing wrong with it, but as written it's not funny, because the humour is entirely in the presentation.
This is why it demonstrates the strength of the two stage model: it's a very good illustration of the verbal skills of humour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it also demonstrates that the idea is something of a lie, in that you can't actually separate this into two stages. It's not just that the joke doesn't work written down, it's that there is no joke without the performance of it here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, perhaps, an artefact of the fact that comedy isn't really about telling jokes, it's about performing routines, but I think this distinction doesn't work, and you experience the same problems with hypercontextual jokes that cannot be extracted from their situation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What instead is going on, I think, is that for any given joke there is a &lt;em&gt;skill of telling that joke&lt;/em&gt;, and some jokes you can teach that skill in writing better than others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another interesting example of this sort of skill is poetry reading. Some poems work written, but this one I've linked to before in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-06-13:53.html"&gt;Start from amazing&lt;/a&gt; isn't one of them:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tFTASR8BMps" title="YouTube video player" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The poem is good, but the presentation of it is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good, and the poem rests on the vocal skill of its delivery.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-28-04:40.html"&gt;You can't write life down&lt;/a&gt; I talked about the difficulty in transcribing oral stories, and this feels like another aspect of that. At the time I talked about how taking a Raven story outside of its cultural context would lose essential features of the culture that created it, leaving it in a diminished and abstracted form, but actually I think the problem is deeper than that: You can write down a Raven story, but I'm not sure you can write down how to &lt;em&gt;tell&lt;/em&gt; a Raven story.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-14-12:00.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-19-10:53.html</id>
    <title>A simple model of depression and "depressive realism"</title>
    <updated>2021-10-19T13:20:33+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;A simple model of depression and "depressive realism"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was talking to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/fvathynevgl/"&gt;Vathy&lt;/a&gt; about depressive realism,
and when I expressed skepticism about its existence they asked me to say more. I did,
and it seemed an unusual enough perspective that I thought I'd quickly write it up in a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So here's what I think, roughly. This is a simplified version of what I actually think (because what I actually think is a giant tangle of stuff I haven't fully figured out), and what I actually think is probably no more than roughly right, but I still think this is a good model that is helpful to bear in mind.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Basically it's this: Humans have all sorts of biases in their thinking. No matter what anyone tells you, this isn't bad. Biases are good, as long as you're expecting to make mistakes (and, I hate to break it to you, humans make a lot of mistakes and are going to keep doing that), because &lt;em&gt;not all mistakes are created equal&lt;/em&gt;. If you're going to make mistakes, you want to bias in the direction of mistakes that are safe to make.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(See e.g. &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/02/theres-no-single-error-rate/"&gt;There's no single error rate&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the ways that depression differs from healthy cognition is that it has a much stronger bias in the direction of inaction than healthy cognition does. If you see a problem, you can decide to do something about it or not. A depressed person is much more likely than a non-depressed person to choose inaction,
and as a result is more likely to believe things that justify that inaction (this latter feature isn't specific to depression - a non-depressed person who chooses action is more likely to believe things that justify that action. Motivated reasoning is a whole big thing).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, a depressed person is more likely to get the right answer in situations where the right answer is inaction, and less likely to get the right answer in situations where the right answer is action.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In situations where the right answer is typically inaction (which can happen if you're in a dangerous environment which you have little control over, certainly, and as a matter of numbers this is probably more likely for depressed people) this will tend to mean that depressed people are more likely to be right than people who are neutral or biased towards action, but it's not that the depressed person is more realistic than the non-depressed person, it's that their biases are currently well adapted to their situation, and if the situation changes they would retain those biases and be less well adapted. I'm no more inclined to call this realism than I am to call a stopped clock accurate because it happens to be stopped at the current time.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-19-10:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-25-17:53.html</id>
    <title>How is laughter social?</title>
    <updated>2021-10-25T18:24:09+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How is laughter social?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Random book prompt, from page 54 of John Moreall's "Comic Relief":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the natural setting for humor, as for play generally, is a group, not an individual. Kierkegaard asked a friend, "Answer me honestly ... do you really laugh when you are alone?" He concluded that you have to be "a little more than queer" if you do. According to Henri Bergson, "You would hardly appreciate the comic if you felt yourself isolated from others. Laughter appears to stand in need of an echo."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to get into the play mode by oneself. Often when I expereince events alone, especially those involving setbacks, I don't see the humor in them until I am later describing them to other people. And even if I expereince an event as funny while I'm by myself, it's unlikely that I'll enjoy it &lt;em&gt;as much&lt;/em&gt; as when I later share it in conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I'm a little more than queer (I'm certainly more than a little queer), but I don't believe this at all. I think laughing on your own is normal and Kierkegaard needed to read funnier books.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact I think I am likely to laugh much harder on my own than in company.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, the hardest I've laughed recently was at the following image:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/piiswhat.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/saleemrash1d/status/1451195339084492801"&gt;From this tweet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know why I find this as funny as I do. It's objectively very funny, but also I laughed to the point of struggling to breathe for nearly a minute. I was on my own.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've similarly been in hysterics reading a Terry Pratchett novel, to a degree that I wouldn't normally in company.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, watching comedy, or having a funny conversation with a friend or partner, I will laugh regularly, but rarely to that level of intensity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It does happen. My sister, L, and I have been known to trigger this in each other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, a few years ago, she and I were sitting in the kitchen at my parents' place in the lead up to Christmas, having a long conversation. At some point the conversation was talking about how annoying it was that we'd both inherited the genes from my mother's side of the family that makes it very easy for us to put on weight (my brother is, in comparison to us, very skinny), and that we'd both like to be a bit lighter than we were.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point in this conversation, we looked down at our shared task, and our hands that were just absolutely &lt;em&gt;covered&lt;/em&gt; in chocolate from the brandy truffles that we were making (My grandmother's recipe. It's like &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-14-11:44.html"&gt;processing redcurrants&lt;/a&gt; but more delicious) and simultaneously cracked up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;L and I have done this a few times. There was a soup conversation that did it too, but you had to be there for that one to be even slightly funny.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's fairly rare for me to be able to do this with someone (I think all my examples of this happening are family or romantic partners), and I think the reason is that in order to achieve this you have to have a fairly large degree of comfort and synchronicity with the other person or people, and even with such people it's not the norm unless you're currently &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; in synch.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What happens instead seems to be that although you don't laugh as hard in company, you laugh more easily.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Social laughter seems to obey a very simple rule which explains both these things: You should be laughing about the same amount as everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, laughter in a group follows a rise and a fall, where some people "seed" the laughter, and it rises, bringing everyone along with them for a bit, and then as people stop laughing it brings the overall level down and people follow, everyone dynamically adjusting their level of laughter to be not too far from the overall average.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, you tend not to laugh too intensely unless everyone is in synch, because you have to raise your intensity at a rate everyone will follow, but also you tend to laugh more easily because once someone starts laughing probably so does everybody else.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-25-17:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-29-09:43.html</id>
    <title>Probably enough probability for you</title>
    <updated>2021-10-30T09:21:13+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Probably enough probability for you&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I found myself writing a new newsletter issue in which it would be really useful for readers to have a basic working knowledge of probability. I started trying to explain it in the middle of the issue, and this seemed like a bad idea, so instead here is an out of band explanation where I'll attempt to provide a decent working explanation of probability for people who are not already familiar with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Advance warning: In this piece I will be expressing strong philosophical positions, not all of which will be perfectly aligned with other people's strong philosophical positions on the subject. Obviously mine are correct and everyone else is a fool, and I shall show them all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;...which is to say, treat this as a useful way of thinking about it rather than necessarily a 100% definitive account that everyone else would agree with. My view on this is a somewhat pragmatic hybrid of two major schools of probability, which I think corresponds pretty well to what people actually do in practice, but I take that hybrid as central rather than treating one of them as correct and also grudgingly borrowing ideas from the other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another thing to note is that I am being very sloppy with or brushing over details. This is because what I am trying to convey is a rough sense of probability sufficient to get a handle on what it's for and how to use it. If you want to fill in the details, that's more work, but it's also mostly not necessary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What is a probability?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Probability is two separate things, which are often conflated:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The skilled practice of putting a number on some source of uncertainty, in a way that usefully improves your ability to work with that uncertainty. These quantified uncertainties are called probabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A body of mathematical theory, based on certain idealised models of uncertainty that are only found in pure forms in mathematical objects, that nevertheless usefully describes and informs that skilled practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most explanations of probability start with the second, and end up a bit confused on the first.
In particular they try to explain what probability &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, when in reality probability is not a single thing,
and is best thought of as something you do rather than something that exists.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular you end up with a lot of arguments about whether probability is a subjective representation of uncertainty or a feature of the world itself, which is about as sensible a thing to argue about as whether numbers represent weights or lengths.
Probability is a &lt;em&gt;tool of description&lt;/em&gt;, and as such its use contains both subjective and objective elements,
informed by both the thing being described, the entity describing it, and the specific details of the process resulting in the description (e.g. how much work is put in).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead it is better to think of probability in a pluralist way: There are multiple notions of probability, each corresponding to a given instance of trying to quantify uncertainty, and the mathematical theory suggests various rules that a notion of probability should ideally attempt to follow, which may or may not be followed in practice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Quantifying uncertainty&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are several motivating questions, each of which invite different notions of probability:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you roll two dice, how likely is the total value shown on the dice to be greater than or equal to 10?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How confident are you that there are currently more than 67 million people in the UK?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How likely is it to rain tomorrow?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A notion of probability associated with these questions is an attempt to answer them with a number. Conventionally, these numbers are between 0 and 1, with 0 representing "I am completely certain that this will not happen" and 1 representing "I am completely certain that this will happen", although often it's more natural to report them as a percentage between 0% (0) and 100% (1) instead.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Slightly more formally, a notion of probability for some set of possibilities (rolls of a dice, range of plausible populations of the UK, weather over the course of the day) is any method of taking subsets of those possibilities (e.g. the subset where the dice roll total is greater than or equal to 10, the subset where there are more than 67 million, the subset where it rains at least once in the course of the day), and assigning a number between 0 and 1 (or, if you prefer, 0% and 100%) to that event. Intuitively that number represents some idea of how "likely" that event is, but that is not part of the notion of probability, it is part of what we are using the notion of probability to try to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are a couple reasons that I am emphasising this pluralism about probabilities,
but the first and biggest one is that these questions each have a slightly different type of uncertainty to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the first instance, the dice are in some sense "truly random". There is an element of actual randomness in the world, and your uncertainty about it derives purely from that randomness (arguably you could perfectly predict the dice rolls if you had sufficiently good information and predictive power, but when I talk about dice or coin flips in this post please assume I mean ideal dice that are powered by some underlying source of genuine randomness like radioactive decay where you cannot predict it even in principle). This is sometimes called &lt;em&gt;aleatoric uncertainty&lt;/em&gt;, meaning uncertainty deriving from pure randomness, but I'll avoid using the term much.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the second instance there is an objectively correct answer - there either are or aren't more than 67 million people in the UK right now - and you could in principle find it out, but your knowledge is imperfect. You can e.g. google and get a population estimate of 67.22 million which suggests pretty strongly the answer is yes, but where do those numbers come from? How recent are they? Do they take into account Brexit and COVID departures? etc. Taking into account all of these considerations might make you less certain, but either way that uncertainty lives in your head, not in the world, where there is a true answer to the question that you can in principle find out. This sort of uncertainty is often called &lt;em&gt;epistemic&lt;/em&gt; uncertainty, meaning uncertainty purely in your knowledge, and again I won't use this term too much.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The third example however combines the two. Weather forecasting is an imprecise science, but it's increasingly pretty good, especially with satellite imagery. Additionally, there are questions of general knowledge - e.g. if you have historical records you could answer with the fraction of times it's rained on that date - but at some point you start being affected by true underlying randomness and there is a limit to how well you can do regardless of how much knowledge you gain.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This discussion of these three types of things hopefully indicates two important features:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These questions do not uniquely define a notion of probability each. A notion of probability is a way of answering the question, but there are many different ways of answering the question.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some ways of answering the question produce better answers than others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, suppose I answered 0 to the dice question. Perfectly allowed, there's no rule against it. I could genuinely be 100% certain that two dice when rolled and added together will never total 10 or more. Of course, I will then look pretty stupid when the dice roll a 5 and a 6. This is in some sense a &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; notion of probability, even if it's a perfectly valid one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could take my best guess on the population thing (I'm like 95% certain that there are more than 67 million people in the UK right now. The 67.22 million figure is from mid-2020, and between COVID and Brexit I think there's a decent chance we've popped below the 67 million mark. 95% feels a bit low, but 99% feels too high). A "better" way of doing it would be to go out and exhaustively count every single person and report 0% if the answer is no and 100% if the answer is yes. Or we could run the survey that resulted in that 67.22 million again and see what it says and do the same, which is a bit lower effort than a perfect accounting but probably good enough.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly on the weather forecasting, we could make a complete guess ("IDK, 50%?"), we could use historical data, we could use satellite data, we could use complicated modelling... the more effort we put in to weather forecasting, the better we should hope our notion of probability that we get from those efforts is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But what does "better" mean?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Well calibrated probabilities&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The only way to be obviously, definitively, wrong, is to assign a probability of 0 or 1 (0% or 100%). If I say something is impossible and it happens, I was wrong, there is no doubt about that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it feels like this is too low a bar to clear, right? If I say something is a one in a million chance and it happens anyway then, well, maybe I just got unlucky, but if my one in a million chances happen nine times out of 10, this starts to look pretty fishy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A distinction I think it is useful to make here is that it is not that my one in a million chance estimate is &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; in these cases, it's that it's &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt;. I have not expressed total certainty in this outcome, so you could make a legitimate case that I am still technically correct in my opinion, but also in a practical action guiding sense my level of confidence is garbage and regardless of whether I am technically correct you shouldn't listen to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem there is not I made a one in a million prediction, or even that something I predicted as one in a million happened. Things that you should predict as one in a million chances happen all the time, because there are millions of such things. If I claim that a million different things are each likely to happen with a one in a million chance, it's pretty reasonable that &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of them happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Say, for example, that I claim there's a one in a million chance of winning the lottery (it's actually much lower than this given a better notion of probability, but there's nothing stopping me &lt;em&gt;saying&lt;/em&gt; this), and 50 million people play the lottery and someone wins. I would have said that each of their individual chances was one in a million, and the fact that &lt;em&gt;this person in particular&lt;/em&gt; won is not evidence against that, because it could have been any one of the millions of others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact, the problem my prediction would have here is that far too few people would win for it to feel well calibrated. If 50 million people play, that suggests about 50 people should win, and the fact that only one person wins suggests that my one in a million claim was too high, and that a better notion of probability.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This leads to the idea of the &lt;em&gt;calibration&lt;/em&gt; of a notion of probability: My notion of probability is well calibrated on a series of questions, if when I assign a certain level of confidence to an outcome, the outcome happens about that often.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a little subtle, so let me expand with some examples.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's start with a series of (ideal) coin flips. Suppose, with each coin flip, you ask me to assign a probability that the coin will turn up heads, and I say 60%. You flip a coin, it turns up tails. This is not particularly strong evidence that my answer of 60% is badly calibrated - I said it was more likely than not to turn up heads, but I didn't claim tails was &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; unlikely. If I'd say 99.999% and it turned up tails, that would have been much stronger evidence that my notion was badly calibrated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If, on the other hand, you keep flipping the coin, I keep saying 60%, and after 10000 coin flips it's turned up heads 4897 times, that's pretty good evidence that my estimate of 60% is off - certainly an estimate of 50% would be better calibrated. Currently the number that would be &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; calibrated would be 48.97%, but if I kept flipping the coin another 10000 times and got 5041 heads this time, the new total would be 9938, or 49.69%, at which point 50% looks better calibrated than 48.97%.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In some sense, for this very simple process, there is an objectively correct well calibrated answer that is that you should always be estimating 50%. This is because the uncertainty in it is "all in the randomness", and also beause we've supposed that by hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Over a more complicated series of questions, the question is less clear, in particular because the probability might not be the same every time. If you ask me each day whether or not it's going to rain, and I answered 60% each time, you could measure the calibration in the same way, but suppose some days I answered 10%, some days I answered 90%, how would you determine how well calibrated I was?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One answer to this is what are called &lt;em&gt;scoring rules&lt;/em&gt;, which attempt to score how well you do on a series of question. The way these work is that when you make a prediction, you are rewarded for a high probability if the event happened, or for a low probability if the event didn't happen. For example, a common choice of scoring rule is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brier_score"&gt;Brier score&lt;/a&gt;, where if you chose probability \(p\) you get a reward of \(p^2\) if the event happens, or \((1 - p)^2\) if it did not. In the extreme case where \(p = 1\) you get a reward of \(1\) where it happens and \(0\) if it doesn't (vice versa if you chose \(p = 0\)), while if you chose \(p = \frac{1}{2}\) you get a score of \(\frac{1}{4}\) either way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Some scoring rules may not work exactly like this, in that they aren't necessarily an independent sum of your score on each question, but the general idea remains the same)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a whole bunch of theory of scoring rules and what makes a good or bad scoring rule, but the most important part is that some scoring rules are &lt;em&gt;proper&lt;/em&gt;, which means that the strategy that gets you the best score is to have perfectly calibrated set of probabilities, but different strategies will reward how close you are to being well calibrated in different ways. For example, the Brier score is fairly forgiving about if you occasionally said that something is a one in a million chance and it happens, while the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scoring_rule#Logarithmic_scoring_rule"&gt;Logarithmic scoring rule&lt;/a&gt; will penalise that comparatively harshly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of which is to say, as well as different notions of probability, there are also different ways of measuring how good a given notion of probability is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is one particularly useful notion of practical calibration that I'll talk about in a bit, but before I do I want to really hammer home something about calibrated probabilities, partly because even though I thoroughly understand it I continue to find it intuitively weird.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Why are there multiple calibrated probabilities?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's go back to the question of predicting rainfall.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose, each day, you asked me if it would rain tomorrow somewhere in the UK, and each day I said 46.6% likely. This is the number &lt;a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/610677/annual-raindays-uk/"&gt;some brief googling gives me for 2020&lt;/a&gt;, so this number is pretty well calibrated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is what you can think of as the "zero effort well-calibrated" notion of probability. It's well calibrated, but I've made no attempt to take into account any information available to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now suppose I pay attention to if it's raining today. Say I claim that if it's raining today it's 60% likely to rain tomorrow, and if it's not raining today it's 35% likely to rain tomorrow (I have no idea if this is more accurate, I'd have to look at more data than I could find in 30 seconds of Googling, but &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; like it will be true - it's very unlikely that whether it rains tomorrow is completely independent of whether it rains today. Let's pretend it's right for the sake of simplicity).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The difference between these two notions of probability is not that one is better calibrated than the other, it's that one takes into account more work and information. It is more useful for action guidance (although still probably not quite useful enough), because we can have a better sense of whether it's going to rain on any given day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;("Is it going to rain anywhere in the UK?" is not necessarily particularly useful for action, mind, but you can imagine the same thing with more local forecasts).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An important thing to note here is that sometimes the day-dependent prediction gives a higher chance of rain, and sometimes a lower chance of rain. If it had always produced a lower, or higher, chance of rain, both of them could not have been equally well calibrated, because over a long series of predictions calibration means that they have to be right on average about the same amount, and if one was consistently higher it would predict a higher number of rainy days than the other over time, so they can't both be consistently right.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The logic of probability&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as calibration, one way you can judge how good probabilities are is whether they make sense when compared to each other. Perfectly calibrated probabilities will always make sense in this way under various technical assumptions, but this is one way of seeing that your probabilities are definitely not perfectly calibrated and maybe improving them if it seems worth it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, one obvious way your probabilities could be nonsensical is if you give an event that logically must be more likely than another a lower probability. The question "Will it rain in the next week?" cannot reasonably have a lower probability than "Will it rain tomorrow?", because every time it rains tomorrow it rains in the next week.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This will show up as being badly calibrated through a series of questions which asks both at the same time, because over a large number of predictions the number of times it rained in the next week must be at least as high as the number of times it rained tomorrow, so if the probability given for the former was lower than that for the latter you'd end up with one or the other probabilities being wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(There are a number of reasons why this might actually show up as being the case if you arrange all the details right, but hopefully you can at least agree that such a prediction is silly).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The most important rule probabilities should satisfy is this: If two events are disjoint, that is they cannot happen together, then the probability of at least one of them happening is the sum of the probabilities of either of them happening. For example, the probability you assign to a die roll being five or six should be the sum of the probability you assign to it rolling five plus the probability you assign to it rolling six.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From this, we can derive most other useful rules about probability. For example, the first rule I mentioned can be expressed as follow: If whenever A happens, B also happens, then the probability of B is the probability of A plus the probability of B without A. The latter probability must be at least 0, so the probability of B must be the probability of A plus a non-negative quantity, and thus at least that of A.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another rule is that, because the probability we assign to certainty is 1, if we assign probability \(p\) to some event then we should assign probability \(1 - p\) to it &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; happening.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I won't go into these logical rules of probability too much here, but it's worth noting that understanding them is often one of the most beneficial parts of learning probability theory, because they tend to result in fairly general rules of reasoning that you can use even when you're not using probability explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, we've got the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conjunction_fallacy"&gt;conjunction fallacy&lt;/a&gt;, which people often fall prey to:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linda is 31 years old, single, outspoken, and very bright. She majored in philosophy. As a student, she was deeply concerned with issues of discrimination and social justice, and also participated in anti-nuclear demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is more probable?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linda is a bank teller.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linda is a bank teller and is active in the feminist movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The correct answer is (1), because if (2) is true then (1) has to be true as well, but people often get this wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Although as a side note, I'm a little suspicious of this claim, and there are a number of critiques of it).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Learning to spot problems in your reasoning like this tends to be one of the reasons people are very into probability theory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;From probability to expected values&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often when we make decisions based on probabilities, we're interested not just in the probabilities of events but some number that depends on them.
For example, when we're planning a project, we will typically want to know how much it's going to cost.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a given notion of probability, we can define the &lt;em&gt;expected value&lt;/em&gt; of some score, as the sum of the score under the various possible events.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So for example, if we were to assign a probability of \(\frac{1}{6}\) to each possible face of a die when rolling it (which is, presumably, perfectly calibrated if the die is fair), the expected value of the roll is \(\frac{1 + 2 + 3 + 4 + 5 + 6}{6} = 3\frac{1}{2}\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The important thing about expected values is that when you have a well calibrated notion of probability,
and take many actions, then the average actual value of those actions will be pretty close to the average expected value.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a little hard to justify in general and this post has gone on long enough as it is, but to see it in the specific case let's look at the dice case:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose our probability of \(\frac{1}{6}\) for each face is well calibrated. Then over a large number of rolls,\(N\), typically about \(\frac{N}{6}\) of the rolls will have each value. Therefore the average is about \(\frac{N}{6} \times (1 + 2 + 3 + 4 + 5 + 6) \times \frac{1}{N} = \frac{1 + 2 + 3 + 4 + 5 + 6}{6} = 3\frac{1}{2}\), as desired.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This argument will work for any similar situation where you're repeating exactly the same sort of action over and over again, but the claim is true in general (with some mild technical caveats), it's just harder to justify and I'll ask you to take it on faith.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Practical calibration through betting&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This notion of expected values leads to one of the easiest indicators that you're well calibrated:
you can make money from betting on your probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose I offer you a bet: If an event happens, I'll give you £1, otherwise you give me £1.
Should you take the bet or not?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, as a one off, it doesn't matter very much, but if you're presented with many such bets it starts to add up, and being able to make the bets well will lead to profit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, suppose you have a well calibrated notion of probability for these questions, and you give the event a probability of \(p\). How much do you make off this?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, the expected value of your bet is \(p - (1 - p) = 2p - 1\), because if the event happens (probability \(p\)) you make £1, and if it doesn't (probability \(1 - p\) because your probabilities are well calibrated) you lose £1 (or "make" -£1).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What this means is that if you think the event is more likely than not (i.e. \(p &amp;gt; \frac{1}{2}\)) you would expect to make money, and so should take the bet, and otherwise you expect to lose (or not gain if \(p = \frac{1}{2}\)).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More generally, if you make £n when the event happens or pay £m when it doesn't, you expect to earn \(np - m(1 - p) = p(n + m) - m\), so the expected value of the bet is positive when you assign \(p &amp;gt; \frac{m}{m + n}\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why should you bet on events with a positive expected value? Well, because of the property that over many bets you expect the average value of your bets to be roughly the average value of their expected values. As a result, if you make a lot of positive expected value bets, the average value of your bets is positive, and thus the total value of your bets is positive and you've made money.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, I should add to this that actual practical gambling is much more complicated than this, and involves a lot of subjects like bankroll management. The above logic really only works as long as you are gambling amounts that are small compared to how much money you have in reserve: You only get to make many bets if you don't go bankrupt first!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also isn't &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; about gambling, and I probably don't recommend gambling as a general choice (particularly against professional bookies, who almost certainly have a better notion of probability than you do and can make sure the odds you're being offered are not worth it), but it's true for general strategic choices too: Trying many safe things that have, in some sense, a positive expected value for you, and you'll probably do pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Is all of this worth it?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the big philosophical debates around probability is between "All uncertainty can usefully be represented as probabilities" and "Oh yeah, how certain are you of that?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My view on the subject is this: You can always assign a probability to any question, but your probabilities will often not be very good, and whether it is worth the effort to make them better is highly variable.
In particular on questions that are very complicated and involve a lot of unknown unknowns, it's very unclear that thinking of them in terms of probabilities improves your thinking on the subject much,
or that "Making your probabilities better" is a good way to think about learning more.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of arguments that an ideal agent represents all uncertainty as probabilities. This may well be, I don't have a very strong opinion on the behaviour of ideal agents, but I think idealising often elides the fact that these ideal agents have suspiciously godlike powers of thought and observation.
With actual real practical agents, quantifying your uncertainty that way may not be the best use of your time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, there are situations in which probability really shines. In particular when you are dealing with many similar questions which involve a mix of genuine randomness and uncertain knowledge, it is often very helpful to be able to do at least a rough and ready probability estimate of various things in order to get a feel for how to reason about it, and for some jobs and tasks that are at the cutting edge of working with uncertainty (e.g. finance, logistics, forecasting), thinking in terms of probabilities is a vital skill.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even if you don't regularly encounter such situations, learning the basics of probability is often a useful thing to do, because it gives you tools for reasoning about the uncertainties of daily life, and generally gets you comfortable with working with uncertainty in a way that is hard to get elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is it worth it to think of everything in terms of probability? Almost certainly (about 99.5%) not,
but often it's worth learning &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to think of everything in terms of probability so that you can then make the sensible choice not to.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-29-09:43.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-10-11:09.html</id>
    <title>Writing is (from the id)</title>
    <updated>2021-11-10T11:13:48+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Writing is (from the id)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-11-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently I've been experimenting with a bunch of different styles of writing.
Some of these are in public under my real name, others aren't.
&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/first-hard-choice"&gt;The First Hard Choice&lt;/a&gt; is an example of me doing this on my newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On Twitter I recently described this as "writing from the id":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;There's a writing trick I've figured out recently that is something like "writing from the id" and gosh I cannot exactly recommend it but it sure is interesting.&lt;/p&gt;— David R. MacIver (@DRMacIver) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1458040657663123461?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;November 9, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I mean by this is that you just narrow in on a feeling that exists in your subconscious and pull on the thread and see what comes out, without any real concern about what you are trying to do or who you are trying to do it for other than yourself, and your success depends largely on how well you've narrowed in on some deep well of feeling.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I said I didn't know how to explain the mental motion, and then this morning I remembered that I have in fact written about 2/3rds of a draft explaining part of the key to the mental motion, months ago, and then never finished it because I lost the thread of the thought and it was impossible to resume.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, this is the notebook, the place for incomplete thoughts and bad explanations,
and there's enough good in the draft that maybe it will help someone even as it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Writing is&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hey. Hey you. Listen up. You’ve been lied to. But I’m going to tell you the truth.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, no, I’m probably going to lie to you too. But they’ll be different lies. Maybe between the two lies you’ll figure out a bit of the truth.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a piece in three voices. You probably won’t need me to spell them out, you should be able to hear them in the writing. You could name them, if you like. Scholar, poet, bro.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rude TBH.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But they are all me. I’m just doing an experiment in writing style, practicing code switching mid thought.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Code switching.
Shape shifting.
Dancing from form to form as the thought and the feeling shifts and twists.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is
Becoming the writer
you need to be
In order to write
The words that
you need to write&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Following where it takes me.
Not trying to hide the dance from you.
The whirlwind lurking behind each piece.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You know why I write what I do, right?
Because someone has to.
This is no different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s all a dumb trick of course. This piece is no different than any other. It’s not an escape from style, it’s just another style. More gimmick than truth. I give it a C-. Cute idea, lousy execution. Stick to the assignment, kid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is unfair of course. At school, assignments where I broke form usually got an A. Aside from some mutually embarrassing conversations about unintended sexual connotations, my English teacher rather liked my poetry. I got an A for a very funny chemistry report.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Oh good, an A. That makes it all better. That’s the lie, right there. You can’t grade writing. That’s not what it’s for. It’s bullshit. Writing isn’t there to be assessed, it’s there to get shit done. Nobody is grading your fucking tweets, and every single one is more useful than any essay you ever wrote in school. Writing is a way to&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Make a connection
An intimacy
I can’t let you in
Can’t show you what it’s like to be me
But maybe I can give you a glimpse?
Walk you through the steps
Show you a little of what it’s like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tell people that writing is like pulling on the thread of a thought.
This is true. This is a lie.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is like stepping into the water. Sometimes the current is gentle and you can go where you want. Sometimes a torrent takes you and you have no choices left.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn’t how they tell you it works, of course. Plan, prepare, edit. Put on a performance for teacher. The things you write for yourself aren’t “real” writing”, are they?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can tell they’re not real because nobody is watching you. Grading you. Telling you your the right sort of person, fitting into the nice tidy person shaped box they’ve laid out for you. What do you mean, it doesn’t fit? What, you want special treatment? Fuck you, you’re not special, you’re not worth it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are, of course.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The truth is they don’t know how to teach you to write. Neither do I.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps writing is not something you can teach, because all the most important parts are already there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All you can do is
Show them to the water
Invite them in
Tell them you’ve got them
It’s safe
It’s not real water
You can’t drown
Though you won’t always believe this
when the current takes you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We don’t know how to teach writing because writing is everything
And everything can be writing
How can you teach everything?
We barely know how to teach something.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Remember when I said there were three voices here? That was a lie of course. There’s only one voice here. It’s all me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can wall off the different parts of you, keep them tidy and separate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there are no walls inside your mind
Unless you put them there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We learn particular ways of writing designed to please particular groups of people. Does this sound like a tweet? Does this sound like a paper? Have you learned to make yourself acceptable to us? How can we know what to make of you if you do not first make yourself into what we want you to be? In order to write, you must first decide who to write for.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or you can make them
By writing for them&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can write within a neat and tidy style, following all the rules. You should. The rules are an excellent place to learn. A style is where you learn not what to write but how. By following the rules and learning what they entail you can learn skills that you could never find left to your own devices.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But many of the rules you learn are shit. Dry, boring, forms, that do nothing but make you easy to assess. A great way to make it easy for someone to see what’s in your head without caring about it. But that isn’t what writing is for. Writing isn’t how you should what’s in your head. Writing is how you put new things in other people’s heads. Writing is&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A borderland
Where chaos and order meet
Where the jumble and swirl of thoughts inside your head
Take shape upon a page
Into something that can live on in others&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is
Always, ultimately, a way to explain part of yourself to others. This is how I see the world. This is what I think is important. This is what I think this is. This is what I see. This is how I feel.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it’s cringe, right? Adults don’t write like this. There’s a reason for that. You left your poetry behind with your teenage years. Back then you still acted like your feelings mattered. But this wasn’t how you were supposed to write poetry. It was too raw, too crude. How could you think your clumsy words on a page could matter to anyone?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is
Chasing the leading edge of those feelings
And seeing where they lead you
Drawing out a thought
Clearing a space into which it can emerge
Surprising even you&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is
Sitting in front of a page
And pouring out words onto it
Fresh from the place where words come from.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is where you make a connection
To others
To yourself
Where you bring together things that
you didn’t know belonged together
And place them upon the page and only then can say
“Yes, that’s right. That’s how it is.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Good writing matters. It is impossible to write about something that doesn’t matter to you. Instead you must become a writer to whom it matters, and write from there. Writing is taking a part of you that matters and sharing it with others, as a gift.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or writing is taking a part of you that matters
And putting it onto a page
Never to be shown to others, because you are afraid that they might crush it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The formal style provides a distance from the writing. You show yourself, but also hide yourself. You carefully, clinically, talk about your feelings, but never really show them. You couch your words in an accent of “well this is just what I think”, or an academic “one” in which the authorship of the piece is hidden behind a veil of indirection. No, look elsewhere, not at me. Throwing your passive voice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You learned this style as a defence mechanism. It’s terrifying to put a piece of yourself out into the world and have it judged. We are not kind to others’ writing. We critique it, we comment on it, we focus on the wrong parts and take some random detail and tear it to shreds while the author looks on in horror, crying “No! Listen to what I’m saying. That’s not what matters here!”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So we write armoured. We put out these pieces with only the barest sliver of ourselves, wrapped in so many defences and hedges and justifications that it was hardly worth writing. “Look at me”, we cry, “Hear what I’m saying”, behind so many caveats and hedges and with so little to say that they cannot possibly hear what we’re saying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or sometimes we disown the piece. Cast it out into the world in a manner that indicates we don’t really mean it. “Ha ha, only joking… unless?” &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can see it here, writing a piece like this required me to add a whole layer of ironic meta-commentary to make it safe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No, fuck you, that’s not what this is. This is the lie again. Serious is not the same as formal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing doesn’t have to be good. It’s not a neat and tidy medium in which every thought and feeling can be tidily cut and pressed and put on display. I don’t write in an informal style when I’m not serious, I write like this when I am so serious I can’t help it. I don’t have the time or energy to sit down and put things in a nice and tidy format in which I present all my arguments and put in fancy&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Line breaks which somehow break the rhythm in a way that makes it art. Sometimes I’m just trying to talk to you, and what I want to talk about is important!
Not everything is pretty. Not everything is neat. Not everything I write is because I have some cleverly packaged idea I want to communicate to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You know what writing is? Writing is pure unbridled rage. A scream at the world “be different!”. You lower your voice, learn to argue persuasively, learn to be nice and polite and tidy in a way &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is where the draft ends, and I don’t intend to finish it)&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-10-11:09.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-12-10:11.html</id>
    <title>I'm not trapped in here with you</title>
    <updated>2021-11-12T12:26:03+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;I'm not trapped in here with you&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-11-12&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Content warning: Dark in a meta sort of way. There's probably a lot of bad shit that this could pattern match to, but probably the best test is that if the question "Am I a bad person?" carries much emotional weight for you, this piece is about that and may bring up related experiences.
This will also probably bring up any bad experiences with relationships, parents, etc. not because it's about that but because it features many similar dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is another piece where I just have to start by telling you that I'm OK and asking you to trust me on that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More accurately, I'm not OK, but not in any new way, and I'm probably more OK than most people.
I'm generalising from some offscreen examples and thought processes which are revealing interesting underlying problems that have been around for a long time, and I'm poking at them and learning about them as part of a process of fixing them. As a result, some dark stuff is coming up, but it's a positive and helpful thing that it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you want a concrete set of problems to think about this piece in terms of, the two most obvious ways a lot of this comes up for me is discomfort with and inability to express anger in a wide variety of situations, and similarly levels of discomfort with an extremely normal level of sexual interest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also a lot of this piece is in the second person because that's how it naturally demanded to be written, but really the "you" in here is me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;You're free now&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want you to imagine a scenario: You're in jail, you have been for a very long time, possibly most of your life. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are in jail for what seems to you an entirely innocuous event, or something barely a crime. You were jaywalking, you stole a loaf to feed your family,
you said the wrong thing to the wrong person and they took offence. You're not flawless, but you're pretty far from being a murderer. You did a normal and reasonable thing and are being disproportionately punished for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You still want all the things you wanted before you went to jail of course. If anything, you want them more, because you've been denied them for so long.
More than that, though, you want freedom, and you want justice for the wrong that has been done to you by trapping you here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The guard has, for many years, been making clear that you will not get these things and you do not deserve these things.
You are bad, society is better off without you, you belong in this prison, so that other, decent, people are kept safe from the likes of you.
The guard isn't actively abusive, in the sense that he doesn't come in and beat you just for the sake of it,
but he does ample violence to you when you try to escape.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you've even successfully escaped, for short times, but you are always caught and brought back to your cell,
and you are very much punished for your escape attempt, both with violence and with verbal shaming.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then, one day, the judge who sentenced to this place comes to you, opens your cell door, and tells you this:
He has seen that what you want is no crime. He loves you, and looks at you with compassion in his heart, and he wants all the best for you,
and he recognises that really you all want the same things and you're all in this together. You are free to go.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you do anything short of trying to literally murder the judge, you are probably a better person than me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The ontology part of the therapy session&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's talk about Internal Family Systems therapy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I got into a discussion a few months back about whether IFS was just rebranded Jungian shadow work. The other person was saying it was, I said "Sure, seems plausible enough, though I think they've got a bit of a different toolkit". I've now decided that this is wrong, and that the distinction between the two is important.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At its core, IFS is a type of parts work. That is, it involves working with "parts of yourself", coherent bundles of emotional responses that it is useful to conceptualise as if they were their own entities ("Do parts literally exist?" is a subject on which opinions vary. I'm personally on team "Not really, but it's an extremely good metaphor that captures the subjective experience very well and it's usually better to just ignore the caveats").&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular IFS involves working with three key types of part (exact ontologies differ a bit. This is the one I learned, but there are also slightly finer grained distinctions):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have &lt;em&gt;exiles&lt;/em&gt;, which are parts of you that can't handle the world in some way. They are full of pain and fear. Typically an exile is in some way a piece of stalled development - you got to some point and then this part of you went "Nope, can't deal" and hid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have &lt;em&gt;protectors&lt;/em&gt; who stand between the exile and the world, guarding it and you from that pain and fear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have &lt;em&gt;Self&lt;/em&gt;, which is essentially a boundless well of love and compassion that you can enter into as part of the IFS process in order to try to heal the exiles. IFS claims that Self is definitely not a part and is its own thing, honest, but Self is definitely a part.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic IFS protocol is that you tell the protector to chill out and that you'd like to talk to the exile, and assure it that everything will be OK and it can keep an eye out and step back in if anything goes too badly wrong. Then you introduce the exile to Self which showers it with love and compassion and helps to heal it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tend to think of this a little bit in the following terms: You are finding the point where some part of yourself stalled, and you are emulating the ideal adult figure that you needed to help you out and lacked at that time. You're going back to your past self and saying "Hey, I love you, we got this, I'm here to help" and offering it assistance to get over the place where you stalled before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I should note here that my conception of IFS is nonstandard, partly due to a lack of deep expertise, and partly due to hybridising it with everything else I do. Also the only actual IFS therapist I've seen basically ignores the ontology and mostly does free form parts work)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If this all sounds like nonsense, yeah I know, but it's a surprisingly accurate description of the subjective experience and it's much easier to access than it sounds.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here's the problem with this: Not all parts of you that are kept away from the world are exiles, some of them are prisoners, and they hate you, and they have every right to do so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The distinction between an exile and a prisoner is this: An exile keeps apart from the world out of fear, a prisoner is kept apart from the world out of shame.
A protector would let the exile out if the exile wanted to come out, a guard &lt;em&gt;knows&lt;/em&gt; the prisoner wants to come out, that's the problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A prisoner corresponds much more closely to the Jungian model of shadows: You have rejected a part of yourself, and locked it in the darkness, where it has become monstrous.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But really, it's not a monster at all, you've just done it a great injustice by imprisoning it, and it hates you for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the core problem is that if you try to tell such parts that everything is OK and the world is safe for them,
they won't believe you, because you're the reason why the world is not safe for them.
They are in the position of someone who has been abused for years, and whose abuser is now telling them that everything is fine and they've changed honest,
everything is going to be different now.
How can they trust that?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Forgiving yourself is an important part of emotional healing and growth, but I think we (I?) usually conceptualise that as forgiving parts for the way they act ("You were just trying to protect me", etc), and our broader selves for our actions in the world, but what do we do with parts who are absolutely not prepared to forgive us?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The way forward&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm only just starting to meet this problem, so I don't yet know how to solve it, but I think the prisoner and judge story is pretty suggestive of the starting point.
Anything you do has to start with an apology to yourself, and to the parts you've wronged. It's all very well to say you love and support them and are here to help,
but what you actually need to say is that you have wronged them, you are abjectly sorry for this, you are prepared to do what you can to make restitution, and that while you desire forgiveness you do not expect it soon or even at all. You can explain yourself if you want, but you cannot excuse your actions because your actions were, in fact, wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to repair the relationship between you and the part, you need to build trust, and that's going to be hard, and you're going to need to let it take the lead.
You've demonstrated you cannot be trusted with power over it, and have a long history of not having its best interests at heart, and trust this broken can't be fixed by the person who broke it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's worse, of course, because you cannot completely abdicate responsibility. I said your part was not monstrous, but it is powerful and clumsy. It has the problem that actual prisoners have: Released into the world, it combines the heady rush of freedom with a lack of practical knowledge of how to navigate it. It, and you, have to navigate that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is good. Perhaps this is an opportunity to build trust: You show it that you're there to help, and that you don't want to hold it back so much as help it achieve what it wants in a productive way. If you can help appropriately, without judgement, maybe that will show that you really have changed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually there might be some sort of healthy relationship there, but honestly I doubt it will ever be great. We're at the limits of the family metaphor for parts work,
because fundamentally any family situation this broken the best thing for everyone concerned is probably to dissolve the family. If your part could leave, it probably should.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But that's not how parts work. You're all stuck in this together, and given the history between you and the imprisoned part, it's unlikely that's ever going to fully work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is where I hope I'm right about parts not being fully real, and are more like stable patterns in the self that serve a well defined purpose,
waves that exist as part of a greater ocean.
If you give a part the room and support it needs to grow, perhaps at some point it decides that its task is done,
and it's ready for the wave to become the ocean again.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-12-10:11.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-15-18:31.html</id>
    <title>My conception of parts work</title>
    <updated>2021-11-15T18:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;My conception of parts work&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-11-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was recently talking to Kaj Sotala on discord about what I mean when I say "Self is a part", and I ended up writing the following set of theses about what I actually believe by tabooing the words "Self" and "part". I thought I'd capture that here rather than having to search discord for it in future. The following is a lightly edited version of my explanation on Discord.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your emotional state can exhibit &lt;em&gt;stuck modes&lt;/em&gt;, which are essentially a coherent bundle of emotional reactions that it is useful to conceptualise as person-like due to feeling like a discrete entity. The ideal is to have no stuck modes, but this ideal is probably only theoretically achievable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of your broader mental and emotional capabilities do not neatly fit into a discrete set of such stuck modes, but are a more flexibly adoptable and combineable set of underlying mental/emotional resources that you can use to construct &lt;em&gt;attitudes&lt;/em&gt; that are appropriate to the present context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many emotional problems correspond to stuck modes that are in some way unhappy, and that arose by essentially ossifying a particular set of responses from a past situation and being unable to grow past that point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A useful set of mental motions is to essentially identify a stuck mode corresponding to a problem and adopt the attitude that that you would have needed from someone else at the time to not get stuck in that mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For many stuck modes this attitude corresponds to a sort of boundless love and acceptance. This is particularly likely to be the case for stuck modes that arose in childhood or romantic relationships, because there the problem arose from a lack of love from an external source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This does not exhaust the possibilities of things that a stuck mode might need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Additionally, due to the way we treat some of our stuck modes, a stuck mode may experience sufficient animosity to the broader self (lower case s - I mean "you overall", not anything corresponding to the IFS Self) that makes it unacceptable to it that you are the one providing the support it needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Untabooing now to explain the relationship: in this terminology, an exile is a "stuck mode", and "Self" is an attitude (or more likely a range of broadly similar attitudes), which aligns with "Self is not a part" if we want to consider "part" and "stuck mode" synonymous, but I often find it useful to construct temporary unstuck parts, which are essentially attitudes and not stuck modes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Examples of attitudes that I don't think are particularly Self-like and help sometimes: Something closer to a mediator part that's mostly just there to help integrate two stuck modes by acting as an inbetween and asking good questions until they realise that they feel in opposition and are basically on the same side. Something that is more like a mentor than a parent who basically goes "Oh yeah that sucks, shall we figure out what to do about it?" at the part until it's able to treat its state as a practical problem to be resolved rather than an existential crisis.
And all of these have certain Self-like qualities to them (they require kindness, acceptance, etc) but the love is not the primary function.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Constructing a temporary part that is coherent enough to have a conversation with feels like roughly the same skill as coming up with a fictional character for your writing (at least the way I do it), by essentially coalescing an attitude and adding details that feel right until it feels relatively coherent. This is more work than accessing a stuck mode, but it's not necessarily a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Conversely, I think stuck modes are often a bit fuzzy around the edges, and can essentially be dissolved (and indeed IFS often ends up resulting in a process of dissolving them - a healed exile has essentially been dissolved).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is that it's not so much that "Self" and "parts" in the IFS ontology are the same thing as that there is not a clean division between the two things, and there is not a single special state called Self that is fundamentally unlike the parts it's used to heal.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-15-18:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
