<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-04-22T08:31:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-12-11:35.html</id>
    <title>Intuition as search prioritisation</title>
    <updated>2020-04-12T12:17:26+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Intuition as search prioritisation&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-12&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Computers and algorithms are not an especially good model of the human mind, but they often provide nice toy models for reasoning processes. These don't necessarily capture general features of human reasoning, but they're often still useful toy models for thinking about how reason might work in particular contexts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this post I'd like to look at some such toy models and see how intuition can have a big impact on them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose we have \(N\) items, and we want to find a good one (and know a priori that at least one of them is good). We can check whether any given item is good, but it requires reasonably careful investigation in order to determine an item's goodness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's no mystery about what we have to do in in order to find a good item: We go through \(N\) items, one at a time, and keep asking "Is this one good? How about this one? This one?" until we find a good item and return it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This simplicity hides an important question though: What order do we search through the items in?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If we're lucky and get a good item first, we only need to examine one item. If we're unlucky, we might have to examine all \(N\). If \(N\) is large this may be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; expensive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, our iteration order is the major driver of how efficient this process is. It has no effect on the result of the algorithm, but it significantly impacts its performance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Intuition can be thought of as the search ordering in this problem: We have some really cheap test that lets us guess whether something is good enough, and we go through the items in order of guessed-good to guessed-bad. If our guesses are remotely accurate, this will speed up the time this takes to find the item.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this stage, intuition affects only the performance, not the outcome, but in real world decision making often we are time constrained, so we might not have time to search through all \(N\) items. A &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/10/vocabulary-building-satisficing/"&gt;satisficing&lt;/a&gt; behaviour might be that rather than looking for goodness in some absolute sense, we evaluate \(k\) out of \(N\) items and pick the best among those.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is effectively the same algorithm as before, but now treated as an &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-23-15:52.html"&gt;anytime algorithm&lt;/a&gt; - we're allowing for the possibility of interrupting early and using our best result.
&lt;em&gt;Now&lt;/em&gt; the order of iteration is still important, because we can observe the quality over time and pick an earlier time to stop, but for essentially the same reason that it affected performance before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This feature becomes especially important when it's not just impractical but utterly infeasible to evaluate all \(N\) possibilities.
&lt;a href="https://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/id/eprint/10045895/1/agz_unformatted_nature.pdf"&gt;AlphaGo Zero&lt;/a&gt; is a particularly good practical instance of a real computer program working a bit like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;AlphaGo Zero has essentially two components:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A tree search, that reasons through and evaluates potential moves for their impact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A neural network, that looks at the board and history and outputs a set of move probabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The tree search is the "reasoning" of the AlphaGo Zero, in that it's the bit that actually attempts to strategise and think through the implications of varying moves, but the neural network is the fast gut feel play.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In theory, AlphaGo Zero would play fine if you were to just make the neural network always pick every move at random and let the tree search be unboundedly deep. In practice, it would play fine by just sitting there generating heat and net never making a move, because trying to do a full tree search on the space of possible Go moves would take longer than the lifetime of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means we're in the situation like the above partial search algorithm: Because are constrained on time, the quality of the moves output by the neural network will heavily influence the quality of AlphaGo Zero's decision making.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a general phenomenon that repeats over and over again: Making decisions perfectly requires unbounded amounts of time, so at some point we have to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;terminate our decision making process and just make our best guess&lt;/a&gt;, and the quality of our intuition helps us prioritise what to consider before we give up. Thus, even the most logical and well reasoned decision making process will usually be heavily dependent on intuition for the quality of its outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-12-11:35.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-13-11:35.html</id>
    <title>The memetic domus</title>
    <updated>2020-04-13T15:13:25+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The memetic domus&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-13&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;NB this is a very &lt;a href="https://notes.andymatuschak.org/Work_with_the_garage_door_up"&gt;working with the garage door up&lt;/a&gt; post.
Sometimes you just get a sense that there's a there there, but you're not quite sure what it is yet.
This post is an attempt to gesture vaguely in the sense of the there that may or may not be there. It probably won't quite make sense yet, because it doesn't yet make sense to &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Ry9RyJ"&gt;Against the Grain&lt;/a&gt; by James Scott&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2V2LNGg"&gt;Sorting Things Out: Classification and its Consequences&lt;/a&gt; by Bowker and Star&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3edMIeC"&gt;Where Good Ideas Come From&lt;/a&gt; by Steven Johnson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3abawwE"&gt;How to talk about books you haven't read&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3ab7hW1"&gt;The Meme Machine&lt;/a&gt; by Susan Blackmore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3cfSN8E"&gt;The Economy of Cities&lt;/a&gt; by Jane Jacobs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2V1VDbo"&gt;The Origins of Unfairness&lt;/a&gt; by Cailin O'Connor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3es4meS"&gt;The Limits of Organization&lt;/a&gt; by Kenneth Arrow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Plus a lot of general background stuff beyond that. You don't have to read any of these to understand this post (I hope), but they vaguely are defining the cluster of what I'm thinking about right now. Also I can't promise that this post will make sense if you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; read them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Against the Grain talks about the idea of a &lt;em&gt;domus&lt;/em&gt;. The term comes from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domus"&gt;the Latin word meaning home&lt;/a&gt;, but can more broadly be used to refer to a freeholding and its surrounding cultivation. It is the origin of "domestication", which can be thought of as the process of taking other species and making them suitable for inclusion in the domus.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because not enough people write like mathematicians, Scott never really precisely defines what he &lt;em&gt;means&lt;/em&gt; by domus in any easy to extract form, but the condensation of it in &lt;a href="https://proteviblog.typepad.com/files/notes-on-scott-against-the-grain.pdf"&gt;these notes&lt;/a&gt; is pretty good:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “domus” is an assemblage, or concatenation of multiple species and environmental 
features – landscape changes, animal pens, houses, butcher shops, blacksmiths, marketplaces 
and so on – that are put together in varying proportions. It is multi-dimensional long-term 
inherited niche construction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Scott talks more broadly about the &lt;em&gt;domus complex&lt;/em&gt; as the effect of humanity on the landscape. We don't just produce small, tightly concentrated, domestic units, but we broadly reshape the landscape around us, and have been doing so long before anything recognisable as modern agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Within this broader domus complex, the domus is more like a local increase in concentration of domestication, but the the domestication of the landscape extends out far beyond where you might naturally think of as being the boundary of human presence. The village is domesticated, certainly, but so are the forests around it where humans hunt, and possibly clear with fire, so are the places where evolution is shaped by human predation, or by escaped domesticated species (plant and animal).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it is not just the rest of the world that is shaped by domestication, but also humanity. In one sense, humanity has shaped grain to serve us. In another sense, grain has shaped humanity to propagate itself. The situation is even more murky when you look at a species like dogs, who we essentially co-evolved with to domesticate each other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1126046264125267968"&gt;previously argued&lt;/a&gt; that you can look at books in the same way as grain: In one sense we create books to serve us, but in another sense books are best seen as a replicator in their own right, using humanity as the background medium of replication.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One could look at a kind of generalised definition of a domus as this: A domus is a set of tightly co-evolved replicators, each of which are dependent on each other and the domus as a whole as a platform driving their success, and which would be significantly altered (and possibly fail entirely) by its removal from the domus.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Books in the absence of humanity cannot replicate. Grain in the absence of humanity is much more subject to the vagaries of weeds, and drought. Humanity in the absence of books would find itself at a significant disadvantage compared to where we are today. Humanity in the absence of grain would starve.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As with Scott's domus complex, the boundary of a generalised domus will usually be fuzzy. There will be things that are obviously in a domus together, and things that are obviously not in a domus together, and a wide range in between. There will also likely tend to be overlapping domus which do not themselves necessarily constitute a larger domus. For example, both a large international business's culture and a city's culture might usefully be considered as domus in their own right, but are not usefully considered as a single unified domus even when the business has an office in that city - although the two domus interact, they do not interact densely enough to be usefully considered as part of the same domus.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This density of interaction is key to whether it is useful to think of a set of replicators as a domus.
Replicators in a domus will create pressure on each other to become more usable to them, by "offering" services. Books create a culture of literacy by turning humans into readers. Grains create a culture of mass agriculture by turning humans into states.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In "Sorting Things Out", Bowker and Star introduce the idea of &lt;em&gt;torque&lt;/em&gt;, the twisting of time lines created by people and categorisation systems on each other: When a person interacts with a categorisation, this creates pressure on both the person (to conform) and the categorisation system (to include the person). People's behaviour and categorisation systems are both examples of replicators (they literally evolve over time, in response to replication with variation and selection), and the torque between these replicators as they interact is the process of each making the other more usable to each other. Mutual torque&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, generalising this, we might say that &lt;em&gt;torque&lt;/em&gt; is the influence between two replicators to make each other more usable to each other. A domus is thus a set of replicators that exert significant torque on each other,
thereby domesticating each other. Torque creates domestication.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Where Good Ideas Come From" is a book largely about treating innovation as an evolutionary process (It's not especially convincingly argued, but that's OK for me because I was already on board with most of its ideas and it was nice to see them sketched out a bit more). In it he describes the idea of a &lt;em&gt;platform&lt;/em&gt; - an ecosystem that essentially acts as a foundation for other things to develop on top of them. Two examples he gives of such platforms are how coral reefs create atolls, which are highly nutrient dense environments supporting a huge amount of diversity of life, and cities, which have the same function for memetic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In "The Economy of Cities", Jane Jacobs talks about how cities are essentially the driver of innovation. She also talks about how cities predate agriculture, which I think "Against the Grain" convincingly disproves (depending on what you "count" as agriculture), but I think her broader point is still sound if you replace "city" with "domus", because there really isn't a city / not-city binary. Instead a better reading of this would be that &lt;em&gt;domus density&lt;/em&gt; is a huge driver of evolutionary diversity. Any domus serves as a platform, both for the replicators currently in it and for new ones to be brought into the fold.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Jacobs talks about "import replacement", where a city starts producing goods it has previously imported, as a driver of city group. In a domus sense this also occurs as something we might call &lt;em&gt;replicator integration&lt;/em&gt;. Once, cats were not part of the domus. Then they started essentially feeding off it (by eating creatures that were parasitizing off the domus). Now cats are a thoroughly integrated part of humanity's domus complex.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The main human domus complex inextricably contains memes (in the original Dawkins sense. Pictures with text on them are less load bearing although still a major feature) - ideas and complexes of ideas which replicate themselves by spreading from person to person. The memetic domus in the title of this post is really just the part of that broader domus that centers on these memetic replicators. It's not necessarily cleanly separable from the rest of the human domus complex, but it's worth considering as an object of study in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One way in which it is worth studying is cultural. As I wrote before, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-28-06:33.html"&gt;culture is deeply contingent&lt;/a&gt;. Here the memes that we are interested in are particularly &lt;em&gt;behaviours&lt;/em&gt;. When you have a domus, people interact often enough and exert enough torque on each other, than where it is useful to synchronise behaviours to be the same, they generally will. Whenever there is a coordination problem, a domus will tend to create homogoneity through torque.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A domus will also tend to use that torque to resist change. If two previously unlinked domuses start interacting, each will induce torque on the behaviours of the other, but because changing one replicator within a domus will cause it to be less useful to the others, the within-domus torque will tend to be greater than the between-domus torque. If interactions are common enough, the two domus might eventually "merge", and eventually the within-domus torque might be enough to eventually remove the inhomogeneity, but without that the two will tend to remain separate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A particularly important feature of this when the domus contains humans (technically "human behaviours" as humans don't have to be present in their capacity as replicators for this to be relevant) is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-02-09:31.html"&gt;legibility&lt;/a&gt; within the domus. Because of this homogenising effect, two people within the same domus will tend to make more sense to each other than people from other domus - many core assumptions about behaviour and communication will be shared and not need explaining, and many shorthands will have been developed that are useful for describing behaviour within the domus. These shorthands will be shared.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This shared legibility is related to something that Kenneth Arrow talks about in "the limits of organization". This is a book about why, if we assume that the price system is very good (which it mostly is, and as an economist Kenneth Arrow is particularly predisposed to believe that it is), why do non-market organisations form? One of the answers he presents to this is that organisations exist to lower communication costs within the organisation, which enables people to acquire information that is valuable but not worth the cost of acquiring it in a broader market economy. Thus by forming an organisation in which communication is cheaper, a number of market failures become soluble.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The mutual legibility within the domus serves a similar function. People will find it easier to communicate with each other, and so many ideas become possible to spread that would not in isolation. Essentially, the domus becomes a platform for a much richer memetic ecosystem that would not be possible without it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One example of a set of replicators that it is useful to think of as part of a memetic domus is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-18-12:24.html"&gt;the libraries of Pierre Bayard&lt;/a&gt;, consisting of various types of books, both literal and figurative, and the collective discussions we have centered around them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is all now quite far from the thought process that spawned this post, and I think I will let these ideas bed down a bit more and try to explain it more coherently and go into this thought process a bit more in a later post, but to touch on it briefly: It is useful to think of yourself as embedded in a domus with your own surrounding information architecture (your "exobrain" as I'd often think of it), and it's worth thinking about behaviours in terms of promoting the health of that domus.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example my own personal memetic domus (something to make me share, something to make me like and subscribe) might contain:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The thoughts I have&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The conversations I have&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Posts on this notebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tweets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Books I read&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It may not seem natural to think of these all as replicators, and some of them are a bit of a stretch I'll grant, but they definitely all exert torque on each other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The domus forms a platform largely to the degree that it is well connected through torque, so behaviours which &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-09:44.html"&gt;promote the formation of ideas&lt;/a&gt; will largely be ones that increase torque within your personal memetic domus.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An example of this, which is largely what prompted this very post, is that I've taken to dipping in and out of books and rereading bits of them to remind me of their contents. This has created significantly higher torque between thoughts and books, and (indirectly) between books and this very notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-13-11:35.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-14-13:56.html</id>
    <title>Spock is a Lie</title>
    <updated>2020-04-14T14:25:06+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Spock is a Lie&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of people's model of peak intelligence is something like Spock (Star Trek Spock, not developmental psychology Spock): Freed from the petty constraints of petty human emotions, one can become a being of pure logic who can reason perfectly as a result.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are two basic problems with this goal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotions are how you assign value, and it doesn't really matter how good you are at reasoning if you don't have preferences over outcomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also freeing yourself of emotion makes you very bad at reasoning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My favourite representation of Vulcans comes from Diane Duane's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2VqGmjn"&gt;Spock's World&lt;/a&gt;, where she presents the version of Vulcan logic that makes the most sense to me: Vulcans aren't intrinsically logical, we're just seeing the results of a world-wide religious norm of good behaviour. Vulcans absolutely have emotions, it would just be considered extremely rude for them to show them, and as part of that they've got &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;very good at managing them&lt;/a&gt;. The Vulcans who wouldn't get on board with this religious program left and became Romulans (Romulans also have their own norms around emotion management, but they tend to be more around staying ruthlessly secretive in the face of totalitarian opression. Or follow the path of Absolute Candor and tell everyone about their feelings as part of their assassin training).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Vulcans are thus basically a more emotionally healthy version of the British: The British (especially the British upper middle class) also consider it rude to have emotions in public, but nobody taught us how to manage them, so the result is that most of us are neurotic messes. Vulcans presumably know better than to do this, so probably meditate on their feelings and write emo poetry about them in private.
The problem is that because we only experience Spock from the outside, we conclude that his presentation is his internal experience, and it is impossible that this can be the case given what we see of his behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is a post about reasoning and emotions, not about Spock's emo poetry about Kirk (I confess I've never actually read any Spock/Kirk, because Kirk does nothing for me and Spock does little).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Damasio's book &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2xkCetv"&gt;Descartes' Error&lt;/a&gt; lays out some of the evidence for this in practice: Damage which affects emotional processing usually results in people being unable to make good decisions, in large part because of inability to prioritise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From a more theoretical standpoint, there are two major obvious candidates for the role of emotion in reasoning:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intuition is a fundamentally emotional experience, and is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-12-11:35.html"&gt;essential for good reasoning under time constraints&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cognitive dissonance is an emotion, and paying attention to it is a major guide for improving our reasoning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Carol Tavris talks about cognitive dissonance in &lt;a href="https://www.preposterousuniverse.com/podcast/2018/07/09/episode-1-carol-tavris-on-mistakes-justification-and-cognitive-dissonance/"&gt;Episode 1 of Mindscape&lt;/a&gt; and it's very good. She also has a book about this, &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2XzN7lz"&gt;Mistakes Were Made (But Not By Me)&lt;/a&gt; that I've not yet got around to reading. The really short version is this though: Cognitive dissonance is the unpleasant feeling of noticing yourself holding two contradictory beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Cognitive dissonance is not intrinsically a bad thing - noticing that contradiction &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; feel bad, in that you should be driven to reduce it, but because we're all so bad at discomfort tolerance we tend to overreact to cognitive dissonance and as a result come to bad conclusions where we justify having been right all along (often this is learned in a social environment where mistakes were &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;unsafe&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The correct response to cognitive dissonance is to treat it as useful information, and to allow it to feed a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; to be more correct, without overreacting to it. This is hard, and it's easy to fail in either direction: We can ignore the cognitive dissonance altogether, which leaves us with no impetus to improve our reasoning, or we can overreact to it and double down on our existing position, which leaves us stuck in a bad reason.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, epistemic competence (being good at acquiring true knowledge) is fundamentally dependent on emotion management skills: We need to be aware of our emotions, and we need to experience them as safe, otherwise we will end up stuck with bad beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-14-13:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-15-06:31.html</id>
    <title>Capabilities can be coerced</title>
    <updated>2020-04-15T08:51:37+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Capabilities can be coerced&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If I can force you to take an action, that implies that you are able to take that action.
The converse of this is that you are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; able to take that action, I cannot force you to do it.
Thus, your inability gives you a certain power over me - you force me to plan in ways that compensate for this inability.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The classic example of this is how to win a game of Chicken (theoretically. I do not recommend you do this).
Chicken is played as follows: Two people drive their cars directly at each other. The one who swerves, loses.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a simple winning move in Chicken: Visibly clamp your steering wheel, or otherwise remove your ability to swerve in a way that is visible to your opponent (the visibility part is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; important).
Now your opponent knows that you not just won't swerve you &lt;em&gt;can't&lt;/em&gt; swerve, so they are forced to swerve instead.
You win (unless your opponent has done the same thing at the same time of you, in which case you both lose very badly).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thomas Schelling goes into this and similar things in great and illuminating detail in &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3a7N3MM"&gt;The Strategy of Conflict&lt;/a&gt;, but this example has the core of it: When interacting with someone in a situation of conflict, the other party will choose their strategy based only on the moves that you can make, so removing the ability to make certain moves can cause them to choose strategies that are more advantageous to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Conflicts don't have to be quite as adversarial as the game of Chicken. Consider something like choosing a meal. Suppose you have a reasonably strong preference against eating meat. Chances are you're often going to be coerced (explicitly or implicitly) into eating meat a lot more often than you want. If, instead, you tell people that you're vegetarian and &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; eat meat, that coercion goes down significantly (not to zero, sadly, but you've got a stronger argument to make against them when they try).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is, of course, often also a game of chicken. More specifically a game of eating chicken).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is also why today's favour is tomorrow's obligation: Once you have demonstrated the ability to perform the favour, now any future refusal to do it is evidence that you are choosing not to do it because it is known that you can do it, so the cost of refusal is now significantly higher.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This dynamic is, I think, at the core of a number of identities. As I've previously written, &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/06/on-not-quite-fitting/"&gt;I'm something of a skeptic of the universality of "born this way"&lt;/a&gt; for sexualities (I'm agnostic as to whether some people's sexuality is biologically determined - it could well be the case, certainly, and I don't think it would be useful to argue with individuals' experiences of this, but at the very least I doubt it's the majority case).
However, it's a very useful &lt;em&gt;political&lt;/em&gt; tool, because it allows you to credibly claim that people have to accept you as you are, because you do not have the option to be otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On what is, in some sense, the other side of the fence, I think this also explains many popular uses of evopsych (evolutionary psychology, that is to say explaining psychological features of behaviour by arguing that they were evolutionarily advantageous).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Evopsych has one really compelling "feature": It's so underdetermined and so hard to verify that you can use it to explain just about anything you want.
That's not to say that evolution didn't influence our psychology. Of course it did. But the specific ways in which evolution influenced our psychology are &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard to test for, and most evopsych arguments don't constitute anything remotely resembling a reasonable standard of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result if you are, say, a man who experiences a particular socially constructed version of masculinity that you're quite attached to and don't want to do the work of changing,
evopsych is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; useful for you, because it lets you make the born this way argument - so sorry, can't possibly change this behaviour, it's just hardwired into us.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the internet seems to have iterated this observation to its logical conclusion, and we are now mostly credibly signalling that we are just unable to accept evopsych arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-15-06:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-17-10:16.html</id>
    <title>Ubiquitous Incommensurability</title>
    <updated>2020-04-17T10:40:38+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Ubiquitous Incommensurability&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We were talking in &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/jm97tDN"&gt;bookchat&lt;/a&gt; about favourite books the other day, and how difficult some people find the problem of listing, say, your top ten favourite books.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I claim the reason that this question is hard is that it's actually impossible, and not in a good way, because even within a category such as books, many things are incommensurable - it doesn't really make sense to compare them in such a way as to say that one is definitively better than another.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to illustrate this, let me tell you about two of my favourite books. &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2VdFtMd"&gt;Sorting Things Out: Classification and its Consequences&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2yiOQBs"&gt;A Civil Campaign&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sorting Things Out is a nonfiction book about the way classification systems are developed and how this affects the people interacting with or being classified by them. A Civil Campaign is a book late in a space opera series that is mostly a romantic comedy about marriage and edible bug byproducts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Both of these are favourite books of mine in the following senses:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My life is significantly improved by having read them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would unambiguously recommend them to anyone who thought they sounded appealing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no book I strictly prefer to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which of these books do I like better? I don't think the question makes sense.
Each book serves a very different role for me, and those roles are not at all interchangeable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is an idea in economics of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revealed_preference"&gt;revealed preferences&lt;/a&gt;, which suggests that preferences can be inferred from behaviour. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Von_Neumann%E2%80%93Morgenstern_utility_theorem"&gt;Von Neumann-Morgenstern Utility Theory&lt;/a&gt; uses a similar idea to attach a single scalar utility value to a set of things being chosen over. These may both be true in some sense, but a naive adoption of them hides something very important: How incredibly context sensitive choices between objects are.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You might imagine that you can find out which of these books I prefer by asking me to make decisions, but the problem is that which book I choose will be heavily influenced by how you ask the question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some possible variants:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I had to give away one of these books, which would I pick? A Civil Campaign, because Sorting Things Out costs more to replace. (Advantage: Sorting Things Out)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I were given an extra copy of one of these books, which would I pick? A Civil Campaign again, because I know many more people who would enjoy it than the former and I'd gift that on. (Advantage: A Civil Campaign)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I could only ever read one of these books again, which would I pick? Sorting Things Out, because I use and refer to its ideas much more often. (Advantage: Sorting Things Out)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I were stuck on a desert island with one of these books, which would I pick? A Civil Campaign, because it's much more emotionally comforting to reread and I'm not likely to be up to much more than that on a desert island. (Advantage: A Civil Campaign)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One way to think of this is in terms of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_efficiency"&gt;pareto optimality&lt;/a&gt;: You can only count a book as better than another if it is better in all degrees. I think this is too strong - for example I'd consider either of these books better than, say, The Tao of Pooh, because I consider the latter to be a dreadful book that I would not recommend to anyone. Are there senses in which The Tao of Pooh is better than either of these books? Yeah, probably. It's more accessible than Sorting Things Out for example, but I would still say Sorting Things Out is the unambiguously better book.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I think it is still true that many pairs of books are &lt;em&gt;incommensurable&lt;/em&gt; - you cannot readily say that one of these things is better than the other, because "better" is so context dependent. Further, nothing about this is book specific - the same is true for meals, films, people, and almost everything else. Context is important a driver of preference between objects as the objects themselves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can certainly demand that I reduce those contexts to probabilities, and make decisions about what I would prefer in each context to reveal my preferences, in order decide which one I strictly prefer by comparing the resulting subjective utilities.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To this demand, I offer the following rebuttal: Nope. Shan't.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-17-10:16.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-18-11:10.html</id>
    <title>Dust Motes and Electric Plugs</title>
    <updated>2020-04-18T12:44:46+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Dust Motes and Electric Plugs&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-18&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the last post I talked about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-17-10:16.html"&gt;incommensurability&lt;/a&gt;,
how in general you can't compare things and say that one is better than another.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is absolutely true, but the reason (that context matters) is important: Without context, you can't say one thing is better than another. With context, you're probably going to have to choose. That choice doesn't have to be stable, it &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;doesn't even have to be deterministic&lt;/a&gt;, but you're still going to have to choose, because not choosing is often the same as choosing by default to go with the status quo.
That may be fine sometimes, but often the status quo isn't so great.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trolley_problem"&gt;Trolley Problem&lt;/a&gt; is very annoying, but one of the reasons it is very annoying is that it deliberately strips the decision making of context.
Implicit in the trolley problem is that you &lt;em&gt;can't ask questions&lt;/em&gt;. Variations are tried to tease out your moral intuition (the fat man version, the surgeon version, etc), but within the frame of a particular trolley problem you are not allowed to defer your decision making to context.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, in trolley-like situations you are going to have to choose. You have access to the context, so you don't have to choose contextless, but you do have to choose.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://robots.law.miami.edu/2019/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/MoralMachineMonster.pdf"&gt;Why the moral machine is a monster&lt;/a&gt; is a paper I really like which talks about the application of the trolley problem to self-driving cars and why you shouldn't: Software isn't ethics, it's policy, and if you consider the behaviour of self-driving cars having implemented a version of the trolley problem, you need to consider not just the effect of individual ethical choices, but also the way people shape their behaviour knowing that cars implement those choices.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general this is what policy is: Decisions that are made in the absence of a specific context, to be implemented in specific cases using context only to the degree that it is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-02-09:31.html"&gt;legible&lt;/a&gt; to the policy makers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://how.complexsystems.fail/"&gt;safety in complex systems literature&lt;/a&gt; is a good source of evidence around how people behave in the presence of policy: Which is that they often violate it. Some of this is &lt;a href="https://danluu.com/wat/"&gt;normalization of deviance&lt;/a&gt;, and some of this is because policy can never be sufficiently powerful and flexible to adapt to local context.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, sometimes you have to set policy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly true with coordination problems. When it comes to walking you can rely on &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-28-06:33.html"&gt;people deciding which side of the path to walk on&lt;/a&gt; but with cars you actually want to set some policy as to which side of the road to drive on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a harmless example because it doesn't actually matter which side you pick, but there are other less harmless ones where you're forced to make hard trade offs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of less harmless ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another annoying thought experiment is &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/3wYTFWY3LKQCnAptN/torture-vs-dust-specks"&gt;torture vs dust specks&lt;/a&gt;, which asks whether it is better to torture someone horribly for 50 years or to give each of an inconceivably large (more than the number of atoms in the universe by some inconceviably large number of orders of magnitude) a speck of dust in their eye. Yudkowsky thinks the answer is obvious, and so do I: The answer is that the question is bad, and he should feel bad for posing it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That being said, I reluctantly agree with what I presume is his position, that the torture is probably the preferable option, and we can see this with a (somewhat) less ridiculous variant: Would you rather one random person on earth have their eye painfully removed, or every single person on earth have a slightly annoying dust speck in their eye?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Note: This is a question of &lt;a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/08/28/contra-askell-on-moral-offsets/"&gt;axiology&lt;/a&gt;, not of ethics. I'm, for the moment, not asking you to choose policy or make a decision, I'm just asking which of these situations are better).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the answer is obvious: Removing a random eye is better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are currently about 7.5 billion people on the earth. Suppose each of those people had to choose between touching their eye to remove a minor inconvenience, and having a one in 7.5 billion chance of losing that eye.
Would they take it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course they would. People touch their eyes &lt;em&gt;all the time&lt;/em&gt;. COVID-19 is teaching us just how often we do it. This has potentially bad consequences, such as disease transmission, and eyes can definitely get infected to the point of losing them as a result of being touched. It's not very likely, but it doesn't have to be very likely for this to matter, all we have to argue is that people shouldn't credibly believe that there's a less than one in 7.5 billion chance of something at least as bad as losing an eye to happen as a result, and I think the reality is that the answer is that there's a significantly greater than one in 7.5 billion chance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What does this have to do with policy?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, consider &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AC_power_plugs_and_sockets"&gt;electrical plug design&lt;/a&gt;. A friend of a friend once pointed out that there's an interesting trade off implicitly being made in the design of the UK sockets. UK sockets are among the safest in the world from the point of view of preventing electrocution - it's really very hard to electrocute yourself on a UK socket (though a sufficiently dedicated small child with exactly the right mix of ingenuity and stupidity can do it, as I learned the hard way). On the other hand, a UK plug can lie on its back in a way that makes it essentially a caltrop, and some people will step on that and hurt their foot (possibly falling over and injuring themselves badly! This too is a fatality risk, especially for older people).
So, here we are presented with a policy trade off between injured feet and electrocutions. You can't play a "Would you rather?" with these exactly, but people confronted with policy do absolutely have to trade these two off against each other. You can potentially improve both, but it will likely come at the cost of something else - possibly time and money as you roll out a new standard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another example of this is speed limits. Why is the speed limit not 20mph everywhere in a city? Why are cars allowed in cities at all? Either of banning cars or reducing the speed limit to 20mph everywhere would have a significant impact on mortality rate, but it would also be incredibly inconvenient for a lot of people, so currently policy is prioritising a large amount of inconvenience against a certain amount of death.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We're also seeing this in COVID-19 planning. Closing schools is an example where policy has chosen a truly vast amount of inconvenience against a relatively small amount of death (possibly partly because the error bars on "relatively small" are really quite large). I'm not saying if I think they're right or wrong to do so (this isn't a thing it's &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-09-11:13.html"&gt;useful for me to have an opinion on&lt;/a&gt;), but I sure am glad I don't have to make the choice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, &lt;a href="https://mindsarentmagic.org/"&gt;Paul Crowley&lt;/a&gt; convinced me that the optimal decision for this is always going to take the form of a linear trade off between these. Say, we might choose that 1000 inconvenienced parents is worth 1 death. The argument only works if the set of available policies is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_set"&gt;convex&lt;/a&gt; but it usually is. I don't think we'll necessarily be able to make good choices about those trade off parameters, andindeed think usually trying to make good choices is probably impossibly hard work, but it's probably often worth thinking about lower and upper bounds, especially ones that are revealed by your preferences in other ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example there are, say, about 3 million cars in London (it's a bit lower than in terms of ownership but people also drive in. This isn't a precise measure). There are also about 100 road fatalities per year in London. So at the bare minimum we've decided that moderately inconveniencing 3 million people for 4 days is worse than a single death. It's not obvious that COVID-19 policy is consistent with that trade off, but equally there are arguments that it shouldn't be (policy during a crisis needn't reflect policy outside that crisis).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am not a utilitarian. I think it's a bad ethical framework, and people shouldn't use it for individual ethical decisions, but I am increasingly coming around to the view point that it might be a good ethical framework for designing policy. You need to be careful about this, because &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2017/11/shaping-the-world/"&gt;trying to impose simple rules on complex systems often destroys them&lt;/a&gt;, but if you're going to set policy this is probably the sort of thinking that you need to engage in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the difficulties with this is that it implies that our individual ethical decision making process should be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different from those of people setting policy. The result will often be that they do things we regard as outrageous like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Value_of_life"&gt;attaching monetary value to a human life&lt;/a&gt;, which they need to do in order to make policy like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems bad, but I increasingly feel that it seems bad for the same reason that national debt looks horribly fiscally irresponsible if you look at it like individual debt: We're trying to analogise between two things that are actually much more different than they look at first glance.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-18-11:10.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-19-10:52.html</id>
    <title>Notes on becoming a cis man</title>
    <updated>2020-04-19T17:20:57+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes on becoming a cis man&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Please note: I ask for clemency and/or good faith reading of this post. This is stuff that is difficult to talk about without stepping on someone's toes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Required prior reading:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alexwlchan/status/1251790486341390338"&gt;Lexie's thread about why cis people should be allowed to think about gender too&lt;/a&gt; (to be possibly replaced with a link to a blog post later if they write one)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/05/the-inner-sense-of-gender/"&gt;The Inner Sense of Gender&lt;/a&gt; (this was in fact written based on a conversation with Lexie)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/06/on-not-quite-fitting/"&gt;On Not Quite Fitting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular this tweet from Lexie's thread is relevant:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I have cis friends who have done introspection of their gender, and are now more sure that they’re cis – but talking about it gets shouted down as “you’re trans but you haven’t realised yet”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm one of those cis friends, and I thought it might be useful to talk about this process given that it's not one that gets talked about much.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First off, some politics: My basic stance on transition is that if you want to do it, go for it, you're entitled to. There may be some sort of intrinsic transness vs cisness, I don't know, but I don't think it matters for the purposes of who gets to count as eligible to transition. Bodily autonomy is important, gender is a thing that it is good for people to experiment with if they want to, and people should be trusted to make their own decisions in this space.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In particular&lt;/em&gt; while I would never suggest this about anyone in particular (and indeed don't have anyone in particular I even suspect of this) I'm morally certain that there are people out there who are at about the same point on the cis/trans spectrum as I am and have decided to transition. That's cool by me. It would both be inappropriate of me to police that, and also I wouldn't want to police that. It's just a thing that they're entitled to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I personally decided that transition wasn't the most useful route for me to go down and took an alternative path, but there's no reason other people should make the same decisions as me even presented with broadly the same experience of gender as I have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another political-ish note: I'm going to be disagreeing with some things some trans people say in this post. This can be dicey, but I feel reasonably confident in doing so because what I'm going to be disagreeing with his how they interpret &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; lived experience, not how they interpret theirs. Also, almost all of these are things that I've also talked extensively with other trans people about and largely agreed with them on - there's no broad consensus that I'm disagreeing with, we're just all figuring this out together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, on to the main point of this post...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I wrote "the inner sense of gender" I described myself as "almost certain that I am cis". This fluctuated a bit (both up and down) in the interim, and various people predicted that I would in the end decide I was trans, but I have largely largely settled on certainty that I am cis, at least to the degree that I think the question still makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I'm not sure it makes sense is that I'm increasingly unconvinced that gender is really a thing.
Many things are &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/09/gendering/"&gt;gendered&lt;/a&gt;, and that the orientation of gendering is kinda defined by the statistical differences between some sort of "archetypal cis" men and women, but that doesn't neatly fall into saying that there is any one thing that we might call gender. Gender isn't a linear progression from man to woman, it's more like a big ball of biopsychosocial... stuff. This is a lot of why my politics of transition are basically "bodily autonomy, end of story" (the other part is that gatekeeping is not a thing that has historically covered itself in glory in this space).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, to be concrete: My pronouns will remain he/him, I'm unlikely to engage in any major gender defiance regarding my aesthetic, and it's basically certain that I will never attempt any sort of medical transition (I'll confess to a certain amount of curiosity about the effects of hormones, but it really is just curiosity). To a very large degree I will continue to play the social role of man, and I will become increasingly comfortable with that (and also comfortable with ditching the bits of masculinity that I think are bullshit).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I still think if we had magic Culture level body changing tech I would experiment with other gender presentations, and I still think there's a decent chance that I might end up choosing a feminine or androgynous presentation as my default given that option, but I'd also like to be able to fly and the level of emotional significance these two facts hold is broadly equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What's changed?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, Lexie has been writing about &lt;a href="https://alexwlchan.net/2020/04/adventures-in-embodiment/"&gt;embodiment&lt;/a&gt; recently. I've been part of some of the conversations that prompted that, and have been working on it myself too. I've, sadly, not achieved the same level of euphoria, but I don't think this is a gender thing I just think euphoria is hard emotion for me to access (I'm working on it). I've specifically been working on it in the context of Focusing and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;my work on feelings&lt;/a&gt;, which has been extraordinarily helpful. I've also been working on it in the context of Alexander Technique and some of what I've been learning from that in the context of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-21-12:35.html"&gt;letting my body drive&lt;/a&gt; (one of the minor personal annoyances of the pandemic is that it's interrupted my study of this).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One side effect of this is that it has resulted in a great deal more comfort in my body, and reduced my dissociation from it. A lot of things that previously looked kinda like gender dysphoria turned out to be fantasies of "If only my body were completely different I'd be able to connect to it", but it turns out to be perfectly possible for me to connect to my body as it is, and to enjoy my experience of it, it's just quite hard work to acquire the skillset. well maybe it would be easier (certainly it's a common reaction to going on estrogen, but I suspect that some of that is genuinely just that estrogen makes it easier to connect to your embodied emotional state).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also ties in to a lot of trauma. A thing that I saw on Twitter the other day (I don't want to refind the tweet because it's a general theme and I don't want to pick on her in particular) was a trans woman saying that one of the reasons why she knew she was trans was that "cis men don't typically experience their masculinity as traumatic" and... I'm sorry to report that this is not true. I'm not going to say that we experience exactly the same sort of traumas from it as trans women do (I'd be very surprised if we do, but I'd also be very surprised if there weren't some large overlap). Some of this is that &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/jiminy-cricket-must-die/"&gt;norm acquisition in general is traumatic&lt;/a&gt;, some of that is that many of our norms around masculinity are really quite bad.
Going through masculinity training just &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; traumatic. I expect the same is true for going through femininity training, though the traumas are different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of my specific traumas around this are that many masculine norms are very violent, both literally and figuratively, and are quite damaging to be coerced into. Current western masculine norms are also very homophobic. This is both a problem if you're not actually straight (which I'm not), and if you just happen to have some more feminine traits (I perform masculinity reasonably well in some ways and quite badly in others - for example I'm much more into talking about feelings than I think even the average woman, let alone the average man).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, gender non-comformance is punished (both by people of the same gender and the opposite), and almost nobody is perfectly gender conformant, so most people will have gender related traumas. Unpacking some of mine was essential for acquiring a healthier relationship with masculinity (and part of that healthier relationship is boundaries! I'm now much happier saying "No, fuck off, that's a stupid way to be a man. Shan't." to the worse bits).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The final aspect for me has been sex. I've been having a lot of it over the last year or two, and it's been very helpful. I don't plan to go into details here, but I'll note a couple significant features.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First off, lets talk about autogynephilia. I basically agree with Scott Alexander on this: &lt;a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2020/02/10/autogenderphilia-is-common-and-not-especially-related-to-transgender/"&gt;Autogenderphilia is common and not especially related to transgender&lt;/a&gt;. I've had more than a few fantasies about myself as a woman. I've had more than a few fantasies about myself as a man. I am reasonably gender flexible in fantasy. It's fun and I don't intend to stop. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-27-08:18.html"&gt;Gender is sexy&lt;/a&gt; and fantasies are supposed to be sexy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you don't realise that this is a thing, it can be very confusing, and the way that literally everybody talks about it (from "autogynephilia isn't real" to "autogynephilia is the main reason people are trans". Both seem to be obviously false) is extraordinarily unhelpful for making sense of a perfectly healthy and common experience.
People do a lot of things in fantasies that they don't especially want to do in real life, and turning this into a whole big thing is a great way to confuse people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Secondly, a lot of gender related traumas are connected to sex. I don't want to go into details here, but they definitely were for me (it's less dramatic than you might be imagining from that). There is a lot of shame connected up with masculinity and desire, and acquiring a whole bunch of emotions skills while also having a whole bunch of sex was a great way to expose, confront, and defuse those.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, for me at least having a penis is fairly central to my experience of masculinity (I'm aware that this is complex for many trans people, so treat this as a personal claim, but I expect it's a personal claim a lot of cis men would make), so uh getting comfortable with using it was a pretty good way of getting comfortable with masculinity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally, sex ties in a lot to embodiment. In many ways the key to good sex is to embody well during it, so sex works very well for providing the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; for growth in this space (of course, finding people you feel &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safe&lt;/a&gt; with is equally important here).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;None of this has added up to me suddenly being completely clear or comfortable with my own gender or body, but I'm vastly more so than I've historically been, and I've acquired the skill set and the understanding that allows me to continually improve on that over time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, at this point, I am reasonably comfortable in saying that yes I've thought about my gender a lot and I have concluded that I am a cis man, and that I am confident that the more work I do in this space the more thoroughly I will come to understand and embody that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-19-10:52.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-20-10:52.html</id>
    <title>The Accelerator/Brake Model</title>
    <updated>2020-04-20T16:07:20+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The Accelerator/Brake Model&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2VOS9IK"&gt;Come As You Are&lt;/a&gt;, a book about sexuality (primarily women's sexuality, but it mostly works for everyone).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is by far the most &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-11-07:15.html"&gt;annoying&lt;/a&gt; book that I will nevertheless recommend. It was about 50% stuff I already knew (which I only skimmed but seemed pretty good), but the other 50% contained a lot of useful ideas that helped make sense of some things I only partially knew. It was also 100% annoying and I hated the author's writing style. I will grant I am not in the target audience for it (it is primarily written for women), but the friend who recommended it was a woman and she also hates the writing style so I don't think that's why, I just think it's objectively very annoying (especially if you're not from the USA).
Nevertheless, it was on balance very worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that was particularly helpful was the brake/accelerator model for sexual arousal. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The model is very simple: There are two systems, the Sexual Excitation System (SES), the accelerator, and the Sexual Inhibition System (SIS), the brake.
The SES is what turns you on, the SIS is what turns you off.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you're currently not interested in sex and you'd like to be, you need to understand which of these is at play:
It might be that your accelerator isn't being pushed by the current sexual context, or it might be that something is pressing hard on your brake.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Different people have different levels of sensitivity on each of the brake and accelerator. On average women have much more sensitive brakes (i.e. are much easier to turn off) and men have much more sensitive accelerators (i.e. are much more easy to turn on), but there's a lot of individual variation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the least helpful things you can do is make a mistake about which system is in play. It doesn't help to try to turn someone on if their foot is slammed hard on the brake, and it doesn't help to try to make someone comfortable and at ease if they're already fine and the problem is just that the context isn't at all arousing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The former is particularly bad, because pressure is one of the things most likely to activate someone's brakes, because it creates negative emotional association with the whole experience. It's also particularly common, because people (especially people who have relatively insensitive brakes, like most guys) often don't realise that the brake is a potential problem at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since reading about the brake/accelerator model I've been seeing it everywhere. I think a lot of motivation is like this, where there are things that we really want to do (the accelerator is on hard) but also procrastinate hard because there's a huge ugh field around the thing and we find it massively hard (so are the brakes) and we just end up with the gearbox in our head grinding.
In the same way as with sex, trying to want to do the thing even more isn't going to help, and treating it as an issue of motivation will just cause one to build up even more guilt and shame around the subject, making it even more aversive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This likely also ties in to the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety&lt;/a&gt; model of growth, where desire acts as the accelerator and a lack of safety acts as the brake (and indeed a lack of safety is often a major brake activator in a sexual context).
Given &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-19-10:52.html"&gt;the context&lt;/a&gt; in which I've been thinking about a lot of the personal growth work, it's probably not entirely a coincidence that these track.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-20-10:52.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-21-08:02.html</id>
    <title>Does a fish have a face?</title>
    <updated>2020-04-21T08:44:15+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Does a fish have a face?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-21&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm trying a new thing today, which is to integrate my daily notebook practice, my daily rereading practice, and a bit of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;randomization of decision making&lt;/a&gt;. I don't plan to do this every day, but I may do it more often.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic mechanism:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I pick a book of my choosing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I generate a page number uniformly at random from the main book contents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I pick an interesting passage and copy it out here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I then write something inspired by it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If this takes off I'll probably build some tooling into the notebook for getting me to do this properly but for now I'm mostly hand cranking it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is partly inspired by having recently-ish been listening to &lt;a href="https://www.harrypottersacredtext.com/"&gt;Harry Potter and the Sacred Text&lt;/a&gt;. I'm deeply indifferent to Harry Potter but have been enjoying their sacred text reading techniques. This process in particular is very loosely inspired by their (in turn somewhat loosely interpreted) practice of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lectio_Divina"&gt;Lectio Divina&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today's reading comes from &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3exHrih"&gt;Finding Our Sea Legs&lt;/a&gt;, page 126:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While he hedges his bets when it comes to dogs, it is hard to imagine Levinas having much time for the idea that a fish might have a face, or the idea that I could be infinitely responsible for a fish. Fish, as far as we human beings are concerned, are more alien to us than the stranger who knocks on our door, or the dog who wags his tail in greeting. They move in a different element, they have no lungs, their blood is cold, not warm, they do not sleep. And yet, while they may not have faces in the sense that Levinas means, they still hav efaces, in the ordinary everyday sense: We can look them in the eye, and these denizens of another world can look back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This might seem like a strange passage (of course fish have faces) but the idea of a "face" in this context is more about our experience of the other as a person. Backtracking to earlier in the book (pages 52-53) we have the following passage:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This curious and seemingly paradoxical idea of the 'face' is that the heart of Levinas's phenomenology of ethics. When we encounter the face of another [our relationship] is 'straightaway ethical.' When I encounter another person, I find myself responsible for them - I find myself unable to do anything other than to respond to them &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; another person - whether I like it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the question of whether a fish "has a face" is about whether our interactions with a fish have this phenomenological character: Do we treat a fish as a subject of ethical experience?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Experiences on this tend to differ, both by person and by context. Many people are vegetarian precisely because they experience animals as ethically relevant, and I know one person who as a child became vegetarian in a way that they literally framed as not wanting to eat anything with a face, a category in which they included fish.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Personally, I don't consider fish to be all that ethically relevant (oddly, I consider animals more ethically relevant than fish and yet I eat animals and mostly don't eat fish. This is primarily for environmental reasons though). I will not mourn the death of a fish. And yet, encountering a fish out of water, gasping on dry land, it is hard not to feel sorry for it.
In the abstract, I don't care about the fish, but confronted with the actual reality of the fish and its suffering, it is hard not to experience it as ethically relevant, as having a face.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Almost (I may have been subconsciously inspired in my choice of book) entirely coincidentally, yesterday I was listening to &lt;a href="https://www.preposterousuniverse.com/podcast/2019/02/18/episode-34-paul-bloom-on-empathy-rationality-morality-and-cruelty/"&gt;the Mindscape podcast episode with Paul Bloom&lt;/a&gt;, the author of &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2xCBEYd"&gt;Against Empathy&lt;/a&gt; (which I haven't read).
His essential argument is that this empathic experience leads us astray from good ethical behaviour. It causes us to overfocus on the individual in front of us - this empathy is what causes us to treat the fish as ethically relevant even if we don't "rationally" believe it to be. It's what causes us to be kind to our neighbour but ignore millions of people living in poverty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also what causes us to overvalue people like us and undervalue people different to us - it's much easier to be empathic to someone whose lived experience we can easily understand, and if we tie our ethics to our empathy then we will tend to prioritise those like us and neglect the Other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, one can bite this philosophical bullet and say that yes we should be rational in our ethics but also we should consider fish as ethically relevant. This is how you end up with things like &lt;a href="https://concepts.effectivealtruism.org/concepts/wild-animal-suffering/"&gt;Effective Altruists who are very concerned about wild animal suffering&lt;/a&gt;. It's possibly they're right - I don't agree with their concerns, but I don't think they're in principle invalid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think he has a point, and that a certain amount of rationality and deliberation in ethics is important, but I think too much of that will drive us towards utilitarianism, which is more like &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-18-11:10.html"&gt;policy&lt;/a&gt; than the sort of living ethics that I think improves our behaviour in day to day life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's worth using rationality as a tool to improve our ethical behaviour, but &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-14-13:56.html"&gt;emotion is key to effective rationality&lt;/a&gt;, and empathy and the experience of the other is a crucial tool in navigating any sort of rational ethics.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-21-08:02.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-22-08:31.html</id>
    <title>Power, baby, power</title>
    <updated>2020-04-22T08:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Power, baby, power&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-22&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm continuing the theme of notebook posts prompted by random passages from books. I've also decided to deliberately do this on books that aren't from my daily rereading practice to try and use it to integrate some of the books I read less often into my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-13-11:35.html"&gt;memetic domus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today's reading comes from "I'm very into you", which is a collection of correspondences between &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kathy_Acker"&gt;Kathy Acker&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McKenzie_Wark"&gt;McKenzie Wark&lt;/a&gt;. This section comes from Page 59. I also randomly selected a line (line 8) because Acker apparently hates paragraphs and this made it hard to select a passage manually.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember going to some Pomo conference Sylvère had a hand in, the early days, and that creep [Bernard Henri] Levy gives a speech (after Sollers has done his usual blather) all about Eve coming out of the rib of Adam, and therefore and therefore... So XXXXXX, very beautiful, asks him a question. Then she disappears. An hour or two later, she reappearing, we ask XXXXXX where she's been. "With Levy." "Why?" "Power, baby, power."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two things most strike me about this exchange:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; unsurprising, despite how nice it would be to imagine that human nature doesn't work this way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It strikes me as very gendered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm interested in unpacking the gendered nature of it. I can just about imagine (possibly inaccurately) the script playing out this way if both people involved were women, or both people involved were men, but the thing I can't imagine is it playing out that way if the speaker was a woman and XXXXXX was a man.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specifically what I can't imagine about it is not that a male XXXXXX wouldn't have been attracted to the powerful woman, but that he would so freely admit it. I genuinely don't know whether it's typical for men to experience power as attractive in a woman (my guess would be yes, but I don't really understand either men or attraction well enough to predict this confidently), but it definitely feels off script for men to &lt;em&gt;admit&lt;/em&gt; that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My impression is that the official cultural script for men being attracted to powerful women is that it's a shame/submission thing. The domme is the official script for the powerful woman who wields power in a sexy manner, and an intrinsic part of the sexiness of this script is partly that you're going off the official gendered script.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have at least two easily available hypotheses for why this is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power is coded masculine (perhaps because of a mix of patriarchy and more general &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/09/gendering/"&gt;gendering&lt;/a&gt;), so power intrinsically feeds in to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-27-08:18.html"&gt;competent performance of a masculine aesthetic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power is just attractive in general and men are supposed to pretend it's not because of masculine bullshit about how we're supposed to be the ones having power over others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A third possibility is that I'm just wrong and this would have played out exactly the same way when gender flipped. I don't &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; this is the case, but even if it is I'm interested in where I've got these scripts from.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One reason power might be intrinsically sexy is its streamlining nature for a lot of the process of generating attraction. In the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-31-09:52.html"&gt;mutual escalation&lt;/a&gt; that is flirting, one of the things that slows it down is a safety aspect - not so much physical safety (also that, but that's not the thing that's directly relevant here). People are hesitant in escalation because of fear of rejection and consequences, and power acts as a certain shield to that. Power essentially lets you take shortcuts in the flirting process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of those shortcuts are bad but work, because they involve violating boundaries because you know you can get away with it. Violating boundaries is another of those things which it would be nice to pretend doesn't work but actually does - the reason not to do it is &lt;em&gt;unethical&lt;/em&gt;, not that it doesn't work. e.g. just kissing someone fairly on in the process whether they want you to or not is a pretty effective way of polarizing and finding out if they're into it. You shouldn't do it, but if you're powerful you can probably get away with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may partly explain the gendered nature of power as sexy - in gender training women get trained not to enforce their boundaries, and men get trained to enforce them too rigidly and interpret anything as an attack. If you do this to a woman, you might get away with it. If you do this to a man, you might get punched.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also, perhaps, explains part of why so many men with power end up turning out to be sexual predators - they've essentially learned that violating boundaries will get them sex. My guess is that many of these men didn't &lt;em&gt;start out&lt;/em&gt; rapey, their sense of appropriate behaviour just gradually eroded over time. This doesn't absolve them of responsibility - their actions were still ultimately unethical - but it puts an interesting spin on it. Are we actively training people with power to be ethically worse? If so, what can we do about it? Relying on people with power to be virtuous enough to resist that training doesn't seem like a good solution.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-22-08:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
