<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2021-07-30T17:53:35+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-19-09:20.html</id>
    <title>Making life less irritating</title>
    <updated>2021-07-19T14:28:02+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Making life less irritating&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me start by telling you two recent things that happened to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is that I &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1416310982943645696"&gt;was complaining on Twitter about how annoying closing many windows is on Windows&lt;/a&gt;: If you click on the X for a window while in the window switcher then the row lays itself out centered so the next window's X is not under your cursor, wasting an entire second. A second I say!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This may not seem like much but I like to deal with my windows &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/triage-your-inboxes"&gt;Triage your inboxes&lt;/a&gt; style so this does add up to a moderate amount of time and a significant amount of annoyance)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Various people ignored my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-17-14:20.html"&gt;injunctions against offering advice in response to complaint&lt;/a&gt; but honestly I didn't mind that much (they were nice about it - more interested than telling me what to do - and I'd have happily taken advice on this front beside), and their advice didn't quite work but pointed me in the right direction and fairly soon I'd figured out two ways to solve this problem:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you hold down alt tab to get to the window list, keep alt pressed down to keep it open, switch to the window of interest using tab and shift-tab to navigate, and then press delete while still holding tab down, the window will close close and the window list will remain open so you can close more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you go to the other window display (there's probably names for the different displays, I don't know them) by pressing windows+tab or triple swiping up, you can navigate it with the arrow keys and delete also closes a window there too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Knowing this genuinely improves my life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also I've been low grade irritated by this for years, and I had a solution within about 15 minutes of complaining about it on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's another thing I've been annoyed about for a while.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The bins for my flat where I have to take rubbish and recycling to are in the basement car park. The only way down to the basement is by a lift. What with there being a pandemic on, I'm not a huge fan of this. It's mostly fine, but it makes me a little anxious each time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that, it's extra stupid because there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; stairs, but there's a door at the top which is one way - it's just a fire exit, and opens with a bar from the inside. You can't go in the other way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway right now our lift is broken - the heavy rain last week flooded the basement, got into the lift pit, and damaged the lift. Which means that I can't access the bins. Particularly with the current heat, this is a Problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I took another look at the outside of the door and spotted that although there wasn't a door handle, there was a keyhole.
Also it looked like the type of key for the deadbolt on my flat door. Nothing to lose in checking, so I gave it a try, and indeed it worked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This problem has been irritating me, and indeed fractionally (I doubt it actually matters that much - I was never in the lift with other people, and I always wore a mask) increasing my statistical risk of COVID, for about 10 months now, and it took me about a minute of actually looking at it in a very obvious way to solve it once I actually had to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have any number of other examples of this I can think of this over the last year, some of which I've now solved, some of which I still haven't. It appears to be a fairly persistent trend that when there is some persistent annoyance that I could solve in five minutes I &lt;em&gt;don't solve it&lt;/em&gt;, and I don't know why.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This looks like, but I think is distinct from, another class of problem, which is the thing you keep putting off that takes five minutes. That tends to be some sort of fear based procrastination. This isn't that. This is instead a persistent irritation that is solvable almost as soon as you think to genuinely try to solve it. It's not an aversion, it just doesn't seem to register that it's a thing I can solve until something finally causes it to shift.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have a couple of theories, and some possible avenues to try, for why this happens, but for now I'm just going to start with a simple recognition prompt: When I notice that I am annoyed, I'll try to think whether it's something I could easily solve. If it's not, that's fine, I'm certainly not committing to solve the irritations that are hard and difficult work to solve, but it seems worth trying to learn to be better at making the world less irritating.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-19-09:20.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-20-00:32.html</id>
    <title>The trauma model of talent blocks</title>
    <updated>2021-07-20T02:30:57+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The trauma model of talent blocks&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something very important you learn as a result of doing a mathematics degree. It's this:
People &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; didn't like studying mathematics at school, and they are keen to tell you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something like a 50% hit rate when you talk to normal people (people in tech don't count) that when you tell someone you did mathematics at university they say "Oh god I hated mathematics at school". Sometimes they say it in different words. "Oh.", in a very flat tone of voice. "You must be very clever". They look at you with the wary look of a gazelle facing off with a lion, fearful and ready to bolt at the slightest sign of you baring your teeth and trying to do an equation at them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, I've historically found this quite irritating, but as time has gone on I've started looking at it differently.
Instead of treating this as an attack on my interests, when people say this to me my first thought is more along the lines of "I'm sorry your mathematics teacher hurt you."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't usually say it that way, that's a good way to get punched. Instead I wince sympathetically and say "Yeah, it's often taught really badly."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I add "Sorry about that".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-16-10:12.html"&gt;clearing hurdles in learning&lt;/a&gt; I talked about how often what happens is that people hit a block where the they require help to progress and think of this as their natural talent limit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The detail this missed out on is what happens next, which is that you get stuck and we do two things, in order:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tell you to try harder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blame you for not succeeding and then tell you it's your fault and is an intrinsic feature of you and your abilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A distinction I find quite useful is that between guilt and shame. Guilt is when you feel bad about what you do, shame is when you feel bad about who you are. "I did a bad thing" vs "I am bad". It's not a perfect distinction but it's a pretty good rule of thumb.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another principle I find useful (see &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/jiminy-cricket-must-die/"&gt;Jiminy Cricket Must Die&lt;/a&gt;, or "Voices: The Educational Formation of Conscience" by Thomas Green) is that moral emotions are the internalised judgement of others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A third principle I find useful is that emotional reactions we learn tend to stick around until we find a way to actively engage with them and change them by recognising that our situations have changed (see &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;Emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html"&gt;Your emotions are valid but probably wrong&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sure &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; like having kids spend a substantial fraction of their entire childhood in an environment in which they are praised or punished for their academic achievement, then telling them that their failure to excel is the result of an intrinsic feature of themselves and punishing them for it anyway might have some uh lasting negative emotional side effects, huh?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let me tell you about my experience learning to drive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My attempts to learn to drive went as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had driving lessons when I was 18. I was bad at it. I stopped driving lessons and went to university in a town where I could cycle everywhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I moved back in with my parents for about six months post university, and used this as an opportunity to practice driving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I took a few more driving lessons to fill in some gaps, I was fine, and I passed my practical test first time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm absolutely fine at driving, and am comfortable enough doing it that I've done multiple long road trips.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What made the difference between my first attempts at learning to drive and my subsequent attempts?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, my first driving instructor was a very angry person, and tended to shout when I made mistakes. The result was that I was so anxious learning to drive and so afraid of making errors that I was unable to drive to any degree of competence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's certainly not the case that I'm a natural driver. My physical coordination and spatial awareness are on the poor side. It's possibly genuinely true that I was dangerous and needed correcting in my first driving lessons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And yet, somehow shouting at me about that didn't help, because it turns out that experiencing intense negative emotions every time you make an error is not &lt;em&gt;remotely&lt;/em&gt; conducive to the acquisition of complex skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't expect feeling shame every time you think of a subject is much different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear: This is, for the most part, not teachers' fault. There are definitely individual teachers who make the problem worse (e.g. by behaving like my driving instructor), and there are individual teachers who make the problem less bad, but fundamentally this is a function of the system. It arises from the system of grading, and is compounded by the fact that when you hit a block you need individually tailored help to overcome it, which our systems of teaching are absolutely not set up to provide unless your parents are rich enough to hire a tutor for you. While a great teacher can ameliorate the worst of this problem, attempting to solve it will break them because the task is too big.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But regardless of whose fault it is, it seems to hurt a lot of people pretty badly, because they end up hitting their "talent limits" - the bits where they needed help - and instead of either helping them progress or telling them that their current level was good enough, the education system chose violence and made their attempts to improve &lt;em&gt;harder&lt;/em&gt;, not just now but effectively forever until they unlearn the incorrect emotional lessons that they got instead of the lessons they should have been getting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suspect that above and beyond the specific subjects that we fail to learn as a result of this dynamic, it has a much broader impact on our conception of ourselves, because we think in terms of subjects we are good at and subjects we are bad at,
when instead we should be thinking more in terms of how good we want to be a subject and how much help we need to get there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also suspect that many people would find it really helpful to get some one on one tutoring in subjects they struggled at at school where they feel bad about that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, suspicions aside, one thing I'm reasonably certain of is that there are a lot of adults walking around with lingering low-grade trauma from school that they think of as their "lack of talent", and would benefit a great deal from the following reframing: It's not that you're bad at it, whatever "it" is, you were just never given the sort of help you needed.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-20-00:32.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-22-01:05.html</id>
    <title>Learning from the real</title>
    <updated>2021-07-22T06:13:45+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Learning from the real&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-22&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-04-11:18.html"&gt;Skirting the edge of disaster&lt;/a&gt; I pointed out that most complex systems that have been running in production for a while (e.g. a legacy software system, the London underground, humanity) have the form that they do as a result of the following two rules:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If an important system is broken, we fix it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a system has spare capacity, we place more demands on it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can tell from the title of the linked piece, I was mostly framing this as a bad thing: The consequence of being at a stable balance of these two things is that the system is constantly almost but not-quite broken, because every time it gets too far from broken it gets loaded more, and every time it breaks it gets fixed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there's another side to this that I think is interesting: If you encounter a reasonably stable complex system in the wild (and you do, very regularly), this reliably means:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It does a lot of things, because capabilities kept accreting over time, and they're often not things you would have thought of without that infrastructure because it changes what's easy and cheap to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything that would have stopped it from doing those things has been solved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of time, work, and ingenuity has often gone into getting it to that state, much of which would have been impossible to figure out from first principles because you had to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;try things and see what happened&lt;/a&gt; before you could even learn that you needed to solve the problems, let alone how.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Gall_(author)"&gt;Gall's law&lt;/a&gt; is "A complex system that works is invariably found to have evolved from a simple system that worked. A complex system designed from scratch never works and cannot be patched up to make it work. You have to start over with a working simple system."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But this then leads to the question: OK smart guy, how do I make a working simple system?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And I think the answer is often this: Go find a complex system that does what you want, and study it until you understand it well enough to extract a simple system from it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-22-01:05.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-23-16:26.html</id>
    <title>First decide what's good enough</title>
    <updated>2021-07-23T17:05:33+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;First decide what's good enough&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of my common pieces of advice is that when doing something or making something, you should separate your planning into two distinct goals:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How good do you need the thing to be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How good would you like the thing to be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Your first priority is to come up with a plan that all but guarantees that the thing you make will be as good as you need it to be. For example, when giving a talk, you don't &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; a lot. If your talk is coherent, vaguely interesting, and doesn't run over time, you've succeeded. You've given a talk that is good enough, well done.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once you've ensured that, you can stop feeling anxious about it, because you've removed any uncertainty about whether you will succeed. You will succeed, it's just up for you to tinker with the details. You can make it better for as long as it's worth making it better, and when it's not worth it any more you can just stop there and declare your planning done.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Generally I find you actually produce better results by doing it this way, because removing the anxiety reliably improves performance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You don't have to though. One nice thing about this approach is that you get very good at making sure something is good enough without having to put much effort on it. Then, when you have times where you really don't feel like putting in a lot of effort, you can massively phone it in, and that's fine too.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-23-16:26.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-25-12:50.html</id>
    <title>You can solve your problems, but you don't have to</title>
    <updated>2021-07-25T13:30:23+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You can solve your problems, but you don't have to&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Before I start, let me tell you some important truths:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because you can solve a problem, does not mean you are obliged to solve it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because you choose not to solve a problem, doesn't mean you don't care about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because you don't care about a problem you think is important, doesn't make you a bad person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because other people think a problem is important, doesn't mean you have to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are a small and finite human being, and you only have so much capacity to deal with the world,
and the world can absorb all of that capacity before you engage with the tiniest fraction of its problems.
There are more than seven billion people out there, every one of them has problems,
and even trying to solve all of &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; problems is probably going to overwhelm you.
Among the billions upon billions of important problems you could devote your efforts to, you've probably got the capacity for at most a few dozen at any given time, and you're probably doing less than that because running permanently at full capacity will make you miserable (and eventually reduce your capacity anyway).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I hope you know these things intellectually, but I bet you don't believe all of them emotionally,
and my evidence is this: There are a lot of problems that I could tell you how to solve that would cause you to immediately get mad at me for suggesting that you can solve them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know what they are, they very from person to person, but most people are walking around with easily solvable problems that they are steadfastly maintaining that they can't solve, because if they could solve them they would still not want to, and then they would feel guilty about that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People are very good at maintaining a set of beliefs that allow them to not feel guilty,
and the easiest way to do this is to believe that anything you think you should do but don't want to is impossible.
If you argue this belief convincingly enough, often other people will believe you and stop trying to get you to solve the problem you don't want to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's a genuinely good strategy, as long as you don't mind (or mind less than the alternatives) walking around in constant fear that you might one day discover the truth.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One way this comes out is that every time I offer generic advice on Twitter, I get people mad at me for suggesting that they could solve the problem I'm advising on.
They're very insistent that it's literally impossible this advice will work. Usually their reason is one that the advice was specifically designed with in mind. e.g. I hear a lot of my advice is terrible because it doesn't work for ADHD. This is particularly funny because it's often developed by listening to or talking with people with ADHD, and developed further to work with my own more ADHD tendencies given that I'm only just below the diagnostic thresholds myself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not every problem in your life is solvable, some really are immutable features of reality, but I am almost certain that vastly more of them are than you're pretending. I fully endorse your right and respect your choice not to solve them. I even fully endorse your right to not listen to me when I tell you that they're solvable. But I do not endorse your right to give me a hard time for talking about solutions, because many people are helped by trying to solve the problems they want to solve, and I have no desire to be complicit in maintaining a shared lie that hurts those people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Options exist. If you want to choose to believe otherwise, that's on you, but don't make your self-protective strategies an excuse to sabotage others.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-25-12:50.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-26-09:00.html</id>
    <title>The edge of the familiar</title>
    <updated>2021-07-26T16:40:53+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The edge of the familiar&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm reading "Why Poetry?" by Zapruder.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why why poetry? Well, why not?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"I don’t know what writers of stories and novels and essays eventually discover for themselves, but I can say that sooner or later poets figure out there are no new ideas, only the same old ones", he says.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He is wrong. This is a poet's problem. The ideas are there, but you cannot do poetry to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We are awash in new ideas, if we let ourselves listen for them. Generally we do not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Zapruder later cites Shklovsky, "Art as technique".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Shklovsky talks about "defamiliarization", or as Zapruder prefers, "strangeifying". The role of art is to trace the contours of the familiar, drawing your attention to it in ways that make it strange.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, if that's what you're doing, how could you have new ideas?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How can you strangeify that which is already strange to you?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think, perhaps, the role of art can never be to create the new.
It shows us what is already there, in a new light, allowing us to imagine that it could be different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It draws you to the very edge of the familiar,
and then tells you: Here we are. This is as far as I can take you. The rest is up to you.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-26-09:00.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-27-04:25.html</id>
    <title>You have to do the easy bits first</title>
    <updated>2021-07-27T05:33:47+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You have to do the easy bits first&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was helping a small child with a jigsaw puzzle the other day. We were assembling a map of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point she asked me "Why is this so easy for you and so hard for me?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was a good question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The easy answer is just "I'm 31 years older than you, I’ve learned a few tricks".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't say this, but I do think it's important. She's seven. There's no reason she should have figured out everything by now. She's still learning. That's what seven year olds do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But really there was only one trick, and it’s well within the reach of a seven year old if they can learn how.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Well, I’m doing the easy bits" I answered.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I explained a bit further, but I don’t think it quite landed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So here is what I would say with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%27esprit_de_l%27escalier"&gt;the wit of the staircase&lt;/a&gt; upon me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What you are doing is picking up a piece, and trying to figure out where to put it. Or you see a space that needs filling, and look for the piece that will fit it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is much too hard. Of course you're struggling, I would struggle too if I tried to solve the puzzle that way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is what I do instead: I do the same thing, and if it's hard, I stop. Then I look elsewhere. I put the piece aside, I look at another space, hoping that that one will be easier.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are many pieces, and many spaces, on the puzzle board, and some of them are hard, and some of them are easy. A blue square in the middle of the ocean is hard, a country boundary with distinctive colours is probably easy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can get good at spotting which ones are likely to be easy, but you mostly don't need to. You just try to place a piece, and if it works, it was one of the easy ones. If it doesn't, you try something else.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually you'll get good at spotting the easy pieces first, but you don't have to. Just be persistent, try them all. It usually won't take long to find an easy piece.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And when you've placed an easy piece, something funny happens: Pieces that were once hard, suddenly become easy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You fill a space, and now you have one less piece to place, and new spaces to place it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bit by bit, the picture takes shape, and as it does the problem becomes easier, because you have more to work with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you've only got a few pieces, you can just try them all, and one of them will work. When you're down to a handful, there are no hard pieces left.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can solve the hardest puzzles this way. All we need is a bit of persistence and some good tactics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't just about puzzles. You do the same with sudoku.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When we play sudoku together, you get stuck on a square. You look at it, trying to figure out what numbers go there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often you get frustrated. "I can't figure out what should go there".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well of course you can't. You've picked one of the hard squares. Pick an easy square.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is what's happening when I point to another square and say "Do you know what goes in this square?" - I look at the board until I find the easy square, and then I show it to you, and you find it easy, because you're perfectly able to solve the sudoku if you look in the right place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And once you've solved the easy square, now you know more about the other squares. A three went there, so there can't be a three in these squares, which means that one must be a two, which means that that one must be a four...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As soon as you've done the easy bit, everything around it becomes easier. This is the way we solve the puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is also the way we fix the world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a story about a seven year old, but it's not really a story about a seven year old, because people far older than me seem to miss this too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People often ask me how I know so many different subjects, or write about so many different things, when they struggle to do a tenth that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, I'm doing the easy bits.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If I run into a problem I can't solve yet, or I encounter a subject that's too hard for me, I go "Huh, interesting", and save it for later, or leave it to someone better suited to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't &lt;em&gt;give up&lt;/em&gt;. This is important. I just move on to something else, often something nearby.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I find a problem I can solve, and then I solve it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And everything else becomes easier.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-27-04:25.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-28-04:40.html</id>
    <title>You can't write life down</title>
    <updated>2021-07-28T06:04:42+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You can't write life down&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From "Trickster Makes this World", pages 313-314:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of the nineteenth century, a certain Father J. Jetté, Jesuit missionary to the Athabascan Indians, lived among the Ten’a in the lower Yukon. In those days the Ten’a told the old stories in the dead of winter, from early December to the middle of January. The group with whom Father Jetté lived would go to bed in the early evening, a dozen or more rolling themselves in blankets on the floor around the cabin, their heads to the wall. The last one blew out the light, throwing the room into complete darkness (every chink and crack was caulked against the cold, and gunnysacks hung outside the windows to keep the window panes from frosting over). Before long, someone would start a story—“In old times, it is said …”—the listeners responding anni! anni! to keep the voice going. “A strange thing had occurred: the sun had disappeared, and all was in the dark. What was to be done? the old women asked. Who will get back the sun for us?” Peals of laughter as Raven is lured from seclusion by the promise of dog meat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Father Jetté wanted very much to make a collection of tales, but there were difficulties. The Ten’a were reluctant to let the Raven stories be put in writing, for one thing (though another group of tales “the inane stories,” Jetté calls them—could be had for the asking). Jetté tried to transcribe tales as they were being told, but the utter darkness frustrated him. Nobody would repeat the stories in daylight, and at night whenever he struck a match to light a candle, the storyteller fell instantly silent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In case it needs be said, Jetté was in the wrong in this piece, and the Ten'a in the right.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not for intrinsic reasons. I take no stance on whether writing down the Raven stories would have been good or bad,
but from a moral standpoint the Ten'a had the right to refuse Jetté's desire to write those stories down,
and Jetté had an obligation to respect that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I confess my sympathies are with Jetté.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I often feel significant distress at the sheer amount of the past that we will never know about.
Depending on who you ask and how you count, modern humans have been around for 50,000 to 200,000 years,
with (necessarily imprecise) estimates of the total numbers of humans who have ever lived being in the region of 100 billion.
So many lives we'll never know anything about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They're probably mostly fine with that. This is my problem, not theirs. Nevertheless, I feel it as a loss.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But really, what would be gained by writing it down? Sure, I would know about them, and that's not nothing,
but it's not really a rendition of what happened either. You write &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; what happened, but you can never capture the actual event.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Peals of laughter as Raven is lured from seclusion by the promise of dog meat." - would I have laughed at the same story? Perhaps it might have elicited a chuckle, or a wry smile. Perhaps if I had been in the room with the Ten'a I might have shared their laughter. I doubt a written account would really convey it though. Maybe you have to be there?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or maybe you have to be them. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-04-12:52.html"&gt;Humour is a test of expertise&lt;/a&gt;, but the ultimate expertise is the full context of a life. There are always jokes that only work in context, and are hilarious but too specific to be able to extract.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first wrote about jokes, I thought of dividing them into the pure ones and the conditional ones. A conditional joke is one that can work only with certain audiences, and typically is meant only for those audiences. The audience must supply something in order either to get the joke or to be amused by it. That something is the condition on which the success of the joke depends. It is a vital feature of much joking that only a suitably qualified audience—one that can meet the condition—can receive the joke, and the audience often derives an additional satisfaction from knowing this about itself. A pure joke would be universal, would get through to everyone, because it presupposed nothing in the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It now seems clear to me that there is no such thing as a pure joke. It is a kind of ideal, but it doesn’t exist. At the very least, the audience will have to understand the language of the joke, and probably much more. But even if all jokes are conditional, it is still useful to note just how strongly conditional a particular joke is, and just what kind of condition is presupposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For something like this, the condition seems deeply cultural.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The idea of writing it down anyway is not, I think, intrinsically bad (except in that the Ten'a don't want you to), but the version of it that you have written down is not the version that the Ten'a told, and there is no way around this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Walter Ong, in the subtitle of his "Orality and Literacy", calls writing the "technologising of the word", and Albert Borgmann in his "Technology and the Character of Contemporary Life" talks about how the role of technology is &lt;em&gt;commoditisation&lt;/em&gt;. You take "things", complex objects with rich history and context, and replace them with "devices", which are largely interchangeable objects whose purposes is to provide some good as an equally interchangeable commodity. A fireplace is a thing, a space heater is a device.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This feels like a good summation of what's happening here: We're treating these Raven stories, and the context in which they are embedded, as if they have a neat, singular, purpose that we can capture by writing it down. The "commodity" that the word provides is its content.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I learned about Cohen's book on Jokes from C. Thi Nguyen's &lt;a href="http://schwitzsplinters.blogspot.com/2021/07/the-philosophy-of-art-technology.html"&gt;The Philosophy of Art is the Philosophy of Technology&lt;/a&gt;, where he says:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This observation [about how a change in the way people went tothe movies changed their contents] teaches us a few things. First: what’s most important about a medium for communication often isn’t in the raw material at the center, but in its social embeddedness. Much of what is crucial to the medium of film isn’t just in the images and sounds — it’s in the social process of theater-going. It’s in the fact that showtimes are, or aren’t, published in the newspaper. Second: tiny changes in the medium can have enormous social repercussions and shift the whole pattern of how people relate to an artform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing down the Raven stories would have utterly transformed them. Even if they had been preserved, the way people engaged with them would be different, and the results would be something new and probably lesser.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But now I will end with a confession: I still half wish someone had written those Raven stories down. I fully respect the right of the Ten'a to refuse this, and would not have pushed and would not push them to choose otherwise, but I am still sad about their absence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The role of the word may be to commoditise knowledge, but everything feeds into everything else, and by writing things down, no matter how disconnected they are from their source, we can provide the seeds of new things that would not otherwise have existed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We will then, of course, also fail to write those things down in a way that preserves them, but I am at peace with that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-28-04:40.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-29-16:22.html</id>
    <title>The changing nature of sick days</title>
    <updated>2021-07-29T16:52:38+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The changing nature of sick days&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting things about the COVID pandemic is that it very much changes the dynamics of sickness (if you're dealing with reasonable people anyway, which I acknowledge many of us are not).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Previously, if you called in a sick day, I feel like this was treated as a moral failing. You should just tough it out, come to work anyway, anything else is weakness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has helped highlight the fact that actually no, the reason to call in sick is to avoid giving people a virus. COVID-19 is a particularly bad virus to give people, but it's not like the other ones floating around are much fun either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The flip side of this of course is that although there's a stronger case to call in sick, when you're already working from home the fact that you just feel a bit grotty doesn't really stop you from working. It just reduces your capacity - unless you're really badly off you still &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do some work, you just would rather not. As a result, you take both more and fewer sick days, depending on how one interprets the term.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you're not noticeably ill, this has no effect. If you're very ill, this also has no effect (or minimal - you need to convincingly demonstrate that you're very ill). In the middle it has the odd effect of making things better if you're not ill enough that you would previously have stayed home, and worse if you are ill enough that you would have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not that too many people are going in to the office right now anyway, so this is mostly hypothetical, I'm just interested in thinking about what impact COVID will have on our social norms. Maybe none.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For my part, the big differences are just that I'm more willing to cancel social events when I have a cold. I don't know if that will last when there's no longer a pandemic on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm essentially self-employed, so COVID didn't make much difference to my attitude personally. I tend to do what I can, such as write a very mediocre post about sick days, when ill, and stick to coaching sessions I've committed to unless I'm utterly nonfunctional, but otherwise don't worry about it too much.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general I feel like modern life is not well set up for the intrinsic unreliability of humans, especially humans as awash in different virus sources as modern life also brings us, but I'll leave musing further on that for some time when my brain is working better.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-29-16:22.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-30-09:52.html</id>
    <title>Can you throw money at the Collatz Conjecture?</title>
    <updated>2021-07-30T17:53:35+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Can you throw money at the Collatz Conjecture?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-30&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Warning: Inside baseball, very much a set of notes rather than a coherent point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For context, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collatz_conjecture"&gt;the Collatz conjecture&lt;/a&gt; is the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For any given natural number \(n\), if \(n\) is even, move to \(\frac{n}{2}\), otherwise move to \(3n + 1\).
The Collatz conjecture is that no matter which \(n\) we start with, we will eventually reach \(1\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is, as far as I know, no particular reason to care about the Collatz conjecture except that it's interesting and that we don't know how to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1421051043266408449"&gt;I claimed on Twitter that you could probably solve the Collatz conjecture in a decade, given $1 billion of funding&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bpgbcg/status/1421057248365776899"&gt;Ben Gunby disagrees&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think we disagreed a lot. My estimate was something like "this would probably work", and I think his is something like "this probably wouldn't work". As far as I can tell neither of us thinks the other's position is ridiculous, we've just got moderately different views on the problem. That being said, having written all of this up, I've concluded that he's right and I'm wrong, because I had significantly underestimated how hard the Collatz conjecture is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the following is a fair summary of his argument that this is likely to be very hard:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are likely quite far away from techniques that would allow us to tackle the Collatz conjecture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If this is the case, there is likely a long dependency chain in which we have to develop tools to develop tools to develop tools etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If this is the case, this likely passes through many fields unrelated to the Collatz conjecture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$1 billion is a lot but it's not enough to literally bend the whole of mathematical research to your whims.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To look at this from another perspective, one can think of this in terms of two questions:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many direct mathematician-years of work do we need to solve the Collatz conjecture? i.e. if you add up all the mathematician-years of work spent on the proof and things it depends on, what do you get?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many mathematician-years of work do we realistically need to do in order to actually achieve that? This would be the same if you could just linearly proceed from A to B, but if you depend on unrelated fields you need to take into account work done in equally plausible unrelated fields that you couldn't have known in advance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much of that work is intrinsically sequential? e.g. if we decided that it will take 1000 mathematician-years, can we do that in 10 years with 100 mathematicians or are you going to have to do a full 1000 years of work with one mathematician building on the results of another, etc?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;("mathematician-years" of course depends on how good the mathematicians in question are. I guess I'm assuming reasonably top end mathematicians)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Ben and my intuitions on these differ as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His estimate of the number of mathematician-years required is much higher than mine initially was.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think you probably can cut out a lot of the unrelated work with a bit of work on focusing people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe this is more parallelisable than he does.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On further reading up on the difficulty of the literature I think that he is right and I am wrong about the first one,
and I've significantly underestimated how hard the Collatz conjecture is. In particular "The Ultimate Challenge" by Lagarias has a good survey that made me realise I'd underestimated the problem. &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.03562.pdf"&gt;Terence Tao made good progress on the problem in 2019&lt;/a&gt; and this good progress established a &lt;em&gt;substantially&lt;/em&gt; weaker result than the full conjecture. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For comparison, I think reasonable estimates for how many mathematician years went into solving Fermat's Last Theorem are somewhere in the region of 1000 to 10,000 mathmatician years, taking 1900 as the starting point (Most of the work on it that got real traction happened in the 20th century, I think). If on average 100 mathematicians were working on it full time at any given point of that century, that gets us to 10,000. If it's only 10, that's 1,000.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is that realistic? I don't know. I could also make a convincing argument that it was less than that (e.g. a lot of the last stretch was Wiles working on his own for 7 years, followed by Wiles and Taylor finishing it off...). But lets say 10,000 mathematicians years is about how much FLT took. It's a nice round number.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is the Collatz conjecture about as hard as FLT starting from 1900? I don't know. Based on my reading since Ben and my initial disagremeent... yeah, probably. Possibly even harder. We've got a number of partial results and angles of attack on it, but certainly nothing resembling a convincing story. It might be that it's actually amenable to some easy attack, but I don't think we've got any reason to expect that to be the case, and people who have studied it more than me seem to think it's probably too hard for us right now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose now that we could just turn money into mathematician-years. A high end mathematician salary seems to be about $100k. Because we want the best, and also need support staff and infrastructure, lets double that and say that one mathematician year costs us $200k. $1 billion now gets us 5,000 mathematician years.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, based on these (admittedly somewhat pessimistic) estimates, even if we could make a perfect beeline for the Collatz conjecture, if it's about as hard starting from now as Fermat's Last Theorem was starting from 1900, we should not expect to be able to solve it with a mere billion dollars.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is before we even get to the harder questions to quantify. What if exploring all the dead ends means we actually need 100,000 mathematician years?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, what happens with the dependencies problem? Can we, realistically, do even those 10,000 mathematician-years in 10 years even if we had infinite amounts of money to throw at it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't have a good handle on this but think the answer is a resounding "Maybe". If we again use Fermat's Last Theorem as a benchmark it doesn't seem unreasonable to me to think that we could do this - that's only one order of magnitude reduction, and I think if we had the relevant parties in a room together and were able to more aggressively speed up the collaboration, offer them support, etc. I don't think this is &lt;em&gt;ridiculous&lt;/em&gt;. Wiles worked on FLT for 7 years on his own, and I wouldn't be surprised if he could have done that in half with a collaborator to discuss things with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is all speculative though, I genuinely don't know, and I don't have any way to know. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polymath_Project"&gt;The polymath project&lt;/a&gt; gives me some hope that hard mathematical problems are parallelisable, but as far as I know it's never been tried on anything nearly this hard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, in conclusion, Ben is probably right. You probably can't solve this is in a decade with $1 billion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; think you could probably make meaningful progress on the Collatz conjecture, up to and including solving it, with a mere $1 billion, but I think if I were to do that it would look more like trying to build resources and community around it in the broader mathematical community.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, for this sort of price tag one could fund:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some sort of ongoing "residency" arrangement where a rotating group of mathematicians get together and work on the Collatz conjecture and related problems for a year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many small cash prizes for Collatz adjacent conjectures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put together a small team whose primary job was to essentially shore up results, generate conjectures, and write up the state of the art of current Collatz research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many post grad positions for getting people working on the problem for a period of time early in their career&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An alternative approach would be to just hire Terence Tao and Jeffrey Lagarias, and any dozen or so other mathematicians they care to name, and let them go wild on the problem. I doubt it would work, but it might produce something interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-30-09:52.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
