<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2021-10-08T01:23:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-08-07-08:15.html</id>
    <title>Notes towards a social technology R&amp;D lab</title>
    <updated>2021-08-07T13:51:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes towards a social technology R&amp;amp;D lab&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-08-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I mentioned on Twitter that I'd like to run a "small R&amp;amp;D lab where we mostly do low budget weird social technology nonsense".
This was not something I mentioned as a serious plan, but a throwaway comment about escapist fantasies.
There was a surprising amount of interest in the idea though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;I should maybe mention that if you want to spot me about £2 million over a 3-4 year period to change the world, I'm all ears and we should definitely talk. &lt;a href="https://t.co/EvHd5tcDXh"&gt;https://t.co/EvHd5tcDXh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— David R. MacIver (@DRMacIver) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1423669891345813507?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 6, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In response to this, people have quite reasonably be asking what it is I actually &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; by this plan, because it's not obvious.
So I thought I'd try to articulate this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is not really a proper pitch document, more of a sketch of the idea, but if you've got some spare cash and &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; a proper pitch document it could definitely turn into one).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What's social technology?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think people might have the wrong idea about what I mean by "social technology", which is fair enough as it's not a particularly commonly used term. By "social technology", I don't mean a type of software, I mean something more like sets of practices that people can do together, that have the character of technology, in that they are a well defined thing that benefits from research and development.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I talked about this in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/the-missing-social-technology-sector/"&gt;The missing social technology sector&lt;/a&gt;. My definition from there is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social technology is “technology” built out of groups of people following rules, maybe with assistance from simple props, rather than software, machinery, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've since read Nguyen's "Games: Agency as Art", which I think has helped refine my thoughts on this subject more. Social technology is technology built out of &lt;em&gt;group agency&lt;/em&gt;. It builds a structure to constrain and support the sort of actions that a group can take together, in a way that helps them achieve some desired end.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of a social technology:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pen and paper roleplaying game. Dungeons and Dragons is the classic example, but I think lightweight games like &lt;a href="http://www.onesevendesign.com/laserfeelings/"&gt;Lasers and Feelings&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://img.fireden.net/tg/image/1491/35/1491350819880.pdf"&gt;Four Sherlock Holmes and a Vampire. (Who Is Also One of the Aforementioned Sherlock Holmes)&lt;/a&gt; where the rules fit in a page are a more interesting set of examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed dating.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://agilecoffee.com/leancoffee/"&gt;Lean Coffee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coaching and therapy type arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are designed with the following ends in mind:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A roleplaying game has a &lt;em&gt;ludic end&lt;/em&gt; (the thing you are trying to achieve in the game - uncover the vampire, prevent Zorgon the Conqueror from building a quantum tunnel that will rip a hole in reality), but the ultimate end is to have fun, and you are adopting the ludic end in order to achieve that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed dating you are looking for people to date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lean Coffee you are trying to have a productive discussion across a range of topics, and the structure supports you in picking interesting topics and keeping the meeting on track.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coaching and therapy provide someone with a space to work through a particular problem of interest to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of other examples, both explicit and implicit. For example, &lt;a href="https://www.liberatingstructures.com/"&gt;Liberating Structures&lt;/a&gt; is an entire group of people designing social technology for meetings, and every interviewing pipeline is an ad hoc and buggy piece of social technology. The academic field of social choice theory (which mostly designs voting systems) is a really interesting area of social technology that to within rounding error of nobody uses.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course in a certain light almost everything people do is social technology. There isn't a hard and fast line that makes some things social technology and some things not social technology, in the same way "But is it art?" is an unanswerable question. As a concept, "social technology" is useful less for categorising things and more as a lens through which to view them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular viewing something as social technology starts from asking two questions:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is this practice trying to do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we do that better?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Why do we need social technology R&amp;amp;D?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the most common pieces of social technology that I've encountered outside of games is meeting facilitation.
Liberating Structures is one of the best examples of meeting facilitation social technology that I'm familiar with,
and mostly seems to be very good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, most other social technology I've encountered for meeting faciliation are quite bad, and leans heavily on the skill of the meeting facilitator rather than the technology, and the technology itself is often quite clunky.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Take lean coffee for example. A lot of people really like lean coffee. I attended some lean coffee sessions and they were awful. I loved the idea, I loved what it was trying to do, and the execution has obvious glaring flaws that I feel would have been obvious and easily fixable if they had ever done any sort of playtesting. I cannot imagine they did.
In response I designed &lt;a href="https://github.com/DRMacIver/systems/blob/master/tempo.md"&gt;TickTalk&lt;/a&gt;, which I think is pretty good. It could certainly use more play testing itself, but it's had some and I really do think it's &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; better than lean coffee.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Brainstorming is another example. Brainstorming doesn't work. We're pretty sure of this now. It produces results that are worse than not using it. Many things &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; brainstorming work, and work well, but brainstorming itself very much doesn't.
A little bit of development and experimentation could have revealed this early on, but instead as far as I can tell people just had an idea, slapped a name on it, and declared it the hot new thing that everyone should be doing, and it worked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The common theme here (and why liberating structures tend to be Actually Good) is obvious I hope: &lt;em&gt;Playtest your social technology&lt;/em&gt;, and learn from it and improve it.
People don't do this enough, and are using really bad systems as a result.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Social technology R&amp;amp;D is the solution to this problem. You treat these systems as a piece of technology like any other, and you develop them as such. You try things, you see what works, and you refine based on that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't a novel idea in social technology, everyone who designes games knows this. If you make a game and don't playtest it, you'll get a game that isn't fun and nobody plays. In contrast, when you design a meeting facilitation system, it only has to be less bad than an unfacilitated meeting (this isn't hard), and also you can usually impose it by fiat, so there's much less direct incentive to be good. This is ridiculous though - meetings are expensive and potentially high value, so anything that increases that value or decrease that cost is obviously good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Weird low budget social technology nonsense?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I'm interested in has two defining features:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing social technologies for a broad range of problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...that can be implemented easily and cheaply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, take speed dating. Has anyone actually ever done any speed dating R&amp;amp;D? Speed dating doesn't seem to work particularly well for people, and some of that is because dating is intrinsically awkward, but a lot of it does seem like the structure is just very poorly designed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm pretty confident nobody has ever done a detailed user experience analysis of speed dating and tried to improve it in a principled way. Someone just had the idea, people tweaked it a bit, and it mostly works well enough. For the same reason meeting design lacks a strong incentive to improve (because meetings are so bad that anything helps), speed dating has little incentive to improve (because there's no shortage of single people who would really like some help with dating).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, speed dating is primarily a low value proposition. People don't pay a lot for speed dating, so where would the budget for improving it come from?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(People &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; use speed dating for research, but it seems to be primarily using speed dating as a methodology for studying romantic interactions. i.e. it's people taking the social technology as read and using it to do social science)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Taking something like speed dating and improving it for its intended purpose, and also finding other interesting applications of those approaches (for example, what would a "Speed dating, but you're there to make friends" event look like? How should one do bi/poly speed dating? Could one do a speed dating event to start up a co-coaching network?), is the sort of low budget social technology I'd like to develop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another example of a problem I think would be interesting to study is this: &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2016/11/democracy-for-lunch/"&gt;How do you decide where to go for lunch?&lt;/a&gt;. Or where to go to the cinema. Or what to cook tonight... You get the idea. Collective decision making is common, but I don't actually know how common, and I don't know what the best way to do it is.
I have a history of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:27.html"&gt;solving this for people by just telling them what to do&lt;/a&gt;, but it sure would be interesting to study this class of problem and how to do it better, wouldn't it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, the sort of thing I would like to do is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify reasonably common social problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop social technologies to improve them that can be explained in one or two pages, and implemented with cheap and/or commonly available tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of low hanging fruit of this nature, mostly based on the fact that the individual examples that gain traction don't seem like they're still very much picking low hanging fruit, and it shouldn't be hard to find others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What would this look like in practice?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Gosh, that's a great question, this has turned from a vague idea into something resembling a structured plan remarkably quickly, so this is the bit underspecified, so please bear in mind that I wasn't planning to do this for a while and part of the thing that this would look like in practice is getting a bunch of people together to figure out the details.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The general procedure we'd want to use for developing social technology is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create or identify a prototype piece of social technology with a Version 0 document describing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Playtest it amongst ourselves, then with random members of the public, until we're happy with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish a Version 1.0 version of the social technology in public, probably under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt; license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over time publish updated and improved versions of it in response to subsequent usage and feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Both (1) and (2) are the bits that need a lot of trial and error. The following are probably the two main sources of prototypes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Study what people actually do in the wild and extract it into something standalone.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often this can start from existing literature. e.g. speed dating comes pre studied. The "teaching open ended style" protocol from Vaughn Tan's The Uncertainty Mindset that I talked about in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-teach-the-local-style"&gt;How to teach the local style&lt;/a&gt; is another example where you can just get it from books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often you can get paid to find this out! Going into a company and consulting with them is a great way to find out what they actually do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting from problems people have (e.g. we could find this out by offering coaching and consultancy services) and then trying to generate solutions to those. This would probably need us to work a bit on the social technology that supports generating these solutions, but I expect we'd be using Liberating Structures or the like as starting points for that rather than trying to invent new ones from scratch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Actively work on the social technology underpinning how the group runs itself, and try to extract this into reusable standalone features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as producing the actual final products, there would probably be:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of writing about the things we learn along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various professional services built on top of this. I think there is quite a lot of scope for this to lead into a lucrative consulting and training business around these things, as a lot of it would be quite useful to companies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What would this need?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My dream version of this where I get to run an actual R&amp;amp;D institution looks something like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Staff would be:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A small team of about 5 for the actual R&amp;amp;D.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone to do admin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probably someone to do sales and marketing? Certainly this would be needed eventually.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of this would need to be done in person (at least post COVID...). This would require an office and a studio space for running events.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that there would need to be budget for:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the usual company stuff. Computers, paying for software, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quite a lot of training, partly for people's personal growth, partly because it's important research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hiring people on one off contracts, for a mix of:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consulting specialists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paying people to do initial playtesting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A flexible group of people who we could bring in to do various research tasks (e.g. send out a bunch of interns to learn more about different meetup groups).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm expecting the professional services arm of the group would do quite well (it's potentially very high value for corporate customers). Initially (and to some degree ongoing - it's a good habit to keep your hand in on) this would be done by the R&amp;amp;D team. With increased demand, it would be necessary to bring on more staff to keep up with it, and eventually I would expect us to transition to having a full training arm.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;How plausible is all this?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly pretty plausible. Some of it is stuff I could do today, and may well start doing as I start providing more consulting and corporate training options built in to my existing work. It's possible that in five years time I may be doing exactly what I describe given no external intervention, assuming I still think it's a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The big questions are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there as much low hanging fruit as I think there is? (I'm reasonably confident there is)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I underestimating the amount of work playtesting takes? (I don't think so, in the sense that the amount of work people currently do is so low that even modest amounts would be an improvement)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there really enough demand for this to fund it? (I'm genuinely unsure about this one, but I think it's likely that there is if it's pitched right).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would this end up a niche thing used only by corporates and weirdos? (This is a totally plausible failure mode. Certainly I expect many of the things we develop would never see wide adoption. But I figure worst case scenario we make a lot of money improving various work environments and maybe make one or two useful prosocial innovations)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All told I'd be very surprised if &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; in this space couldn't be made to work, and also very surprised if what ends up working looks exactly like I've outlined in this document, because technology startups never work out that way, and that's ultimately what this idea is.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-08-07-08:15.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-08-08-12:28.html</id>
    <title>how to write like this</title>
    <updated>2021-08-08T12:59:15+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;how to write like this&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-08-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drossbucket.com/"&gt;Lucy&lt;/a&gt; and I were talking about the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-27-04:25.html"&gt;You have to do the easy bits first&lt;/a&gt; piece, and she asked me how I wrote it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's a good question. I didn't answer it very well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here, let's have another go.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way to write like this is to write like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That isn't a very helpful answer, huh.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One more time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way to write like THIS is to write like THIS!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the way to write&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;like this&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;is to write&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;like this&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;thewaytowritelikethisistowritelike this&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You see?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way to change how you write is to change how you write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The best part of the answer I gave Lucy earlier is that the thing where the paragraphs are short (I said one sentence, but actually looking again they're not) is more important than you'd think.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way to change the voice you write in is to write in a different voice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the voice of your writing is&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;determined by its form. As you shift&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the layout&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the format&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the literal physical way the words appear on the page&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the sound of what you are writing changes, and with it the voice in which you write moves to match.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I write like this, in long discursive paragraphs, in which I patiently explain the thing I am doing to you, that is one voice. I can fuck with it if I want, right? Code switch mid paragraph. I don't have to write like a tedious book, but this is the tone that I naturally fall back into, because habits of writing are entrained ways of being, that one grows comfortable in. If you try to do a thing that is well served by a particular mode, you have to actively exert effort to avoid falling back into that mode. It's entirely possible, especially if you have other modes that you're used to and can borrow from, but without the clarity that those modes provide, it is difficult to avoid. It is hard to write differently without first deciding what that difference is, and the easiest form of difference is to be able to say "More like &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you fuck with the form&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;you instantly break the habit&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;because&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the habit can no longer serve you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Will the result be good? Nah, probably not. That's OK.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/arts/english/currentstudents/undergraduate/modules/fulllist/first/en122/lecturelist-2015-16-2/shklovsky.pdf"&gt;Viktor Shklovsky thinks that art is about defamiliarisation&lt;/a&gt;, and I think this is even more true for the artist than for the viewer of the art.
In order to create art, you must first break out of your habitual mode of engaging with the thing you are depicting.
Anything that breaks the habit by forcing you outside of what it can do will help you to achieve that,
by pushing you into a mode where everything is strange, and giving you a space in which to learn that strangeness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;but if you do what you also do&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;you'll get what you always get.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is uncomfortable at first, of course it is. You're learning a whole new way of engaging with the world through writing.
Stay with that discomfort, and write through it, and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or, in short:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way to write like this is to write like this.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-08-08-12:28.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-02-08:53.html</id>
    <title>On feeling blocked, redux</title>
    <updated>2021-10-02T09:05:22+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;On feeling blocked, redux&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ages ago, when struggling to write, I wrote &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-20-10:33.html"&gt;On feeling blocked&lt;/a&gt;, in which I describe the phenomenology of writer's block.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been really struggling with writing my newsletter recently, so I've decided to solve this with resuming daily writing, and it seemed natural to start by returning to the subject. A year and a half on I have a very different perspective on writer's block.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's this: Writer's block is not wanting to write, or wanting not to write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may seem overly simple, but it's not. It just moves the complexity. Wanting is complicated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular, often some parts of you will want to write, and some parts of you will want not to write, and the resulting inner conflict leads to writer's block.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In "On feeling blocked":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being blocked feels like this. It's not that there's an actual block, it's that you reach for a part of your brain where the words come from and it's not there. You can't run out of ideas and you know this, but you try to follow the steps of the idea generating process and the world glitches and you realise you cut off mid-sentence and have been reading Twitter for the last half hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That sort of distraction is exactly what (at least one type of) an inner conflict feels like. A part of you drives you to write, a part of you resists with some emotional judo and redirects you somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3l08rfl"&gt;On Writer's Block&lt;/a&gt; by Victoria Nelson is a good book about the emotional dynamics of writer's block which, ultimately, boils down to a long discussion of reasons why you might want not to write. Typically they're some variation on wanting to write something that you don't feel able to, or that you feel scared about in some way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular they often come down to trying to adhere to a standard that you don't feel you can be good enough for, or feeling that you should write in a way that isn't actually very good.
e.g. a lot of people get blocked because they're trying to write like they learned to in school and everything comes out boring.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm blocked on my newsletter at the moment. I don't entirely know why, but the symptom is that I have lots of unfinished posts. The solution is probably to write the newsletter more like I do the notebook. I don't feel able to do that, I don't know why yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I'm going to get back to writing even if I can't write the newsletter. Life is much better when I write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The fundamental principles are the same as they always are. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-05-08:59.html"&gt;Make success trivial&lt;/a&gt; then apply &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/05/how-to-do-hard-things/"&gt;the fully general system&lt;/a&gt;. The fact that in this case the hard thing is something that I already in theory know how to do doesn't matter, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-12-08:19.html"&gt;things can be hard for lots of reasons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-02-08:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-02-12:17.html</id>
    <title>Book speedrun: On Humour by Simon Critchley</title>
    <updated>2021-10-02T14:52:06+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Book speedrun: On Humour by Simon Critchley&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lucy Keer has a thing she does called &lt;a href="https://drossbucket.com/2021/09/17/research-speedruns/"&gt;Research Speedruns&lt;/a&gt; where she sets a timer for an hour and learns everything she can about a topic during that time, writing as she goes. I've liked the idea for a while but rarely have this sort of problem where there's a topic I want to speedrun finding out about, but I do have a lot of books that I'd like to delve more deeply into (usually ones I've done a first pass on) and an intention to write more, so I thought I'd try a similar experiment of doing book speedruns.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic plan is to just write about the book for an hour in whatever mode takes me. A lot of it will be about random prompts from the book, some of it will be non-random thoughts on the book. It won't necessarily hang together in any especially coherent way. In particular it's not a book review, it's just thoughts inspired by the book.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The book I'll be speedrunning to start with is "On Humour" by Simon Critchely. It's a book about philosophy of humour that I found because Critchley was mentioned in Carr and Greeve's book about humour "The Naked Jape". It's short and I've read it in full, but at the time I didn't feel like I got a great deal out of it. It was locally interesting, but I didn't feel like I really changed my thinking based on it at all, so I thought it would be good to see if a speedrun could help with that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Structured Fun&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 12:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humour is being employed as a management tool by consultants - imagine, if you will, a company called 'Humour Solutions International' - who endeavour to show how it can produce greater cohesion amongst the workforce and thereby increase efficiency and productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...it is difficult not to feel a little cynical about these endeavours, and the question that one wants to pose to the idea of 'structured fun' is: who is structure the fun and for what end?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I must admit I've never run into this, and I'm very thankful for that because it probably wouldn't have gone well for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have a couple objections to this sort of structured fun use of humour. I guess the morally strongest of them is the one that Critchley goes on to mention, which is that it's a tool of control by management, and trying to impose humour on people is interfering with their private lives.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It also reminds me of the whole problem of corporate mindfulness. One of the virtues of humour is that it helps cope with a bad situation, but when that virtue is being touted by people responsible for that bad situation, that seems intrinsically problematic.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I must admit though my true objection is that I bet such corporate workshops are painfully unfunny.
I have a real aversion to people trying too hard to be funny and falling short.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am in fact interested in humour partly for its benefits to organisations, and as a communal practice among workers, but I can't help but think that any attempt to impose that from above is likely to do more harm than good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Humour's us&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 73:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, humour is what returns us to our locale, to a specific &lt;em&gt;ethos&lt;/em&gt; which is often identified with a particular people possessing a shared set of customs and characteristics. A sense of humour is often what is felt to be best shared with people who are from the same place as us, and it is that aspect of social life which is perhaps the most difficult to explain to people from somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In context this is talking about literal places - countries, villages, etc. But I do think this is more general - in "Jokes: Philosophical Reflections on Joking Matters", Ted Cohen talks about how contextual humour is - there is always an audience of people for whom the joke is intended - and talks about &lt;em&gt;hermetic jokes&lt;/em&gt; which are those that you have to be part of a specific profession to get. I think humour can return us to a parochial "place" within their profession as well as their country. There are very much the sorts of jokes you tell as engineers, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A shared sense of humour with someone is how you know they are "one of us", and helps define what that "us" is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This ties back in to the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-04-12:52.html"&gt;humour test for expertise&lt;/a&gt;, but in a very broad sense of expertise. Getting the national sense of humour is often how you know you're a native, fluent in the local culture.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Humour's them&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 76:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;jokes can be read in terms of what or who a particular society is subordinating, scapegoating, or denigrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The fact of the matter is that a lot of humour is about people you look down on. In context, Critchley is talking about anti-semitism and other racist jokes, and what they say about our subconscious feelings that we are repressing (though of course they can equally say things about the conscious things that we are expressing).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't help but tie this back to a bit from the structured fun section. From page 14:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has worked in a factory or office knows how the most scurrilous and usually obscene stories, songs and cartoons about the management are the very bread and butter of survival. Humour might well be a management tool but it is also a tool against the management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is of course very different from the case of racist jokes, in that it is humour against those with power rather than those who are marginalised (punching up vs punching down, if you must).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the jokes do have one common function: They are very clearly delineating the line of us vs them. If "us" is the group of people we laugh &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt;, then "them" are the group of people we laugh &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Whether this us and them division is bad is hard to comment on in generality - it seems like it's clearly sometimes bad and clearly sometimes a necessary coping mechanism.
e.g. you can tell how politics is going by how Soviet the jokes get.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't find the original source of this joke but it's been doing the rounds recently:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boris Johnson visited a village in Cornwall and asked the inhabitants what the government could do for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"We have two big needs" said the village spokesman. "The first is we have a health centre but no doctor."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boris whipped out his phone, talked for a while then said, "OK, =that's sorted, you'll have a doctor here tomorrow. Now, what was your other need?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Well, we have no mobile reception at all in our village."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yeah, so that's how our politics is going.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While I have you here, here's a joke from page 21 of "Forbidden Laughter (Soviet Underground Jokes)".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An old woman ran with all her might to catch the jam-packed city bus. "Thank God!" she sighed, having made it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A citizen sitting next to her said: "You expressed that improperly, auntie. You should know that there is no God. You should have said 'Thank Stalin'."
"You're right, son, you're right," said the old woman in agreement. "Excuse me, I'm a little behind the times."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after thinking awhile, the old woman asked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"God forbid this should happen, but what am I supposed to say if Stalin should die?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"In that case, perhaps you may say 'Thank God'."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Well you've got to laugh about it&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Page 101 has a section called "Humour as an antidepressant". His approach to this is very Freudian and I'm not sure I fully follow his argument, but on page 102 he declares:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would argue that humour recalls to us the modesty and limitedness of the human condition, a limitedness that calls not only for tragic-heroic affirmation but comic &lt;em&gt;acknowledgement&lt;/em&gt;, not Promethean authencity but a laughable inauthenticity."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recently finished reading John Marmysz's "Laughing at Nothing: Humour as a response to nihilism", which argues that nihilism can be viewed as a conjunction of three things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humanity is alienated from perfection (true meaning, perfect goodness, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is other than it should be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This situation cannot be remedied.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The book was a (ultimately somewhat unconvincing, though I enjoyed it anyway) argument that instead of, as nihilists traditionally do, regarding that combination as tragic, we can regard it as comedic, laughing at the incongruity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Critchley's argument that humour acts as an antidepressant by reminding us of "the modesty and limitedness of the human condition" feels similar. We take the tragic and attempt to find it funny, perhaps by putting it into perspective.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems to tie in to the laughing at the people with power over you. That power exists and is other than it should be, but we can find it funny as well as oppressive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At the end of the book, on page 111, Critchley recounts an extract from a French city that had been bombed in world war 2 and the concludes the book:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it is this smile - deriding the having and the not having, the pleasure and the pain, the sublimiity and suffering of the human situation - that is the essence of humour. This is the &lt;em&gt;risus purus&lt;/em&gt;, the highest laugh, the laugh that laughs at that which is unhappy, the mirthless laugh of the epigraph of this book. Yet, this smile does not bring unhappiness, but rather elevation and liberation, the lucidity of consolation. This is why, melancholy animals that we are, human beings are also the most cheerful. We smile and find ourselves ridiclous. Our wretchedness is our greatness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The epigraph in question is the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bitter, the hollow and - haw! haw! - the mirthless. The bitter laugh laughs at that which is not good, it is the ethical laugh. The holow laugh laughs at that which is not true, it is the intellectual laugh. Not good! Not true! Well, well. But the mirthless laugh is the dianoetic laugh, down the snout - haw! - so. It is the laugh of laughs, the &lt;em&gt;risusu purus&lt;/em&gt;, the laugh laughing at the laugh, the beholding, the saluting of the highest joke, in a word the laugh that laughs - silence please - at that which is unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Samuel Becket, &lt;strong&gt;Watt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hey Critchley, what's yellow and equivalent to the axiom of choice? Zorn's Lemon.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Try finding some misery in that joke, gloomy guts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can tell, I'm starting to lose a bit of patience with Critchley. If humour is, as he claims, an antidepressant, why is his book on humour coming across so morbid?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is, I think, a thing that happens with a lot of philosophy of humour where you're supposed to make what is ultimately a light hearted subject very serious, and the easiest way to do that seems to be to ground it in human misery. Humour is cruel, humour is exclusionary, humour is a coping mechanism for the intrinsic misery of the human condition, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of this is true, but I do think it misses one of the most important features of humour, which is that humour is &lt;em&gt;funny&lt;/em&gt;, and in being funny is fun.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is me being a little unfair to Critchley and is in part a consequence of the thread I pulled on with these samples so far, but I do think there is a significant undercurrent of this in the book, and the epigraph and conclusion very much highlight that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Only as good as its jokes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 66:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any study of humour, again like anthropology, requires fieldwork and detailed contextualisation. Finally, it is only as good as its examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned above, I recently finished reading "The Naked Jape". It's not an amazing book, but it's a lot of fun to read, and one of its virtues is that it has a joke at the bottom of every page.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm particularly fond of the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two nuns are driving through Transylvania when Count Dracula suddenly jumps on their car. "Quick, show him your cross" says one of the nuns. The other nun shouts, "Hey, Dracula! Fuck off!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rikkhill/status/1432051001264156674"&gt;Previously introduced to me by Rikk Hill&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And I think the difference between this and On Humour is telling. A study of humour might only be as good as its examples, but a book of philosophy of humour is only as good as its jokes, and honestly the jokes in On Humour aren't very good. There are a few that raised a smile (The chapter on humour of the body is entitled "Post-Colonal Theory", and I must admit that's a good one), but the book takes itself more seriously than I think is warranted, and some better jokes might have helped offset that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm sortof surprised by how this went, as I thought I liked the book, but I apparently have some quite negative feelings about it that I hadn't noticed before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I liked doing a speedrun based on it, but I don't really feel like it gave the book a fair showing. Its was more like pulling on an interesting thread of the book, and that thread was certainly there in the book, but I don't think it was the whole of the book.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It might be worth returning to it later and doing another run through with a clear set of eyes and seeing if I get a different thread, but I will probably speedrun some other books first.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-02-12:17.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-03-08:59.html</id>
    <title>Notes on moral disorder</title>
    <updated>2021-10-03T10:04:42+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes on moral disorder&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a problem I keep trying to write about and failing to write a coherent longer piece on,
so here's some rough notes on it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Many people have emotional problems that are centrally concerned with &lt;em&gt;moral emotions&lt;/em&gt;. Guilt, shame, pride (in the good sense of pride).
Emotions that are centrally concerned with the question of whether you are acting or living morally.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The central example of moral disorder is this: Your life is made substantially worse, on an ongoing basis, by feelings of guilt and shame, stemming from a fear that your behaviour is bad or that you are a bad person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something that &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; count as moral disorder is &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;Acedia-based burnout&lt;/a&gt;, burnout from living out of line with your values. Not necessarily guilt and shame over your actions, but a lack of pride in your actions, &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Non-examples of moral disorder include:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone who has done a thing they feel guilty about, makes restitution, and stops feeling guilty about it (this is the emotion of guilt working as intended).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone who is a genuinely bad person but doesn't feel guilty about or ashamed of that (this is still a problem, but it's not what I would think of as moral disorder)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you're experiencing moral disorder people will probably tell you that genuinely bad people don't feel this way, your therapist might tell you that it's an attachment problem, or help you analyse where these feelings come from, and doubtless you'll find that they're part of some lesson you learned incorrectly or from the wrong people or etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But very few people helping you with this problem will consider what I think is a crucial question here: What if the reason you feel like a bad person is that you're a bad person?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is important to be able to ask this, even if the answer is no, because you can't trust the answer "no" unless the answer "yes" is allowed.
If you are not able to acknowledge moral failings if you have them, you will keep worrying about the possibility because you can't just shove feelings of guilt away like that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also the answer is probably actually yes, sorry.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the most common reason for moral disorder actually &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; something like "being a bad person".
Moral disorder will often not shift in response to therapeutic means, because your emotional responses are broadly correct: Your actions are ones you consider morally bad,
and you are experiencing the correct emotional response to that,
so attempting to feel fine by persuading yourself that your actions are fine won't work because you're basically just gaslighting yourself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead I think moral disorder typically comes from one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An incorrect moral framework. A moral framework that declares necessary actions to be bad, or makes no allowance for human limitations, will leave you always feeling guilty because you cannot act in a way that you judge to be moral.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An incorrect understanding of the relationship between bad action and being a bad person - there is no option for doing good in the world that does not sometimes have you doing harm, and the appropriate response to a harm is to feel guilty and, if possible, make restitution. Importantly, the amount of guilt should be proportionate to the amount of badness. If you step on someone's toe you should say "oops, sorry" and then mostly forget about it. You don't need to go full "Oh no I am the worst I am a worm can you ever forgive me?"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unhealthy emotional behaviours where you cannot deal with any amount of guilt, causing you to push it away, causing the level of guilt to rise until you can't ignore it, because that's how emotions work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(In case you're wondering which of these is me: Yes, all of them at one point or another)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are definitely more problems than this, e.g. I haven't currently got a good theory for where moral disorder that is an absence of positive moral emotions come from, or what to do about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The solution, I think, is some combination of therapy and ethical philosophy (especially virtue ethics, which is the good one for this, and especially not utilitarianism, which is a central example of (1). Yes I've heard your argument about why if you do utilitarianism hard enough it's good actually because it becomes one of the moral systems that actually work. I'd prefer to &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; with one that actually works without having to do five dimensional chess to get to the right answer though) - working with both right action and the emotions that go along with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The details? Ah, well, I'm still working on that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-03-08:59.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-07:03.html</id>
    <title>What does a good person look like?</title>
    <updated>2021-10-05T21:45:03+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;What does a good person look like?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From Intelligent Virtue by Julia Annas, page 106:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"A philosopher", says "Hume, "might select this character as a model of perfect virtue". It is always hard to be sure that we have got Hume's tone right, but if he is not being ironic here it is obvious that something is amiss. A yuppy lawyer who is great company at parties is a model perfect virtue? Can this be serious? What has gone wrong here? We do not need to go into Hume's account of virtue in depth to discover it (one reasonw hy the example is useful in the present connection). What the description of Cleanthes brings out is that someone may have a character that is useful and agreeable to himself and others, and still be utterly &lt;em&gt;uninspiring&lt;/em&gt;, somebody tha tnobody could take an &lt;em&gt;ideal&lt;/em&gt; of a 8good* person to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us compare Cleanthes with someone who really is admirable and inspiring and has served as an ideal to countlessly many: Socrates. Socrates' dispositions were of course not all useful to himself or his family; his commitment to searching for truth led him to neglect his own business affairs and reduce them all to poverty. Socrates' character was in fact useful to the Athenians, in stirring them to think about their values, but this was hardly clear to them, since they recognised this too late after executing him. Also, Socrates' character may or may not have been agreeable to himself, but it was certainly very disagreeable to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This passage follows a description of Cleanthes which makes him sounds pleasant but very bland.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When trying to be a better person, you can try to do less harm, or you can try to do more good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In theory you can do both, but in practice doing good requires doing more and more interesting things, and this includes increased risk of doing harm. Also one has only so much time, and time spent working on learning to do less harm is often trading directly against time to do more good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of which is sortof irrelevant, because regardless of whether you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be perfectly good, most people aren't, and this picture Annas paints does feel like it rings fairly true: You can have pleasant and harmless people who are, ultimately, fairly mediocre forces for good in the world, and the ones who are out there actively doing good are often deeply flawed people with many problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel like a lot of people, especially on the left, have an attitude that people like this are a problem. This tends to come from a good place ("Nobody is above criticism"), but I'm not sure it's helpful. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this doesn't affect the people in question (Although they did very much kill Socrates), but it tends to drive people to become very morally risk averse, and provides a lack of good role models for developing agency, because the people who are actually doing good in the world are more likely to be held up as bad examples.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't have a good solution for this. It's important not to let good works act as moral license for bad - e.g. just because someone saves hundreds of lives it's not suddenly OK for them to murder just one person as a treat - but I do think we need to start cutting people some slack.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-07:03.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-18:40.html</id>
    <title>Book Speedrun: Intelligent Virtue by Julia Annas</title>
    <updated>2021-10-04T22:21:24+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Book Speedrun: Intelligent Virtue by Julia Annas&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a book speedrun, where I set a timer for one hour and write a bunch of stuff inspired by a book.
The goal is to get one hour's worth of value out of the book.
It's far from a complete and comprehensive engagement with the book, it's just me flicking through the pages and seeing what comes to mind as I do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Backstory&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often when I try to explain or justify virtue ethics to people, I describe it thus: Virtue ethics is what happens when you treat the problem of doing good in the world like you would any other skilled practice, as something that you have to develop expertise in in order to do it well. Being a good person is not simpler than, say, repairing a car, and nobody thinks you can reduce repairing a car to a simple set of rules, so why should being a good person be simple?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is the book I got that framing from, although it's been filtered through and combined with a lot of other thoughts from other books and discussions about ethics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I probably first read it because it's referenced in the &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-virtue/"&gt;Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy's entry on virtue ethics&lt;/a&gt;.
This page was authored by Rosalind Hursthouse, who wrote "On Virtue Ethics", which I have with me while I'm writing this and may also refer to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The opportunity for virtue&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 31:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of us grow up in bad environments which warp our ability to come to understand the virtues. Are we not excluding these people from the community of the virtuous for something they can do nothing about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important, though, not to confuse the fact that we do not expect virtue here, which is reasonable, with the different thought that these people are incapable of virtue, which is mistaken. Most of these people fail to become virtuous because of the difficulties of their situation, not because they are not capable of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The present account is not, then, committed to elitism about virtue. We are all capable of developing the kind of understanding that virtue requires. For some their circumstances make it hard for them to develop this, but we we have no reason to think that any are naturally incapable of it. It remains the case that, given the world as it is, not everybody does actually develop the virtues; but this is a problem for every account, not for this one in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems like a reasonable and important position: Not everyone is good, and sometimes when people are bad, it is because they were raised in an environment which did not enable them to learn to be good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it leaves me with two questions:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What, exactly, are we to do with this information? If someone is a bad person because of the environment they are raised in, but are unlikely to change that, why should we treat that differently than if they had every opportunity to be virtuous and chose not to take it? In particular for the purposes of interacting with them, their actual ethical character seems more important than whether they are culpable for it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why are her examples so bad?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To elaborate on the second one I need to include some of the bits that I left out of the above: &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are very many people in the world today who live in terrible conditions of poverty and violence (for example, in the slums of large cities) which makes it unreasonable to expect them to reflect on and criticize the lessons tey are taught by the role models they have, people who frequently (and understandably) emphasize the importance not of the virtues but of looking out for yourself, not getting held back by caring baout others, becoming used to violence and cruelty, and worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do not expect people raised on garbage dumps outside a Third World megalopolis to be kind and generous in their everyday behaviour, but this is, I suggest, for the same kind of reason that we also do not expect them to play the piano or do crowsswords. Their environment has obviously lacked the opportunities to learn and do these things, and because this is so obvious we do not assume that they are naturally unable to do them. The same holds for failure to develop the virtues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know, these don't actually seem like very reasonable expectations to me. It seems to me that people in conditions of poverty are more likely to develop a sort of community minded approach where they're all in it together. I'd want to see an actual survey of behaviour in third world slums - it's certainly not going to be a bed of roses, and low trust environments definitely exists, but it seems to me that often the worst environments for developing virtue are actually highly privileged ones. The sort that produce billionaires and politicians more than the sort that produce communities.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could be completely wrong, but this seems to be an opinion formed on fairly narrow stereotyping of groups of people unlike the author, and I'm not wild about that. [citation needed] I guess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's also a footnote on page 32 that I don't like very much:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Bloomfield has emphasize to me that the development of virtue does require a minimum of intelligence not possessed by, for example, people with Down's syndrome. Such people can develop analogues to the virtues, but not the virtues themselves. I think that any ethical theory has to allow that in cases like this there is a qualification to the way such people can be full members of the ethical community in so far as this is thought of as a community of active reasoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know what the author's experience, but most people I've met with Downs' syndrome have been lovely. Can they reach the highest heights of virtue? I don't know, probably not, it certainly requires a degree of influence over the world that they probably lack, but I'm not sure that's a limitation of their character. To the degree that they are excluded from the ethical community, this feels more like a problem for the conception of ethics than the people in question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't have a real conclusion to this section except to note that a close reading of this bit very much made me go "Hmm" and suggests to me the author's conception of ethics is useful to a much smaller set of people than I would previously have thought, and the defence of her conception of ethics as non-elitist seems suspicious to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although fortunately I still think I'm within that set of people, so it's probably still a useful book for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Is this 🦋 a virtue?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 97-98:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being generous, kind, etc. carries no implication that you will be clean, hard-working, or witty; and none of these traits implies that you will be generous or kind. It is obvious that you can be clean, hard-wrking, or witty in a generous or ungenerous, kind or unkind way. In general, it is a good indication that a character trait is not a virtue if it neither implies nor is implied by central virtues, such as courage, but could be exercised in ways which are either courageous or cowardly, virtuous or vicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a way of working out which traits are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; virtues; can the theory say anything useful about which traits &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;? Earlier I treated patience and generosity as vitues; on what grounds? They pass the 'filter' test of fitting into the virtues thoguht of as unified by the holistic development of practical wisdom. Does this imply that they are really just forms of a more basic virtue such as benevolence? What would show that they are forms of a more basic virtue or distinct virtues?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is all as part of a chapter on the unity of the virtues, which is a concept I continue to be a bit ambivalent about. The unity of the virtues is the claim that to attain the highest level of mastery of any given virtue you need to attain it for all the virtues. You cannot be maximally courageous without being maximally kind, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think what seems to me the strongest argument in favour is roughly that to the degree that virtue is the skilled practice of being a good person, &lt;em&gt;relative to a particular conception of good&lt;/em&gt;, virtue is unitary in the sense that you have to in principle be able to do all of it all of the time. A given situation might elicit both the virtues of generosity and courage, and one requires the practical wisdom to navigate the combination of the two. If their is a virtue of courage and a virtue of benevolence, there is a joint virtue of benevolence-and-courage, and the exercise of any one of the individual virtues will sometimes be bottlenecked on the exercise of the joint virtue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not, I think, the traditional conception of the unity of the virtues, and I might hold off thinking more about this for a future research speedrun on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The skill analogy is better than she thinks it is&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the chapter "Virtue and enjoyment", Annas argues that virtues have a trait above and beyond skills, which is that they have a strong emotional component.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 66:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A skill can be exerised in independence of affective commitment; a skilled potter can produce pots, and a skilled plumber can fix leakes, in an unconcerned way. A virtuous person, by contrast, does not perform virtuous actions impassively and with lack of concern. The virtuous person not only does the right thing for the right reason, she has the right feelings about it. Someone handing out money, for example, but indifferent to the people receiving it and their responses, is not generous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Actually I think this is entirely wrong, and misunderstands both generosity and pottery.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm slightly nitpicking here, and will delve further into the chapter in a bit, but I think this is an important point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's absolutely true that you can produce pots in an unconcerned way. You know what happens if you always do that? You produce shitty pots.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm a big fan of Radimentary's &lt;a href="https://radimentary.wordpress.com/2020/11/24/pain-is-not-the-unit-of-effort/"&gt;Pain is not the unit of effort&lt;/a&gt;, in which he makes the argument that if you're not enjoying yourself you're probably not doing your best work. This is crucial to the development of skill - people learn what Thomas Green calls a "professional voice of conscience" with regards to their skills. They've got a sense of pride in making a good pot, a sense of dissatisfaction at a bad pot, etc.
It's true that any given pot that they make they're probably not pouring their heart and soul into it, but in order to get to the point where they're able to make good pots without much emotional investment, they've probably developed pretty strong feelings about pot making.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Conversely, suppose you are someone who spends every day helping people, and you wake up one morning feeling super depressed. Nothing feels particularly good, you have no love in your heart for your fellow human, and you're certainly not feeling particularly benevolent. What do you do?
Typically you go out and help people anyway.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As with pots, you probably never get to the point where you're living your life like this unless you have a strong emotional investment in helping people, but also as with pots once you know how to help people skillfully you probably do not require the emotional investment of doing so every time your help is deployed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think probably she is still right that there is a different emotional component to virtues and "normal" skills, but I don't think that the mere presence of &lt;em&gt;an&lt;/em&gt; emotional component is key.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A learner, such as a child can perform a just action because her parents tell her to, and without caring about being just, or even resenting the whole business. As she becomes more virtuous she learns to perform just actions for the right reasons. We expect the process to lead to her giving fair shares, not being unduly influenced in friends' favour and so on, easily and without effort; eventually she may give gladly. Suppose that this does not happen: she learns to give fair shares and be unbiased, but continues to resent having to do so. Such a person is not just; there is something lacking that a virtuous person would have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may be a naive question but... does this actually happen?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My model of someone who does the right things for the wrong reasons is that they tend not to be very good at it, only do it when other people are watching, and do the bare minimum. People who aren't actually just and only pretend to be tend to be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; obvious, because they lack the easy and automatic attitude towards it. They are often stuck at the conscious competence stage at best.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I would agree, in principle, that someone who goes around behaving perfectly virtuously but with malice and resentment in their heart shouldn't count as virtuous, but I'm somewhat skeptical of the relevance of such a person unless they actually exist. I think most people who can sufficiently maintain a habit of virtue are going to learn the feelings of virtue associated with that habit automatically, and this may be more of a bleen and grue situation than something that we need to take particularly seriously at a practical level.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Lives worth living&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 147:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is virtue even a starter as a candidate for making you happy? By now it's obvious that the answer is: probably not, on contemporary accounts of happiness as feeling good, getting what you want, and feeling satisfied with your life. But we've seen we don't have to think of happiness this way. If happiness is the overall end you aim to achieve by living your life well, then virtue does look like a very obvious starter, for it looks like a better idea to be loyal and sincere than to be disloyal and deceptive. It is absurd to think that we really have no more reason to acquire the virtues than not when we are thinking about how best to live. Rosalind Hursthouse has made the point forcefully: we want our children to grow up honest and brave, rather than shifty and cowardly, and we bring them up to have these virtues (as far as we can) not just for our own sake, in order to be able to rely on them in pursuing our own interests, but for their sae, because we think that they will live better lives being honest and brave rather than being shifty and cowardly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There seems something to this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I started from the claim that virtue ethics was the skill of "doing good in the world", but perhaps it would be more accurate to say that it is the skill of leading a good life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are thinking of a happy life, then, it is just common sense that we want ourselves and our children to have the virtues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I agree, but perhaps I'm not entirely sure why.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intuitive place to start is the ordinary, commonplace assumption that a person's life will, to put it generally, &lt;em&gt;go better&lt;/em&gt; if they have the virtues - if they are generous and brave, for example - than if they don't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... we moderns have come to have a problematic conception of happiness. On the one hand, we think of it as an overall end to be achieved in living a happy life, and to this extent we can make ready sense of the idea that living a good life is a way of living a happy life.(...) But on the other hand we also have another, more passive notion of happiness - the more recent idea that happiness is pleasant feeling, or getting what you want, or being satisfied with your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't really understand why she thinks these are in tension. I don't think she's &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; necessarily, I just don't understand here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular I think the thing that confuses me is that "being satisfied with your life" seems inextricably bound up with the question of living a good life? What does it mean to be dissatisfied with your life except to have judged it to not be a good one? This seems to tie in again to the ideas of &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;burnout as acedia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-03-08:59.html"&gt;moral disorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion and notes on the format&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly I think I'm coming to the, somewhat unsurprising, conclusion that I cannot really do a good book justice in an hour, especially not one like this where I probably last read it in detail over a year ago. Certainly the format of randomly flipping through the book and writing based on prompts doesn't seem to be doing it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That isn't necessarily bad. This still produces a set of interesting thoughts and writing. But perhaps the random book prompt is enough on its own.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I might in future try something closer to Lucy's original conception of the research speedruns, and might try a different format for book speedruns. I'm not yet sure what though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two questions that might make interesting future speedruns:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unity of the virtues: What is it, and is it true?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What exactly is the eudaimonist account of human happiness / flourishing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'll probably try doing another speedrun on this book about each of those questions specifically.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-18:40.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-06-00:02.html</id>
    <title>What's up with the unity of the virtues?</title>
    <updated>2021-10-06T01:54:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;What's up with the unity of the virtues?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-18:40.html"&gt;yesterday's post about Intelligent Virtue&lt;/a&gt; I said that The Unity of the Virtues deserved a speedrun all of its own, so this is me doing that speedrun.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What does 'unity of the virtues' actually mean?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Starting from Rosalind Hursthouse's "On Virtue Ethics" and just going through the index for unity of the virtues as a starting point leads me to the following interesting footnoe on Page 153:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timothy Chappell, in an unpublished paper (now, alas, lost), once argued that there were (something like) thirty (!) versions of the doctrine of the unity of the virtues. I cannot now remember how he did it, but I think the first eight came from ‘(i) The possession of any one virtue is necessary and sufficient for (or (ii) necessary for or (iii) sufficient for or (iv) conducive to) the instantaneous possession (or (v–viii) the eventual possession) of all the other virtues too’ and the next eight from the same structure with ‘The possession of some one virtue (e.g. phronesis)’ as the opening clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Side note: Timothy Chappell has transitioned since the publication of this book and is now Sophie-Grace Chappell).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So part of why it's not totally clear to me what people really mean by "The unity of the virtues" is that people mean all sorts of different things. Great.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Garbage arguments that unity of the virtues is plausible&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On page 155 is the following argument that we probably already believe in the unity of the virtues, and I hate it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That we do not believe in the disunity of the virtues is, I think, shown by our reaction to certain sorts of stories we sometimes read in the newspapers. We read of people doing what seems splendid; the sort of action that seems to call for an exceptional level of, say, courage or generosity. And then we learn about them that they have also done something morally repellent and we are surprised and often puzzled. I do not only mean something repellent in the same area—cowardly or selfish, as the case may be, which might immediately lead us to say that we had obviously made a mistake in ascribing courage or generosity to them in the first place. I mean something in a different area; the agent who dashed into the burning building and saved a stranger turns out to be a rapist; the one who has given a huge proportion of his income to the homeless turns out to be someone whose lies are keeping an innocent person in gaol. And we are surprised and puzzled: how could they be so splendid in the one instance and so despicable in another, we wonder? Now isn't that an interesting fact—that we are surprised and puzzled?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we thought of the virtues as discrete, isolable traits, such that someone could be, for example, truly courageous but also cruel and licentious in character, or truly charitable but also cowardly and dishonest, there would be no reason to be surprised or puzzled. We would expect one who acts from courage to be reliable and predictable as far as courageous acts were concerned, but have no expectations about their kindness or honesty. But we do. We believe the virtues form some sort of unity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this argument is fairly suspicious, to the point of outright disbelieving it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First off: I personally do not feel terribly surprised by any of these combinations. Hypocrisy and moral complexity abounds. It's in fact extremely common for people known for doing good to be total assholes in private.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I think our intuitions about who is a good person and in what way they are a good person tend to be reliably wrong. We're more likely to judge attractive people to be good. We're more likely to judge someone we think is an asshole to be bad, but &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-07:03.html"&gt;this causes us to prefer Cleanthes to Socrates&lt;/a&gt;. Halo effects are a whole big thing and our judgement is &lt;em&gt;reliably&lt;/em&gt; compromised by them, and seeing people doing good is very much a form of halo. So even if people &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; surprised, this is in a direction where their judgement is known to be compromised.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, this is also what you would observe even if your judgement were entirely accurate and virtues were correlated but not unified.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My go to example of such a trait is strength. If Bob deadlifts more than Joe, I'd probably also expect Bob to beat Joe in an arm wrestling competition. But he might not! Because strength is very much not unitary, there are all sorts of different feats of strength that use different muscles and different skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But they're still pretty strongly correlated. If Bob and Joe are close in deadlift I won't be at all surprised if it flips for arm wrestling. If Bob deadlifts twice as much as Joe I'll be pretty surprised if it reverse for arm wrestling, but it wouldn't blow my mind or anything, it just violates expectations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not to go all rationalist at you, but surprise is probabilistic, and something can be surprising and yet completely consistent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More, we have every reason to expect virtues to be correlated, because a desire to do good in the world is what drives one to cultivate the virtues, and so there is a common causal mechanism in the development of virtue. Therefore we would expect someone who exhibits one virtue to have spent at least some time cultivating the others, and thus to do better at them even if they were completely unrelated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, regardless of whether unity of the virtues is true, this is a garbage argument for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The Limited Unity of Virtue&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't find anything very convincing in Hursthouse's section on the unity of the virtues (which is quite short), but she references "The Limited Unity of Virtue" by Neera K. Badhwa, which is my next stop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She opens with the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aristotle's conception of virtue of character as a habitual emotional and rational disposition to feel, choose, and act in the right way for the right ends is accepted by many contemporary philosophers. But his claim that the virtues are united, such that you can have one virtue if and only if you have all of them is, typically, rejected out of hand. The doctrine of the unity of virtue follows from Aristotle's declaration that "we cannot be fully good without practical wisdom or practically wise without virtue of character, "and that "as soon as [someone] has practical wisdom, which is a single state, he has all the virtues as well."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Practical wisdom" is normally left untranslated as "phronesis" and I suspect something is being lost in translation here. It would potentially be interesting to do a future speedrun on what people really mean by "phronesis". I think I've mentally been treating it as "the pragmatic skill of being good at getting shit done" - a sort of generalised competence - but perhaps it's more qualified than that. It's at this point I should confess that I've gotten distracted while reading the Nichomachean ethics multiple times. It's not you, Aristotle, it's me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Badhwa proposes the following &lt;em&gt;limited unity of the virtues&lt;/em&gt; thesis:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The existence of a virtue in a particular domain of a person's life does not imply the existence of that (or any other) virtue in any other domain. So P may be kind towards her friends and colleagues without being kind (or virtuous in any other way) towards acquaintances or strangers, or she may be kind towards those who have been unlucky in their careers without being kind towards those who have been unlucky in their personal relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The existence of virtue in one domain implies the absence of vice as well as of ignorance in most other domains. Hence, if P is kind, just, etc. in her friendships, she cannot be vicious towards everyone else or, for that matter, ignorant of the basic elements of everyone else's good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every virtue requires the others within the same domain, and so none is incompatible with, or independent of, any other. Hence, if P is kind towards her friends and colleagues, she must also be generous, just, temperate, and courageous with respect to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think (3) is the most interesting of these three, in that it still seems to be a stronger claim than I think is necessarily obviously true, but I'm not sure if I'm just unclear on what she means by "must".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reading onwards I find:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A vicious person may be clever in achieving his ends, but since his ends are bad, he cannot be wise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;OK so "practical wisdom" does include the requirement that the shit you're trying to get done is actually good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Actually, I think this plus skimming the rest of the paper (no direct quotes sorry) makes me think that the unity of the virtues as being presented is roughly the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a given domain there is a well defined set of "good ends".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phronesis, or practical wisdom, is the skill of achieving those ends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtues are the character traits which dispose one, rationally and emotionally, towards achieving those good ends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus virtues and phronesis are intimately intertwined, in that the development of phronesis is dependent on and in turn cultivates the virtues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems right to me, and largely agrees with &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-18:40.html"&gt;my comments about the skill analogy yesterday&lt;/a&gt; but I think the crucial feature of this is that the virtues are unified &lt;em&gt;with respect to a given set of good ends&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the restriction to a domain makes this claim very limited indeed. If the domain is just a set of people or a given aim, that's not much of a restriction, but you can for example imagine someone who is very dedicated to helping people who are in danger but lacks patience with the emotional side of the problem - cultivating the virtue of courage but not of kindness. Is this just a restricted domain? They've included in their set of good ends people's physical but not emotional wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also think this has a sort of "in the limit" character to it - it's true, for example, that cultivating kindness is very important for firefighters, or soldiers, or people in other dangerous professions, but I bet you'll find they're skewed pretty heavily towards courage. Maxing out the skill of phronesis might require you to cultivate all the virtues, but I bet you can get pretty far on only some of them, and most people don't make it to the peak of any skill they develop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Teaching the virtues&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Returning to Intelligent Virtue, on page 84 we have the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important indication of the nature of virtue comes from the point that we can't teach the virtues in isolation, one by one, since they can't be learnt that way. Generosity gives us a good example here. A child doesn't learn to be generous by just giving her things away, or sharing things whether they belong to her or not. Generosity involves considerations of fairness and justice. For, as Aristotle points out, generosity requires taking from the right sources as well as giving to the right people in the right way.' And 'giving in the right way' involves a great deal. Giving a gift which is indifferent to what the recipient wants is not generous. Generosity requires intelligence about what people both need and want, and also about appropriate ways, times, and manners of giving, avoiding obtrusiveness and condescension. Generosity thus requires, at the least, benevolence, a real interest in other people, their needs, and their wants. To get it right in giving, how to give, when and to whom, not to mention how much, you have to have an interest in the welfare of others beyond their role as your beneficiaries; otherwise you risk your giving becoming selfish showing-off. Generosity thus requires real benevolent concern for others, along with minor virtues such as tact. Obviously children don't get all of this at once, and even as adults we find we constantly need improvement; the point here is that we can all see, in the course of ethical development, that some virtues 'cluster'. This indicates something about the nature of virtue; it is not just a casual point, extraneous to an account of virtue, about how we learn to be virtuous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, I think, a good point and ties in well with the above "limited unity of the virtue". Within a given domain, we have a set of "good ends", and we must learn to value those ends, and it often doesn't make sense to split them up. You don't learn to value being generous and value being fair, you learn to value other people and thus be generous and fair to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(As a side note, an ongoing point of annoyance with the world for me is that it seems most people &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; do this. They learn to value other people and then put in the minimum effort they can get away with with thinking through the implications of that)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Later on page 88:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do not need far-fetched thought experiments to grasp that the way we develop in one area of our lives can indeed have an impact on the way we develop in other parts. The compassionate person might well need courage to insist that a victim be treated properly, or to stand up to a bully on someone else's behalf. If he lacks courage, his compassion will be flawed too; victims can't rely on it, and others generally can't rely on him to be compassionate in appropriate circumstances. In general a virtue which is unreliable in its exercise because of facts about the person (rather than external circumstances) is a compromised virtue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems right. One of the things the drives unity of the virtues is that sometimes you might need both virtues at once. I think this is the same argument I put forth yesterday (which isn't surprising as my thoughts have previously been informed by this book, and I was reading bits of this chapter):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think what seems to me the strongest argument in favour is roughly that to the degree that virtue is the skilled practice of being a good person, relative to a particular conception of good, virtue is unitary in the sense that you have to in principle be able to do all of it all of the time. A given situation might elicit both the virtues of generosity and courage, and one requires the practical wisdom to navigate the combination of the two. If their is a virtue of courage and a virtue of benevolence, there is a joint virtue of benevolence-and-courage, and the exercise of any one of the individual virtues will sometimes be bottlenecked on the exercise of the joint virtue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So virtues are unitary in the sense that one has to be able to unify them in order to reliably perform them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She ties this in to virtues developed in separate domains and why we might expect them to be unified:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A trial lawyer, for example, may develop adversarial traits in the courtroom which, in the context of her family, would distress both her and her family, where the virtues she exercises are cooperative. Often it is not clear that both sets of traits are in fact virtues, but let us suppose that they are. The person is still living in a compartmentalized way, one with divisions and compromises always present, and one in which the values sought in one aspect of life may well be in conflict with those pursued in another. Moreover, the less the person sees it as her aim to live an integrated life, the more these conflicts will be both painful and hard for her to predict. This is hardly an ideal for a virtuous life. For one thing, it comes into sharp conflict with the aspect of virtue discussed in the last chapter-the point that the virtuous person finds her life enjoyable, in part because of lack of inner conflict or its threat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does virtue require a lack of inner conflict? It doesn't seem unreasonable to me, although I don't know that I have a strong feeling on it one way or the other. Certainly it seems plausible to me that cultivating virtue requires resolving inner conflicts, along the lines of the sort of therapy-meets-virtue-ethics I discussed in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-03-08:59.html"&gt;Notes on moral disorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Does maximal virtue imply omnicompetence?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Intelligent virtue, page 94:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third objection is the most important. How can the virtues be so unified by practical intelligence that they imply one another, when different people obviously lead different ways of life and need to exercise different virtues? A soldier needs one set of virtues, a caregiver to an Alzheimer's patient needs another set. Someone in a position of leadership will need a different set of virtues from the people being directed.We are faced by an apparent dilemma. On the one hand, if we are committed to holding that nobody can be fully virtuous unless they can exercise all the virtues, we seem committed to the absurd conclusion that to live a fully virtuous life you will have to live the life of a soldier and that of a caregiver (and many more besides). For if you have all the virtues, you must be able to exercise all the virtues, and it seems that you must live a life in which opportunities to exercise all the virtues are available to you. An addition to this claim can be made: to exercise a virtue will probably require fairly specialized knowledge. The virtue of compassion is not exercised by merely standing around wishing you could help: the compassionate person actually helps the wounded, aids the suicidal, and so on. But now it looks as though the fully virtuous person, in being omni-virtuous also has to be omni-competent, equipped to be, on demand, a doctor, psychiatrist, computer expert, plumber, and so on; which is even more absurd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next couple of pages include a bunch of discussion of this in which she tries to weasel out of this problem by saying that the &lt;em&gt;possession&lt;/em&gt; of the virtues is independent of whether your life offers you equal opportunity for the &lt;em&gt;expression&lt;/em&gt; of the virtues.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If we take the skill analogy for virtue that she advocates for seriously (and I do), this is like saying that just because one doesn't have any opportunity in one's life to practice piano one might still possess in principle the piano playing talents of a maestro. Obviously you don't. The development of a skill requires practice, and if your life does not offer opportunities for the use of a virtue then you will not develop it to its maximal potential.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also that's fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it's in some sense clearly true that being omni-virtuous requires omni-competent, but so what? Being maximally virtuous is obviously completely unachievable for mortal beings. How could it be otherwise? If virtue ethics is to be usable (and its focus on practical wisdom suggests it must be) it must be focused on the sort of virtue pursuable by human beings, not gods, and that doesn't involve striving to be the best possible, only to be better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The argument that the virtues are unified via practical wisdom is interesting and seems to be pointing at something useful, but I think falls short. It's not that virtues are unitary, but that they unify, and that sometimes the thing we are bottlenecked on in improving one virtue is another virtue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think the concept of practical wisdom having to be directed towards good ends very much hides the relativism implicit in virtue ethics. It's clear that virtues can only be unified within a given conception of the good. This isn't a problem as I'm comfortable with relativism, but it also makes the "the" in "the unity of the virtues" somewhat suspect.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All this being said, I think I need to spend more time with the unity of the virtues chapter in Intelligent Virtue, as I left it a bit to the end and don't feel like I really did it justice as a result. I may or may not actually do that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-06-00:02.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-06-16:21.html</id>
    <title>Revisiting Intelligent Virtue</title>
    <updated>2021-10-06T19:01:57+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Revisiting Intelligent Virtue&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure if it counts as a speedrun if you've already done the book, but I thought I'd spend another hour on Intelligent Virtue today, as I keep coming away from it thinking I haven't really done it justice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to mix up the format of it a little bit by trying to do a chapter-by-chapter breakdown in this hour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On page 1:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... the present distinctive account of virtue results from attending to two ideas. One is that exercising a virtue involves practical reasoning of a kind that can illuminatingly be compared to the kind of reasoning we find in someone exercising a practical skill. Rather than asking at the start how virtues relate to rules, principles, maximizing, or a final end, we will gain by looking at the way in which the acquisition and exercise of virtue can be seen to be in many ways like the acquisition and exercise of more mundane activities, such as farming, building, or playing the piano. The other idea is that virtue is part of the agent's happiness or flourishing, and that it is plausible to see virtue as actually constituting (wholly or in part) that happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So roughly her point is that:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtues are developed like skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtues are a key part of "human flourishing"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Oversimplifying, one can think of virtues as the skills of promoting human flourishing, which is how I tend to characterise it (in large part based on prior readings of this book).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rest of the introduction mostly covers things that are going to be covered in future chapters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Virtue, Character, and Disposition&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is the chapter in which she tries to explain what virtues are, and very much falls prety to the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-02-09:29.html"&gt;People are bad at defining things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are the places in this chapter where the phrase "virtue is" or "virtues are" occur, with some surrounding context:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A virtue is a lasting feature of a person, a tendency for the person to be a certain way. It is not merely a lasting feature, however, one that just sits there undisturbed. It is active: to have it is to be disposed to act in certain ways&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A virtue is not a static condition like [the tendency of glass to shatter]; it is a disposition as a result of which Jane acts and thinks in a certain way, and which is at any time strengthened by her generous responses and weakened by failures to have them. If she is generous, her generous actions and feelings both come from a virtue and fortify it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A virtue is also a reliable disposition. If Jane is generous, it is no accident that she does the generous action and has generous feelings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, a virtue is a disposition which is is, the virtuous (or vicious) person is acting in and from character when acting in a kindly, brave or restrained way. This is another way of putting the point that a virtue is a deep feature of the person. A virtue is a disposition which is central to the person, to whom he or she is, a way we standardly think of character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...  virtue is a disposition which is from the start an active and developing one. It is not a passive product of a string of impacts from outside; it is the way I (or you), an active creature, develops a character through formation and education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the virtues are educated developments of our unformed motivations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since virtue is a disposition of the above kind, becoming virtuous will naturally take time. Scrooge may have been converted suddenly to compassion and kindliness on Christmas Eve, but the story is careful to tell us that he continued over time the process of becoming a compassionate person. Coming to see that being loyal or brave is a worthwhile way to live is just the first step. Becoming virtuous requires habituation and experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is natural to worry at this point whether habituation is just habit, and whether a virtuous disposition is just one built up by force of habit. Our experience leads us, in a number of areas of our lives, to develop habits which save time and effort. If developing a virtue is like this, why should we think it amounts to anything more than habit and even mere routine?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtue is unlike routine in a host of ways. [Followed by a long discussion of why piano playing is not a virtue that I don't entirely understand]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skilled dispositions are not static conditions; they are always developing, being sustained or weakened. One of the major suggestions of this book is that virtue is like practical skill in this respect (as well as some others). Because a virtue is a disposition it requires time, experience, and habituation to develop it, but the result is not routine but the kind of actively and intelligently engaged practical mastery that we find in practical experts such as pianists and athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A central feature of routine is that the reaction to the relevant situation is always the same, which is why routine can be depended on and predicted. But practical skill and virtue require more than predictably similar reaction; they require a response which is appropriate to the situation instead of merely being the same as that produced in response to other situations. This appropriateness comes from the habituated disposition that a virtue is. As Aristotle says: 'It ... seems to be characteristic of the more courageous person to be unafraid and unruffled in sudden alarms rather than to be so in those that are foreseen; it comes more from his state of character [hexis, often translated 'disposition'], because less from preparation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this produces a set of &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; conditions for something to count as a virtue. It must be:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a characteristic disposition of the person to act in a particular way (generously, courageously).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in some way &lt;em&gt;fundamental&lt;/em&gt; to the person exercising it - that is, if you were to somehow take away the virtue they would have to be a very different person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;oriented towards something that we desire in and of itself (our "unformed motivations")&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consciously and knowingly practiced, leading to its further development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this cannot count as sufficient to be a virtue because many vices could also satisfy this condition e.g. "nastiness" or "hedonistic debauchery" also satisfy this for people who are motivated towards such things, but it's a good start for at least distinguishing virtues from other skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Skilled and virtuous action&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this she is trying to further distinguish virtues from skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some practical skills do seem to involve mere routine - this is true of daily activities such as getting to work which we are sometimes prepared to call skills, though at other times we call them routines or rituals. (...) We find the important similarity of virtue to skill in skills where two things are united: the &lt;em&gt;need to learn&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;drive to aspire&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the "skill analogy" is highlighting the idea that virtues are things where excellence must be sought and is something we should desire in and of itself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She goes on to say (some pages later after a bunch of detailed intermediate discussion)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtue can most illuminatingly be seen as like this kind of skill; it shares the intellectual structure of a skill where we find not only the need to learn but the drive to aspire, and hence the need to 'give an account, the need for articulate conveying of reasons why what is done is done. The learner in virtue, like the learner in a practical skill, needs to understand what she is doing, to achieve the ability to do it for herself, and to do it in a way that improves as she meets challenges, rather than coming out with predictable repetition. This conies about when the virtue is conveyed by the giving and receiving of reasons, in contrast with the non-rational picking up of a knack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This view does rather explain why she thinks people with Downs syndrome can't be virtuous, but suggests that perhaps one way of thinking about virtue ethics is that it's not actually intended to be universally normative. That is, it's entirely possible to be fully ethical without being virtuous.
You can imagine (although I suspect no such person exists) someone who always unthinkingly does the right thing out of a natural pleasantness of character, and never strives for it.
Such a person is ethical but not virtuous.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this light, I think perhaps a good way to read Annas (and ethicists in general?) is as a sort of "Ethics for Nerds" - if you don't automatically know the right thing to do, how would you go about learning to do so?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the way to think of the virtues is as a sufficient but not necessary set of conditions for being a good person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The Scope of Virtue&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this she starts by defending virtue against the critique of relativism, but I am in fact completely comfortable with relativism and think her defence is probably wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In it she mentions &lt;a href="https://www.virtuesproject.com/"&gt;The Virtues Project&lt;/a&gt; as an example of an attempt at a cross-cultural list of the virtues. This sounds interesting and I may spend more time with it, but also I did a card pick on it and it lead me to the &lt;a href="https://virtuesdev.com/vpicks/Prayerfulness.png"&gt;Prayerfulness&lt;/a&gt; virtue at which point I said "Oh fuck you" out loud and closed the site for now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The chapter does contain the following interesting passage:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Aristotle says in the passage I have quoted more than once, everyone seeks the good, not just what their parents did. Becoming virtuous starts the process by making it clear that the virtuous life cannot just be the life your parents lead. Anyone can come to realize this, and anyone can continue the progressive enlargement of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why then do so few do so? This is not a problem particular to thinking in terms of virtue, since any ethical theory has to face the fact that most people do not live by it. The answer given by the present account is that while we are all capable of aspiring to become virtuous, most of us resist being pulled away from our familiar original contexts by becoming progressively more virtuous. Rather than deal with the fact that our family is dishonest, our country jingoistic, the values we have learnt inadequate, we make rationalizations, or simply refuse to face facts. We are unwilling to criticize the contexts and institutions within which we learned the virtues, because we are unwilling to be pulled away from those contexts in the way that would be required. The community of the family, or society, is a visible and tangible one, providing real comfort and support. The community of the honest (the brave, the open-minded, and so on) is an invisible one composed of all those who, past, present, and future, act, reason, and feel in certain ways; accessible only through thought and reflection, it offers less help in getting through the day.' If we think of community as a form of solidarity, pre-existing solidarities can make it hard to be detached from them.' To identify with the community of the just, rather than with your own fellow citizens, is often hard, for it requires detachment from the existing support you get from relations with your fellow-citizens. What requires explanation, then, is not so much the slackness of most people in developing the virtues, but the strength of the few in achieving them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Strong vibes of what I've written about in the past in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html"&gt;The social obligation to be bad at things&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-31-09:20.html"&gt;Norms of Excellence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think what she is essentially arguing in this chapter is that culture can &lt;em&gt;limit&lt;/em&gt; our virtue, but that there is a single overarching but imperfectly expressed universal notion of virtue, which striving to be vituous allows us to move our communities towards.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To which I say: Well, maybe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Virtue and Enjoyment&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this chapter she is arguing that one of the key features of virtue is that the virtuous like being virtuous. They don't experience it as a chore, but as a thing that is worthwhile in and of itself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, one aspect of the virtuous person's moral psychology, perhaps surprisingly, points us to another important analogy between skill and virtue. Aristotle famously comments that the virtuous person is distinguished by finding what he does pleasant: 'We must take as an indication of a person's states the pleasure or pain consequent on what he does, because the person who abstains from bodily pleasures and finds his enjoyment in doing just this is temperate, while the person who finds doing it oppressive is intemperate; and the person who enjoys facing up to danger, or at least does not find it painful to do so, is courageous, while he who does find it painful is a coward. The temperance example is not hard to understand. Someone resolving to give up meat, for example, will at first have to fight against temptation and will find the forbidden food attractive; but as they develop the relevant disposition to be vegetarian they cease to find it tempting. Eventually they take more pleasure in not eating what they now reject than they did when they ate it; the vegetarian finds it more enjoyable to be a vegetarian than she did being someone who enjoyed eating meat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly this sounds to me like the sort of thing you tell people even if it's false.
My personal experience of being vegetarian (which may not be representative of "true virtue" in that I did eventually decide not to be) is that while I found the idea of eating meat actively unappealing, I never &lt;em&gt;enjoyed&lt;/em&gt; not eating meat. I enjoyed what I was eating, and I didn't want to eat meat, but there was never any sense that vegetarianism in and of itself was enjoyable, it was just a thing, and I expect this is normal. I think this is just a weak example though - I can certainly see the argument that some exercises of virtue are enjoyable, I just don't think vegetarianism works like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Much of the rest of the chapter is connecting up virtue with the idea of &lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt;, and that virtue is enjoyable because it creates flow. This seems too cute to me, but I think the core idea that virtue is enjoyable because it is a skilled practice and using your skills in worthwhile ways is enjoyable is reasonably solid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Virtues and the unity of the virtue&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm running out of time and feel like &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-06-00:02.html"&gt;I covered this adequately yesterday&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can we say anything more specific about the distinctive kind of admiration called forth by virtue?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first answer is that in the case of the virtues our admiration is for the person's character: possession of virtues indicates something about what the person is like, whereas possession of traits such as tidiness or wittiness indicates only traits that the person has. Take someone who is characteristically tidy, who, noticing that his car has got messy, cleans it out. What does this tell us about his character? Very little. Let us suppose that the same person is characteristically brave, and that in the course of the subsequent drive he stops and courageously rescues passengers trapped in a crashed and burning car. This action, unlike the previous one, does indicate what kind of person he is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly I think tidiness tells you a lot about the sort of person someone is, and could legitimately get behind the idea that cleanliness is a virtue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might think at this point that the contrast here is not between virtues and other traits, but between virtues and vices on the one hand and other traits on the other. For surely, we think, vices indicate character as much as virtues do? This is true up to a point, and shows that virtues do more than merely indicate character. Suppose another person who sees the burning car, but pretends not to, and drives on. This is a cowardly act, and if it is characteristic of the person it does tell us something about him as a person, namely that he is a coward. But there is an important difference here, which can be brought out by the claim that the brave person is, by virtue of being brave, expressing a commitment to goodness, a commitment to positive value. Although this is a very general point, it is intuitive. The brave person's action reveals that he is committed to something valuable that is centrally important to him. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, I think, where the idea of unity of the virtues comes from: The central feature of virtue is "commitment to goodness".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ran out of time at this point, without having finished covering the last few chapters, and I think this demonstrates the weakness of the format - Intelligent Virtue isn't even a very long book!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I'm going to rebrand these from "speedruns" to "studies", because it's clear that I can't do justice to a book in an hour (this is of course not surprising, although bear in mind these are also books I've already read), and I may well do a further study on the last couple of chapters of this book because they seem quite important.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-06-16:21.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-08-01:23.html</id>
    <title>Scurrying</title>
    <updated>2021-10-08T01:23:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Scurrying&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was going to do another study on Intelligent Virtue today but the day kinda got away from me (ironically, partly due to an in depth discussion of virtue ethics on discord),
and now I'm tired, so I'm not going to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead let me tell you about the Alexander Technique lesson I had earlier, which gave me a good handle on a problem I didn't know existed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me set the scene.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;P and I were about to play catch (this is surprisingly helpful) and I spotted that I had left my coffee cup right behind him. I felt that my throwing balls in the direction of a nearly full cup of coffee was probably a poor idea, so I said "Hang on a second, let me just move that" and walked across the room to put it somewhere less precarious.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;P stopped me. "Did you maintain your Alexander while doing that?" "No, probably not."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"I'm going to use an unkind word to describe what you just did. You were &lt;em&gt;scurrying&lt;/em&gt;."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We then had a good conversation about how I had also done this earlier when I arrived. I was in the middle of a conversation on Twitter and he came out a bit earlier than expected. Now I needed to put my bag on and pick up my coffee cup and oops I've forgotten my mask let me put the coffee cup down and...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is these abrupt and slightly flustered looking movements that signal "I need to do this in order to get to the important thing". A sort of furtive rushing through the motions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing about these motions is that they're not actually that much faster than calmly doing the thing, and to the degree that they are they are probably increasing the error rate (consider how I forgot my mask and had to go back and sort that out), so may even be slower. But what they do is &lt;em&gt;signal that you are going fast&lt;/em&gt; regardless of whether you are actually going fast. Moving in a way that indicates that you're trying to get this over and done with and you want those around you to know that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think henceforth this label of "scurrying" is going to live in my head as referring to specifically doing something in such a way as to indicate you're trying to trying to get it over with so you can get on to the important bit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This ties in to what Alexander Technique calls "end gaining", but I think "scurrying" points to something more specific here - it's not just that you're focused on the goal, but are simultaneously treating the goal as unimportant except in that it's necessary)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is scurrying bad? Maybe. I don't think rushing through something to get on to the important bit is &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; bad, to the degree that it actually helps rather than is counterproductive, but I do think that often scurrying happens in cases where it shouldn't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Take for example the earlier incident where I went to move the coffee. Why was I scurrying? I was there to learn to stay in the Alexander state and move accordingly, so getting the cup of coffee was every bit as important as playing a game of catch, but I treated the former as something to get out of the way in order to do the latter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the nice things about scurrying as a concept here is that it's so visually clear as a set of movements. I've been struggling to really integrate anything Alexander Technique related into my life because I don't remember to do it, but scurrying is something I can go "Oh, I'm doing the thing. Do I want to be?" to, and use as a prompt for change.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-08-01:23.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
