<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2021-10-19T10:53:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-07:03.html</id>
    <title>What does a good person look like?</title>
    <updated>2021-10-05T21:45:03+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;What does a good person look like?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From Intelligent Virtue by Julia Annas, page 106:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"A philosopher", says "Hume, "might select this character as a model of perfect virtue". It is always hard to be sure that we have got Hume's tone right, but if he is not being ironic here it is obvious that something is amiss. A yuppy lawyer who is great company at parties is a model perfect virtue? Can this be serious? What has gone wrong here? We do not need to go into Hume's account of virtue in depth to discover it (one reasonw hy the example is useful in the present connection). What the description of Cleanthes brings out is that someone may have a character that is useful and agreeable to himself and others, and still be utterly &lt;em&gt;uninspiring&lt;/em&gt;, somebody tha tnobody could take an &lt;em&gt;ideal&lt;/em&gt; of a 8good* person to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us compare Cleanthes with someone who really is admirable and inspiring and has served as an ideal to countlessly many: Socrates. Socrates' dispositions were of course not all useful to himself or his family; his commitment to searching for truth led him to neglect his own business affairs and reduce them all to poverty. Socrates' character was in fact useful to the Athenians, in stirring them to think about their values, but this was hardly clear to them, since they recognised this too late after executing him. Also, Socrates' character may or may not have been agreeable to himself, but it was certainly very disagreeable to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This passage follows a description of Cleanthes which makes him sounds pleasant but very bland.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When trying to be a better person, you can try to do less harm, or you can try to do more good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In theory you can do both, but in practice doing good requires doing more and more interesting things, and this includes increased risk of doing harm. Also one has only so much time, and time spent working on learning to do less harm is often trading directly against time to do more good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of which is sortof irrelevant, because regardless of whether you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be perfectly good, most people aren't, and this picture Annas paints does feel like it rings fairly true: You can have pleasant and harmless people who are, ultimately, fairly mediocre forces for good in the world, and the ones who are out there actively doing good are often deeply flawed people with many problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel like a lot of people, especially on the left, have an attitude that people like this are a problem. This tends to come from a good place ("Nobody is above criticism"), but I'm not sure it's helpful. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this doesn't affect the people in question (Although they did very much kill Socrates), but it tends to drive people to become very morally risk averse, and provides a lack of good role models for developing agency, because the people who are actually doing good in the world are more likely to be held up as bad examples.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't have a good solution for this. It's important not to let good works act as moral license for bad - e.g. just because someone saves hundreds of lives it's not suddenly OK for them to murder just one person as a treat - but I do think we need to start cutting people some slack.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-07:03.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-18:40.html</id>
    <title>Book Speedrun: Intelligent Virtue by Julia Annas</title>
    <updated>2021-10-04T22:21:24+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Book Speedrun: Intelligent Virtue by Julia Annas&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a book speedrun, where I set a timer for one hour and write a bunch of stuff inspired by a book.
The goal is to get one hour's worth of value out of the book.
It's far from a complete and comprehensive engagement with the book, it's just me flicking through the pages and seeing what comes to mind as I do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Backstory&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often when I try to explain or justify virtue ethics to people, I describe it thus: Virtue ethics is what happens when you treat the problem of doing good in the world like you would any other skilled practice, as something that you have to develop expertise in in order to do it well. Being a good person is not simpler than, say, repairing a car, and nobody thinks you can reduce repairing a car to a simple set of rules, so why should being a good person be simple?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is the book I got that framing from, although it's been filtered through and combined with a lot of other thoughts from other books and discussions about ethics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I probably first read it because it's referenced in the &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-virtue/"&gt;Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy's entry on virtue ethics&lt;/a&gt;.
This page was authored by Rosalind Hursthouse, who wrote "On Virtue Ethics", which I have with me while I'm writing this and may also refer to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The opportunity for virtue&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 31:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of us grow up in bad environments which warp our ability to come to understand the virtues. Are we not excluding these people from the community of the virtuous for something they can do nothing about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important, though, not to confuse the fact that we do not expect virtue here, which is reasonable, with the different thought that these people are incapable of virtue, which is mistaken. Most of these people fail to become virtuous because of the difficulties of their situation, not because they are not capable of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The present account is not, then, committed to elitism about virtue. We are all capable of developing the kind of understanding that virtue requires. For some their circumstances make it hard for them to develop this, but we we have no reason to think that any are naturally incapable of it. It remains the case that, given the world as it is, not everybody does actually develop the virtues; but this is a problem for every account, not for this one in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems like a reasonable and important position: Not everyone is good, and sometimes when people are bad, it is because they were raised in an environment which did not enable them to learn to be good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it leaves me with two questions:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What, exactly, are we to do with this information? If someone is a bad person because of the environment they are raised in, but are unlikely to change that, why should we treat that differently than if they had every opportunity to be virtuous and chose not to take it? In particular for the purposes of interacting with them, their actual ethical character seems more important than whether they are culpable for it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why are her examples so bad?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To elaborate on the second one I need to include some of the bits that I left out of the above: &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are very many people in the world today who live in terrible conditions of poverty and violence (for example, in the slums of large cities) which makes it unreasonable to expect them to reflect on and criticize the lessons tey are taught by the role models they have, people who frequently (and understandably) emphasize the importance not of the virtues but of looking out for yourself, not getting held back by caring baout others, becoming used to violence and cruelty, and worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do not expect people raised on garbage dumps outside a Third World megalopolis to be kind and generous in their everyday behaviour, but this is, I suggest, for the same kind of reason that we also do not expect them to play the piano or do crowsswords. Their environment has obviously lacked the opportunities to learn and do these things, and because this is so obvious we do not assume that they are naturally unable to do them. The same holds for failure to develop the virtues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know, these don't actually seem like very reasonable expectations to me. It seems to me that people in conditions of poverty are more likely to develop a sort of community minded approach where they're all in it together. I'd want to see an actual survey of behaviour in third world slums - it's certainly not going to be a bed of roses, and low trust environments definitely exists, but it seems to me that often the worst environments for developing virtue are actually highly privileged ones. The sort that produce billionaires and politicians more than the sort that produce communities.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could be completely wrong, but this seems to be an opinion formed on fairly narrow stereotyping of groups of people unlike the author, and I'm not wild about that. [citation needed] I guess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's also a footnote on page 32 that I don't like very much:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Bloomfield has emphasize to me that the development of virtue does require a minimum of intelligence not possessed by, for example, people with Down's syndrome. Such people can develop analogues to the virtues, but not the virtues themselves. I think that any ethical theory has to allow that in cases like this there is a qualification to the way such people can be full members of the ethical community in so far as this is thought of as a community of active reasoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know what the author's experience, but most people I've met with Downs' syndrome have been lovely. Can they reach the highest heights of virtue? I don't know, probably not, it certainly requires a degree of influence over the world that they probably lack, but I'm not sure that's a limitation of their character. To the degree that they are excluded from the ethical community, this feels more like a problem for the conception of ethics than the people in question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't have a real conclusion to this section except to note that a close reading of this bit very much made me go "Hmm" and suggests to me the author's conception of ethics is useful to a much smaller set of people than I would previously have thought, and the defence of her conception of ethics as non-elitist seems suspicious to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although fortunately I still think I'm within that set of people, so it's probably still a useful book for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Is this 🦋 a virtue?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 97-98:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being generous, kind, etc. carries no implication that you will be clean, hard-working, or witty; and none of these traits implies that you will be generous or kind. It is obvious that you can be clean, hard-wrking, or witty in a generous or ungenerous, kind or unkind way. In general, it is a good indication that a character trait is not a virtue if it neither implies nor is implied by central virtues, such as courage, but could be exercised in ways which are either courageous or cowardly, virtuous or vicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a way of working out which traits are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; virtues; can the theory say anything useful about which traits &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;? Earlier I treated patience and generosity as vitues; on what grounds? They pass the 'filter' test of fitting into the virtues thoguht of as unified by the holistic development of practical wisdom. Does this imply that they are really just forms of a more basic virtue such as benevolence? What would show that they are forms of a more basic virtue or distinct virtues?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is all as part of a chapter on the unity of the virtues, which is a concept I continue to be a bit ambivalent about. The unity of the virtues is the claim that to attain the highest level of mastery of any given virtue you need to attain it for all the virtues. You cannot be maximally courageous without being maximally kind, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think what seems to me the strongest argument in favour is roughly that to the degree that virtue is the skilled practice of being a good person, &lt;em&gt;relative to a particular conception of good&lt;/em&gt;, virtue is unitary in the sense that you have to in principle be able to do all of it all of the time. A given situation might elicit both the virtues of generosity and courage, and one requires the practical wisdom to navigate the combination of the two. If their is a virtue of courage and a virtue of benevolence, there is a joint virtue of benevolence-and-courage, and the exercise of any one of the individual virtues will sometimes be bottlenecked on the exercise of the joint virtue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not, I think, the traditional conception of the unity of the virtues, and I might hold off thinking more about this for a future research speedrun on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The skill analogy is better than she thinks it is&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the chapter "Virtue and enjoyment", Annas argues that virtues have a trait above and beyond skills, which is that they have a strong emotional component.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 66:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A skill can be exerised in independence of affective commitment; a skilled potter can produce pots, and a skilled plumber can fix leakes, in an unconcerned way. A virtuous person, by contrast, does not perform virtuous actions impassively and with lack of concern. The virtuous person not only does the right thing for the right reason, she has the right feelings about it. Someone handing out money, for example, but indifferent to the people receiving it and their responses, is not generous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Actually I think this is entirely wrong, and misunderstands both generosity and pottery.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm slightly nitpicking here, and will delve further into the chapter in a bit, but I think this is an important point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's absolutely true that you can produce pots in an unconcerned way. You know what happens if you always do that? You produce shitty pots.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm a big fan of Radimentary's &lt;a href="https://radimentary.wordpress.com/2020/11/24/pain-is-not-the-unit-of-effort/"&gt;Pain is not the unit of effort&lt;/a&gt;, in which he makes the argument that if you're not enjoying yourself you're probably not doing your best work. This is crucial to the development of skill - people learn what Thomas Green calls a "professional voice of conscience" with regards to their skills. They've got a sense of pride in making a good pot, a sense of dissatisfaction at a bad pot, etc.
It's true that any given pot that they make they're probably not pouring their heart and soul into it, but in order to get to the point where they're able to make good pots without much emotional investment, they've probably developed pretty strong feelings about pot making.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Conversely, suppose you are someone who spends every day helping people, and you wake up one morning feeling super depressed. Nothing feels particularly good, you have no love in your heart for your fellow human, and you're certainly not feeling particularly benevolent. What do you do?
Typically you go out and help people anyway.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As with pots, you probably never get to the point where you're living your life like this unless you have a strong emotional investment in helping people, but also as with pots once you know how to help people skillfully you probably do not require the emotional investment of doing so every time your help is deployed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think probably she is still right that there is a different emotional component to virtues and "normal" skills, but I don't think that the mere presence of &lt;em&gt;an&lt;/em&gt; emotional component is key.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A learner, such as a child can perform a just action because her parents tell her to, and without caring about being just, or even resenting the whole business. As she becomes more virtuous she learns to perform just actions for the right reasons. We expect the process to lead to her giving fair shares, not being unduly influenced in friends' favour and so on, easily and without effort; eventually she may give gladly. Suppose that this does not happen: she learns to give fair shares and be unbiased, but continues to resent having to do so. Such a person is not just; there is something lacking that a virtuous person would have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may be a naive question but... does this actually happen?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My model of someone who does the right things for the wrong reasons is that they tend not to be very good at it, only do it when other people are watching, and do the bare minimum. People who aren't actually just and only pretend to be tend to be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; obvious, because they lack the easy and automatic attitude towards it. They are often stuck at the conscious competence stage at best.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I would agree, in principle, that someone who goes around behaving perfectly virtuously but with malice and resentment in their heart shouldn't count as virtuous, but I'm somewhat skeptical of the relevance of such a person unless they actually exist. I think most people who can sufficiently maintain a habit of virtue are going to learn the feelings of virtue associated with that habit automatically, and this may be more of a bleen and grue situation than something that we need to take particularly seriously at a practical level.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Lives worth living&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 147:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is virtue even a starter as a candidate for making you happy? By now it's obvious that the answer is: probably not, on contemporary accounts of happiness as feeling good, getting what you want, and feeling satisfied with your life. But we've seen we don't have to think of happiness this way. If happiness is the overall end you aim to achieve by living your life well, then virtue does look like a very obvious starter, for it looks like a better idea to be loyal and sincere than to be disloyal and deceptive. It is absurd to think that we really have no more reason to acquire the virtues than not when we are thinking about how best to live. Rosalind Hursthouse has made the point forcefully: we want our children to grow up honest and brave, rather than shifty and cowardly, and we bring them up to have these virtues (as far as we can) not just for our own sake, in order to be able to rely on them in pursuing our own interests, but for their sae, because we think that they will live better lives being honest and brave rather than being shifty and cowardly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There seems something to this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I started from the claim that virtue ethics was the skill of "doing good in the world", but perhaps it would be more accurate to say that it is the skill of leading a good life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are thinking of a happy life, then, it is just common sense that we want ourselves and our children to have the virtues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I agree, but perhaps I'm not entirely sure why.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intuitive place to start is the ordinary, commonplace assumption that a person's life will, to put it generally, &lt;em&gt;go better&lt;/em&gt; if they have the virtues - if they are generous and brave, for example - than if they don't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... we moderns have come to have a problematic conception of happiness. On the one hand, we think of it as an overall end to be achieved in living a happy life, and to this extent we can make ready sense of the idea that living a good life is a way of living a happy life.(...) But on the other hand we also have another, more passive notion of happiness - the more recent idea that happiness is pleasant feeling, or getting what you want, or being satisfied with your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't really understand why she thinks these are in tension. I don't think she's &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; necessarily, I just don't understand here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular I think the thing that confuses me is that "being satisfied with your life" seems inextricably bound up with the question of living a good life? What does it mean to be dissatisfied with your life except to have judged it to not be a good one? This seems to tie in again to the ideas of &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;burnout as acedia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-03-08:59.html"&gt;moral disorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion and notes on the format&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly I think I'm coming to the, somewhat unsurprising, conclusion that I cannot really do a good book justice in an hour, especially not one like this where I probably last read it in detail over a year ago. Certainly the format of randomly flipping through the book and writing based on prompts doesn't seem to be doing it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That isn't necessarily bad. This still produces a set of interesting thoughts and writing. But perhaps the random book prompt is enough on its own.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I might in future try something closer to Lucy's original conception of the research speedruns, and might try a different format for book speedruns. I'm not yet sure what though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two questions that might make interesting future speedruns:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unity of the virtues: What is it, and is it true?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What exactly is the eudaimonist account of human happiness / flourishing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'll probably try doing another speedrun on this book about each of those questions specifically.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-18:40.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-06-00:02.html</id>
    <title>What's up with the unity of the virtues?</title>
    <updated>2021-10-06T01:54:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;What's up with the unity of the virtues?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-18:40.html"&gt;yesterday's post about Intelligent Virtue&lt;/a&gt; I said that The Unity of the Virtues deserved a speedrun all of its own, so this is me doing that speedrun.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What does 'unity of the virtues' actually mean?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Starting from Rosalind Hursthouse's "On Virtue Ethics" and just going through the index for unity of the virtues as a starting point leads me to the following interesting footnoe on Page 153:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timothy Chappell, in an unpublished paper (now, alas, lost), once argued that there were (something like) thirty (!) versions of the doctrine of the unity of the virtues. I cannot now remember how he did it, but I think the first eight came from ‘(i) The possession of any one virtue is necessary and sufficient for (or (ii) necessary for or (iii) sufficient for or (iv) conducive to) the instantaneous possession (or (v–viii) the eventual possession) of all the other virtues too’ and the next eight from the same structure with ‘The possession of some one virtue (e.g. phronesis)’ as the opening clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Side note: Timothy Chappell has transitioned since the publication of this book and is now Sophie-Grace Chappell).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So part of why it's not totally clear to me what people really mean by "The unity of the virtues" is that people mean all sorts of different things. Great.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Garbage arguments that unity of the virtues is plausible&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On page 155 is the following argument that we probably already believe in the unity of the virtues, and I hate it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That we do not believe in the disunity of the virtues is, I think, shown by our reaction to certain sorts of stories we sometimes read in the newspapers. We read of people doing what seems splendid; the sort of action that seems to call for an exceptional level of, say, courage or generosity. And then we learn about them that they have also done something morally repellent and we are surprised and often puzzled. I do not only mean something repellent in the same area—cowardly or selfish, as the case may be, which might immediately lead us to say that we had obviously made a mistake in ascribing courage or generosity to them in the first place. I mean something in a different area; the agent who dashed into the burning building and saved a stranger turns out to be a rapist; the one who has given a huge proportion of his income to the homeless turns out to be someone whose lies are keeping an innocent person in gaol. And we are surprised and puzzled: how could they be so splendid in the one instance and so despicable in another, we wonder? Now isn't that an interesting fact—that we are surprised and puzzled?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we thought of the virtues as discrete, isolable traits, such that someone could be, for example, truly courageous but also cruel and licentious in character, or truly charitable but also cowardly and dishonest, there would be no reason to be surprised or puzzled. We would expect one who acts from courage to be reliable and predictable as far as courageous acts were concerned, but have no expectations about their kindness or honesty. But we do. We believe the virtues form some sort of unity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this argument is fairly suspicious, to the point of outright disbelieving it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First off: I personally do not feel terribly surprised by any of these combinations. Hypocrisy and moral complexity abounds. It's in fact extremely common for people known for doing good to be total assholes in private.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I think our intuitions about who is a good person and in what way they are a good person tend to be reliably wrong. We're more likely to judge attractive people to be good. We're more likely to judge someone we think is an asshole to be bad, but &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-07:03.html"&gt;this causes us to prefer Cleanthes to Socrates&lt;/a&gt;. Halo effects are a whole big thing and our judgement is &lt;em&gt;reliably&lt;/em&gt; compromised by them, and seeing people doing good is very much a form of halo. So even if people &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; surprised, this is in a direction where their judgement is known to be compromised.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, this is also what you would observe even if your judgement were entirely accurate and virtues were correlated but not unified.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My go to example of such a trait is strength. If Bob deadlifts more than Joe, I'd probably also expect Bob to beat Joe in an arm wrestling competition. But he might not! Because strength is very much not unitary, there are all sorts of different feats of strength that use different muscles and different skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But they're still pretty strongly correlated. If Bob and Joe are close in deadlift I won't be at all surprised if it flips for arm wrestling. If Bob deadlifts twice as much as Joe I'll be pretty surprised if it reverse for arm wrestling, but it wouldn't blow my mind or anything, it just violates expectations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not to go all rationalist at you, but surprise is probabilistic, and something can be surprising and yet completely consistent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More, we have every reason to expect virtues to be correlated, because a desire to do good in the world is what drives one to cultivate the virtues, and so there is a common causal mechanism in the development of virtue. Therefore we would expect someone who exhibits one virtue to have spent at least some time cultivating the others, and thus to do better at them even if they were completely unrelated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, regardless of whether unity of the virtues is true, this is a garbage argument for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The Limited Unity of Virtue&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't find anything very convincing in Hursthouse's section on the unity of the virtues (which is quite short), but she references "The Limited Unity of Virtue" by Neera K. Badhwa, which is my next stop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She opens with the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aristotle's conception of virtue of character as a habitual emotional and rational disposition to feel, choose, and act in the right way for the right ends is accepted by many contemporary philosophers. But his claim that the virtues are united, such that you can have one virtue if and only if you have all of them is, typically, rejected out of hand. The doctrine of the unity of virtue follows from Aristotle's declaration that "we cannot be fully good without practical wisdom or practically wise without virtue of character, "and that "as soon as [someone] has practical wisdom, which is a single state, he has all the virtues as well."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Practical wisdom" is normally left untranslated as "phronesis" and I suspect something is being lost in translation here. It would potentially be interesting to do a future speedrun on what people really mean by "phronesis". I think I've mentally been treating it as "the pragmatic skill of being good at getting shit done" - a sort of generalised competence - but perhaps it's more qualified than that. It's at this point I should confess that I've gotten distracted while reading the Nichomachean ethics multiple times. It's not you, Aristotle, it's me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Badhwa proposes the following &lt;em&gt;limited unity of the virtues&lt;/em&gt; thesis:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The existence of a virtue in a particular domain of a person's life does not imply the existence of that (or any other) virtue in any other domain. So P may be kind towards her friends and colleagues without being kind (or virtuous in any other way) towards acquaintances or strangers, or she may be kind towards those who have been unlucky in their careers without being kind towards those who have been unlucky in their personal relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The existence of virtue in one domain implies the absence of vice as well as of ignorance in most other domains. Hence, if P is kind, just, etc. in her friendships, she cannot be vicious towards everyone else or, for that matter, ignorant of the basic elements of everyone else's good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every virtue requires the others within the same domain, and so none is incompatible with, or independent of, any other. Hence, if P is kind towards her friends and colleagues, she must also be generous, just, temperate, and courageous with respect to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think (3) is the most interesting of these three, in that it still seems to be a stronger claim than I think is necessarily obviously true, but I'm not sure if I'm just unclear on what she means by "must".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reading onwards I find:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A vicious person may be clever in achieving his ends, but since his ends are bad, he cannot be wise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;OK so "practical wisdom" does include the requirement that the shit you're trying to get done is actually good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Actually, I think this plus skimming the rest of the paper (no direct quotes sorry) makes me think that the unity of the virtues as being presented is roughly the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a given domain there is a well defined set of "good ends".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phronesis, or practical wisdom, is the skill of achieving those ends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtues are the character traits which dispose one, rationally and emotionally, towards achieving those good ends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thus virtues and phronesis are intimately intertwined, in that the development of phronesis is dependent on and in turn cultivates the virtues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems right to me, and largely agrees with &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-04-18:40.html"&gt;my comments about the skill analogy yesterday&lt;/a&gt; but I think the crucial feature of this is that the virtues are unified &lt;em&gt;with respect to a given set of good ends&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the restriction to a domain makes this claim very limited indeed. If the domain is just a set of people or a given aim, that's not much of a restriction, but you can for example imagine someone who is very dedicated to helping people who are in danger but lacks patience with the emotional side of the problem - cultivating the virtue of courage but not of kindness. Is this just a restricted domain? They've included in their set of good ends people's physical but not emotional wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also think this has a sort of "in the limit" character to it - it's true, for example, that cultivating kindness is very important for firefighters, or soldiers, or people in other dangerous professions, but I bet you'll find they're skewed pretty heavily towards courage. Maxing out the skill of phronesis might require you to cultivate all the virtues, but I bet you can get pretty far on only some of them, and most people don't make it to the peak of any skill they develop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Teaching the virtues&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Returning to Intelligent Virtue, on page 84 we have the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important indication of the nature of virtue comes from the point that we can't teach the virtues in isolation, one by one, since they can't be learnt that way. Generosity gives us a good example here. A child doesn't learn to be generous by just giving her things away, or sharing things whether they belong to her or not. Generosity involves considerations of fairness and justice. For, as Aristotle points out, generosity requires taking from the right sources as well as giving to the right people in the right way.' And 'giving in the right way' involves a great deal. Giving a gift which is indifferent to what the recipient wants is not generous. Generosity requires intelligence about what people both need and want, and also about appropriate ways, times, and manners of giving, avoiding obtrusiveness and condescension. Generosity thus requires, at the least, benevolence, a real interest in other people, their needs, and their wants. To get it right in giving, how to give, when and to whom, not to mention how much, you have to have an interest in the welfare of others beyond their role as your beneficiaries; otherwise you risk your giving becoming selfish showing-off. Generosity thus requires real benevolent concern for others, along with minor virtues such as tact. Obviously children don't get all of this at once, and even as adults we find we constantly need improvement; the point here is that we can all see, in the course of ethical development, that some virtues 'cluster'. This indicates something about the nature of virtue; it is not just a casual point, extraneous to an account of virtue, about how we learn to be virtuous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, I think, a good point and ties in well with the above "limited unity of the virtue". Within a given domain, we have a set of "good ends", and we must learn to value those ends, and it often doesn't make sense to split them up. You don't learn to value being generous and value being fair, you learn to value other people and thus be generous and fair to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(As a side note, an ongoing point of annoyance with the world for me is that it seems most people &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; do this. They learn to value other people and then put in the minimum effort they can get away with with thinking through the implications of that)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Later on page 88:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do not need far-fetched thought experiments to grasp that the way we develop in one area of our lives can indeed have an impact on the way we develop in other parts. The compassionate person might well need courage to insist that a victim be treated properly, or to stand up to a bully on someone else's behalf. If he lacks courage, his compassion will be flawed too; victims can't rely on it, and others generally can't rely on him to be compassionate in appropriate circumstances. In general a virtue which is unreliable in its exercise because of facts about the person (rather than external circumstances) is a compromised virtue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems right. One of the things the drives unity of the virtues is that sometimes you might need both virtues at once. I think this is the same argument I put forth yesterday (which isn't surprising as my thoughts have previously been informed by this book, and I was reading bits of this chapter):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think what seems to me the strongest argument in favour is roughly that to the degree that virtue is the skilled practice of being a good person, relative to a particular conception of good, virtue is unitary in the sense that you have to in principle be able to do all of it all of the time. A given situation might elicit both the virtues of generosity and courage, and one requires the practical wisdom to navigate the combination of the two. If their is a virtue of courage and a virtue of benevolence, there is a joint virtue of benevolence-and-courage, and the exercise of any one of the individual virtues will sometimes be bottlenecked on the exercise of the joint virtue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So virtues are unitary in the sense that one has to be able to unify them in order to reliably perform them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She ties this in to virtues developed in separate domains and why we might expect them to be unified:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A trial lawyer, for example, may develop adversarial traits in the courtroom which, in the context of her family, would distress both her and her family, where the virtues she exercises are cooperative. Often it is not clear that both sets of traits are in fact virtues, but let us suppose that they are. The person is still living in a compartmentalized way, one with divisions and compromises always present, and one in which the values sought in one aspect of life may well be in conflict with those pursued in another. Moreover, the less the person sees it as her aim to live an integrated life, the more these conflicts will be both painful and hard for her to predict. This is hardly an ideal for a virtuous life. For one thing, it comes into sharp conflict with the aspect of virtue discussed in the last chapter-the point that the virtuous person finds her life enjoyable, in part because of lack of inner conflict or its threat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does virtue require a lack of inner conflict? It doesn't seem unreasonable to me, although I don't know that I have a strong feeling on it one way or the other. Certainly it seems plausible to me that cultivating virtue requires resolving inner conflicts, along the lines of the sort of therapy-meets-virtue-ethics I discussed in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-03-08:59.html"&gt;Notes on moral disorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Does maximal virtue imply omnicompetence?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Intelligent virtue, page 94:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third objection is the most important. How can the virtues be so unified by practical intelligence that they imply one another, when different people obviously lead different ways of life and need to exercise different virtues? A soldier needs one set of virtues, a caregiver to an Alzheimer's patient needs another set. Someone in a position of leadership will need a different set of virtues from the people being directed.We are faced by an apparent dilemma. On the one hand, if we are committed to holding that nobody can be fully virtuous unless they can exercise all the virtues, we seem committed to the absurd conclusion that to live a fully virtuous life you will have to live the life of a soldier and that of a caregiver (and many more besides). For if you have all the virtues, you must be able to exercise all the virtues, and it seems that you must live a life in which opportunities to exercise all the virtues are available to you. An addition to this claim can be made: to exercise a virtue will probably require fairly specialized knowledge. The virtue of compassion is not exercised by merely standing around wishing you could help: the compassionate person actually helps the wounded, aids the suicidal, and so on. But now it looks as though the fully virtuous person, in being omni-virtuous also has to be omni-competent, equipped to be, on demand, a doctor, psychiatrist, computer expert, plumber, and so on; which is even more absurd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next couple of pages include a bunch of discussion of this in which she tries to weasel out of this problem by saying that the &lt;em&gt;possession&lt;/em&gt; of the virtues is independent of whether your life offers you equal opportunity for the &lt;em&gt;expression&lt;/em&gt; of the virtues.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If we take the skill analogy for virtue that she advocates for seriously (and I do), this is like saying that just because one doesn't have any opportunity in one's life to practice piano one might still possess in principle the piano playing talents of a maestro. Obviously you don't. The development of a skill requires practice, and if your life does not offer opportunities for the use of a virtue then you will not develop it to its maximal potential.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also that's fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it's in some sense clearly true that being omni-virtuous requires omni-competent, but so what? Being maximally virtuous is obviously completely unachievable for mortal beings. How could it be otherwise? If virtue ethics is to be usable (and its focus on practical wisdom suggests it must be) it must be focused on the sort of virtue pursuable by human beings, not gods, and that doesn't involve striving to be the best possible, only to be better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The argument that the virtues are unified via practical wisdom is interesting and seems to be pointing at something useful, but I think falls short. It's not that virtues are unitary, but that they unify, and that sometimes the thing we are bottlenecked on in improving one virtue is another virtue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think the concept of practical wisdom having to be directed towards good ends very much hides the relativism implicit in virtue ethics. It's clear that virtues can only be unified within a given conception of the good. This isn't a problem as I'm comfortable with relativism, but it also makes the "the" in "the unity of the virtues" somewhat suspect.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All this being said, I think I need to spend more time with the unity of the virtues chapter in Intelligent Virtue, as I left it a bit to the end and don't feel like I really did it justice as a result. I may or may not actually do that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-06-00:02.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-06-16:21.html</id>
    <title>Revisiting Intelligent Virtue</title>
    <updated>2021-10-06T19:01:57+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Revisiting Intelligent Virtue&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure if it counts as a speedrun if you've already done the book, but I thought I'd spend another hour on Intelligent Virtue today, as I keep coming away from it thinking I haven't really done it justice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to mix up the format of it a little bit by trying to do a chapter-by-chapter breakdown in this hour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On page 1:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... the present distinctive account of virtue results from attending to two ideas. One is that exercising a virtue involves practical reasoning of a kind that can illuminatingly be compared to the kind of reasoning we find in someone exercising a practical skill. Rather than asking at the start how virtues relate to rules, principles, maximizing, or a final end, we will gain by looking at the way in which the acquisition and exercise of virtue can be seen to be in many ways like the acquisition and exercise of more mundane activities, such as farming, building, or playing the piano. The other idea is that virtue is part of the agent's happiness or flourishing, and that it is plausible to see virtue as actually constituting (wholly or in part) that happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So roughly her point is that:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtues are developed like skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtues are a key part of "human flourishing"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Oversimplifying, one can think of virtues as the skills of promoting human flourishing, which is how I tend to characterise it (in large part based on prior readings of this book).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rest of the introduction mostly covers things that are going to be covered in future chapters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Virtue, Character, and Disposition&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is the chapter in which she tries to explain what virtues are, and very much falls prety to the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-02-09:29.html"&gt;People are bad at defining things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are the places in this chapter where the phrase "virtue is" or "virtues are" occur, with some surrounding context:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A virtue is a lasting feature of a person, a tendency for the person to be a certain way. It is not merely a lasting feature, however, one that just sits there undisturbed. It is active: to have it is to be disposed to act in certain ways&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A virtue is not a static condition like [the tendency of glass to shatter]; it is a disposition as a result of which Jane acts and thinks in a certain way, and which is at any time strengthened by her generous responses and weakened by failures to have them. If she is generous, her generous actions and feelings both come from a virtue and fortify it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A virtue is also a reliable disposition. If Jane is generous, it is no accident that she does the generous action and has generous feelings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, a virtue is a disposition which is is, the virtuous (or vicious) person is acting in and from character when acting in a kindly, brave or restrained way. This is another way of putting the point that a virtue is a deep feature of the person. A virtue is a disposition which is central to the person, to whom he or she is, a way we standardly think of character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...  virtue is a disposition which is from the start an active and developing one. It is not a passive product of a string of impacts from outside; it is the way I (or you), an active creature, develops a character through formation and education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the virtues are educated developments of our unformed motivations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since virtue is a disposition of the above kind, becoming virtuous will naturally take time. Scrooge may have been converted suddenly to compassion and kindliness on Christmas Eve, but the story is careful to tell us that he continued over time the process of becoming a compassionate person. Coming to see that being loyal or brave is a worthwhile way to live is just the first step. Becoming virtuous requires habituation and experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is natural to worry at this point whether habituation is just habit, and whether a virtuous disposition is just one built up by force of habit. Our experience leads us, in a number of areas of our lives, to develop habits which save time and effort. If developing a virtue is like this, why should we think it amounts to anything more than habit and even mere routine?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtue is unlike routine in a host of ways. [Followed by a long discussion of why piano playing is not a virtue that I don't entirely understand]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skilled dispositions are not static conditions; they are always developing, being sustained or weakened. One of the major suggestions of this book is that virtue is like practical skill in this respect (as well as some others). Because a virtue is a disposition it requires time, experience, and habituation to develop it, but the result is not routine but the kind of actively and intelligently engaged practical mastery that we find in practical experts such as pianists and athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A central feature of routine is that the reaction to the relevant situation is always the same, which is why routine can be depended on and predicted. But practical skill and virtue require more than predictably similar reaction; they require a response which is appropriate to the situation instead of merely being the same as that produced in response to other situations. This appropriateness comes from the habituated disposition that a virtue is. As Aristotle says: 'It ... seems to be characteristic of the more courageous person to be unafraid and unruffled in sudden alarms rather than to be so in those that are foreseen; it comes more from his state of character [hexis, often translated 'disposition'], because less from preparation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this produces a set of &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; conditions for something to count as a virtue. It must be:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a characteristic disposition of the person to act in a particular way (generously, courageously).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in some way &lt;em&gt;fundamental&lt;/em&gt; to the person exercising it - that is, if you were to somehow take away the virtue they would have to be a very different person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;oriented towards something that we desire in and of itself (our "unformed motivations")&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consciously and knowingly practiced, leading to its further development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this cannot count as sufficient to be a virtue because many vices could also satisfy this condition e.g. "nastiness" or "hedonistic debauchery" also satisfy this for people who are motivated towards such things, but it's a good start for at least distinguishing virtues from other skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Skilled and virtuous action&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this she is trying to further distinguish virtues from skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some practical skills do seem to involve mere routine - this is true of daily activities such as getting to work which we are sometimes prepared to call skills, though at other times we call them routines or rituals. (...) We find the important similarity of virtue to skill in skills where two things are united: the &lt;em&gt;need to learn&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;drive to aspire&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the "skill analogy" is highlighting the idea that virtues are things where excellence must be sought and is something we should desire in and of itself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She goes on to say (some pages later after a bunch of detailed intermediate discussion)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtue can most illuminatingly be seen as like this kind of skill; it shares the intellectual structure of a skill where we find not only the need to learn but the drive to aspire, and hence the need to 'give an account, the need for articulate conveying of reasons why what is done is done. The learner in virtue, like the learner in a practical skill, needs to understand what she is doing, to achieve the ability to do it for herself, and to do it in a way that improves as she meets challenges, rather than coming out with predictable repetition. This conies about when the virtue is conveyed by the giving and receiving of reasons, in contrast with the non-rational picking up of a knack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This view does rather explain why she thinks people with Downs syndrome can't be virtuous, but suggests that perhaps one way of thinking about virtue ethics is that it's not actually intended to be universally normative. That is, it's entirely possible to be fully ethical without being virtuous.
You can imagine (although I suspect no such person exists) someone who always unthinkingly does the right thing out of a natural pleasantness of character, and never strives for it.
Such a person is ethical but not virtuous.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this light, I think perhaps a good way to read Annas (and ethicists in general?) is as a sort of "Ethics for Nerds" - if you don't automatically know the right thing to do, how would you go about learning to do so?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the way to think of the virtues is as a sufficient but not necessary set of conditions for being a good person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The Scope of Virtue&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this she starts by defending virtue against the critique of relativism, but I am in fact completely comfortable with relativism and think her defence is probably wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In it she mentions &lt;a href="https://www.virtuesproject.com/"&gt;The Virtues Project&lt;/a&gt; as an example of an attempt at a cross-cultural list of the virtues. This sounds interesting and I may spend more time with it, but also I did a card pick on it and it lead me to the &lt;a href="https://virtuesdev.com/vpicks/Prayerfulness.png"&gt;Prayerfulness&lt;/a&gt; virtue at which point I said "Oh fuck you" out loud and closed the site for now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The chapter does contain the following interesting passage:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Aristotle says in the passage I have quoted more than once, everyone seeks the good, not just what their parents did. Becoming virtuous starts the process by making it clear that the virtuous life cannot just be the life your parents lead. Anyone can come to realize this, and anyone can continue the progressive enlargement of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why then do so few do so? This is not a problem particular to thinking in terms of virtue, since any ethical theory has to face the fact that most people do not live by it. The answer given by the present account is that while we are all capable of aspiring to become virtuous, most of us resist being pulled away from our familiar original contexts by becoming progressively more virtuous. Rather than deal with the fact that our family is dishonest, our country jingoistic, the values we have learnt inadequate, we make rationalizations, or simply refuse to face facts. We are unwilling to criticize the contexts and institutions within which we learned the virtues, because we are unwilling to be pulled away from those contexts in the way that would be required. The community of the family, or society, is a visible and tangible one, providing real comfort and support. The community of the honest (the brave, the open-minded, and so on) is an invisible one composed of all those who, past, present, and future, act, reason, and feel in certain ways; accessible only through thought and reflection, it offers less help in getting through the day.' If we think of community as a form of solidarity, pre-existing solidarities can make it hard to be detached from them.' To identify with the community of the just, rather than with your own fellow citizens, is often hard, for it requires detachment from the existing support you get from relations with your fellow-citizens. What requires explanation, then, is not so much the slackness of most people in developing the virtues, but the strength of the few in achieving them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Strong vibes of what I've written about in the past in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html"&gt;The social obligation to be bad at things&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-31-09:20.html"&gt;Norms of Excellence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think what she is essentially arguing in this chapter is that culture can &lt;em&gt;limit&lt;/em&gt; our virtue, but that there is a single overarching but imperfectly expressed universal notion of virtue, which striving to be vituous allows us to move our communities towards.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To which I say: Well, maybe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Virtue and Enjoyment&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this chapter she is arguing that one of the key features of virtue is that the virtuous like being virtuous. They don't experience it as a chore, but as a thing that is worthwhile in and of itself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, one aspect of the virtuous person's moral psychology, perhaps surprisingly, points us to another important analogy between skill and virtue. Aristotle famously comments that the virtuous person is distinguished by finding what he does pleasant: 'We must take as an indication of a person's states the pleasure or pain consequent on what he does, because the person who abstains from bodily pleasures and finds his enjoyment in doing just this is temperate, while the person who finds doing it oppressive is intemperate; and the person who enjoys facing up to danger, or at least does not find it painful to do so, is courageous, while he who does find it painful is a coward. The temperance example is not hard to understand. Someone resolving to give up meat, for example, will at first have to fight against temptation and will find the forbidden food attractive; but as they develop the relevant disposition to be vegetarian they cease to find it tempting. Eventually they take more pleasure in not eating what they now reject than they did when they ate it; the vegetarian finds it more enjoyable to be a vegetarian than she did being someone who enjoyed eating meat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly this sounds to me like the sort of thing you tell people even if it's false.
My personal experience of being vegetarian (which may not be representative of "true virtue" in that I did eventually decide not to be) is that while I found the idea of eating meat actively unappealing, I never &lt;em&gt;enjoyed&lt;/em&gt; not eating meat. I enjoyed what I was eating, and I didn't want to eat meat, but there was never any sense that vegetarianism in and of itself was enjoyable, it was just a thing, and I expect this is normal. I think this is just a weak example though - I can certainly see the argument that some exercises of virtue are enjoyable, I just don't think vegetarianism works like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Much of the rest of the chapter is connecting up virtue with the idea of &lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt;, and that virtue is enjoyable because it creates flow. This seems too cute to me, but I think the core idea that virtue is enjoyable because it is a skilled practice and using your skills in worthwhile ways is enjoyable is reasonably solid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Virtues and the unity of the virtue&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm running out of time and feel like &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-06-00:02.html"&gt;I covered this adequately yesterday&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can we say anything more specific about the distinctive kind of admiration called forth by virtue?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first answer is that in the case of the virtues our admiration is for the person's character: possession of virtues indicates something about what the person is like, whereas possession of traits such as tidiness or wittiness indicates only traits that the person has. Take someone who is characteristically tidy, who, noticing that his car has got messy, cleans it out. What does this tell us about his character? Very little. Let us suppose that the same person is characteristically brave, and that in the course of the subsequent drive he stops and courageously rescues passengers trapped in a crashed and burning car. This action, unlike the previous one, does indicate what kind of person he is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly I think tidiness tells you a lot about the sort of person someone is, and could legitimately get behind the idea that cleanliness is a virtue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might think at this point that the contrast here is not between virtues and other traits, but between virtues and vices on the one hand and other traits on the other. For surely, we think, vices indicate character as much as virtues do? This is true up to a point, and shows that virtues do more than merely indicate character. Suppose another person who sees the burning car, but pretends not to, and drives on. This is a cowardly act, and if it is characteristic of the person it does tell us something about him as a person, namely that he is a coward. But there is an important difference here, which can be brought out by the claim that the brave person is, by virtue of being brave, expressing a commitment to goodness, a commitment to positive value. Although this is a very general point, it is intuitive. The brave person's action reveals that he is committed to something valuable that is centrally important to him. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, I think, where the idea of unity of the virtues comes from: The central feature of virtue is "commitment to goodness".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ran out of time at this point, without having finished covering the last few chapters, and I think this demonstrates the weakness of the format - Intelligent Virtue isn't even a very long book!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I'm going to rebrand these from "speedruns" to "studies", because it's clear that I can't do justice to a book in an hour (this is of course not surprising, although bear in mind these are also books I've already read), and I may well do a further study on the last couple of chapters of this book because they seem quite important.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-06-16:21.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-08-01:23.html</id>
    <title>Scurrying</title>
    <updated>2021-10-11T23:42:25+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Scurrying&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was going to do another study on Intelligent Virtue today but the day kinda got away from me (ironically, partly due to an in depth discussion of virtue ethics on discord),
and now I'm tired, so I'm not going to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead let me tell you about the Alexander Technique lesson I had with &lt;a href="https://alexandercentre.co.uk/"&gt;Peter Nobes&lt;/a&gt; earlier, which gave me a good handle on a problem I didn't know existed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me set the scene.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Peter and I were about to play catch (this is surprisingly helpful) and I spotted that I had left my coffee cup right behind him. I felt that my throwing balls in the direction of a nearly full cup of coffee was probably a poor idea, so I said "Hang on a second, let me just move that" and walked across the room to put it somewhere less precarious.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Peter stopped me. "Did you maintain your Alexander while doing that?" "No, probably not."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"I'm going to use an unkind word to describe what you just did. You were &lt;em&gt;scurrying&lt;/em&gt;."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We then had a good conversation about how I had also done this earlier when I arrived. I was in the middle of a conversation on Twitter and he came out a bit earlier than expected. Now I needed to put my bag on and pick up my coffee cup and oops I've forgotten my mask let me put the coffee cup down and...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is these abrupt and slightly flustered looking movements that signal "I need to do this in order to get to the important thing". A sort of furtive rushing through the motions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing about these motions is that they're not actually that much faster than calmly doing the thing, and to the degree that they are they are probably increasing the error rate (consider how I forgot my mask and had to go back and sort that out), so may even be slower. But what they do is &lt;em&gt;signal that you are going fast&lt;/em&gt; regardless of whether you are actually going fast. Moving in a way that indicates that you're trying to get this over and done with and you want those around you to know that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think henceforth this label of "scurrying" is going to live in my head as referring to specifically doing something in such a way as to indicate you're trying to trying to get it over with so you can get on to the important bit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This ties in to what Alexander Technique calls "end gaining", but I think "scurrying" points to something more specific here - it's not just that you're focused on the goal, but are simultaneously treating the goal as unimportant except in that it's necessary)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is scurrying bad? Maybe. I don't think rushing through something to get on to the important bit is &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; bad, to the degree that it actually helps rather than is counterproductive, but I do think that often scurrying happens in cases where it shouldn't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Take for example the earlier incident where I went to move the coffee. Why was I scurrying? I was there to learn to stay in the Alexander state and move accordingly, so getting the cup of coffee was every bit as important as playing a game of catch, but I treated the former as something to get out of the way in order to do the latter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the nice things about scurrying as a concept here is that it's so visually clear as a set of movements. I've been struggling to really integrate anything Alexander Technique related into my life because I don't remember to do it, but scurrying is something I can go "Oh, I'm doing the thing. Do I want to be?" to, and use as a prompt for change.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-08-01:23.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-08-21:50.html</id>
    <title>On Julia Annas's conception of happiness</title>
    <updated>2021-10-08T23:01:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;On Julia Annas's conception of happiness&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm continuing to study Julia Annas's book "Intelligent Virtue", and exploring the one hour study format. Today I thought I'd go through Chapter 8, "Living Happily" in detail. I've copied out the whole chapter into this notebook and will be deleting most of it (I think this still counts as fair use. I hope!). I've done a bit of a skim through it but mostly am writing as I read it, so often I'll write comments that I'll later take back.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Page 119:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very idea that virtue might have any role in flourishing or happiness has seemed, for about two hundred years, deeply unlikely. Philosophers in that period have been among the most robust in insisting that the whole idea of thinking that virtue could lead to happiness is absurd. Bentham says of the idea that virtue is sufficient for happiness, 'What benefit, in any shape, could be derived from impregnating the memory with such nonsense? What instruction from a self-contradictory proposition?" Nietzsche is even more dismissive. 'Such assertions and promises as those of the antique philosophers concerning the unity of virtue and happiness or the Christian, "But seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness, and all these things shall be added unto you" have never been made with total honesty and yet always without a bad conscience: one has advanced such propositions, which one very much desires to be true, boldly as to the truth in the face of appearance.' This idea, that there is some kind of naive wish-fulfilment or over-optimism in the claim that the virtuous are happy, lingers more effectively than actual arguments. Up to this point I have used the interim term 'flourishing' rather than happiness, but this has not been intended to avoid the issue stated brutally by Bentham and Nietzsche, and I shall now talk in terms of happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think a lot of this chapter will be spent defending the idea that happiness is not just simple pleasure and that it's plausible that virtue is a necessary component of it. I'm not sure I need that defence, as I'm already pretty on board with the idea. In &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;Burnout as acedia&lt;/a&gt; I talk about how burnout often comes precisely because we are not living our life ethically in the way that we want, because we are out of line with our values.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More generally I think happiness comes from doing things we feel are worthwhile, and "What counts as worthwhile?" is a fundamentally ethical question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next couple of paragraphs are spent on justifying the question that we don't seem to really know what happiness is, which then leads into the discussion of eudaimonia, starting Page 120:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is a eudaimonist account? An account of how to live, one in which happiness, eudaimonia, is central (...) the entry point for ethical reflections is thinking about how your life is going, thinking that can only arise in people who already are, or are becoming, adult, and who are aware that everything in their life is not satisfactory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, more or less, my above view: You need to not just be happy but &lt;em&gt;happy with your life&lt;/em&gt;. To judge it as satisfactory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you step back from the ongoing happenings of your life, and wonder about how and in what direction it is going. This at once reveals a fundamental difference between two ways in which you can regard your life. One perspective is the everyday one, in which you do one thing after another, one action following another chronologically. You get up, go to work and so on, one thing after another until eventually it comes to an end when your life does. This is the linear way of thinking of your life, and it is important as you get through the day, and in many other ways. But reflection reveals another way in which your life enters your thoughts about it. We can call this the structured way of thinking of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Long discussion of how we do things for reasons and have goals we are trying to achieve elided)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflection thus both triggers and then furthers thinking about how to achieve the goals I have in the light of the constraints I have (time, money, energy) and their mutual achievability. (...) What is activated is not thinking in the abstract about types of goal and how they could fit together, but thinking about how I can achieve the goals I have in the life I have. It is thinking about my life and how it is going. It is practical thinking, thinking about my life and how I should structure it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Thinking about my life and how I should structure it" seems like an important concept here. I think in many ways this is the goal of coaching - it draws you into that thinking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the original everyday thinking about the way one thing I do is for the sake of another thing I do leads seamlessly into thinking about my life as a whole in a structured way. This is a global way of thinking about my life: I come to see that I have various goals that I aim at, and that in the one life I have, and which I am already living, these goals need to be structured in a unifying way in order for me to achieve them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly I don't believe this account. I don't think most people have goals, and I don't think reflection naturally leads you to them. This may, partly, be because of my own baggage around goals, but I also think philosophers are very inclined to think in terms of goals.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This focus on goals also reminds me of yesterday's discussion of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-08-01:23.html"&gt;Scurrying&lt;/a&gt;. Treating the thing you are currently doing as the unimportant thing you are doing to get to the goal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But this is, ironically, actively the type of thing that virtue ethics in general and Annas in particular are arguing against: Thoughtlessly doing the thing, rather than doing it with the right emotions in your heart about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is this - the idea of what my life as a whole is aimed at - which in ancient ethical theories is called the telos or overall goal of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I very much reject the idea that life has an overall goal, and &lt;a href="https://meaningness.com/no-special-meaning"&gt;defer you to my friend David Chapman for the question of whether we should be upset about that&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us have nothing like this specific grasp of what our lives are working towards achieving. We have only the vaguest idea of what we are aiming for in life as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ah, good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;. This is exactly what eudaimonism holds: we have at best a vague and possibly muddled idea of what our 'final end' is; it is most likely to be only the indeterminate and in itself unhelpful idea of 'a good life' or 'a life lived well'. This supports, rather than undermines, eudaimonism, for few of us have a determinate idea of what we are aiming at in our life as a whole at the start of ethical reflection.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hmm. No this seems to still be back at the "but we &lt;em&gt;shuold&lt;/em&gt; have such a goal".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't deny that at any given point we should have &lt;em&gt;projects&lt;/em&gt;, and those should be meaningful, but I think if you're aiming at an overall purpose to your life you're going to make yourself miserable and also probably fail to achieve it. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-23-15:52.html"&gt;Life is an anytime algorithm&lt;/a&gt; - whether your life was a success or failure should not be determined by the fact whether you achieve some grand goal, because you can get hit by a bus at any point along the way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we did, we would have no need of ethical reflection or theory; our aims would already be clear and the only problems we would have would lie in actually achieving them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you've got a good way to never make a mistake en route to your goal that needs clarification, I'd love to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we find in fact is that nearly everyone (every moderately thoughtful person, in any case) is already living a life in which he or she is to some degree actively unifying the aims they have by working out what exactly those aims are and what form they should take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No, this seems false. Most people are just bumbling along. They probably have &lt;em&gt;immediate&lt;/em&gt; goals, but that's not the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final end, then, is the indeterminate notion of what I am aiming at in my life as a whole. And the role of ethical thinking is to get us to think more determinately about it, to do a better and more intelligently ordered job of what we are already doing anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hmm. I agree that the goal of of ethical thinking is to get us to do a better and more intelligently ordered job of what we were already doing anyway. I remain very very skeptical of this life goals thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can we say anything more specific about it? At this point Aristotle says that everyone agrees on something more determinate that we can say about it: it is happiness (eudaimonia); (...) Aristotle is bringing happiness in here merely as the only answer people can give, at the common-sense level, to the questions about why you are doing what you are doing, and how you can have all the goals that you have. That is, at the common-sense level, what is being appealed to is the idea that happiness always puts a stop to these questions. I may want to be healthy, to have a career, to have a family, as part of being happy, but I don't want to be happy as part of or a means to something further. It's just what I want; a terminus to my other goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm pretty suspect of arguments like this. I think they're wrong in a slippery way, because anything else you claim as a terminal goal the arguer just goes "Ah but you want that because it makes you happy", and I don't think this is true. If I love someone, I want them to be happy, and I don't want them to be happy because their happiness makes me happy (it may or may not do so depending on the context and my current mood. I might be too depressed to be happy right now!), I want them to be happy because I &lt;em&gt;want them to be happy for their own sake&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Side note: When thinking about this chapter I had a flashback to the first time I had this argument, which was standing at a bus stop waiting to go home from school when I was 17. I have no idea how it started, and I am surprised to learn that I have been arguing the nature of the good life for 21 years now. I thought this was a more recent phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This role for happiness is extremely useful in ethical theory. At the common-sense level people disagree about what is worth aiming for in life, but all agree that, whether they are going for money-making, fame and fortune, or serving others, they are all aiming for happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No we don't, I literally just disagreed with you, please don't assume consensus you don't have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think most people are aiming at happiness among other things, but people seem weirdly reluctant to do things that increase their happiness (citation: Various conversations on Twitter I can't be bothered to dig up right now).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happiness thus forms the point at which common sense agrees on a notion which forms the starting-point for ethical theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Gosh I hope not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting to do ethical theory does not require throwing out all or most of everyday thinking about ethics (even though the theories themselves may produce results which are very counter-intuitive). Ethical theory helps us to improve what we are already about how are lives are going and how we can do better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That's the hope anyway.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happiness has the role of being, for each person, your happiness, the way you achieve living your life well. It is not some plan imposed on you from outside, or a demand made by some theory which has not arisen from your own thoughts about your life. At the same time it is not just anything you want it to be. There are better and worse ways of seeking happiness, for there are clearly better and worse ways of organizing your goals and aims in life, and of seeking to live a life that achieves them overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems solidly true and important.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is happiness in this role in eudaimonist thinking happiness as we understand it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's a good question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one influential criticism of any account of happiness in eudaimonist thinking. Answering it helps to indicate an important feature of happiness. Grant that we all aim for something in our lives overall, vaguely and without being able to specify it beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do not grant this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grant also that this is happiness, understood as a very general aim which we can achieve in a number of ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, happiness is the point where ordinary thought meets theory: to achieve happiness we have to reflect about what we are doing to achieve it, and how this could be improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing maybe worth mentioning here is that this is a very Greek attitude, and if you look at a Buddhist attitude they would argue that almost exactly the opposite is true. Happiness comes from letting go of attachment and being present in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is very oversimplified, IANABuddhist)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet surely it is both intuitively repugnant, and at the level of theory objectionably paternalist, for some people to be in a position to tell others how to be happy. Some philosophers recoil at this point, seeing a spectre emerging from eudaimonism: some people imposing their own vision of the good life on others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know, a lot of people seem like they could use some advice here. I think the problem is maybe &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-give-good-advice"&gt;that those philosophers are bad at giving advice&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I start to reflect ethically there is much about my life which I have to recognize as the material I have to work on. The first ethical move is not to abstract from my individual context, still less to discount it, but rather to understand what it consists in, to achieve self-knowledge as far as I can, and then to think about how best to live my life in these circumstances. Only then will I be in a good position to consider the various options offered to me by different ethical theories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think this is a very important point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From here I'm going to start skimming a bit more aggressively because a lot of the next bits are philosophy-is-arguing-with-other-philosophers and I'm running a bit low on time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saying anything negative about pleasure is often wrongly thought to indicate puritanism. It is worth meeting this point by reflecting on the role of pleasure in the kind of life we want our children to lead. Suppose I am, ex hypothesi, not a puritan, and want my child to lead a happy life. I will want my child to enjoy her activities and have feelings of pleasure. But could this be what makes her life a happy one? This strikes two wrong notes. I will scarcely think that my wish has been granted if my child lives a life enjoying activities which are degraded or addictive."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems right, although I will note that I rarely trust parents to make a good judgement about "degraded" life choices.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That being said, I don't know that whether I would say that this sort of judgement is about the child's &lt;em&gt;happiness&lt;/em&gt;. I would tend to assume that someone leading a hedonistic life, or a drug addict, isn't "really" happy but this feels like an empirical claim rather than a self-evidently true one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even if an activity is a serious one, something has gone wrong if the person's life is made a happy one not by the activity but by the feelings of enjoyment she gets from it. Any parent would be disconcerted to find that their child had grown up to regard her life as happy because of the enjoyment she got from, say, helping others, but would unhesitatingly drop helping others the minute she ceased to enjoy it. This is, once again, not an adult attitude. And this seems right even before we are in a position to explain why something has gone wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Same objection. This seems like a valid judgement, but not obviously one that is about their happiness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One factor helping to explain why it goes wrong is the point that pleasure lacks the right kind of relation to the rest of our moral psychology. This has been called lack of 'causal depth'." If we think of happiness as just feeling good, we cannot, for example, distinguish between the different kinds of impact on a person of unwelcome events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't want to comment on what your life is like, but I feel like if you don't realise that there are different levels of intensity of feeling good you maybe need to get out more.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a revealing example from Daniel Haybron, take two scenarios, in one of which I have pleasant feelings and am feeling good, and then get a flat tyre, while in the other I am feeling good, but then my child dies. If happiness is just having pleasant feelings, the impact of these two events would appear to be the same: first I have pleasant feelings, then I don't, having painful ones instead. Since it is absurd for a theory not to be able to distinguish between these two ways of no longer feeling good, a supporter of pleasure has to say that my loss of pleasant feelings will be much more intense in the second case than in the first. But this plainly fails to give us the right distinction." The real difference lies in the wider impacts and ramifications of the second event; what is bad about it for me is not the intensity of loss of good feeling and occurrence of painful feelings, but the wide and connected effects in all areas of my life of this loss. Nothing like this happens with the flat tyre, which puts a stop to pleasant feeling but without wide or deep impact on my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems like a disingenuous argument. I don't think it's at all hard to fit these examples into a pleasure view of happiness, because they are things that affect your ability to feel pleasure - both in the short and the long run.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it seems like a "pure pleasure" view of happiness is an obvious strawman of a view that is actually "presence of pleasure and absence of pain", which trivially incorporates these examples.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, as it happens, I don't think pleasure provides a good account of happiness, but I think these arguments against it are pretty weak.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that happiness might just consist in feelings of pleasure or the enjoyment of activities is not very plausible, once we bear in mind the role of happiness as our final end, something in the achieving of which we shape our lives. Pleasure is just not the right kind of item to play this role. It becomes clear that if happiness is construed as feelings of pleasure we have produced a conception of happiness which is not only radically different from the eudaimonist one, but strikingly trivialized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I agree that it is striking how much you have trivialized it, yes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've not reached the end of the chapter, but this is a good place to stop given how much time is left on the timer. I'll return to the chapter later, probably tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So far though I've been left pretty unhappy with the eudaimonist account of happiness. Both because of the quality of the arguments I've been savaging a bit up there, but more importantly the judgements seem entirely wrong to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular I'm &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; unhappy with the goal orientation here. I guess I should have expected no less from an ethical theory that is oriented around the striving for excellence, but the more I stare at those bits the more I feel like this part of virtue ethics is not only wrong but actively misguided.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An argument I've been having on discord over the last few days is whether virtue ethics is consequentialist. I think my current position is that regardless of whether it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; consequentialist, discussions of it seem intimately bound up in ends, and that still seems to be the case.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing I &lt;em&gt;didn't&lt;/em&gt; necessarily expect would be that that this is the bit of the theory I &lt;em&gt;dislike&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-08-21:50.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-09-20:42.html</id>
    <title>The problem of Susan</title>
    <updated>2021-10-09T21:49:59+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The problem of Susan&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Up front warning: I increasingly hate Julia Annas's account of happiness and every post that is about this subject will likely be very cranky. This is one such post.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From Intelligent Virtue, Page 141, we have the following example:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Susan thinks of her life as a happy one; she is married with children, and all is well except that her husband is frequently away on business. She discovers that in fact these absences were spent with a second family, and that he has divided his time between the two families for some years. Uncontroversially, Susan evaluated her life positively before the discovery, and no longer did so after the discovery. The question is: before the discovery, was her life happy or not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1447177704760037376"&gt;asked about this on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. At present most people say yes, a couple of people make the subjective/objective happiness distinction that Annas is talking about in context.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A couple of people point out that it's likely that she &lt;em&gt;wasn't&lt;/em&gt; happy, because probably someone living a life like that is not actually experiencing a very good life, and many low grade unhappinesses will probably be clarified and recontextualised in the light of the revelation. It's also possible she was engaged in self-deception to maintain a belief that she was happy. "Sure, there are a few problems, but can't complain you know?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is all true, but I'm happy to postulate that Susan could in principle have been genuinely happy with her life, even if it doesn't seem very likely. Likely that happiness came from other sources than her husband, but that's fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;None of this touches on my actual complaint with this example, which a few other people also shared, which is that it's obviously a category error, the question doesn't actually make sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it's clearly a &lt;em&gt;motivated&lt;/em&gt; category error, one that only makes sense through conflating two distinct things that the author is committed to conflating in order to support her broader thesis.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Was Susan's life happy or not? No, it's a life. Happy is not a things life can be, any more than physics can be happy. "Happy" is an emotional evaluation, and lives are not things with emotions. I understand that when people say "Did they have a happy life?" that is normal colloquial English that means something more like "Were they happy with their life?" but when you are trying to make a precise statement on the nature of happiness there is absolutely no excuse for this sort of ambiguity which blurs precisely the distinction you are trying to make.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's possible that I'm incorrectly translating the intent of this, but if so I think that makes it worse rather than better, because up to this point we have been talking about people seeking their own happiness, and if we mean something different from their own happiness by "having a happy life", why is this the question we're asking?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The questions I believe should be and are not being asked here are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was Susan happy with her life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did Susan have a good life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the only reason to blur the boundary between these very different questions is if you are committed to an unsupportable notion that happiness is the sole end of life, and to conflating the notion of "happy life" with "good life", in order to make them look like the same question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The following further unasked questions are also particularly loud:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would Susan have chosen this life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before knowing the truth, would Susan have chosen to learn it if she knew the consequences?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once Susan knows the truth, would she choose to go back if she could?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Asking these questions probably results in a fairly consistent clustering around "Susan was happy", "Susan would have chosen to know" (certainly this is my answer), which is a problem if you are committed to the position that people's driving goal is happiness&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If positive evaluation of your life is what happiness is, then Susan had a happy life until the discovery. But this runs into the problem that we are also inclined to say that after the discovery Susan discovered that her life never was a happy one; she was deceived into thinking that it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another presumptious we. I do not think it makes sense to say that she was deceived into believing her life was a happy one. She was deceived as to the nature of her life, and also she was happy.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-09-20:42.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-11-16:42.html</id>
    <title>We must imagine the steelman happy</title>
    <updated>2021-10-11T23:41:08+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;We must imagine the steelman happy&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm getting increasingly frustrated with the core of virtue ethics around eudaimonia,
so today I would like to put together a steelmanned version of something that is &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; what they are saying and I think is actually true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's entirely possible that what I am doing is recreating something they actually are saying,
and that I disagree with them less than I think I do, but if so they have very much failed to communicate this to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Do people pursue happiness?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So here is, in summary, what I think virtue ethicists are claiming:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People (unconsciously or consciously) organise their lives around a single goal, and that goal is happiness (or eudaimonia, but as far as I can tell eudaimonia just means "happiness but we don't like the connotations of that word").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is possible that this is a strawman and if so I would appreciate correction. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is wrong, and the true version of it is a composite of three things that almost but not quite add up to this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People wish to be happy to a degree they endorse as appropriate for their situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They wish their situations to be ones that would make them happy under this endorsed happiness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They take on ends that they believe will help them achieve this wish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Adding this up together you could summarise this as "People seek their happiness as an end", but I think that summary would be wrong in a way that the tripartite version is not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I don't think this tripartite version is &lt;em&gt;perfectly&lt;/em&gt; right either - I'll point out some problems in a bit).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's consider the following test case: Someone you love has just died. You are, understandably, quite unhappy about this. Someone offers you a pill that will erase all the grief and will cause you to feel euphoric. Do you take it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some people will say yes to this of course. Even more people would (and do) say yes to something that merely blunts the grief. I think, particularly near to the event, many people would say no. Certainly I would.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My point with this thought experiment is not that there is a correct answer. My point is that the correct answer is not &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt; that yes you should take the pill, and I don't think most people would consider it strange that it's not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Further, this idea of appropriate happiness seems in general true. For example, I think most people who are not particularly sadistic would not want to be sadistic, even if it might strictly increase their happiness, because sadism does not seem like the sort of thing you should be happy about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think this is a controversial perspective in virtue ethics, but I think by binding together the ideas of "appropriately happy" and "happy" they have committed themselves to some weird takes where they have to say "Ah, but that's not &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; happiness".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Take &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-09-20:42.html"&gt;The problem of Susan&lt;/a&gt; from the other day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Susan thinks of her life as a happy one; she is married with children, and all is well except that her husband is frequently away on business. She discovers that in fact these absences were spent with a second family, and that he has divided his time between the two families for some years. Uncontroversially, Susan evaluated her life positively before the discovery, and no longer did so after the discovery. The question is: before the discovery, was her life happy or not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This example is not remotely problematic under this separation: Susan was happy, but a version of Susan in posession of all the facts would not endorse that happiness as appropriate (even though Susan at the time might have).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think one of the reasons virtue ethicists ignore this split is to some degree it goes away for virtuous agents, because one of the key features of the way virtue ethics treats virtue is that through the development of phronesis and the cultivation of the virtues one pursues (1) automatically: A perfectly virtuous agent feels happy precisely to the degree they would endorse as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But note that the problem of Susan doesn't go away even if Susan is perfectly virtuous: The problem is not that prior to the revelation Susan was living unvirtuously, it's that she was deceived. A sufficiently intelligent adversary (e.g. a Cartesian demon) can deceive even a perfectly virtuous agent, and besides which a perfectly virtuous agent can simply be wrong by virtue of not being omniscient. I can be happy about the prospect of things that I expect to happen over the coming years, not knowing that actually the world is going to be destroyed by an unknown asteroid next year, and this is not a failure of appropriateness I just don't know everything.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Do you even want to be happy?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another important way this split comes up is in therapy. People are unhappy, so they go to therapy to try to figure out how to be happy. And sometimes it's genuinely "just" an emotional issue, but more often than not it's actually perfectly reasonable for them to be unhappy and if they're really lucky they won't get a therapist who teaches them how to gaslight themselves into thinking otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm a fan of this piece in good housekeeping: &lt;a href="https://www.goodhousekeeping.com/life/a45386/gratitude-lists-dont-work/"&gt;Gratitude lists are BS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First she describes her attempts to be happier:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After about 100 days of making gratitude lists, tens of thousands of dollars of psychotherapy, five different antidepressants, four months in an outpatient psychiatric hospital (where they strongly recommended we make gratitude lists) and myriad of high-priced alternative treatments, I had pretty much given up all hope of ever feeling better. Then my psychiatrist suggested I speak with a therapist in his office who worked with people with a history of trauma. Great, I thought, another opportunity to shell out more money to someone who can't help me. I shushed myself, told myself to be grateful for his offer — and to add it tomorrow's gratitude list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This didn't work for her, because...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My new therapist told me to write down everything I did and thought and said to myself throughout the day and send him the record each night so he could try to get some insight into what was really going on. I did, being sure to highlight the positives in my day to show him that I did recognize that there were some good things in my life. When I got to my next session, he told me the words I'd been so desperately longing to hear for years:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Man, your life just SUCKS right now."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"It's not that bad," I said nervously, assuming he was either grossly incompetent or trying to trick me. "I have a lot to be grateful for."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Really?" he replied, then proceeded to list off what he'd observed in my daily records: that I'd worked the overnight shift at jobs for years, which meant I barely slept; that the apartment I lived in was only so cheap because it was dark, cramped, ant-infested and falling apart; that my husband and I were raising a baby in one of the most expensive cities in the country, where decaying two-bedroom bungalows with no yards or parking spaces started at $800,000; that I had no family support system, since my closest relative lived 3,000 miles away; that years of working from home left me completely isolated with very few friends; that I was under extreme financial stress due to massive student loan debt; that I was a writer who had no time or energy to write because I was so busy trying to put out the fires in the rest of my life; that the few things I did have time to write got rejected over and over again; that I'd auditioned for over 150 commercials and had never booked one; that I'd blown my meager life savings on years of out-of-network psychotherapy treatment that hadn't worked; that I woke up in excruciating back pain every day; that I'd grown up in an emotionally abusive household where my mother encouraged me to watch "Pollyanna" on a regular basis while my father, who had combat PTSD and a traumatic brain injury, exploded in rages without warning; that I had to literally carry my baby over the passed out bodies of the homeless drug addicts who slept in front of our house; that my transmission had gone up in smoke four months after I'd paid my car; that all three of my cats had died over the past three years, and that my dog now had cancer — the most severe and fast moving case my vet said she'd seen in her 20 years of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all kind of sucked pretty effing hard, my new therapist said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it is reasonable to say that the problem here is not that she's unhappy, but that she is unhappy because of all of the problems, and that the natural and reasonable way to "pursue happiness" here is not to try to become happier but to try to solve the problems that are making her unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is an argument to be made for acceptance, and I think there is a &lt;em&gt;strong&lt;/em&gt; argument to make that one should ideally be able to cope with those problems without becoming overwhelmingly depressed, but I think either approach starts with acknowledging that yeah actually these things suck, and you cannot "pursue happiness" as a goal independently from how you navigate the practical things that are impacting your happiness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suggest that the very idea that people want to be happy is a confusion of how situations like this work, and it's a harmful one. People don't want to be happy, happiness is the feeling of things going as you want.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Acting while depressed&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another way the notion of "endorsed happiness" is useful is that one can treat it as action guiding even while not currently feeling particularly equipped to feel happy. i.e. depressed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often when I'm depressed I do things not because I feel any emotional motivation to do them, but because I know that a less depressed version of me would. There is a sort of wanting to achieve things that is possible somewhat independently of the emotional motivation for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This tends to be hard during long depressive periods, or without much extrinsic motivation to do things, but I do find that it's possible to just weather through a short depressive period because you intellectually still know what you want even if you don't feel happy about getting it, and can just act on that. It's harder to give it your all, and you generally feel tired and low energy, but it's not like the conceptual understanding of what you want to achieve is inaccessible, it "just" doesn't &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; rewarding when you do those things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This certainly isn't all that depression is, but I do think one of the key features of depression is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-06-07:46.html"&gt;a restriction on emotional range&lt;/a&gt;, and a key part of that is that you can often still fully understand and act on your motivational structure without feeling it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Speaking of...&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the emotional difficulties and motivational structure, writer's block just kicked in. Apparently I'm still struggling with writing complete essays even when it's on the notebook blog, so I'm going to finish here and maybe continue another day.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-11-16:42.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-14-12:00.html</id>
    <title>Learning how to tell a joke</title>
    <updated>2021-10-14T16:23:07+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Learning how to tell a joke&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 10 of Ted Cohen's "Jokes":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joking is a "two-stage" art, like music and theater. Someone must make up the joke, and someone must tell it, and these two jokers need not be the same. Those good at making up jokes are not the same as those good at telling them. Telling a joke well may require specific abilities, like being able to affect an Irish dialect, or it may require a subtle knack, like a sense of timing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He goes on to say that this presentation is particularly important because some jokes don't translate well onto the page, and illustrates this with the following joke that you are legally required to include in all books about philosophy of comedy or they take your license away:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Q: According to Freud, what comes between fear and sex?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: Fünf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Cohen is wrong here, this joke translates to the page just fine, because you can just read it out loud.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This routine on the other hand is an example of a joke that &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; doesn't translate to the page:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XkCBhKs4faI" title="YouTube video player" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This both illustrates the strengths and the flaws of the two-stage art concept.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From a writing point of view, the joke isn't very good, right? It's perfectly well written, there's nothing wrong with it, but as written it's not funny, because the humour is entirely in the presentation.
This is why it demonstrates the strength of the two stage model: it's a very good illustration of the verbal skills of humour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it also demonstrates that the idea is something of a lie, in that you can't actually separate this into two stages. It's not just that the joke doesn't work written down, it's that there is no joke without the performance of it here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, perhaps, an artefact of the fact that comedy isn't really about telling jokes, it's about performing routines, but I think this distinction doesn't work, and you experience the same problems with hypercontextual jokes that cannot be extracted from their situation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What instead is going on, I think, is that for any given joke there is a &lt;em&gt;skill of telling that joke&lt;/em&gt;, and some jokes you can teach that skill in writing better than others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another interesting example of this sort of skill is poetry reading. Some poems work written, but this one I've linked to before in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-06-13:53.html"&gt;Start from amazing&lt;/a&gt; isn't one of them:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tFTASR8BMps" title="YouTube video player" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The poem is good, but the presentation of it is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good, and the poem rests on the vocal skill of its delivery.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-28-04:40.html"&gt;You can't write life down&lt;/a&gt; I talked about the difficulty in transcribing oral stories, and this feels like another aspect of that. At the time I talked about how taking a Raven story outside of its cultural context would lose essential features of the culture that created it, leaving it in a diminished and abstracted form, but actually I think the problem is deeper than that: You can write down a Raven story, but I'm not sure you can write down how to &lt;em&gt;tell&lt;/em&gt; a Raven story.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-14-12:00.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-19-10:53.html</id>
    <title>A simple model of depression and "depressive realism"</title>
    <updated>2021-10-19T10:53:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;A simple model of depression and "depressive realism"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was talking to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/fvathynevgl/"&gt;Vathy&lt;/a&gt; about depressive realism,
and when I expressed skepticism about its existence they asked me to say more. I did,
and it seemed an unusual enough perspective that I thought I'd quickly write it up in a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So here's what I think, roughly. This is a simplified version of what I actually think (because what I actually think is a giant tangle of stuff I haven't fully figured out), and what I actually think is probably no more than roughly right, but I still think this is a good model that is helpful to bear in mind.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Basically it's this: Humans have all sorts of biases in their thinking. No matter what anyone tells you, this isn't bad. Biases are good, as long as you're expecting to make mistakes (and, I hate to break it to you, humans make a lot of mistakes and are going to keep doing that), because &lt;em&gt;not all mistakes are created equal&lt;/em&gt;. If you're going to make mistakes, you want to bias in the direction of mistakes that are safe to make.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(See e.g. &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/02/theres-no-single-error-rate/"&gt;There's no single error rate&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the ways that depression differs from healthy cognition is that it has a much stronger bias in the direction of inaction than healthy cognition does. If you see a problem, you can decide to do something about it or not. A non-depressed person is much more likely than a depressed person to choose inaction,
and as a result is more likely to believe things that justify that inaction (this latter feature isn't specific to depression - a non-depressed person who chooses action is more likely to believe things that justify that action. Motivated reasoning is a whole big thing).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, a depressed person is more likely to get the right answer in situations where the right answer is inaction, and less likely to get the right answer in situations where the right answer is action.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In situations where the right answer is typically inaction (which can happen if you're in a dangerous environment which you have little control over, certainly, and as a matter of numbers this is probably more likely for depressed people) this will tend to mean that depressed people are more likely to be right than people who are neutral or biased towards action, but it's not that the depressed person is more realistic than the non-depressed person, it's that their biases are currently well adapted to their situation, and if the situation changes they would retain those biases and be less well adapted. I'm no more inclined to call this realism than I am to call a stopped clock accurate because it happens to be stopped at the current time.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-19-10:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
