<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-03-11T09:35:51+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:12.html</id>
    <title>If a task is impossible, try making it harder</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T12:18:55+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;If a task is impossible, try making it harder&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If a lecture is a struggle, try speeding up the video.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you struggle to read fast enough, try using a speed reader app that just scrolls the words by at 1000wpm.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If a book is too hard, try making it harder by reading it aloud. Maybe do weird balancing acts while doing it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often the rate limiting factor on difficult tasks is not actually that they're too hard, it's that we are failing to engage our full attention on them. This is particularly true if you're very smart and/or ADHD or somewhere vaguely in its vicinity. The world is literally moving too slowly for you, which means that you cannot bring your full attention to it, and as a result you never enter flow and the entire thing becomes a painful exercise which you can't help but fail.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This creates the paradoxical solution that impossible seeming tasks are not too hard for you, they're too easy for you.
If you make them harder, you might find that they become possible, because they become something that can absorb your full attention. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel like this is actually the true secret to success to a lot of productivity methodologies. They don't actually help, but by focusing on the methodology they become something that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html"&gt;you can nerd out about&lt;/a&gt; and because your nerding task is integrated with your grounding task, the two together can consume your full attention in a way that the mere task on its own could not. &lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:12.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:35.html</id>
    <title>Untangling moral concepts</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T13:33:55+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Untangling moral concepts&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The following are not the same thing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have an &lt;em&gt;obligation&lt;/em&gt; to do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;morally permissible&lt;/em&gt; to do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;morally virtuous&lt;/em&gt; to do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;morally required&lt;/em&gt; to do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Figuring this out is a process I call &lt;em&gt;untangling&lt;/em&gt;, which is essentially just a skill that you learn doing mathematics:
Finding a bunch of examples where the concepts separate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When untangling it's important that your examples pass the "c'mon, really?" test. They shouldn't be contrived or annoying, but should be points of separation that actually matter in daily life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Obey the laws of physics". This is definitely 1 and 4, and definitely not 3, 5, or 6. There's no real moral component to physics, so there's no real moral significance to it. It's certainly permissible, because if you literally have no option but to do the thing it would be bizarre to consider it forbidden.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Obey the speed limit" is an example where 2 through 6 apply to varying degrees, but 1 does not. People clearly &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; break the speed limit and do so all the time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More, it's &lt;em&gt;common&lt;/em&gt; to have examples like this where people behave low grade unmorally for convenience.
Moral norms are more like guidelines than rules, and almost everyone implicitly understands this and treats them as such.
So, when considering moral norms, don't consider them as ironclad rules, consider them as things you're going to &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; follow. Depending on how serious they are, you'll probably want to follow them more often than not (the moral norms against killing people are stronger than the moral norms against spitting. You would probably still kill someone in some circumstances, even ones you didn't consider morally justified, but they'd have to be pretty extreme).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Brush your teeth" is something you should do which mostly lacks an moral component, so is (2) without any of the others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you have made a promise to do something minor. Say, meet a friend for coffee. Suppose also that a major family crisis has occurred and they need you. "Meeting your friend for coffee" is an example of 3 on its own. You have an obligation (3) but you shouldn't do it, it's not permissible, it's not required, and it's not virtuous.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose someone is being a dick to you. You get angry at them. This is morally permitted, but it's not required or virtuous. Whether you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; do it is situation dependent (it might be tactically wise to do so), but lets say it's not a good idea. So this is an example of (4) without any of the others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So none of (1) through (4) imply anything else on the list. Now we get into the tricky bits where I'm not entirely sure how cleanly they separate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Staying calm in a heated situation where someone is being a dick to you is an example of (5) that is not (6) - it is morally virtuous without being required. Giving all your money to charity is another example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Are there things which are morally virtuous but not morally permissible? I'm not sure. I can come up with some contrived examples where the answer is "Maybe?" (trolley problem type stuff). I think in practice this is probably not an interesting category and all the details will be too contextual.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Are there examples which are morally required but not morally virtuous? Another maybe. I'd say "not committing murder" is definitely ethically required, but it's not particularly praiseworthy. Unclear that it's virtuous, but it's certainly more virtuous than committing murder.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My inclination is that for practical purposes we have (6) implies (5) implies (4), and the examples above show that these are the only implications possible.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:35.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-14:06.html</id>
    <title>Computer games as therapeutic tools</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T14:21:47+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Computer games as therapeutic tools&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think computer games are underrated therapeutic tools. Many people seem to know this, but it seems surprising to others, so I'd like to tell you about three that I find useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celeste&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slay the Spire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Untitled Goose Game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They each have slightly different functions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Celeste is very good for inducing flow state. If I'm in a bad mood, or otherwise need to recover from something, Celeste allows me to drop into flow state almost instantly, because it's impossible to play Celeste and think at the same time, and it is a rich source of challenges that are right at the edge of my skill level.
This is why it works - it is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:12.html"&gt;hard enough to require full concentration&lt;/a&gt; but not too hard to be unachievable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another game in a similar genre to this is Hollow Knight. Hollow Knight does not work like Celeste for this. It's a decent enough game, but it's a bit too erratic in its pacing and the sort of decision making it requires to be a flow state on tap like Celeste is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Slay the Spire's function is very simple: When I need a break from my brain I can play it for however long I want. It's the opposite of Celeste, in that it doesn't require flow, it just requires very basic reactivity and can be played while half zoned out. If Celeste lets me dial up my level of presentness in the moment, slay the spire lets me dial it way down.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Playing Slay the Spire well requires more concentration and thought than that, but I never claimed I played it well)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Untitled Goose Game has an entirely different purpose. It's a diagnostic tool.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="https://shkspr.mobi/blog/2020/01/the-value-of-videogames-or-why-i-think-untitled-goose-game-was-a-rip-off/"&gt;edent has pointed out&lt;/a&gt;, when considered on its merits as a game, Untitled Goose Game doesn't really have any. It's a very weak puzzle based game with not much play time and not a great deal of challenge to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, you're a goose wreaking mayhem, and you can steal a man's slippers and drop them in the pond, then run around with his pipe in your beak, so there's that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Untitled Goose Game is great if and only if you are currently able to experience the emotion of &lt;em&gt;malicious glee&lt;/em&gt;. You are causing problems on purpose, and that's hilarious. As such I find it a very useful diagnostic tool for telling how depressed I am. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-06-07:46.html"&gt;Depression is in large part a restriction on emotional range&lt;/a&gt;, and having a tool that will reliably provoke a particular emotional response if I'm currently capable of experiencing it is very helpful for calibrating my current level. "Gleelessness" may lack the cachet of "Hopelessness", but it still seems to be a pretty reliable predictor of my depression levels. HONK.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These aren't the only games I play, but they're the main ones. And having a small library of them that I've played a lot of is helpful because they serve as a sort of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-11:33.html"&gt;COULDDO list&lt;/a&gt; where if I'm not sure what to do, I can pick one of these up, and play them more or less on autopilot, and the effect works reliably. I expect I'll add to the list over time, but for now these seem to be a good set of tools for my personal therapeutic toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-14:06.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-14:34.html</id>
    <title>Touch starvation and group responsibility</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T15:21:06+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Touch starvation and group responsibility&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to use this post to talk about the intersection of two things dear to my heart:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touch starvation, especially in men.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Group responsibility as distinct from the sum of individual responsibilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Touch starvation is also common in other groups. I've heard and read a lot about it in disabled women too for example. I'm talking about men primarily because that's the aspect I'm most qualified to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Touch starvation is a big deal. Regular physical contact, ideally with other human beings, seems to be fairly essential to our emotional regulation. This isn't a sex thing, people just really need to be touched.
I could probably cite studies etc for that but this is a notebook post, so I won't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Touch starvation is a very personal subject for me because I've spent a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time touch starved, mostly because I've spent a lot of time single (which I'm fine with) and society is weirdly precious about men and platonic touch (which I'm very much not).
I'm also a very huggy person (a fact which I think the overwhelming majority of my friends would be suprised to hear, for reasons), so this feels extra acute to me, but it's probably pretty bad for everyone in a similar situation.
Right now I'm in a great relationship so I'm getting plenty of touch in the official socially approved way for men, but that doesn't make me less grumpy about the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These norms are of course a thing done by men as well as to men. There are no conspiracy theories here about how this is somehow women's fault. Gender norms are a product of collective behaviour, and women are absolutely part of the shaping of norms around masculinity in approximately the same way that men are responsible for shaping the norms around femininity (if you find this a controversial point, I invite you to not argue with me about it), but it's at the very least a problem &lt;em&gt;primarily&lt;/em&gt; driven by men.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But setting aside who exactly is included in "we", I think it is clear that we are collectively failing men in this way.
Touch starvation in men is epidemic, and it's a major problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Set against this is the fact that no one individual is obligated to participate in fixing it.
I feel when we, society, are failing half of our members to such a large degree, we are &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:35.html"&gt;morally required&lt;/a&gt; to do something about that,
but that does not imply that any individual person is morally required to individually participate in the solution.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's certainly morally virtuous to go hug the men in your life if you want to do that. They'll probably be very grateful, unless &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/jiminy-cricket-must-die/"&gt;they've internalised the norm too heavily&lt;/a&gt; to accept, but it's in no sense morally required.
The moral obligation is at the collective level, and trying to address that at an individual level is so far into "I don't even know where to start" territory that I'm not even sure "morally virtuous" is enough to cover it.
The strongest moral requirement I would put forth here is that if you personally are actively enforcing these norms (which is distinct from being silently complicit in them), it is morally imperative that you should get in the sea.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Uh, sorry, I did say I was quite angry about this)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is another untangling: When men are upset about this issue, a number of bad things happen.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They conflate touch starvation with a need for romantic and/or sexual love, again because they've internalised the norms around touch too heavily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They confuse collective and individual obligations to them ("society is failing me, you are part of society, therefore you are failing me" is a very tempting trap to fall into)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Even if they successfully understand the problem&lt;/em&gt; people pattern match them into one of the first two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly (3) is my biggest concern in writing this piece. I'm kinda expecting to get told I'm a horrible patriarch who thinks he's entitled to women's bodies just for pointing out this problem (please note: Men are allowed to hug men. It doesn't have to be women providing the hugs. Although as someone who is mostly friends with women I would ideally prefer a gender neutral solution).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It would be nice to wrap this post up with a nice pithy call to action, but I don't really have one. Lets just pretend I asked you to normalize hugging men or something equally inspiring but unactionable like that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-14:34.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:27.html</id>
    <title>Be the more decisive person</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T15:51:21+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Be the more decisive person&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you an amazing favour you can do for your friends: Be the one to make decisions when nobody else is willing to step up. Especially unimportant ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I learned this skill the hard way. Getting a bunch of indecisive socially awkward nerds to decide where to go for a meal is worse than herding cats, because it's watching cats try to self organise,
so at some point I just started saying "Hey, why don't we go to $RESTAURANT. Any objections?" and observing how much easier the whole process became once I started doing that. Nobody minds you doing this, everyone is grateful, and a long annoying pointless dither is averted.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People don't want to be the one to make a decision for any number of reasons, but it's mostly anxiety, and they're mostly offloading anxiety onto everyone else. You can stop the cycle of anxiety through the simple realisation that 90% of the decisions that are causing this just don't matter that much. It doesn't matter that much where you go for a meal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you want to help people this way, go read &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;how to make decisions&lt;/a&gt; so that this is low cost for you, and then start making suggestions like this once it's clear you're stuck in an indecision loop that nobody involved wants to break out of.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Remember that the decision you're making is a &lt;em&gt;first pass&lt;/em&gt;. People can object to it, and that's fine. The system is working. This is a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;fastest way to learn something is to do something&lt;/a&gt; situation. By making a suggestion (doing something) you are learning about people's constraints, which you can then feed back in by making another suggestion, or by asking that person to make some more concrete suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For more important decisions you need to start looking into serious facilitation skills and techniques for running meetings and such, but that's a different problem. For now, just help people break out of indecision on the simple stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:27.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:59.html</id>
    <title>Install cut out switches in your mind</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T17:48:37+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Install cut out switches in your mind&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you my favourite joke. It comes from Scott Aaronson's "Quantum Computing Since Democritus":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a joke about a planet full of people who believe in antiinduction: if the sun has risen every day in the past, then today, we should expect that it won’t.
As a result, these people are all starving and living in poverty.
Someone visits the planet and tells them, “Hey, why are you still using this anti-induction philosophy? You’re living in horrible poverty!”
“Well, it never worked before...”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A different Scott recently wrote about &lt;a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2020/02/12/confirmation-bias-as-misfire-of-normal-bayesian-reasoning/"&gt;Confirmation bias&lt;/a&gt;. His view is very Bayesian, which I'm not that into, but the basic premise is sound: If you come across a piece of evidence that contradicts your worldview, it's probably right to discount it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a recent discussion of &lt;a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5250/fronjwomestud.33.1.0024?seq=1"&gt;one of my favourite papers&lt;/a&gt; a friend pointed out that the arguments depended in quite a critical way on certain values (obvious sensible ones like "racism bad" which he agreed with, but even so) and that this presented difficulties with how to use it properly for breaking out of your frame of reference.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The common thread here is that in all of these cases there is an underlying concern: "But what if my fundamental worldview was wrong in some critical way? How would I break out of that?" - the arguments that were being presented were fine, but they intrinsically rested on unjustified, and possibly unjustifiable, assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recently reread "Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance", which is a deeply flawed book that is much more interesting in its flaws than in the things people normally get out of it. One of the things I found fascinating was observing the author's thought process (the author is schizophrenic, and this was very obvious to me when reading it). This provoked the following thought process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes, this is a very familiar line of reasoning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now comes the bit where you stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...why aren't you stopping?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He was getting involved in thought loops that were obviously deeply unproductive, and he wasn't stopping. This was quite distressing to me to watch because of how carefully I have cultivated a series of cutoff switches in my thought processes to avoid this from happening.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The most basic one is this: If you are concerned with your worldview being fundamentally wrong in some way... Eh, don't worry about it. It's probably fine. Put that to one side and come back to it later if you really feel like it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; you do grounds out in basic premises about how the world works and what the appropriate values are, and those things are arbitrary and contingent and not even necessarily that consistent. If you allow yourself to reevaluate your worldview as part of every basic thought process, what will happen is that you will be constantly spiralling into unproductive areas of thought.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You should, of course, occasionally consider that your fundamental worldview might be wrong, but mostly the way to do that is by talking to people who are different from you and learning from them and how they see the world. Getting trapped in thought spirals will not do this, and you need to install cut off switches to block off those spirals when you run into them.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:59.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-08-08:53.html</id>
    <title>You can't actually explain everything to laypeople</title>
    <updated>2020-03-08T09:27:49+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You can't actually explain everything to laypeople&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's an annoying meme that, as with many annoying memes oft-cited by nerds, seems to date back to Feynmann.
It's that your ability to explain a subject to a layperson is a test of whether you understand it.
I often hear it as "If you can't explain it to your grandmother you don't understand it". The version I heard earlier was "explain to a five year old".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Feynmann, to his partial credit, doesn't seem to have deliberately coined an aphorism here and also said "freshman" (i.e. first year university student). &lt;a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Talk:Richard_Feynman#Teaching_quote"&gt;Discussion at wikiquote&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feynman was a truly great teacher. He prided himself on being able to devise ways to explain even the most profound ideas to beginning students. Once, I said to him, "Dick, explain to me, so that I can understand it, why spin one-half particles obey Fermi-Dirac statistics." Sizing up his audience perfectly, Feynman said, "I'll prepare a freshman lecture on it." But he came back a few days later to say, "I couldn't do it. I couldn't reduce it to the freshman level. That means we don't really understand it."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Freshman students are already not laypeople, but even so I don't think this is a reasonable standard for understanding.
It &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be a reasonable standard for the specific context, I don't know enough about quantum mechanics to say, but it's certainly not universal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But first, lets consider how freshmen already differ from laypeople:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They've got a lot of prerequisites that a layperson doesn't. A freshman in a physics lecture already knows a lot more about physics than a five year old, or indeed most educated people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They're prepared to learn and engage with the material.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(2) is one of the most important parts, because the main reason that you can't explain most things you do to laypeople is that they don't care. When someone who isn't a software developer / computer scientists / etc asks me about my PhD I can just about explain the problem before they switch off (which honestly is doing better than most PhDs in computer science, but I have a relatively accessible problem domain), I'm certainly not going to get them to sit through an explanation about the solution.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(1) is also a major feature: Some areas of knowledge just have prerequisites. It's a simple fact. And often there are a lot more prerequisites than you think. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-18-12:24.html"&gt;How to talk about books you haven't read&lt;/a&gt; has a great section on reading Hamlet to the Tiv tribe in Western Africa, and how much cultural bridging that required. Hamlet is pretty much designed to be accessible to laypeople (Shakespeare was a popular entertainer!) but because these are laypeople from a different cultural context, it failed to land without a lot of explanation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My degree is in mathematics. There were a number of courses in the final year I struggled with, though I generally got there in the end. If you had thrown me in the deep end on those courses in my first year, I would have had no chance, because they built on material that I had learned earlier.
Knowledge has prerequisites, and you have to teach those first.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Could I have somehow taught those courses to my younger self anyway? Certainly. I'd have done it by putting him through a four year maths degree.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, in the end, the biggest problem with the idea that you can teach anything to laypeople:
Sometimes the only way to do that is to first make them not a layperson.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-08-08:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-09-11:13.html</id>
    <title>The art of not having opinions</title>
    <updated>2020-03-09T12:52:35+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The art of not having opinions&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the same conversation with Dave that lead to us &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-28-06:33.html"&gt;talking about which way people veer to avoid collisions&lt;/a&gt; we ended up playing a sort of game.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For context: Dave works in transport. Transport is something we all encounter on a very regular basis, so we all tend to think about it a lot. However, transport is a complex system, so it's &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-04-11:18.html"&gt;more broken&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-11:43.html"&gt;less comprehensible&lt;/a&gt; than you might intuitively expect it to be. As a result, most people's opinions on transport are &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, the game: I had to keep coming up with transport opinions I held, and Dave would judge if they were bad opinions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually we ran out of time or got distracted or something (I forget) and I made it to that point without having any bad opinions. I was quite pleased by this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another place I was pleased with myself recently was my performance on the &lt;a href="https://programs.clearerthinking.org/common_misconceptions.html"&gt;common misconceptions&lt;/a&gt; test. The number of things I got right was only so so (I forget exactly, but I think about 85% right?), but I was almost perfectly calibrated: The ones where my confidence was high were right, the ones where my confidence was low were right in about the proportion they should be.
This was a bit surprising to me, as in the past I have definitely not been that well calibrated on similar things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think these both happened for fairly general reasons: Over the last decade, I've gotten much better at not having opinions on things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This might be surprising to you, as I have a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of opinions, but it makes sense: I've not gotten better at having fewer opinions, I've gotten better at not having opinions on any given thing unless it makes sense for me to do so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of social pressure against doing this.
We basically use having opinions at eachother as a social bonding activity to make sure that the person we're talking to has the "right" sort of politics, so there's a lot of social pressure against this, but I think it's worth doing if we want our opinions to be truth tracking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two useful prompts for recalibrating opinions:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; for me to have an opinion on this? If not, why do I have one?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If this opinion were wrong, would I be able to tell?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If the answer to either of these is no, why are you having an opinion on it? At the very least, you should be less confident in asserting it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-09-11:13.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-10-12:38.html</id>
    <title>Homophily and the tyranny of false positives</title>
    <updated>2020-03-10T13:37:44+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Homophily and the tyranny of false positives&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A while ago a friend of mine told me about what he called his Terribly Goth Theory of Friendship:
You can't trust people who don't have problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason is of course that &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; have problems, and that it's hard to trust people without them to know how to handle that well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it goes deeper than that: Actually many people with fewer or different problems than ours are in fact perfectly lovely human beings who we would get on fine with, but we can't tell that.
So we select for people who are like us because we can predict how they will react.
This is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homophily"&gt;homophily&lt;/a&gt;, the tendency to hang out with people like us. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, the question of who to be friends with is a classic example of the sort of thing I talked about in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/02/theres-no-single-error-rate/"&gt;there's no single error rate&lt;/a&gt;, where the only error rate that is visible to you is the false positive rate. As I argued in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-22-11:37.html"&gt;you should try bad things&lt;/a&gt; this will tend to cause you to narrow your selection over time:
If you only ever update to remove false positives, you will tend to increase the degree of homophily you exhibit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't necessarily a bad thing at the individual level, but bear in mind the way that bad rejections (false negatives) can contain &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/06/the-ethics-of-false-negatives-in-interviewing/"&gt;systemic biases&lt;/a&gt;.
My suspicion is that a lot of communities will tend to become more homogenous over time purely as a result of this effect: People who don't match the community expectations will tend to get filtered out, not necessarily because they're a bad fit, but because they don't act like the kind of people the community understands how to tell if they're a fit or not.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-10-12:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-11-07:15.html</id>
    <title>Suspension of annoyance</title>
    <updated>2020-03-11T09:35:51+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Suspension of annoyance&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been banging on a bit about "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/38I7D5z"&gt;The Courage to be Disliked&lt;/a&gt;" since &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/m_ashcroft/"&gt;Michael Ashcroft&lt;/a&gt; recommended it.
My friend &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rixxtr"&gt;Tobi&lt;/a&gt; read it as a result, and the following is his review from &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/jm97tDN"&gt;bookchat discord&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished The Courage to be Disliked. It's a thoroughly annoying book, obnoxiously written, and I strongly disagree with a whole lot of what it says. At the same time it has been extremely useful to me, in an immediate and actionable way, and I'm very glad I've read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Useful, yet punchable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only found this thread on Twitter afterwards, and it contains pretty much all of the book without the obnoxiousness: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1037715339314847747"&gt;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1037715339314847747&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I cannot disagree with this review. The book is objectively very annoying. However I was not particularly annoyed while reading it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this I've had practice. The particular foibles of this book were new to me, but I've read a lot of self-help and niche (especially trauma centric) therapy books recently, which has allowed me to get used to a particular style: That of a slightly self-obsessed author telling you their life story and the transformation they've been through, wrapped around what would probably be a fairly decent essay about a useful technique threaded through the entire thing in a way that makes it slightly hard to skip reading about the journey.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I said I wasn't annoyed while &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt; the books, not that I wasn't annoyed about the books)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When reading those books, I could look for things to argue with. It wouldn't be hard. The books are full of poorly supported pseudoscience, weak arguments, and irrelevant digressions. But I knew they would be going in, so why worry about it? I'm there to see if I can extract anything interesting from the book. I don't really care about whether the author is right or wrong, and I expect they're mostly wrong, but I can still try to derive some useful insights from their work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To go a bit Adlerian about this, what purpose is the annoyance with the book serving you?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it's mostly protective: Someone is saying wrong things, and you want to treat it as someone arguing with you, because if you were to take on the wrong things you would go on to believe wrong things, and that's bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But you could just do neither of those things. Don't read the book on the assumption that you'll believe anything the author has to say, but also don't be annoyed when you don't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead, take on the information that this is what the author believes. Acknowledge the possibility that some of it &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;might be worth trying&lt;/a&gt;, but don't read it with any greater expectation of truth than that.
Once you've done that, the protective mechanism of annoyance is not especially useful,
and you might as well just choose not to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-11-07:15.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
