<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-06-03T09:56:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-25-09:18.html</id>
    <title>Identity and Legitimisation of Knowledge</title>
    <updated>2020-05-25T09:55:20+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Identity and Legitimisation of Knowledge&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;PSA: Posts this week are going to be especially short because I need to focus on actual writing for my PhD this week. I'll just be copying out interesting passages from random pages of random books from my "canon" and making very short commentaries on them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3d3aby7"&gt;Epistemic Injustice: Power and the Ethics of Knowing&lt;/a&gt; by Miranda Fricker, page 9:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see that [a silencing of a woman by a man] involves an exercise of power, of of gender power in particular. But what do we mean by power? And how does gender power relate to the general notion of social power? In order to paint a portrait of testimonial injustice and to home in on its distinctive central case, we need to answer these questions about the nature of social power in general and the particular kind of social power (of which gender power is one instance) that I shall call &lt;em&gt;identity&lt;/em&gt; power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The "testimonial injustice" that Fricker is talking about here is a notion she introduces in this book, and is an injustice done to people in rejecting their testimony based on their identity - e.g. in the case she is talking about, rejecting someone's testimony because she is a woman.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've just finished reading Lyotard's "The Postmodern Condition", an experience which I cannot really recommend, and in it he talks about the role of &lt;em&gt;legitimisation&lt;/em&gt; in knowledge - i.e. if we think of a community of practice as telling each other stories about the world, what are the social practices involved in accepting some of those stories into our canon as legitimate knowledge. He argues that sciences in particular can be thought of as having a set of particularly stringent set of criteria for legitimisation, and tend to reject other modes of legitimisation as hopelessly fuzzy and informal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Read in this light, I think one interesting lens on Fricker's work would be this:
One of the roles of social power is control over the legitimisation process for knowledge. When social power is rooted in identities, this has the particularly pernicious effect of resulting in a community's canon of recognised legitimate knowledge that systemically underrepresents knowledge originating in marginalized groups.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, as has been pointed out before by &lt;a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5250/fronjwomestud.33.1.0024?seq=1"&gt;Kirsty Dotson&lt;/a&gt;, Fricker has badly misunderstood one aspect of the nature of knowledge in a way that this highlights: There is no single canon, but instead many loosely overlapping ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This misunderstanding is also present in her notion of identity power. In fact, identity power does not exist, because social power does not exist in individuals. Social power is a relationship between an individual and a community. The same identity that denies you credibility in one community may gain you credibility in another.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that the problems of testimonial injustice she is pointing out don't exist - they absolutely do - but that they need to be more carefully contextualised. "You're only oppressed by the dominant community who controls most of the economy" is not actually any more reassuring than thinking you're oppressed in some absolute sense, but the fine grained distinction is still useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly significant in another book I've read recently, which is James Scott's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2yzIMF8"&gt;Domination and the Arts of Resistance&lt;/a&gt;, where he introduces the idea of the &lt;em&gt;hidden transcript&lt;/em&gt; - essentially the canon of knowledge that is present within a marginalised group and is actively concealed (possibly by hiding it in plain sight) from the more dominant group.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Putting these together, one way of looking at Dotson's notion of contributory injustice, which is the refusal of dominant groups to take on the ideas of the marginalised (e.g. white people refusing to acknowledge the idea of racism), is that sometimes the transcripts of marginalised groups are hidden by the marginalised, but equally often they're instead ignored by the powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-25-09:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-26-06:22.html</id>
    <title>Attractive People on Magazine Covers as Hermeneutical Marketing</title>
    <updated>2020-05-26T07:40:18+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Attractive People on Magazine Covers as Hermeneutical Marketing&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3c0QDt4"&gt;Exuberant Animal&lt;/a&gt; by Frank Forencich, page 242:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The images we see on magazine covers are not authentic; they are manufactured. The models, beautiful as they might happen to be at the outset, are simply raw material for the digital hacks who do the ultimate make-over. What we see on the magazine rack are caricatures, not real human beings. They are not us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No wonder we are confused. No wonder our eyes are out of focus. No wonder everyone looks ugly. By comparison to magazine covers, none of us can come close to measuring up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Later, on page 243:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In each case, the subliminal message is the same: "Here is what you're supposed to look like. You don't, so now you've got a problem. But if you buy this magazine, and the products advertised in this magazine, you'll have a chance of looking this way, someday." Thus the magazines give a two-pronged marketing approach: create a sense of anxiety and offer a solution, all in one stroke. The strategy is nakedly, shamelessly manipulative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A couple thoughts sparked immediately from this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Magazines... those are a boomer thing, right?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Huh, visual hermeneutics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Huh, the supply of prototypes is a hermeneutic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermeneutics is a great marketing strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's an interesting market coordination problem here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Hermeneutics" means "The Study Interpretation", and "A hermeneutic" is something you use to interpret the world.
Also I &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/life-as-nonproductive-act"&gt;did say&lt;/a&gt; that I see everything as being about hermeneutics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These were all surprisingly interesting thoughts for a book that I didn't feel like I really got that much out of on my first pass through.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The magazines thing: Magazines still exist, obviously, but this book is from 2006 and I can't tell how much I'm just completely oblivious to the consumption of magazines and how much the world has just genuinely moved on. I feel like social media and youtube and the like have plugged the gap a bit and our supply of visual prototypes of what people are supposed to look like are a bit better than they used to be - still very filtered and aspirational, but not quite the degree of total airbrushing than they used to be then.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The fact that there  were purely visual hermeneutics is not something I'd realised before. I tend to think of hermeneutics as quite a verbal thing, because I'm quite a verbal thing, but of course the way we literally look at the world has a huge interpretive element to it. You don't just look at something/someone and then judge after the fact that it's/they're beautiful, beauty is part of how you orient your visual experience of it in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The use of prototypes as a hermeneutic is also something that... I guess if you'd pointed it out to me I would have said "Yeah, of course" but it wasn't foreground information. A lot of how we interpret the world is going to be by comparison to other things in it, and so the supply of salient things to compare against are a huge part of my hermeneutic.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hermeneutics as marketing: If you can control how people look at the world it makes it much easier to sell them on your particular solution to the problems that you highlight.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Market coordination: There's something of an arms race here. Each magazine is made more competitive by advertising with pictures that are only slightly more attractive than its competitors, but they then catch up, which is how we end up with this hyperoptimised scenario where people are attractive to a degree that actual humans can't really manage.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel like I could expand any one of these into a full notebook post, but I'm supposed to be focused on other things this week, so I won't.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-26-06:22.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-27-07:21.html</id>
    <title>The Inner Pedestal of Tennis</title>
    <updated>2020-05-27T09:19:32+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The Inner Pedestal of Tennis&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2LUnchH"&gt;The Inner Game of Tennis&lt;/a&gt; by W. Timothy Gallwey, page 129:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been my own worst stressor. But slowly I have found that the demands I'm trying to fulfill when I'm stressing myself are not really my own, but ones I have "picked up" or "bought into" for perhaps no better reason than I heard them early in life, or because they seemed to be so generally accepted. Soon they begin to sound right - and are therefore easier to listen to than the subtle but insistent urging of my own being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this gets to the heart of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-21-12:35.html"&gt;my disagreement with Gallwey&lt;/a&gt;, which largely stems from the fact that in this paragraph almost every word he says is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I think this book is entirely a giant bait and switch: He makes the (mostly) useful distinction between (ugh) "Self 1", the teller, and "Self 2", the doer. This is a reasonable split which is useful in many circumstances. I don't necessarily think it's a &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; split, but it works pretty well for about 90% of cases.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately he then goes on to posit that:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self 1 is intrinsically dysfunctional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self 2 is intrinsically functional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every other binary split of your self, including "the bad bits" and "the good bits" also lines up with this distinction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every single one of these premises is badly wrong. It is certainly true for many people that Self 1 is dyfunctional and Self 2 is functional, but those dysfunctions are not intrinsic and treating them as such is actively harmful. The third is just intrinsically nonsense and is the sign of someone with an explain everything theory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these errors manifest in this paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, specifically what he is wrong about in this paragraph boils down to two important glaring errors:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost everything in you is learned from outside of you. That's not you listening to things that are "not really your own". That is how being a person works. We socially construct our knowledge and behaviours by engaging with the people around us. You are complaining about being a person, Tim.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The arising internally/learned externally split of your behaviour &lt;em&gt;in no way&lt;/em&gt; maps on to the self 1 / self 2 distinction. Self 2 &lt;em&gt;absolutely&lt;/em&gt; learns and internalises lessons from the outside world. That's what trauma, and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;emotional responses more broadly&lt;/a&gt;, are. This is why operant conditioning works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I mean FFS, really.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I listen to a lot of &lt;a href="https://www.therapistuncensored.com/"&gt;Therapist Uncensored&lt;/a&gt; and an interesting theme that keeps coming up listening to it is that they're also quite into a similar split to Self 1 vs Self 2 (they tend to neurowash it and refer to it by parts of the brain, but that's neither here nor there), but they think that &lt;em&gt;Self 2&lt;/em&gt; is the dysfunctional one and that a lot of the skills they're trying to learn are essentially trying to use Self 1 to help Self 2 heal from its entrained fear reactions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think here I must adopt my usual brand of fence sitting: Actually, both sides are wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Self 1 and Self 2 each have their own strengths and weaknesses, and you cannot operate as a fully healthy human being without:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A functional Self 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A functional Self 2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A functional relationship between the two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Self 2 needs to give Self 1 a hug, and Self 1 needs to help Self 2 to talk about its feelings. They're literally both in this together, and they should behave as such.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The relationship is the important part, and Gallwey's framing basically fucks up any chance of a healthy relationship.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Putting someone on a pedestal basically dooms any possibility of a healthy relationship with them, and this is what we are doing when we claim Self 2 is in some sense intrinsically whole and just needs to be let free. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html"&gt;Self 2 is wrong all the time&lt;/a&gt; and that's OK. It's wrong in ways that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;Self 1 is good at helping it resolve&lt;/a&gt;. Self 1 does tend to get a bit neurotic if left in control, it's true, but Self 2 just needs to give it a bit of a hug and tell it to calm down and let the body do its thing (I've not yet figured out a better tool for this than actual hugs unfortunately).&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-27-07:21.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-28-07:42.html</id>
    <title>Life is neither poker nor tennis</title>
    <updated>2020-05-28T09:18:29+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Life is neither poker nor tennis&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3deDz4N"&gt;Thinking in Bets&lt;/a&gt; by Annie Duke, page 10:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hindsight bias is the tendency, after an outcome is known, to see the outcome as having been inevitable. When we say "I should have known that would happen," or, "I should have seen it coming," we are succumbing to hindsight bias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those beliefs develop from an overly tight connection between outcomes and decisions. That is typical of how we evaluate our past decisions."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is from a chapter called "Life is poker, not chess."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Before I start, I'd like to say that I think "Thinking in Bets" is a very good book and I would recommend that most people read it. It is probably the most accessible practical manual of rationality that I know of (there may well be better ones, but I don't know of them), and most people's thinking would be improved by a good primer in that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which is why I now want to explain why it's also wrong about everything.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In discussions on Twitter about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-27-07:21.html"&gt;yesterday's diatribe against The Inner Game of Tennis&lt;/a&gt;, I made &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1265765964915904514"&gt;the following point&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem being that because he got his start in tennis where verbal intelligence mostly &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; need to get out of the way, and because most people don't have tennis-related trauma, his model works pretty there but has fatal flaws when you try to generalise it off the court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Gallwey is making a classic error: He is a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html"&gt;nerd&lt;/a&gt;, and he thinks his special interest is universally applicable. Most of the advice in the inner game of tennis is very good &lt;em&gt;if you only ever apply it on the Tennis court&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's absolutely a good thing to take ideas from a specific nerddom and try to generalise them. I love doing that, and claiming that it was bad would be the rankest hypocrisy on my part. The problem is not generalising his Tennis related learning off the tennis court, the problem is that having learned all these skills in a context where they are useful close to 100% of the time, you do not learn to understand the preconditions under which those skills are useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Annie Duke has made the same mistake: She has learned a skill set within the context of a game of poker, and is now viewing the relevant skill set as applicable to life as a whole. Unfortunately, Poker has some very distinctive features over life:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is intrinsically adversarial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is highly structured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The probabilities of different outcomes are well defined and easily calculable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has a single well-defined utility function (money made) describing success in the game.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you may or may not be aware I love to hate on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subjective_expected_utility"&gt;Subjective Expected Utility Theory&lt;/a&gt;, but poker is an example where utility theory is great because you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have a utility function and you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have probabilities. Regardless of whether you believe in SEU, life outside poker simply isn't like that because the probabilities and the utility function are at best much more complex and less well defined.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Note: Thanks to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelly_criterion"&gt;The Kelly Criterion&lt;/a&gt; the utility function of poker is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; just straight up money made, but its logarithm, but the point still stands).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Poker is an &lt;em&gt;excellent&lt;/em&gt; game with which to hone your skills for a particular type of technical rationality, but technical rationality will only take you so far.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;C. Thi Nguyen suggests that games are &lt;a href="https://philpapers.org/archive/NGUGAT-2.pdf"&gt;ways of experimenting with different structures of agency&lt;/a&gt;. In playing a game, you are entering a world in which your choices are constrained to follow the rules of the game, and so you learn to play &lt;em&gt;as if&lt;/em&gt; those were the only choices possible. As a result you will &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-21-10:04.html"&gt;learn skills that you are neglecting in other contexts&lt;/a&gt; where those constraints on your agency do not apply. Learning the inner game of tennis &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; teach you about embodied cognition, because you can't think your way out of the problem. Learning poker &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; teach you about technical rationality, because you can't sweet talk your way out of the problem. Both embodied cognition and technical rationality are very good skills that you can apply in life more broadly, but because life lacks that restricted structure of agency that the game had. The reason the game taught you that skill so well was precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; the skill is not universally applicable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;David Chapman has recently published an &lt;a href="https://meaningness.com/eggplant/introduction"&gt;updated introduction to his Eggplant Book&lt;/a&gt;, which is about what he calls metarationality, that I rather like. In particular:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[People with metarational skills] produce these insights by investigating the relationship between a system of technical rationality and its context. The context includes a specific situation in which rationality is applied, the purposes for which it is used, the social dynamics of its use, and other rational systems that might also be brought to bear. This work operates not within a system of technical rationality, but around, above, and then on the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This applies more broadly than technical rationality: The foundational skill of life is figuring out what other skills you need to bring to bear on the situation. You cannot learn that from a game, because games work precisely by removing the need for that skill.
Games are an excellent way to hone certain skills, but they intrinsically lack the ability to teach you the fundamental life skill of &lt;em&gt;knowing which game you are playing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of which is a very long winded way of getting around to a very basic point prompted by the initial quote: Hindsight bias is good, actually.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hindsight bias is generally bad in poker where you can have very well defined strategies and intrinsic quantifiable uncertainty in the problem, but in life more broadly hindsight bias serves several fairly important functions. For example:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It forces you to look at problems much more carefully than you otherwise would have, giving you incentives to improve your skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It lets you hold people accountable for actions even when they are individually harmless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An example of the first is that when writing it is generally worth assuming that any misunderstands are your fault. They may often not be - many people are very bad readers - but by treating them as your fault anyway your writing skills will generally improve.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An example of the second is something I often use as a moral test case and requires a bit more of an extended anecdote.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Near my parents' place there is a more-or-less blind bend in the main road with a small road that joins on to the main road right after that bend. It is very poor design.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Almost nobody comes down that small road. I've seen someone joining on to the main road from there maybe two or three times during many years of driving that road.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's entirely viable to take the bend at 60mph if you ignore the side road. It's not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; sharp a bend. However, the signage wants you to take it at 25mph in order to account for that basically-never-used side road.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, my question is this: How fast should you take that bend?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From a subjective expected utility point of view, it's actually probably fine to take that bend at 60mph. Slowing down at that point in the drive is quite annoying, and the chances of causing an accident are extremely low given the low usage of that side road (and it's not like an accident is inevitable at 60mph and more than it's entirely avoidable at 25mph, you're just increasing the likelihood and severity). Yes you're trading convenience for an increased probability of your own and/or someone else's death but of course you are, you're &lt;em&gt;driving&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, if everyone else makes the same calculation, driving in from that side road is now basically a death sentence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Subjective Expected Utility calculations often look &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different if you universalise them by assuming that everyone else will make similar calculations, but SEU calculations are hard enough as it is without reasoning this way, and there's an easy kludge to achieve much the same effect: Hindsight bias.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If we treat low-probability consequences as if we should have seen them coming, and punish them accordingly, then we change the incentives to shape individual behaviour away from creating outcomes that were inevitable in aggregate even if they were low probability in any given instance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is this unfair on the indidual who happens to trigger the low probablity consequence? Probably. But so is dying because everyone else was making individually rational calculations that decided a low probability of your death was an acceptable consequence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is hindsight bias always good? No, of course not. You have to figure out from context whether it is or not. But that skill of figuring it out from context is not, I'm afraid, something you can learn from a game.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-28-07:42.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-28-21:05.html</id>
    <title>Key Performance Indicators</title>
    <updated>2020-05-28T23:41:11+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Key Performance Indicators&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;TLDR: Drunk and more than slightly self-indulgent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have inspired &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/captain_mrs/status/1266063855018532865"&gt;the creation of a blog&lt;/a&gt; which is absolutely one of my victory conditions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This caused me to think about some others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every word I inspire someone to write.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time you curse my name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every comment by someone who is annoyed by my being right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time my perfectly reasonable behaviour seems impossible to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time someone sends a link to my writing to their therapist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time someone uses something I wrote to win an argument.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time I make someone happier for my presence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But also every time someone understands themself better because of me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time I change how you look at the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every conversation we have that you thought was impossible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every person whose life I make better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do these seems inadequately selfish to you? They do to me. We ground our values in the people around us, but if we don't &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/09/being-an-example-to-others/"&gt;learn to be a little bit selfish&lt;/a&gt; then those values result in everyone being miserable through trying to make everyone happy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of them are, perhaps, a little selfish, in that they allow me to embrace my inner villain,
but villains, too, are unselfish: We're the ones who want to change the world for the better.
The heroes are just there to maintain the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So what are my victory conditions for me?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every "Ah ha!" moment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every hug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time I get to uncomplicatedly enjoy myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time I figure out why I can't, and fix that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time I get to act with my whole self, without holding back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every (redacted).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This doesn't seem enough. I can think of a few more, but I don't want to write them down,
and perhaps that's the problem: Admitting to wanting, let alone needing, things is vulnerable,
and I don't like being vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may seem surprising, as I share a lot, but what I share is in fact carefully curated. It doesn't count as vulnerability if by sharing it I rob it of its power, or if I do the work to become safe first.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, if I'm honest, I don't really feel like the ones for me count. They feel pointlessly self-indulgent, or like things I'm supposed to want to want. Where they don't the emotions don't feel exactly &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. I feel like the emotion associated with healing and growth should be something akin to joy, but that's not quite how it feels. It's more like a "Ha ha! Fuck you! You can't beat &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;!". It's still other-oriented.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been spending the last year or two trying to work on emotional skills, and that's been pretty good. I liked the bit where I figured out how to turn off social anxiety. But a lot of the drive for that has been other oriented too: I started a relationship, I realised my emotional baggage was now someone else's problem, and it caused me to prioritise it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1265585499500089344"&gt;I suggested recently to Luli&lt;/a&gt; that two good books about being selfish were "The Courage to be Disliked" and "Conflict is not Abuse". I feel it's kinda telling that both of my book recommendations about how to be selfish were about how to have healthier relationships with others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think perhaps the problem starts with how we conceptualise selfishness, and the idea of boundaries. Boundaries are things you put there to defend yourself. Defending yourself is good and proper and you have a right to do so,
so it's not hard to assert those rights. "You are hurting me. Stop." is not a complicated sentiment, and it's one that most healthy communities acknowledge a right to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But "acting to minimize suffering at the hands of others" isn't the hard part for me. I've had a lot of training in that one I'm afraid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The question is, what's next? Minimizing suffering doesn't lead to happiness, it just leads to non-suffering. Neutrality isn't that great. There's a reason "emotional blunting" is a diagnostic term.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think part of why I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-27-07:21.html"&gt;got quite so cranky at the inner game of tennis&lt;/a&gt; is the idea that you can just turn off the verbal self and the embodied self will rise to the occasion because it's fundamentally fine. The embodied self &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; fine sometimes. Sometimes you need to coax it out of its shell.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://clarissalittler.github.io/2020/05/28/feelings-of-being-final.html"&gt;Clarissa wrote about horizonal damage earlier&lt;/a&gt; and this feels fairly apt. My experience is different from theirs, but the space of the possible is constrained.
I can be selfish or unselfish in my interaction with others, but I can't really at present see how to be self-oriented.
I am aware of it as a theoretical possibility, but it does not appear as a practical orientation in the world that I can access.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had some more thoguhts but it's late and I should go to bed before this gets even more angsty, so I'm going to leave it there.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-28-21:05.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-29-05:46.html</id>
    <title>Defects are the responsibility of programmers</title>
    <updated>2020-05-29T08:34:06+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Defects are the responsibility of programmers&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This post is an elaboration on a &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1265967699743649793"&gt;Twitter thread about software I did yesterday&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hillel wrote &lt;a href="https://buttondown.email/hillelwayne/archive/defects-are-not-the-fault-of-programmers/"&gt;Defects are not the fault of programmers&lt;/a&gt;. It is a good post and I encourage you to read it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, the bigger issue with “programmers create defects” is an essential issue with the worldview. Its basis in facts is less important than its value as a “lens” we can use to understand defects. If we know where defects come from, we know what we need to do to manage them. To emphasize this: Our worldview on defects shapes our means of reducing defects. We measure the value of a lens by how useful it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does the “defects are the fault of programmers” worldview tell us about our means? It says that the only way to reduce defects is to improve programmer discipline. Either the programmer is sufficiently disciplined and nothing can cause defects, or the programmer is insufficiently disciplined and nothing can prevent defects. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd like to argue that Hillel is mostly correct, but bugs should &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; be considered the fault of the programmers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd also like to argue that the idea that bugs are the fault of the programmer, as implemented in practice, is in fact &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; worse than Hillel is making it out to be. The worst part of "defects are the fault of the programmer" is not that it doesn't help us to reduce defects, but that in fact that over time it virtually guarantees to increase them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A software development process is not just there to produce software, it's also there to produce a software development team, and in order to understand the effect of any given process you need to consider its effect on both. Systems which have positive effects on the software while having negative effects on the team, will, in the long run (which often is not that long - a year or two if often more than enough) end up backfiring horribly on the software as well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular, defects are a normal part of the software development process. People make mistakes, people misunderstand things. If you've never had a bug in production then that's probably because nobody is using your software or you spend &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; too long developing it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So independently of the question of whose &lt;em&gt;fault&lt;/em&gt; a defect is, the more important question is: When a defect occurs, does your software development team get better or worse?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd like to suggest that any system that relies &lt;em&gt;solely&lt;/em&gt; on personal responsibility will get worse in response to bugs, but so will any system that treats bugs as not the programmer's fault.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ideally we want people to take responsibility for shipping high quality software. The basic problem is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If people don't care about getting good results, there is no system that will get good results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If people do care about getting good results, basically every system works well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The system you choose determines which of these scenarios are stable states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular if a system &lt;em&gt;relies&lt;/em&gt; on people caring about getting good results, in the absence of support for that, you will &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;burn out the people who care the most&lt;/a&gt;, they will stop caring and/or leave, and you will end up with a team that doesn't care about getting good results.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the easiest ways to create this dynamic is to have a culture of personal responsibility for defects while pressuring people to ship, and providing no collective support for what to do in the event of failure.
If you treat "defects are the programmer's fault" as your guiding correctness principle, you will end up with a team whose response to that is "Yeah, but who cares?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; if you treat defects as intrinsically not the programmer's fault, you do this. "Human error" is a bad attribution in that you can always find a human to blame, but "System error" is also a bad attribution because you can always find a system to blame. Humans in the system are what create performance as well as defects, and if you treat humans as &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; the problem, what you end up with is &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/14773996.2018.1491147?journalCode=tphs20"&gt;safety clutter&lt;/a&gt; where people's hands are tied.
And, once again, people will tend to get frustrated ane leave. They won't necessarily be the same people as left in the other scenario, but having a team full of people who are entirely comfortable with plodding bureaucratic slowness at every step of the way is also not a great end state.
A key part of getting good results is that you have to get results.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I would suggest that a crucial part of getting to a system that creates a good team is that &lt;em&gt;guilt&lt;/em&gt;. When something goes wrong, the person responsible should feel appropriately guilty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem with this is that we are all very bad at guilt.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yes, I can hear you thinking "Oh don't worry David, I'm &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good at guilt". That is exactly the problem I am talking about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being good at guilt doesn't mean feeling a lot of guilt. It means feeling an appropriate amount of guilt, which can range from "Oops, my bad" to "Yeah that was a massive fuck up on my part. I'll make it right".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem we collectively have with guilt, both in terms of how we experience it and how we inflict it on others, is that we treat it as a binary with very little between no guilt and massive irredeemable shame. This is intrinsically unhealthy. Guilt, properly handled, is an acknowledgement that you have done badly and an impetus to do better. It cannot serve that function as we currently manage it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second crucial part of getting to a system that creates a good team is that "I'll make it right" part.
If people feel guilty but are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; empowered to fix it, then you once again end up in the situation where everyone who cares burns out and/or leaves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes that empowerment to make it right will consist of the programmer, as an individual, resolving and learning to do better. Sometimes it will be about changing the system. Sometimes they'll be able to manage it on their own, sometimes they'll need support.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is, sadly, no universal prescription that works. The world is messy and complicated. But if you give people the support they need to do better, and create a system that tends to improve rather than degrade the moral, emotional, and professional skills of its members, and responds healthily to the normal trials and tribulations that the world has to throw at it, it will probably go pretty well for you.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-29-05:46.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-30-13:17.html</id>
    <title>Knowing what to look for</title>
    <updated>2020-05-30T15:12:09+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Knowing what to look for&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-30&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(A short post today because I have run out of brain)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3d3M3vs"&gt;Finding Our Sea-Legs&lt;/a&gt; by Will Buckingham, page 69:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were to travel to Japan and stand before Mount Fuji, I would do so not with an attentiveness born of bare seeing, but with an attentiveness made keen by my love of Hokusai's prints. I would see the mountain with the care and the love that comes from knowing it is precisely &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; mountain, and not some other, before which I stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This ties interestingly in to my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-26-06:22.html"&gt;previous post about visual hermeneutics&lt;/a&gt;. Because Buckingham has prior context the mountain, that causes him to interpret it in a particular way - he feels certain things about it, but also he attends to it differently. He knows things about it, and his eye is trained to look for them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think we often have a broken intuitive model of how vision works. Vision is not actually us statically observing what is there. It is an active, engaged, process, where our eye looks for and tracks certain details. Your visual field is mostly incredibly blurry, outside of a very narrow range, but your eyes dart around picking out detail wherever you're paying attention to so you mostly don't notice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means that interpretation isn't just a matter of post-processing after you've seen an image, it determines where you focus your attention, so it literally changes what you see.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-30-13:17.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-31-09:20.html</id>
    <title>Norms of Excellence</title>
    <updated>2020-06-01T11:07:28+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Norms of Excellence&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-31&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1267043077673357312"&gt;I promised people a spicy notebook post&lt;/a&gt;, but I decided that actually it was rather rambling and didn't achieve its intended purpose, also I didn't want to write it in the end, so here's a shorter notebook post that achieves its goals better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wrote before about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html"&gt;the social obligation to be bad at things&lt;/a&gt;. One of the things that I have been working on recently is trying to figure out what the opposite looks like. What are some moral norms that promote excellence, and how do we embody them?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Yes, I need to read some virtue ethics, no I haven't read more than &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-virtue/"&gt;the SEP entry on it&lt;/a&gt; yet. Also this is as much a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-10-08:54.html"&gt;practice of ethics&lt;/a&gt; question).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this starts from some basic principles:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to value being good at things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to be OK with being bad at things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to be OK with other people being better at them than you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to be OK with being better at them than other people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to build growth relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first two principles are ones I've written about before, they're the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety&lt;/a&gt; model: You have to want to be good at the thing, and it has to be safe for you to experiment and find out that you're bad at the thing.
That's not to say that you can't feel annoyed, or guilty, or other negative emotional responses to being bad at something, but those have to be bounded. Your reaction to failure should be "Oh, that's annoying, I'll do better" rather than a giant toxic shame spiral.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The others are more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;When other people are better than you&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If someone is better at something than you, that's great. You can use them as inspiration, and possibly as a teacher, to improve.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been ragging on &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2LUnchH"&gt;The Inner Game of Tennis&lt;/a&gt; a lot recently, but despite my complaints I got a lot of value out of reading it, so let me quote from my absolute favourite passage from it for you, from page 121 in the chapter about competition (a chapter which I unreservedly like):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] true competition is identical with true cooperation. Each player tries his hardest to defeat the other, but in this use of competition it isn’t the other person we are defeating; it is simply a matter of overcoming the obstacles he presents. In true competition no person is defeated. Both players benefit by their efforts to overcome the obstacles presented by the other. Like two bulls butting their heads against one another, both grow stronger and each participates in the development of the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you value being better at something than someone else, you are driven to put them down - their improvement is your loss. If, however, you value being good at something, you should aim to build them up, so that they in turn can help build you up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of valuing being good without valuing better is, I think, the key feature to any norm of excellence, because it creates a positive feedback loop: When someone is good, everyone around them gets better, which causes them to get better in turn.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other reason you have to be OK with other people being better than you is that it's inevitable. There might be &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; you are the world expert at (and in fact, I would suggest that being the world expert at something is both much more achievable than you think and a worthy goal for anyone to pursue), but you're definitely not the world expert at everything, and some people are just going to be better than you at things that matter in ways that you can never hope to catch up to. If you're not comfortable with that, you cannot be comfortable with the world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;When you are better than other people&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being better at things than other people can often be quite emotionally difficult,
for reasons that are largely moral in nature.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first reason is simply that it's often annoying when people are bad at something and you can see how to do it better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think undoing this is essentially a two step process:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decide what level you think it is &lt;em&gt;morally obligatory&lt;/em&gt; for people to be good at the thing. When they are failing to adhere to that level, do something about it - point it out to them, help them get better, etc. (How much it's appropriate to do depends on context and your relationship with the person).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If people clear that level of moral obligation and you're still better at it than them, get over it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Examples where the first matter are mostly ones where skill level has an impact on other people. Someone who is bad at driving, or consent, has a significant chance of hurting someone else. Therefore competence is not merely a nice to have, it's a moral imperative. But at some point there's a diminishing return - the current median level of driving is probably too low, but but 90% level is probably fine despite almost everyone in the 90% level having someone who is better at driving than them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second is important too: A norm in which you are annoyed at people for not being as good as you utterly fails to promote excellence (as well as being a jerk move), because people are finite beings with differing priorities. If someone is not good at something, that's their responsibility, and it may be because they don't value being good at it as much as you do, or because they've spent their time on other things they value more. If you want to promote excellence in general rather than just in one specific area, you have to allow people to pick what they excel at.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next major issue which comes up when you're better at things than someone else is that they will feel bad about that (this would be less of an issue if everyone was a perfect adherent to the norm of being OK when other people are better than them).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This has been something of a problem for me, and is something I've been working on fixing this year: There are things that are widely valued in my social group that I am just very good at, and that other people who also value them are not very good at, and the fact that I am good at them makes them feel bad about the fact that they are not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The easiest example of this is reading. I read a lot. People express a certain amount of awe at this, but it's nothing mysterious. I read a lot because I spend about ten hours per week reading. I read moderately but not remarkably fast, so it's possible I read about twice as much as you would if you also spent ten hours a week reading, but I read something closer to ten times as much as most people do. If I didn't have other things I should be doing as well, I would happily (and easily) double that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's perfectly OK to not read that much. You don't have to be a reader at all. The minimum morally obligatory level of reading is zero hours spent reading books. But if you are someone who thinks of themselves as a reader, and attaches personal value to that identification, the fact that I'm spending ten hours a week reading books highlights the fact that they're not, and that makes them feel bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is the uncomfortable but true thing I have had to learn this year:
That's not my problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's no way to sugar coat this: Being good at things will make your friends feel bad about themselves, and you have to be OK with that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3emI4ud"&gt;Conflict is Not Abuse&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/36vb9Rt"&gt;The Courage to be Disliked&lt;/a&gt; were very useful in helping me resolve a bunch of my emotional issues around this earlier this year.
The two relevant concepts, which pair very well together, are the idea of "Separation of Tasks" and "Overstating Harm".
In short:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How others feel is not under your control. (Separation of Tasks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Causing someone discomfort is not causing them harm. (Overstating Harm)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you feel bad about your non-reading, that's not under my control, and my attempting to control it does us both a disservice. If what I am doing for myself makes you uncomfortable, that is not me doing harm to you - and may even be helping you - and avoiding it is not doing you a favour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Causing someone discomfort is not causing them harm" seems particularly unintuitive,
so here are two examples of causing someone discomfort that I find help untangle things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A black person's presence may cause a racist white person discomfort.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A therapist may help their client have uncomfortable realisations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Neither of these are harm, and neither of these are things that the person causing the discomfort is &lt;em&gt;remotely&lt;/em&gt; culpable for.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That's not to say everything that causes discomfort is fine, obviously. Many things that cause discomfort &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; bad and &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; morally culpable (if nothing else, being harmed is quite uncomfortable), only that discomfort itself is not evidence of harm.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular it is not to say that I should rub your face in the fact that I read more than you. That would be an obviously jerk move. But I should make no more than reasonable accommodations - ideally at your explicit request - about how to handle this, and holding myself back because it makes you feel bad is not a reasonable accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, and importantly, it's not an accommodation that I think any of my friends would &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;,
and by attempting to make it unasked I become &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-06-15:20.html"&gt;unsafe&lt;/a&gt; for them to tell me how they feel.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Building Growth Relationships&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've talked about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-26-07:28.html"&gt;growth relationships&lt;/a&gt; before,
but in short a growth relationship is one where everyone in the relationship gets better for the relationship, in the way that they want to get better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are key to norms of excellence, because how much you can help someone &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; much depends on the strength of your relationship. These writings are, ultimately, an attempt to help all of you reading them grow (in whatever way works for you), but they're very impersonal: I'm casting them out into the world, hoping that they help.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A growth relationship helps everyone get better because you can help each other out more directly - you have higher context, you can invest more effort, and you can deliberately provide people each other a platform for becoming better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as excellence norms requiring growth relationships, I think growth relationships are also a good place to practice excellence norms, so if these norms are at all appealling I'd recommend exploring them in the context of some of your close friendships and romantic relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-31-09:20.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-02-08:25.html</id>
    <title>Being friends with your coworkers</title>
    <updated>2020-06-02T15:54:17+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Being friends with your coworkers&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2WYeYew"&gt;Talking About Machines&lt;/a&gt; by Julian Orr, page 35:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;their [team] has developed personal bonds in addition to their professional association, including friendship outside the job. His narration reveals a division among technicians over the propriety of such bonds, and while he clearly values them, he is wary of revealing them to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The question of whether you should be friends with your coworkers is an interesting one.
For me the answer is "Obviously yes, except it's kinda problematic."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At a personal level, being friends with your coworkers is good. You're going to spend a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of your time together, and your life will be improved if you actually like spending time together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At a professional level, being friends with your coworkers is also good: It significantly improves your team productivity. One of the things that is clear from Orr's book is that talking to each other, swapping war stories, sharing technical problems and advice, is almost inseparable from having a friendly conversation with each other. This isn't the equivalent of having a daily standup or a team meeting, it's a conversation, and it's much easier to have conversations with your friends. These conversations are an essential part of learning together and sharing important information.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being friends with your coworkers makes literally everything better, and it is very hard to have a functioning company without a certain amount of bonds of friendship.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also... this is how marginalisation works and reinforces itself, because not everybody can easily be friends with their coworkers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm reminded of &lt;a href="https://www.ft.com/content/da6a33be-bd8f-11e8-8274-55b72926558f"&gt;this piece from the FT&lt;/a&gt; (apologies for the paywall):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an instant, if brutal, reminder of the value of smoking at work. It is one of the cheapest and most effective ways of finding out what is really going on in the office. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am indebted to a reader for my favourite ploy: an office beer fridge. A man from the US who has started and managed several companies wrote to tell me on-site grog had several proven benefits. Everyone got to know each other quickly, he said, “from production worker to the CEO”, and that made a big difference to the way they worked with one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These sorts of nonwork activities that promote socialisation end up being extremely good for establishing lines of information and common knowledge within the company that run orthogonally to formal lines of information.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, both smoking and drinking are hugely exclusionary ways of setting up those lines, right? They're &lt;em&gt;effective&lt;/em&gt;, but they're effective for the people who are willing to participate them. Personally, I don't mind office drinking (but no thanks on the beer), and will find the presence of smokers around the office actively unpleasant, never mind &lt;em&gt;joining&lt;/em&gt; them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Many people have had bad experiences with alcohol, or avoid it for religious reasons, and above and beyond not drinking will not be at all comfortable around people who are drinking. It also tends to exacerbate other ways in which a group is exclusionary - if you're part of an underrepresented minority, people who are on their best behaviour while sober may start to show their true colours while drunk (and even if it turns out that their true colours are actually that they're perfectly nice people and there are zero problems, it's hard to know that in advance and this prevents the event from being relaxing and enjoyable).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of criticism of the tech industry's reliance on alcohol for social bonding on grounds of it being exclusionary, and this criticism is entirely correct.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the criticism tends not to get listened to, for one very simple reason: Drinking as a way of socialising works really well, and without something to replace it, this criticism asks the majority to make a significant personal sacrifice for the minority's comfort. This doesn't tend to go well. Should the majority do it? Well, maybe. But you need to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-19-09:35.html"&gt;work with the audience that you have&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even if you overcome this and find a perfectly innocuous way of doing team socialisation,
you end up with issues of conflicting identity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was at a London &lt;a href="http://www.liberatingstructures.com/"&gt;Liberating Structures&lt;/a&gt; meetup group right before lockdown started, and someone there suggested that on Mondays they tried to get a lot of discussion going between people about what they'd done over their weekend, as a kind of ice breaker / social bonding exercise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I gently suggested to them that this might not work so well because you're trying to force people to disclose things they may not want to disclose. People don't generally want to tell their coworkers that they spent the weekend at a sex party (this is a common problem among my friend group).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn't have to be a sex party either. People are probably equally unwilling to tell their staunchly atheist coworkers that they spent the weekend at a bible study. Telling people that they spent their weekend at a protest risks office politics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More innocuously, you have a divide between parents and non parents. If a parent talks about how they spent their weekend with their kids, the other parents in the room may join in talking about their kids, while the non-parents sit there twiddling their thumbs. Or, equally, if you're the only parent in the room and everyone is talking about the fun things they were up to this weekend and you were mostly doing childcare duties.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think part of the problem here is that we are too used to playing friendship on easy mode and largely lack the skill of having heterogenous friends groups. It's much easier to be friends if you can find strong points of commonality with each other and minimise points of conflict. When your main point of commonality is that you work together, you will often lack that easy mode.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem gets worse when you take into account that some people actually just may not be able to make friends that easily. They may be lacking in social skills, or they may just be kinda traumatised and find it difficult to trust people. Many of these people are lovely, brilliant, people, and even those who aren't probably need to work &lt;em&gt;somewhere&lt;/em&gt; - because, alas, capitalism. How do we make a system that works for them?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, when you try to deliberately help those people integrate, this may seem like an attack on them, because it reads like a social test that they can fail.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these problems are, I think, even worse at a small company. I wrote about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-25-10:40.html"&gt;the problem with not fitting in in small towns&lt;/a&gt; before, and small companies are like that but more so. If you work in an office with a thousand other people there are probably others like you there (whether you can find them is another issue). That doesn't necessarily solve your problem if you're not on their team, but it at least &lt;em&gt;helps&lt;/em&gt;. If you work at a company of five other people, chances are good that you have a number of traits that are unique to you, and some of those may be ones that result in you being excluded.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is at this point that I reveal the easy, brilliant, and obvious solution that will solve all of these problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Err.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe it's not. I was kinda hoping you would do that for me. Because this problem seems like a giant insoluble mess and I barely have any idea where to start - any solution seems far too contextual for me to propose any general principles.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mostly I'd like people to start by acknowledging the problem: Being friends with your coworkers is important and valuable, and currently we only make it accessible to people who get to play friendship on easy mode.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-02-08:25.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-03-09:56.html</id>
    <title>Some Useful Emotion Management Principles</title>
    <updated>2020-06-03T09:56:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Some Useful Emotion Management Principles&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was talking about anxiety management a bit on Twitter, and it occurred to me that it would be useful to write down a bunch of general principles that I use for understanding emotions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These principles aren't necessarily &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt;, but I've found them useful. I'd say that they're probably... about 90% true. They're worth using as defaults for understanding things, but they probably have some hidden preconditions and missing features that I have not fully mapped out yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the primary features of emotions is a disposition to act in a particular way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A disposition to act is not an obligation to act.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These dispositions are experienced, at least in large part, through your body, so paying attention to your body helps you understand your emotions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no "bad" emotions, in the sense that there always a situation where the disposition prompted by the emotion would be appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a given context, an emotional reaction may or may not be appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotional reactions are learned pattern matching in response to particular events.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When an emotional reaction is active, you can retrain those patterns into ones that better suit the situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retraining requires you to acknowledge that the emotion might, in principle, be a valid reaction in context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you ignore an emotion, it will tend to increase in intensity to get you to act on it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning to act competently on dispositions can improve emotional experiences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If an emotion is debilitating or otherwise interferes with your life, that's often a sign of some sort of dysregulation in how you are managing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me unpack each of these.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Emotions as dispositions towards action&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A disposition in this context is an inclination towards a certain class of things, an inclination to act in a particular way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you are angry, it is because you are being prompted to act angrily. You are getting ready to have a fight, and you are orienting yourself towards actions that are useful for that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some people (e.g. Antonio Damasio I think) argue that emotions &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; these dispositions. I'm somewhat agnostic on this question, in that I think our use of the word "emotion" is variable enough that it's not clear to me that "What are emotions?" is a well-defined question, and any attempt to promote it as a definition is probably a lost cause.
However, regardless of what theory of emotion we end up with, understanding the dispositions associated with an emotion is key to understanding that emotion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some other examples of disposition:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anxiety might dispose you to reducing the uncertainty in a situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fear might dispose you to getting out of a situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guilt might dispose you towards repairing some damage you've done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curiousity might dispose you to learning more about something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contentment might dispose you towards luxuriating in something you're enjoying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delight might dispose you towards immersing yourself in a particular activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Side note: I realised while writing this that it was much easier for me to figure out what the dispositions associated with negative emotions are. Given that part of my goals right now are to improve my experience of positive emotions, I find that very interesting)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Dispositions are not obligations&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you get angry, you are not being &lt;em&gt;forced&lt;/em&gt; to act angrily. You can feel angry without acting angry (although people will probably be able to tell that you are angry. This is not necessarily bad). But the emotion of anger includes, as a key feature, a dsposition towards angry action - you are inclined to shout at someone, to attack them, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An important skill in emotion management is to acquire a bit of a separation between disposition and action. To pause and say "Actually, I know that emotionally this is the way I am disposed to act, but &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; I do that?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly, this is not &lt;em&gt;suppressing&lt;/em&gt; the emotion. That has to be an honest question, to which it is possible that the answer is allowed to be yes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Dispositions are experienced bodily&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We act in the world through our body, so experiencing a disposition is, in large part, experiencing an arrangement of our body (including our senses) to act. If we are disposed to fight, we will feel our body tensing to fight. If we are curious about something, we might feel our attention physically drawn to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Learning this is basically what &lt;a href="https://focusing.org/"&gt;Focusing&lt;/a&gt; is - learning to pay attention to your bodily dispositions towards particular actions, as a preliminary step towards understanding the emotional reactions that underly them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;There are no bad emotions&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We have these dispositions because &lt;em&gt;they are useful&lt;/em&gt;. If you are experiencing a disposition, there are circumstances under which that disposition is the right one. If you feel afraid, that is not bad in and of itself, because there are circumstances under which a disposition to get out of the situation is a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We (for some suitably culture specific value of we) tend to think of negative emotions as being bad for a couple of reasons:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They might frequently be inappropriately deployed (anger).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They might be overused, or misused, against us (guilt, shame)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We might have unhelpful habits built up around them (anxiety)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These all give us a bad relationship with a particular emotion, but they primarily result in a conflation between the disposition, the situation prompting it, and the actions it prompts. The disposition &lt;em&gt;in and of itself&lt;/em&gt; is neither bad nor good, and sometimes it will be exactly the right thing to have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Emotions may promote inappropriate action&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you say something, and I mishear you and think you have insulted at me, and I respond in kind, and a fight results. That is an example of an inappropriate reaction - I have misunderstood the situation, I have acted in a way that is (arguably) appropriate &lt;em&gt;if the situation were as I understood it&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is what an inappropriate emotional reaction is like: You have responded with a disposition because the situation makes you think it is the appropriate one, but you are in some way mistaken about the situation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Emotional reactions are learned pattern-matching&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Generally your emotional reactions are based on very simplified models of the world.
For example, social anxiety might be a learned reaction that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; social situations are unsafe and you have to be on high alert and monitor for threats. A bad experience with men might cause a disposition to be on your guard around &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; men.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You don't necessarily have access to these simplified models. There's not necessarily a conscious part of your brain that goes "This is a party. Parties are THE WORST. Therefore I now decide to be anxious." - the anxiety generally starts preverbally, and the thoughts come after (although the thoughts can in turn promote action).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It can be useful to think of your mind having a subsystem that is "the bit that decides to be anxious" (or angry, or delighted, or...) which is monitoring the world for certain features and putting you into the particular disposition when its conditions are met. The subsystem is not necessarily particularly intelligent, and you have a lot of these subsystems going on so they don't necessarily have a lot of resources available to them, so they're trying to do the best they can on a limited budget, and they sometimes get it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Active emotional reactions can be relearned&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because emotions are learned pattern matching, changing your emotional reactions is a matter of relearning that pattern matching. You want to take the subsystem and get it to respond better in some circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems to be &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; easier when the emotional subsystem is activated. I don't want to say you &lt;em&gt;can't&lt;/em&gt; do it when it's not activated (and certainly you can lay useful groundwork for this process), but it's not something I've been able to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Activated" doesn't necessarily mean when you're in the situation in question (although I do often use it there) - it can through a process of imagination, talking it out, thinking about the prompting situation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once you're in this state, you can gently start to question the premises of the emotional reaction. Draw your attention to certain aspects of the situation, explore whether this is the right disposition for you to take in this context.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, social anxiety can be relearned around people you have much stronger evidence are safe. The level of anxiety you experience when talking to a close friend should be lower than the level of anxiety you have talking to someone at a party, and drawing your attention to the things that make it so can help relearn the emotional reaction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Ignoring an emotion intensifies it&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that &lt;em&gt;doesn't&lt;/em&gt; seem to work is to try to suppress and ignore the emotion.
Emotions are there to dispose you to act, so will often rise to the level of intensity required to get you to act.
If you repeatedly suppress an emotion and pretend it's not there,
it will tend to get worse over time rather than better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Relearning starts with accepting the emotion in principle&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because ignoring the emotion doesn't work, and because emotions are dispositions to act,
you need to acknowledge it as potentially valid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What this means is that you need to start from the premise that if this is the correct disposition to have in this scenario, you would act on it. If you're actually being attacked, it's OK to be angry and act angrily. If there's genuine risk in the situation, it's OK to be anxious and act to reduce that risk.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Starting from the premise that the emotion &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be valid, and exploring the question of whether it is, allows you to work with yourself rather than creating internal conflict, and maximises your chance of successfully retraining the emotion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Learning to act competently on dispositions&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the big problems we often end up with emotions is that we're not very good at acting on them not in the sense that we ignore them, but we act on them in ways that don't actually improve the situation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anxiety and guilt are two big examples of this. If anxiety causes us to panic and make the situation worse, we have &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; reduced the risk in the situation, so our level of anxiety goes up rather down. If we feel guilty and avoid the whole situation to avoid feeling that guilt, we end up feeling more guilty rather than less.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Learning skills in a safe environment (when the emotion is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; active) that we can apply in these cases helps us fix this: If cleaning makes us anxious, creating a safe environment in which to learn a bit of cleaning skills will help the next time we have cleaning anxiety. If we feel guilt about a particular situation, talking through the situation and deciding on some practical steps you can take to improve it (or indeed deciding that you don't need to feel guilty about it at all).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The ideal situation is that we have the emotional responses that dispose us to act in the right way in the right context, and learning to act in the right way is a key part of that that we can manage separately from the emotional responses themselves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Debilitating emotions are probably dysregulation&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If your emotional reactions are so strong that they prevent you from acting, something has gone wrong (except in the rare specific cases where preventing you from acting is what they're &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to do, as in the freeze trauma response). Emotions are dispositions towards actions, but if those dispositions get too overwhelmingly intense they may stop you from acting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't have too much experience with this side of things (my problems are, if anything, at the opposite end of the spectrum - I don't tend to have intense enough emotional reactions), so I'm wary of offering too much advice in this space. I think all of the above principles are still likely to be useful to you, but I'd recommend also looking into &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dialectical_behavior_therapy"&gt;Dialectical Behavioural Therapy&lt;/a&gt; and possibly the literature on cPTSD. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dialectical_behavior_therapy"&gt;Meg-John Barker's piece on the subject&lt;/a&gt; is good, and provides pointers to further literatures.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(The literature on cPTSD may also be useful even if you &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; experience overwhelming emotions. Certainly I've found it so.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are the principles underlying most of my emotion work right now. You can read some more of my thoughts on the subject in:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;Emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html"&gt;Your emotions are valid but probably wrong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-17:58.html"&gt;How I fix anxiety triggers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you'd like to read more qualified people's thoughts on the subject the books I've read that are most directly relevant to this are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2AUQ2vW"&gt;Descartes' Error&lt;/a&gt; by Antonio Damasio is largely theoretical but is good for understanding the mind/body link.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Mnm1Hx"&gt;Focusing&lt;/a&gt; by Eugene Gendlin helps understand how to use a sense of your own body to understand your emotions. People recommend &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3gMG3cB"&gt;The Power of Focusing&lt;/a&gt; as a better introduction but I haven't got around to reading it yet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3gQUdcT"&gt;Unlocking the emotional brain&lt;/a&gt; is in theory the source of a lot of my work on retraining emotions, but I must admit I never get around to reading it. I just read &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/i9xyZBS3qzA8nFXNQ/book-summary-unlocking-the-emotional-brain"&gt;Kaj Sotala's review of it&lt;/a&gt;, went "Oh right", and immediately incorporated it into my own practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Axf1W0"&gt;The Emotion Machine&lt;/a&gt; by Marvin Minsky was useful for thinking about how the mind organises itself around resources which create dispositions to action. I'm suspicious of whether the book is actually &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;, but it's proven a useful source of metaphors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't necessarily promise you'll get the same things out of these resources that I did - there's a lot of surrounding additional reading, discussion, and experimentation, but they're all good books that I've found quite helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-03-09:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
