<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2025-04-10T16:38:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-02-18:59.html</id>
    <title>Building a library of stories</title>
    <updated>2025-04-02T21:09:14+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Building a library of stories&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One comment I got on &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-28-12:43.html"&gt;Behaving
as if you were trying to succeed&lt;/a&gt; was that the chicken thing was a
great anecdote. I liked getting this comment, and it made me think:
“Huh, yeah. It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a great anecdote. I don’t have many of
those.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is sortof weird. It’s not exactly like I haven’t had
plenty of things happen to me that could take the form of great
anecdotes. When I try to think of examples, I do worry that the rate of
anecdotes per year has gone down a bit. I don’t know that this is
actually true. e.g. &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/using-what-youre-given"&gt;Using
what you’re given&lt;/a&gt; is basically me telling a bunch of recent
anecdotes.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Also my current life events are a rollercoaster of
between two and five very dramatic storylines right now, it’s just that
I’m in the middle of them and they involve other people’s privacy so I
can’t exactly share them easily in public.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Certainly a lot of historic anecdotes feel… wackier. For example,
there was that time that I went to work in my pajamas. Or the time I
brought a giant frog to a wedding. More recently, I do get a lot of
mileage out of telling the story of my first date with my partners.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It took me about halfway through the date to figure out
that I was on a date and until our second date to realise that neither I
nor they were poly prior to that point. I brought notes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But… I don’t know, I’m not sure it ever occurred to me to tell the
chicken anecdote before, and it’s not exactly a big event.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think part of what’s going on is that I simply don’t think of my
life in terms of well packaged stories to tell, so anecdotes come up
when I’m talking or writing about something and I pull on the thread of
something and the next thing that comes out in the chain is something
that actually happened to me. The anecdote, in this context, serves as a
tool to solve a problem, but isn’t something I necessarily experience as
a primary thing in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not, I think, unrelatedly, I have very poor narrative memory. There
are whole swathes of my life that feel just… gone. I bet they’re not
though. I bet they’re just somewhere I’m not looking. Generally I find
when I pull on a thread of thought or memory there’s quite a lot there,
it’s just not indexed in a way that I easily have access to, but if I
actually go digging I recall quite a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example (look, an anecdote!) Dave and I were talking about our
seemingly-abandoned family D&amp;amp;D game the other day. We were vaguely
talking about resuming it, and he said something like “The first
challenge is anyone remembering what even happened in the last session”,
to which I said “God even I don’t remember”.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I am normally the one who remembers perfectly what
happened in the previous session and tells everyone about it at the
beginning of the session. No, I don’t know how this squares with my
belief that I have poor narrative memory either. I think it’s because
I’m using a different skill, the one where I just unwind the stack of
the conversation and perfectly tell you the thread of what we’ve been
talking about so far. It’s a weird superpower, but one I’m grateful to
have.&lt;/span&gt;
Then I said “hmmm… actually I do remember a bit, right. Jess joined us
for that one, right? She was a monk. We’d just finished making friends
with the flesh eating monster… Oh! And we fought the wizard we were
ostensibly there to rescue.” and then went on filling in more and more
details, each one becoming accessible as I remembered the bits adjacent
to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I think this claim that I don’t have a lot of anecdotes I can tell
is just a skill issue. Or, not even really a skill issue, a habit issue.
All the raw material is there, and I can forge it into anecdotes if I
want to, I just don’t. I’m not really sure why not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of “why not?” is of course that not doing things is the default,
but there’s a sort of half formed feeling that this would be a good
thing to do, therapeutically speaking, and also just useful as a way of
improving my understanding of myself and my ability to communicate with
others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think just starting to tell more anecdotes will probably just
result in being much better at remembering and telling stories from my
life in general. Talking about my dreams almost immediately started
causing me to remember my dreams better, and I suspect this is similar -
once you direct yourself towards some external goal, the internal
experiences that you’ve been ignoring and need for this goal suddenly
rise to the occasion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there’s also a sort of… fluency issue here. There’s a book by
Boris Shekhtman called “How to improve your foreign language
immediately” that I think about a lot despite not really working much on
speaking any foreign languages.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Technically, I speak Spanish, French, and German as well
as being a native English speaker. In practice, I speak all of these at
such a bad level that I’d be unable to claim with a straight face that I
really spoke them. I have been able to hold very basic conversations in
German in the past, did get an A at French GCSE, and have been the least
bad person at communicating with a waitress in Spanish in Mexico, but
that was more because I was able to speak Spanish badly with confidence
where everyone else around me was too shy. Oh, look, another anecdote.&lt;/span&gt; In particular one of the
things he recommends is developing “islands of competence” - areas where
you’ve gamed out a lot of the conversation in advance, where you’ve
memorised certain set phrases, filled in gaps of your vocabulary,
etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Practicing telling specific anecdotes feels like it’s adopting this
strategy more broadly, because it helps you find interesting talking
points about your life, and helps connect you up to a kind of fluency in
living that feels hard to access sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m not quite sure how this will works. Consider this post more a
declaration to experiment than a well articulated thesis.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-02-18:59.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-03-11:36.html</id>
    <title>Threads of existence</title>
    <updated>2025-04-03T12:53:50+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Threads of existence&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have a sort of running “joke” that I don’t have chronic fatigue,
I’m just… fatigued… chronically. Same with pain. Similarly I’m not
disabled, it’s just that sometimes I can’t walk.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I don’t have depersonalisation…&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Someone on discord recently described my writing as:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this guy has actually thought about the most basic mechanics of
“being a person in the world”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I have to do that is that I don’t feel very good
at being a person, and I’m having to figure it out the hard way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I genuinely don’t think I actually meet many (any?) of the diagnostic
criteria for depersonalisation, but there’s definitely some sort of
background feeling of… what would it like to actually just effortlessly
be a person?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I’m not actually under any illusions about whether I am
or am not a person, and don’t actually benefit from external
reassurances about this. I’m factually clear on the empirical question
of my personhood. But it doesn’t feel like I’m very good at it, and I
don’t trust external observers’ opinions on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason I don’t trust external observers here is that I think
people rarely notice this about me, because I’m highly functional in
short bursts and in company, and so this adds up to seeming extremely
like a person in any externally observable scenario. But what that feels
like from the inside is that I &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/cohering-and-decohering"&gt;cohere&lt;/a&gt;
when observed or otherwise prompted to by circumstances, but can’t
easily do so under my own steam, and by default just collapse into a
sort of decohered blob that left to its own devices will just &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-06-12:00.html"&gt;drift&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;If you’re wondering if that’s related to the
aforementioned definitely-don’t-have-chronic-fatigue, yeah me too. I
don’t know how much, or in which direction, but it sure seems like a
thing. If you’re thinking “gosh David, it sure sounds like what you’re
describing is depression”, yes I know. I did start by talking about a
key major common diagnostic feature of depression after all…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It feels, almost, like having a self that lacks object permanence.
It’s not there if someone isn’t looking. And, sure, it’s relatively
stable in its characteristics each fresh time it exists, because it’s
made out of roughly the same parts each time, but it still went through
a phase of not existing and coming back into existence, with a
discontinuity between those two things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this seems bad, and I’d like to fix it. In some ways, fixing
it is probably a core feature of my project, although I don’t know that
I’ve done a very good job of that.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I tend to think of my personal project as something more
like “Figure out how to be less depressed”, but it has a lot of details
and pulls in a lot of life in general&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of fixing it is just &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-31-18:47.html"&gt;finding
more circumstances in which I can cohere&lt;/a&gt;, but I think another bigger
part is a sort of… OK, sometimes you’re not a person. That’s normal.
Going to sleep for example is a legitimate interruption in continuity.
Or sometimes you just lose yourself in flow in a way that interrupts
your conscious awareness of what’s going on, or get drunk, or are ill,
or… You get the idea. If an enduring sense of self requires full
continuity, you’re never going to have it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the analogy to object permanence is interesting, because the
thing about lacking object permanence is that &lt;em&gt;objects actually are
permanent&lt;/em&gt;. The fact that they cease to exist for you in between
viewings doesn’t actually mean they cease to exist. What’s lacking is
not a permanence to their existence, but your sense of that permanence
as a unified thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think part of how you build that unity between different fragments
of yourself across time is that you start to build links between them.
Part of what’s interesting about the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-30-11:41.html"&gt;attitude
to commitments&lt;/a&gt; I’m trying to foster is that it is casting a link
forward in the future between yourself now and who you will be. Being
able to do this reliably starts to help you feel that you will continue
to exist in the future as an entity contiguous with who you are now. You
are, but actually being able to act on that helps you &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;alieve&lt;/a&gt;
that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-02-18:59.html"&gt;telling
stories about your life&lt;/a&gt; is likely the other part of this link, and
it’s part of why I’m trying to figure out how to explore that. In much
the same ways commitments cast a link forward, a story casts a link
backwards, connecting up who you are now with who you were then.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Alasdair MacIntyre has this notion of “narrative identity” as the
thing that constitutes selfhood. I haven’t read much about this, though
I do keep vaguely intending to. I guess I’m gesturing at something like
that, although I’m not sure we’re talking about exactly the same sort of
thing. I don’t think you can view self as wholly constituted by
narrative, but I do think that narrative is perhaps an important tool
for building a skeleton that a self can grow on top of.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-03-11:36.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-04-13:33.html</id>
    <title>Why do you do things?</title>
    <updated>2025-04-04T22:03:21+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Why do you do things?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recently watched CJTheX’s &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GZg_36utl2w"&gt;6 Shapes of God&lt;/a&gt;.
I don’t really know if I recommend it or not. I recommend giving it a go
and either you’ll find it weirdly compelling and watch it or you won’t
want to watch it and both are fine outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things they talk about in it, partially rooted in some
work by the philosopher Harry Frankfurt that I’m passingly familiar
with&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And really should read more of. I find Frankfurt a bit
dry, but generally he makes really interesting points about stuff I care
about.&lt;/span&gt; is that there’s a sort of division
into “instrumental ends” (e.g. I want to make money) and “terminal ends”
(I want to have fun) that is natural to make, and also is sortof fake,
because we also take on our “terminal ends” for instrumental reasons: If
we didn’t have something to strive for, we’d be bored.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I think I might here be conflating Harry Frankfurt’s
views with Elijah Millgram’s “On being bored out of your mind”, but in
my defence that paper is specifically building on Frankfurt’s work
here.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Frankfurt&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I think.&lt;/span&gt; introduces the idea of “maeutic”
ends - ends which lead to you taking on other ends in order to achieve
them. e.g. you might want to be happy, but merely aiming directly at
happiness doesn’t work. In order to achieve happiness, the most
effective means is to find something that can matter to you for its own
sake, and then &lt;em&gt;sincerely take that on as an end&lt;/em&gt;, and happiness
will emerge. e.g. when deciding what to do with your life, you might
decide to be a doctor because that seems fulfilling to you, but you
can’t be a doctor to seek fulfillment and expect to be fulfilled, you
need to decide that being a doctor genuinely matters. You might later
decide that it is not if it’s making you miserable and lacks the
qualities that matter to you, but in the moment your day-to-day reason
has to be about the end of &lt;em&gt;being a doctor&lt;/em&gt;, not &lt;em&gt;being a
doctor in order to be fulfilled&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The instrumental/terminal distinction is still useful though, it’s
just important to understand that “why?” answers are weird and
defeasible and necessarily incomplete.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why did you eat that cake? Because it was delicious.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you look at this as a sort of pure logical syllogism sort of
answer it’s obviously ridiculously incomplete. You’re not committing to
eat all delicious cake. You’re just highlighting that deliciousness was
among the most salient reasons to you for why you ate this particular
cake.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think you can tie yourself into logical knots very easily this way,
but it’s still worth asking why you do things, and you can ask why those
are motivating, etc. Some of htese will feel like more purely
instrumental, some will feel more purely terminal, although most of them
it will feel like you’re missing something.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I notice if I try to come up with a list of things that you get at
the end of a chain of whys it doesn’t bottom out at a very large number
of different things. e.g. I might come up with something like:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because it was interesting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because it was funny&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-27-10:24.html"&gt;because
I was horny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because it made something less distressing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because it was comforting in some way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-29-10:40.html"&gt;it
needed to be done&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;out of some sort of weird hard to understand compulsion&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I often experience “because it was delicious” and a lot
of adjacent things like this actually. I find deliciousness initially
motivating but it seems hard for me to treat this as the actual reason I
continue eating the food. It might be the reason I go back for seconds.
There’s something weird going on here though.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is in no way a complete list)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I notice that it’s relatively hard for me to treat something like
“because it would bring me joy” as a motivating reason. Like… there’s
something vaguely uncomfortable about that as an answer and I feel like
I almost deflect it with some sort of interstitial answer. Like… if you
asked me why I pet a cat, I would answer “because it was cute and
fuzzy”. It feels somehow unnatural to take the next step. I don’t know
that that’s necessarily wrong, in the same way that you &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/a-good-start"&gt;feed the beggar
because he is hungry&lt;/a&gt; but there’s &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; weird there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think as useful a tool of introspection as “Why?” is, I think maybe
the problem is that it assumes a causal structure that isn’t there. You
don’t do things for reasons, reasons are things that you use to explain
the things you do. In some global sense, the reason you do anything is
that it fits naturally into the practical activities of your life at
that point there. You can do the dishes for a reason, or you can just do
the dishes because the dishes are what you do now. You can pet a cat
because it brings you joy or because it is cute and fuzzy or you can
just pet a cat.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reasons for doing things aren’t something you need when your life is
functioning fluidly on its own. They’re a tool to fix when it isn’t, or
to communicate something to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But… I do often find myself casting around for reasons. Why? Partly
because it’s interesting, but mostly because I am distressed and I am
trying to understand so I can reduce this distress.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the other fake but useful distinctions in this space is the
idea that you have ends and you have means and they’re distinct. You can
partly see this because of all the implicit constraints on means - you
can achieve an end you want through undesirable means. You could argue
that this is just that you have multiple ends, and that’s certainly
true, but I don’t think it’s unreasonable to think that using a
particular means can be an end in itself. If you’ve got a skillset, you
probably enjoy using that skillset, and that enjoyment is pretty close
to a terminal end.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This comes up a lot in programming. e.g. I like using the union/find
algorithm to solve problems. Why? I think it’s neat. I enjoy using it.
Like yes I &lt;em&gt;suppose&lt;/em&gt; you could describe that as my terminal end
being joy, but it feels weird to reduce my motivations here. The joy
&lt;em&gt;describes the action&lt;/em&gt;, it doesn’t justify it. It’s the same as
petting the cat: I do it because the cat is fuzzy and the algorithm is
neat.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of why I’ve been thinking about this at the moment is that I’ve
been noticing that there are all sorts of… free floating wants, that
seem attached to a specific action but has no really clear “why?”
associated with it. I think this is what David Chapman calls a &lt;a href="https://buddhism-for-vampires.com/hunting-the-shadow"&gt;velleity&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It would be uncouth to point out that &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Velleity"&gt;this is a Western
philosophical term&lt;/a&gt;, a discipline that David Chapman &lt;a href="https://meaningness.substack.com/p/four-kinds-of-philosophy-i-dont-do"&gt;heartily
rejects&lt;/a&gt;, so I will.&lt;/span&gt; but if so it feels like they are
more complicated than I’d believed. A velleity is “the lowest degree of
volition, a slight wish or tendency” but this doesn’t feel necessarily
like it’s small. It can feel actually quite strong, but it feels strong
in a way that doesn’t motivate action, or that feels like it requires &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-17-11:40.html"&gt;permission
to act&lt;/a&gt; in some way that’s missing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example I’ve been &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-02-18:59.html"&gt;thinking
about anecdotes recently&lt;/a&gt; and one of the problems I keep running into
is &lt;em&gt;when do I tell anecdotes&lt;/em&gt;? And why? My writing is actually
fairly peppered with anecdotes, but that’s fine because they’re there
with a clear purpose. But… I don’t know, can you just &lt;em&gt;tell people
things&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It feels like I’ve got a bunch of free floating anecdotes that are
just sitting around with nothing clear to do. Means without an end
attached to them. And I… think I’d like to share them? Or do something
with them in some way?&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;The complexity here is that there are a bunch of them
that are quite embarrassing or shameful, either for me or for other, and
I don’t know that sharing is what I want to do with them but if it’s not
then I &lt;em&gt;don’t know what to do&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; They feel like they have to be
&lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; something, but I don’t have a thing that they’re for.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Harry Frankfurt thinks we take on final ends for instrumental
purposes to avoid being bored, but I think there’s another missing move:
Sometimes we take on ends because we’ve got these means we want to use,
and we choose them first and then set out to find reasons to use
them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Except… I don’t think I know how to do that. Maybe the answer is just
make them into art, but I struggle with art at the best of times.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is very much a half completed thought, but I think I need to
finish here and sleep on the rest of this.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-04-13:33.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-05-10:53.html</id>
    <title>Sources, Sinks, and Flows</title>
    <updated>2025-04-05T11:26:12+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Sources, Sinks, and Flows&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is going to be a very computer flavoured self help post.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here, for you, is a very useful general organising principle, which
is that there is &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt;, and there are things that &lt;em&gt;operate
on stuff&lt;/em&gt;&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Those things, can themselves, be stuff, although usually
at any given level of representation it’s not helpful to consider them
as part of the stuff being operated on.&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sources&lt;/em&gt; are where stuff comes from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sinks&lt;/em&gt; are where stuff goes to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Flows&lt;/em&gt; are what guide stuff between sources to sinks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often there are different types of stuff. For example, you can view
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-23-21:48.html"&gt;my
process for cleaning the kitchen&lt;/a&gt; through this lens, and two types of
stuff here are &lt;em&gt;clean dishes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Which further subdivide into &lt;em&gt;wet clean dishes&lt;/em&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;dry clean dishes&lt;/em&gt;, but that’s mostly not relevant for the
process which stops at the point where they’re left for air drying.&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dirty
dishes&lt;/em&gt;. The sink is, appropriately, a sink for dirty dishes, but it
is a source for clean dishes. One flow in this system is the process of
washing up by which dirty dishs go into the sink and clean dishes come
out.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’m being a bit imprecise about all of this. I recommend
not worrying about it.&lt;/span&gt;. There are plenty others -
e.g. there are sources of dirty dishes on the dining room table, which
flow to sinks (not usually the literal sink) in the kitchen, from which
they flow through to one of various sinks for dirty dishes (literal sink
or dishwasher) until they come out clean, from where they flow to one of
various sinks for clean dishes (a place where they can sit to air
dry).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often when systems don’t work it’s due to badly designed flows.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example: I talked in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-30-11:41.html"&gt;Necessity
creates possibility&lt;/a&gt; about my new writing habit of writing down ideas
when they occur to me, and then using that to figure out how to write
about.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;That habit has broken down a bit and needs tinkering. I
didn’t, it turns out, have a good system for what happens when the list
fills up.&lt;/span&gt; What was happening there is that I
had good sources of ideas to write about (they come to me when e.g. in
the shower, on a walk, doing the dishes, talking to someone), but there
was no reliable flow directing them to the sink for ideas to write about
(the actual process of writing). Introducing a written list creates a
reliable flow by means of adding a persistent queue to the process
rather than just having them fall into the sink of forgetting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the problem is that there are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good flows, but
they direct your sources to sinks you don’t want them to go. e.g. I find
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-06-12:00.html"&gt;drifting&lt;/a&gt;
often plays out this way. If I block myself from the internet, suddenly
all the attention that was flowing into the “idly scrolling” sink stops
vanishing down an infinite black hole of distraction and I just start
spontaneously doing stuff.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And sometimes the problem is that there aren’t any sinks that you
want things to go into, and as a result the source gets stifled.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of what I’m pointing at with the “means and ends” thing in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-04-13:33.html"&gt;Why do
you do things?&lt;/a&gt; is that sometimes you need to create outlets that
don’t exist. A sink that it feels actually worthwhile for your source to
flow into. Like… imagine having all of these shower thoughts and
conversations and so on and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; writing about them? I bet most
of you don’t have to imagine very hard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One easy fix I have access to is creating discord channels. I
suddenly got much better at remembering my dreams when we created a
#dreams channel to report dreams into&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’ve lost the habit of this. I should get back into
it.&lt;/span&gt; I’ve created an
#anecdotes channel for similar stories about our lives to see if that
helps here.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;NB neither of these channels are publicly accessible to
people immediately joining the discord.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general it seems to me that there’s something unhealthy about
getting &lt;em&gt;stuck&lt;/em&gt;, and that if you have a regular source of stuff
being produced, it needs an outlet to go somewhere. If you don’t find
somewhere good for it to go, it will probably go somewhere bad instead,
and that seems like a problem worth solving.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-05-10:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-06-09:41.html</id>
    <title>Good queues and bad queues</title>
    <updated>2025-04-06T16:49:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Good queues and bad queues&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a follow on from &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-05-10:53.html"&gt;Sources,
Sinks, and Flows&lt;/a&gt; and won’t make much sense if you haven’t read
that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An important category in this model is the &lt;em&gt;queue&lt;/em&gt;. A queue is
basically a source/sink pair in which stuff does nothing except enter
and then leave at some point later.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some queues are bad. Some queues are good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me give you some examples:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A literal queue of people waiting to be seen at the shops is a
queue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The kitchen cleaning example has a lot of queues in it. Dirty dishes
first move to the kitchen counter, where they are buffered until they
are ready to be washed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The place where I write down ideas for what to write is a
queue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That growing pile of papers that has been sitting ever grosing
somewhere in your office waiting to be dealt with is also a queue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The storage space in your attic that you keep putting stuff into
because you don’t want to get rid of it but also don’t actually know
what to do with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m using “queue” somewhat informally here, as not all of these have
FIFO (first-in/first-out) behaviour. Please ignore that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of these are very good because they improve the smooth flow of
stuff through the system. You can get one task done before having to
start on the next (imagine if you had to hand wash every dish as soon as
you brought in into the kitchen rather than cleaning the dining room
table first), and you can parallelise it (one person brings stuff into
the kitchen, another washes).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The place where I write down ideas is also a pretty good queue, but
it has a significant problem viewed as a queue: If the only way for
items to come off the queue is for me to write something, items are
being added to the queue much more often than they are being removed
from it, and this causes the queue to grow unboundedly. My current
solution to this is that when the list fills up I start a new list and
copy over anything from the old list that still feels appealing.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;What will happen when all of the ideas seem appealing?
Uhhh. Hope that doesn’t happen and if it does I guess I’ll just have to
write more?? Problem for future David.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The pile of papers on your desk? That’s a bad queue. That queue is
not working.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The two key features needed for a queue to be a good queue are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over some suitable period of time, as much has to come out of the
queue as go into it. If you put stuff into a queue to “deal with it
later”, &lt;em&gt;you have to actually deal with it later&lt;/em&gt;, and the rate
at which you deal with it must exceed the rate at which you create stuff
to deal with.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;As the &lt;a href="https://x.com/tef_ebooks/status/875882791954677761"&gt;sage tells
us&lt;/a&gt;, basic queueing theory means that queues either grow unboundedly
over time or reliably return to empty.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The queue must either &lt;em&gt;not fill up&lt;/em&gt; during the gap between
stuff entering it and stuff leaving it, or you must have some graceful
process for handling when it does.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Which can, and sometimes should, be “you start throwing
stuff away”. This is particularly a good idea for queues of ideas of
stuff to do.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The biggest failure mode of queues is that often we introduce queues
into our flows because &lt;em&gt;we don’t want to deal with the thing&lt;/em&gt;.
When this happens, the queue makes our life worse rather than better,
because instead of having a small amount of stuff we don’t want to deal
with we have a large amount of stuff we don’t want to deal with, and the
result is our environment acquires a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-06-09:51.html"&gt;fnord&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, for stuff you’re perfectly happy to and have the
capacity to deal with, a queue is often extremely useful for smoothing
out irregularities - when you’ve got large bursts of production and a
more gradual process of consumption such as in the dishes example - or
to more efficiently connect up sources and sinks so that stuff doesn’t
get lost and you don’t have to frantically multitask between different
types of activity.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-06-09:41.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-07-17:35.html</id>
    <title>Digital object permanence</title>
    <updated>2025-04-07T18:07:38+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Digital object permanence&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here’s a useful idea that I often mention in passing and people seem
to find helpful but I don’t think have ever written down as its own
thing: Digital objects lack object permanence. That is, they stop
existing for you when you stop looking at them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I first started noticing this with the kindle. I like having physical
books partly because I can stop reading them and they don’t go away and
I can pick them up later. It’s vastly easier for me to juggle multiple
physical books because they’re real in a way that digital ones aren’t.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is aggravated by Kindle’s library management being
terrible, but I think it would happen even without that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve also noticed this with e.g. things I’m writing. I have many half
abandoned Google docs with stuff I was writing that felt very important
at the time and I just forgot. In contrast, I relatively rarely forget
e.g. the essay I’m currently writing on my typewriter, because it’s
right there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Conversely though, I also never really forget about this notebook, or
my substack to a lesser degree. I sometimes go long periods without
touching them but that’s not because they stop existing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think they have two major features that cause this to happen:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rather than being objects, they are &lt;em&gt;places&lt;/em&gt;, and they are
places where I put public content, so an object that goes into them
&lt;em&gt;doesn’t need&lt;/em&gt; to be permanent to me, because it exists for other
people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They act as &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-05-10:53.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;sinks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
for when I want to think about something in writing, so there is a
natural thing that keeps me coming back to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Digital places that act as sources also seem to have a degree of
permanence, but I find it often feels like it achieves that permanence
through addiction. You’re not going to forget that Twitter exists,
because you’ve got a twitchy reflex to click it. I think you probably
&lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; have digital places that act as non-addictive sources, but
it doesn’t seem to be where we’ve ended up in design space. I think some
of that is just incentive following, but it does feel genuinely
hard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I like to think my discord server managed to be a place that achieves
its permanence through non-addictive means, but based on some people’s
relationships to it I’m not sure it does that reliably.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-07-17:35.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-07-18:38.html</id>
    <title>Python has structural pattern matching</title>
    <updated>2025-04-07T18:47:25+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Python has structural pattern matching&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hey, did you know that this works?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class="pycon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; from dataclasses import dataclass
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; @dataclass
... class Foo:
...     x: int
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; @dataclass
... class Bar:
...     x: str
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; match Foo(x=1):
...     case object(x=x):
...         print(x)
...
1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; match Bar(x=1):
...     case object(x=2):
...         print(x)
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; match Bar(x=1):
...     case object(x=x):
...         print(x)
...
1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; match Bar(x=1):
...     case object(x=2):
...         print(x)
...     case object(x=1):
...         print("hello!")
...
hello!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can use “object” as a matcher to match based solely on whether a
value being passed in has a particular field, and you can descend into
the value of those fields with other match expressions as you like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Python’s pattern matching is a bit of a weird beast because those
things in a case expression that look like constructor parameters are
nothing of the sort, they’re just fields, and they don’t have any
relationship to the type you’re matching on, they’ll just bind to the
field of that name on the object being matched &lt;em&gt;and the match will
fail if the field is not present&lt;/em&gt;. The type you’re matching on is
just an instanceof check&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And, of course, &lt;a href="https://www.hillelwayne.com/post/python-abc/"&gt;that instanceof
check doesn’t have to be a real instanceof check and can use ABC
subclass nonsense&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and doesn’t have anything to do with
the fields.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, you can use an &lt;code&gt;object&lt;/code&gt; match (or any other
type you want to match on) with arbitrary fields, and the match
expression will check for the presence of the field.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In some sense this is how it &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; to work but it was
non-obvious to me that it would work. In particular I thought there was
a decent chance that this would raise an AttributeError if you tried to
match on a missing field, but instead it handles that and you get
arbitrary structural pattern matching on record types if you want
it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can’t decide if this is cool or gross or both. More importantly, I
can’t actually think of a case where I’d actually need to use this
feature. I think it definitely straddles the line between “weird hack”
and “genuinely interesting language feature”, but because we’ve mostly
moved away from duck typing in Python, and because most of my usage of
pattern matching is effectively with closed algebraic data types, I
can’t actually immediately think of many places I’d want to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-07-18:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-08-09:56.html</id>
    <title>Asking for purpose disrupts action</title>
    <updated>2025-04-08T13:46:24+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Asking for purpose disrupts action&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was feeling unmotivated by my back collection of suggested writing
topics so I decided to try flicking through Hasok Chang’s “Realism for
Realistic People” for inspiration, and I found a useful distinction that
I think helps untangle one piece of what I was pointing at in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-04-13:33.html"&gt;Why do
you do things?&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He makes the distinction between the “inherent aim” and “external
functions” of an activity, using the example of lighting a match. If
asked why you are moving a match in a particular way across a surface,
your answer is simply “to light the match”. You can explain things in
more detail - why holding it at this particular angle helps, why you
have to move fast rather than slow, etc. but it is all relative to to
the specific goal of trying to get a match lit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also ask “Why are you lighting a match?”, to which the answer
might be “I’m trying to light a bunsen burner” or “I’m trying to figure
out how matches work” or “I like the pretty flames”. These are the
&lt;em&gt;extenral functions&lt;/em&gt; of the activity of lighting a match.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is as part of trying to point to what a well-defined activity
is, and the inherent aim is part of what constitutes something being a
particular activity. There is an action of “lighting a match” that you
can do more or less well, independently of the external functions of the
activity.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is of course not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; true. If you’re
trying to learn how matches work, your external function actually
includes lighting matches badly as well as well, because you want to
know what doesn’t work as well what does work. In contrast, if you’re
trying to light a bunsen burner, you just want to light a match well. I
think this is fine though - “lighting a match badly” can I think
legitimately be argued as a distinct activity that you can succeed or
fail at, even if it can externally look the same as trying to light a
match well and failing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In “Games: Agency as Art”, C Thi Nguyen talks about games as an
example of taking on &lt;em&gt;disposable ends&lt;/em&gt;. A game is an adoption of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lusory_attitude"&gt;the lusory
attitude&lt;/a&gt; - a voluntary attempt to overcome unnecessary obstacles.
This lusory attitude is one of voluntarily taking on the activity of
playing the game. With that activity, the &lt;em&gt;inherent aim&lt;/em&gt; is to
score the most points (or achieve some other victory condition). The
external function of the game might be to have fun, to spend time with
your friends, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you focus on those external functions of the game as primary it
can disrupt your abiltiy to play the game, which in turn can disrupt the
ability to achieve those external functions.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Except this isn’t quite true! For example, when Dave and
I play Root together, we often will go “This is probably a bad plan, but
it would be funny…” and take a move that from the perspective of the
game is clearly a suboptimal choice. I also do this in Slay the Spire
pretty regularly. The external function can inform choices in the game,
but I think it does this by changing the game you play. After making a
funny but suboptimal move, you go back to sincerely trying to win the
game.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nguyen points this out as an interesting and unusual feature of
games, but actually I think maybe it’s not. I think it is &lt;em&gt;often&lt;/em&gt;
the case that focusing on the external functions of the activity is
disruptive to the activity itself.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Sometimes that activity needs disruption of course. If
you’re doing the wrong thing, thinking about the external functions will
help you realise that and stop you doing the wrong thing. That’s
disruptive, because you’re doing something that should be disrupted!&lt;/span&gt; Being able to focus on a
singular goal and smoothly trying to achieve it allows you to enter an
effective flow state around that goal, and only when it is completed do
you find yourself returning to the question of why you were doing this
in the first place. If you try to act with the full set of external
functions of your activity in mind, most of the time you’ll fail to act
fluidly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This, to me, I think does a better job of capturing the right sorts
of distinctions that I want to make about why we do things. You can talk
about activities, and their aims, and how they fit together, and having
the notion of an activity effectively creates boundaries in the chain of
whys. Every end is terminal &lt;em&gt;while you are immersed in an activity
with it as its aim&lt;/em&gt;, and only on emerging from the activity (either
at its natural completion or as the result of some disruption) do you
ask how it fits into the broader patterns of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-08-09:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-09-18:44.html</id>
    <title>When I learned to read</title>
    <updated>2025-04-09T19:57:09+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;When I learned to read&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently Dave, Lisa, and I, were all helping sort through my parents’
giant boxes of books that have been sitting untouched for years to
decades. We were sorting them into various dubious ontologies - roughly…
worth keeping, worth trying to sell, worth giving away, bin. Dave and
Lisa in particular were trying to hunt out any gems that looked worth
selling.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point, Lisa hands me this tiny battered book of some cheap
adventure novel and said “Well, this one isn’t worth anything to
anyone.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She was, I think, unprepared for the look of absolute delight on my
face as I grabbed it off her. “I’ve been trying to find this for so
long!” I said.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let me backtrack 35 years or so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s extremely on brand that one of my first really coherent memories
is of learning to read in my head.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My school had a reading system. It was a whole thing - there was a
box of books, you picked what book you wanted, then you had to read it,
log your reading of it, and return it when you were done.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It may surprise you to know that I &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt; this. I dragged my
heels over it and had to be nagged into reading. Couldn’t stand reading,
me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, one evening I was reading out loud to mum, begrudgingly, and
complained about this. I don’t remember my specific complaint, but she
told me that I didn’t have to read out loud to her if I didn’t want to,
I could just read books in my head. I said “Oh, OK!” or words to that
effect, sent her away, and finished the book.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It didn’t take me long to finish the rest of the books in that box
after that, and I quickly turned from a kid who hated reading to one who
was regularly getting through giant doorstopper books.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Not, you understand, good ones. I read a lot of Robert
Jordan and Brian Lumley (don’t tell my parents about the second one.
They were not age appropriate) and other authors of similar quality
levels. My love of SFF trash continues to this day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was a pretty life-defining moment - I’m sure I’d have had it at
some point, but that was the specific point at which I had it, and it
sticks in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could even tell you quite a lot about the book that I was reading.
It was quite a short book, about some British soldier who is trying to
ship logs down from a mountain and wants to pass them through some
underground river, but they get lost in the middle, so he rides a log
through and finds a giant whirlpool there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried multiple times over the years to find it - asked around on
reddit, did a bunch of searching. Never could find it. I can’t remember
if I ever asked Claude or ChatGPT, but just testing it now Claude
straight up hallucinates an answer.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It says that it’s Rudyard Kipling’s “The Man Who Would
Be King”. It’s not.&lt;/span&gt; I’d asked my parents
about it but they had no specific memory of this event at all, let alone
what the book was.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was for a while half-convinced this was a fake memory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And then, totally unexpectedly, Lisa just handed me the book.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;“But David”, you may ask, “if it was a book from the
school reading box, why did &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; have it? That is an excellent
question. I have no idea. But it does have a sticker on it with my
school form so I’m pretty sure I should have returned it to a box and
didn’t.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is another variant on the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-07-17:35.html"&gt;digital
object permanence&lt;/a&gt; thing. If I’d read this book on a kindle, there is
no chance that I would ever have found in this way,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I mean I could have searched in my kindle library, but
do you want to take a bet that Amazon will maintain another 35 years of
continuity of archive? Admittedly they’re doing OK with the 15 they’ve
got so far, but I am not wildly confident. They also have a history of
disappearing things that you’ve bought.&lt;/span&gt; but
because the book just exists as a physical object in the world, it could
just stick around in my parents’ house until I found it again.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It wasn’t even the only book I found this way! I was
also trying and failing to remember the name of Karen Traviss’s &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wess%27Har"&gt;Wess’har books&lt;/a&gt;, and
found “City of Pearl” there, which helped me track down the whole
thing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The book is “The Cave of Death”, by Ian Serrallier. It’s very little
wonder that I couldn’t find it, because it barely exists. It’s part of
the “Wide Horizon Reading Scheme”, which I can provide very little
evidence of being a real thing that really existed other than a
scattering of other books with the same labelling. It’s a retelling of a
story originally written by J. H. Williams, in “In Quest of a Mermaid”.
I originally thought it was an extract, and felt moderately grumpy about
Ian Serraillier taking credit for it by being the only name on the
cover, but actually having now acquired a copy of the original, it seems
to be the same story entirely rewritten. I assume to make it more
self-contained and accessible to children, but I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s in many ways quite an interesting story. It’s very “boys own
adventures” and quite colonialist, but… fundamentally it’s a children’s
story about an engineering problem, and that feels rare to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even the colonialism is surprisingly interesting - yes, it’s a book
about a white British soldier leading a team of “natives” in Burma,
assisted by a bunch of itinerant Chinese workers. Yes, there’s a whole
bunch of racial stereotyping going on it. But… the fundamental message
about race relations in it seems to be “different cultures have
different beliefs, but they’re generally still good people, and you’ve
got to respect their beliefs in order to work with them”. I’m not going
to claim it’s completely unproblematic - the author would certainly get
cancelled for writing such a book today - but it genuinely seems like
quite a positive message for its time and probably quite a lot better
than many things written today.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And way less bad than, say, Narnia. All of this would
have completely gone over my head at the time though, as evidenced by
the fact that I was &lt;em&gt;living in Saudi Arabia&lt;/em&gt; when reading the
Narnia books and didn’t notice the islamaphobia. In my defence I also
didn’t notice the Christianity.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I think the really interesting thing for me about this whole
thing is not the specific book, but the degree to which figuring out
your past is just intertwined with actual mundane history, and how much
of history is bordering on lost because it’s not, as Lisa said, really
worth anything to anyone. This is an obscure book from an obscure
series. Of course I couldn’t find it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Except, of course, I totally could have. I bet you if I found a
research librarian and gave them a couple hundred pounds, they’d have
found the book for me in a few weeks, especially these days. I’m not
sure this possibility even really occurred to me as a live one, but in
retrospect it was very possible. I find these sorts of questions
interesting - things which clearly have an empirical answer, and finding
out the empirical answer is entirely within your means,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although! This is only true in this case &lt;em&gt;if the
answer is positive&lt;/em&gt;. If it turns out I’d dreamed the whole thing and
the book didn’t exist, establishing that with any degree of certainty
would be very costly.&lt;/span&gt; but
it’s just not clearly worth it. My go to example of this is look at a
random person passing you on the street, what’s their name? You could
just go ask them. It would be weird, but they’d probably tell you.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And if they don’t, you can probably still find out!
Probably not ethically, possibly not without being arrested, but you
can.&lt;/span&gt; And yet you don’t do it, because the
question is just an idle fancy, and the effort isn’t worth it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it’s often worth doing things that seem like they’re not
worth it, and this seems like a potentially good learning opportunity.
Even if the answer to the question isn’t worth the cost, maybe the
experience of figuring out how to answer it is. If I’d thought to ask a
research librarian of some sort about this, yes they’d have found the
book, but also I’d have learned more about how to interact with research
librarians, and that would in and of itself been worth it even if
finding the book was not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if going to ask a random stranger on the street their
name would be a good experience in the same way, but it seems like it
might be. It seems harmless, and I think generally figuring out how to
take greyed out options is good for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think that, perhaps, it would be good to notice such questions as
they arise, and every now and then even if it doesn’t seem worth it to
try to answer the question, answer it anyway, and see how that changes
you.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-09-18:44.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-10-16:38.html</id>
    <title>The scent of reality</title>
    <updated>2025-04-10T16:38:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The scent of reality&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes when I’m alone, I like to smell myself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Usually I sniff my hands or arms (sometimes my armpits) because
that’s the most easily accessible way of doing this.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although, prompted by writing this, I did try sniffing
my foot. It’s an interesting experiment but not nearly as pleasant. I
probably won’t repeat it often. Also maybe I need to wash my feet more
thoroughly and/or go around barefoot more.&lt;/span&gt; I
also like smelling other people, but generally only do that with
partners.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why smell myself? Well, it’s weirdly comforting, for starters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think sometimes that’s because I smell of me - certainly that’s the
big benefit of sniffing my arms - but that’s not all of it. Hands often
pick up scents from what I’ve been interacting with, and that’s often
even more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, whenever I’ve been using a measuring tape, I’ve noticed
that my hands always end up smelling of a sort of metallic oil scent
that I pick up from it. I think that may even be where this habit
started. It’s an oddly charming smell. I could tell a story about
associating it with my father’s workshop and that might even be true,
but I mostly just think that it’s interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I get a similar effect from using the typewriter - my hands often
pick up a smell of typewriter from it. Typewriter and measuring tape are
very similar smells, although I think I could probably tell the
difference if I compared them side by side. I don’t know if different
typewriters smell different - very likely. I’ve got two measuring tapes
here next to me but they smell the same. They are from the same brand
and of similar vintages, so that makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right now, my left and right hands smell different, because prompted
by thinking about scent I put on my essential oil vaporiser with some
sandalwood and bergamot. I got some of the bergamot on my hands when I
was doing this, so on my left hand the scent is textured between
measuring tape and bergamot.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Sandalwood is a much thicker oil which will barely come
out of the bottle willingly, so doesn’t get all over you in the same
way.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Except… actually I’m not sure that’s bergamot I’m smelling. I don’t
know what it is. Some sort of essential oil fusion from the various
outsides of the bottles mixing together. I had a sniff of the vapouriser
directly (it’s not yet vapourising enough to give off the scent very
far) and it smells like earl grey tea, because obviously that’s what
bergamot smells like. I think what I’m getting off my hand is maybe…
lemongrass? Certainly seems plausible. I do have a lemongrass in my
collection, and I rarely use it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My ability to discern individual scents is surprisingly bad. I feel
like I should train it more.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At about this point in writing, the vapouriser got up enough heat
that I suddenly got hit by a wave of very recognisable earl grey
scent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, smell and taste have a lot of range, and I think it’s
actually quite easy to detect, it’s just that you very rarely receive
much training in it. I’d like to do more.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in, I think, 2019, I did a blind gin tasting for my family for
Christmas, where we tried a number of different gins.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And, because I’m a jerk, one vodka and one Seedlip
non-alcoholic spirit that I didn’t tell anyone were in the mix.&lt;/span&gt;
Many of my family believed previously they couldn’t tell the difference
between different gins, but when actually comparing them side by side I
think it quickly became apparent that actually all of the gins had quite
distinctive tastes, and they did have genuine preferences among them
that they hadn’t previously noticed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every time I do a blind gin taste testing we come to two
conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tanqueray is everyone’s first or second favourite gin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We do not agree about what our favourite gin is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, in the gin taste testing we did then, the one I liked
the most was Mason’s tea gin. I don’t think anyone else put it in their
top 3, but I thought that the addition of the tea flavour was really
interesting.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This post is perhaps suggesting that I’m more into tea
than I am, but on the other hand I am British so maybe it’s just
accurately reflecting my love of tea.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think, in general, with scents and flavours I’m drawn to
interesting and complex. There’s a running joke with my paretners that I
don’t like nice things, especially in drinks, because &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/meditations-on-taste"&gt;I’m drawn
to complex bitter herbal flavours&lt;/a&gt; but this is partly because there’s
so much going on in them and I really like that. In contrast, I find a
lot of ostensibly “nice” things just a bit boring.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This comes up a lot in scent as well as spirits. Air freshener scents
and other highly artificial scents are often very upsetting to me. Air
fresheners in bathrooms are often actively upsetting to me - I can
handle the naturally unpleasant smell of a bathroom, but I can’t handle
the fake floral scents that are being used to cover it up.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’m actually not wild about floral scents in general, at
least not inside.&lt;/span&gt;
Fake fruit is even worse - I had to ask my partners to change washing up
liquids quite early in our relationship because I absolutely couldn’t
handle the “apple blossom” scented atrocity that they used.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Complexity isn’t enough though. My personal vision of hell is walking
into a Lush, because I just get bombed in the face with a complete
cacocophony of scents. It’s certainly complex, but it’s just noise, it’s
got no depth to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this point by the way the candle in my vapouriser burned down (it
had a weirdly short wick from previous use and hadn’t been doing well)
so I replaced it with a new candle. This gave me a chance to smell the
hot wax. It’s standard paraffin wax rather than beeswax - I’ve
previously experimented with beeswax candles and learned to my surprise
that I actually prefer the smell of paraffin wax. I think of paraffin
wax as pretty odourless, but a good up close sniff makes it clear that
this isn’t the case. It’s a mild smell, but actually quite a pleasant
one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don’t know exactly what scent is doing for me in these cases. It
feels something like… connecting me up from the world I’m in. The world
feels real, and I a part of it, when I’m able to smell it, and it feels
like the strongest counter I have to just regarding myself as a pure
information processing unit that happens to exist in a physical
world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given that, it’s interesting that the scents I prefer seem to have
relatively little connection up to the “natural”. It feels like some
sort of expression of what the world I want to be connected up to is.
It’s real, and complex, but it’s very much the world that we built
rather than some pristine state of nature, and it feels good and real to
be a part of that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-10-16:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
