<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-04-27T08:52:02+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-19-10:52.html</id>
    <title>Notes on becoming a cis man</title>
    <updated>2020-04-25T14:51:48+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes on becoming a cis man&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Please note: I ask for clemency and/or good faith reading of this post. This is stuff that is difficult to talk about without stepping on someone's toes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Required prior reading:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://alexwlchan.net/2020/04/thinking-about-gender/"&gt;Lexie's post about why cis people should be allowed to think about gender too&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/05/the-inner-sense-of-gender/"&gt;The Inner Sense of Gender&lt;/a&gt; (this was in fact written based on a conversation with Lexie)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/06/on-not-quite-fitting/"&gt;On Not Quite Fitting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular this paragraph from Lexie's post is the prompt for this one:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do have some cis friends who’ve done deep introspection of their gender, and in doing so they became more sure that they were cis. I think they’d all agree the process was worthwhile – it gave them a better understanding of their gender, and how it affects them. But if they ever talk about this on the Internet, people tell them, “You’re trans, you just haven’t realised it yet”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm one of those cis friends, and I very much agree that it's worthwhile. I've also absolutely heard "You're trans, you just haven't realised it yet" (usually less bluntly than that, but I've also heard it that bluntly). Given how rarely this experience is talked about, I thought it might be useful to share some of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First off, some politics: My basic stance on transition is that if you want to do it, go for it, you're entitled to. There may be some sort of intrinsic transness vs cisness, I don't know, but I don't think it matters for the purposes of who gets to count as eligible to transition. Bodily autonomy is important, gender is a thing that it is good for people to experiment with if they want to, and people should be trusted to make their own decisions in this space.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In particular&lt;/em&gt; while I would never suggest this about any individual person (and indeed don't have anyone I even suspect of this) I'm morally certain that there are people out there who are at about the same point on the cis/trans spectrum as I am and have decided to transition. That's cool by me. It would both be inappropriate of me to police that, and also I wouldn't want to police that. It's just a thing that they're entitled to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I personally decided that transition wasn't the most useful route for me to go down and took an alternative path, but there's no reason other people should make the same decisions as me even presented with broadly the same experience of gender as I have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another political-ish note: I'm going to be disagreeing with some things some trans people say in this post. This can be dicey, but I feel reasonably confident in doing so because what I'm going to be disagreeing with his how they interpret &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; lived experience, not how they interpret theirs. Also, almost all of these are things that I've also talked extensively with other trans people about and largely agreed with them on - there's no broad consensus that I'm disagreeing with, we're just all figuring this out together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, on to the main point of this post...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I wrote "the inner sense of gender" I described myself as "almost certain that I am cis". This fluctuated a bit (both up and down) in the interim, and various people predicted that I would in the end decide I was trans, but I have largely largely settled on certainty that I am cis, at least to the degree that I think the question still makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I'm not sure it makes sense is that I'm increasingly unconvinced that gender is really a thing.
Many things are &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/09/gendering/"&gt;gendered&lt;/a&gt;, and that the orientation of gendering is kinda defined by the statistical differences between some sort of "archetypal cis" men and women, but that doesn't neatly fall into saying that there is any one thing that we might call gender. Gender isn't a linear progression from man to woman, it's more like a big ball of biopsychosocial... stuff. This is a lot of why my politics of transition are basically "bodily autonomy, end of story" (the other part is that gatekeeping is not a thing that has historically covered itself in glory in this space).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, to be concrete: My pronouns will remain he/him, I'm unlikely to engage in any major gender defiance regarding my aesthetic, and it's basically certain that I will never attempt any sort of medical transition (I'll confess to a certain amount of curiosity about the effects of hormones, but it really is just curiosity). To a very large degree I will continue to play the social role of man, and I will become increasingly comfortable with that (and also comfortable with ditching the bits of masculinity that I think are bullshit).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I still think if we had magic Culture level body changing tech I would experiment with other gender presentations, and I still think there's a decent chance that I might end up choosing a feminine or androgynous presentation as my default given that option, but I'd also like to be able to fly and the level of emotional significance these two facts hold is broadly equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What's changed?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, Lexie has been writing about &lt;a href="https://alexwlchan.net/2020/04/adventures-in-embodiment/"&gt;embodiment&lt;/a&gt; recently. I've been part of some of the conversations that prompted that, and have been working on it myself too. I've, sadly, not achieved the same level of euphoria, but I don't think this is a gender thing I just think euphoria is hard emotion for me to access (I'm working on it). I've specifically been working on it in the context of Focusing and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;my work on feelings&lt;/a&gt;, which has been extraordinarily helpful. I've also been working on it in the context of Alexander Technique and some of what I've been learning from that in the context of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-21-12:35.html"&gt;letting my body drive&lt;/a&gt; (one of the minor personal annoyances of the pandemic is that it's interrupted my study of this).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One side effect of this is that it has resulted in a great deal more comfort in my body, and reduced my dissociation from it. A lot of things that previously looked kinda like gender dysphoria turned out to be fantasies of "If only my body were completely different I'd be able to connect to it", but it turns out to be perfectly possible for me to connect to my body as it is, and to enjoy my experience of it, it's just quite hard work to acquire the skillset. It's possible that it would be easier if I transitioned (certainly it's a common reaction to going on estrogen, but I suspect that some of that is genuinely just that estrogen makes it easier to connect to your embodied emotional state), but transition doesn't, for me, seem at all necessary for reconnecting with my body.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also ties in to a lot of trauma. A thing that I saw on Twitter the other day (I don't want to refind the tweet because it's a general theme and I don't want to pick on her in particular) was a trans woman saying that one of the reasons why she knew she was trans was that "cis men don't typically experience their masculinity as traumatic" and... I'm sorry to report that this is not true. I'm not going to say that we experience exactly the same sort of traumas from it as trans women do (I'd be very surprised if we do, but I'd also be very surprised if there weren't some large overlap), but there is a great deal of trauma associated with cultural indoctrination into masculinity norms. Some of this is that &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/jiminy-cricket-must-die/"&gt;norm acquisition in general is traumatic&lt;/a&gt;, some of that is that many of our norms around masculinity are really quite bad.
Going through masculinity training just &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; traumatic. I expect the same is true for going through femininity training, though with a different specific traumas.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of my specific traumas around this are that many masculine norms are very violent, both literally and figuratively, and are quite damaging to be coerced into. Current western masculine norms are also very homophobic. This is both a problem if you're not actually straight (which I'm not), and if you just happen to have some more feminine traits (I perform masculinity reasonably well in some ways and quite badly in others - for example I'm much more into talking about feelings than I think even the average woman, let alone the average man).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, gender non-comformance is punished (both by people of the same gender and the opposite), and almost nobody is perfectly gender conformant, so most people will have gender related traumas. Unpacking some of mine was essential for acquiring a healthier relationship with masculinity (and part of that healthier relationship is boundaries! I'm now much happier saying "No, fuck off, that's a stupid way to be a man. Shan't." to the worse bits).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The final aspect for me has been sex. I've been having a lot of it over the last year or two, and it's been very helpful. I don't plan to go into details here, but I'll note a couple significant features.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First off, lets talk about autogynephilia. I basically agree with Scott Alexander on this: &lt;a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2020/02/10/autogenderphilia-is-common-and-not-especially-related-to-transgender/"&gt;Autogenderphilia is common and not especially related to transgender&lt;/a&gt;. I've had more than a few fantasies about myself as a woman. I've had more than a few fantasies about myself as a man. I am reasonably gender flexible in fantasy. It's fun and I don't intend to stop. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-27-08:18.html"&gt;Gender is sexy&lt;/a&gt; and fantasies are supposed to be sexy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you don't realise that this is a thing, it can be very confusing, and the way that literally everybody talks about it (from "autogynephilia isn't real" to "autogynephilia is the main reason people are trans". Both seem to be obviously false) is extraordinarily unhelpful for making sense of a perfectly healthy and common experience.
People do a lot of things in fantasies that they don't especially want to do in real life, and turning this into a whole big thing is a great way to confuse people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Secondly, a lot of gender related traumas are connected to sex. I don't want to go into details here, but they definitely were for me (it's less dramatic than you might be imagining from that). There is a lot of shame connected up with masculinity and desire, and acquiring a whole bunch of emotions skills while also having a whole bunch of sex was a great way to expose, confront, and defuse those.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, for me at least having a penis is fairly central to my experience of masculinity (I'm aware that this is complex for many trans people, so treat this as a personal claim, but I expect it's a personal claim a lot of cis men would make), so uh getting comfortable with using it was a pretty good way of getting comfortable with masculinity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally, sex ties in a lot to embodiment. In many ways the key to good sex is to embody well during it, so sex works very well for providing the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; for growth in this space (of course, finding people you feel &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safe&lt;/a&gt; with is equally important here).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;None of this has added up to me suddenly being completely clear or comfortable with my own gender or body, but I'm vastly more so than I've historically been, and I've acquired the skill set and the understanding that allows me to continually improve on that over time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, at this point, I am reasonably comfortable in saying that yes I've thought about my gender a lot and I have concluded that I am a cis man, and that I am confident that the more work I do in this space the more thoroughly I will come to understand and embody that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-19-10:52.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-20-10:52.html</id>
    <title>The Accelerator/Brake Model</title>
    <updated>2020-04-20T16:07:20+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The Accelerator/Brake Model&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2VOS9IK"&gt;Come As You Are&lt;/a&gt;, a book about sexuality (primarily women's sexuality, but it mostly works for everyone).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is by far the most &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-11-07:15.html"&gt;annoying&lt;/a&gt; book that I will nevertheless recommend. It was about 50% stuff I already knew (which I only skimmed but seemed pretty good), but the other 50% contained a lot of useful ideas that helped make sense of some things I only partially knew. It was also 100% annoying and I hated the author's writing style. I will grant I am not in the target audience for it (it is primarily written for women), but the friend who recommended it was a woman and she also hates the writing style so I don't think that's why, I just think it's objectively very annoying (especially if you're not from the USA).
Nevertheless, it was on balance very worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that was particularly helpful was the brake/accelerator model for sexual arousal. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The model is very simple: There are two systems, the Sexual Excitation System (SES), the accelerator, and the Sexual Inhibition System (SIS), the brake.
The SES is what turns you on, the SIS is what turns you off.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you're currently not interested in sex and you'd like to be, you need to understand which of these is at play:
It might be that your accelerator isn't being pushed by the current sexual context, or it might be that something is pressing hard on your brake.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Different people have different levels of sensitivity on each of the brake and accelerator. On average women have much more sensitive brakes (i.e. are much easier to turn off) and men have much more sensitive accelerators (i.e. are much more easy to turn on), but there's a lot of individual variation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the least helpful things you can do is make a mistake about which system is in play. It doesn't help to try to turn someone on if their foot is slammed hard on the brake, and it doesn't help to try to make someone comfortable and at ease if they're already fine and the problem is just that the context isn't at all arousing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The former is particularly bad, because pressure is one of the things most likely to activate someone's brakes, because it creates negative emotional association with the whole experience. It's also particularly common, because people (especially people who have relatively insensitive brakes, like most guys) often don't realise that the brake is a potential problem at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since reading about the brake/accelerator model I've been seeing it everywhere. I think a lot of motivation is like this, where there are things that we really want to do (the accelerator is on hard) but also procrastinate hard because there's a huge ugh field around the thing and we find it massively hard (so are the brakes) and we just end up with the gearbox in our head grinding.
In the same way as with sex, trying to want to do the thing even more isn't going to help, and treating it as an issue of motivation will just cause one to build up even more guilt and shame around the subject, making it even more aversive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This likely also ties in to the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety&lt;/a&gt; model of growth, where desire acts as the accelerator and a lack of safety acts as the brake (and indeed a lack of safety is often a major brake activator in a sexual context).
Given &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-19-10:52.html"&gt;the context&lt;/a&gt; in which I've been thinking about a lot of the personal growth work, it's probably not entirely a coincidence that these track.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-20-10:52.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-21-08:02.html</id>
    <title>Does a fish have a face?</title>
    <updated>2020-04-21T08:44:15+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Does a fish have a face?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-21&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm trying a new thing today, which is to integrate my daily notebook practice, my daily rereading practice, and a bit of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;randomization of decision making&lt;/a&gt;. I don't plan to do this every day, but I may do it more often.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic mechanism:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I pick a book of my choosing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I generate a page number uniformly at random from the main book contents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I pick an interesting passage and copy it out here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I then write something inspired by it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If this takes off I'll probably build some tooling into the notebook for getting me to do this properly but for now I'm mostly hand cranking it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is partly inspired by having recently-ish been listening to &lt;a href="https://www.harrypottersacredtext.com/"&gt;Harry Potter and the Sacred Text&lt;/a&gt;. I'm deeply indifferent to Harry Potter but have been enjoying their sacred text reading techniques. This process in particular is very loosely inspired by their (in turn somewhat loosely interpreted) practice of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lectio_Divina"&gt;Lectio Divina&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today's reading comes from &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3exHrih"&gt;Finding Our Sea Legs&lt;/a&gt;, page 126:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While he hedges his bets when it comes to dogs, it is hard to imagine Levinas having much time for the idea that a fish might have a face, or the idea that I could be infinitely responsible for a fish. Fish, as far as we human beings are concerned, are more alien to us than the stranger who knocks on our door, or the dog who wags his tail in greeting. They move in a different element, they have no lungs, their blood is cold, not warm, they do not sleep. And yet, while they may not have faces in the sense that Levinas means, they still hav efaces, in the ordinary everyday sense: We can look them in the eye, and these denizens of another world can look back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This might seem like a strange passage (of course fish have faces) but the idea of a "face" in this context is more about our experience of the other as a person. Backtracking to earlier in the book (pages 52-53) we have the following passage:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This curious and seemingly paradoxical idea of the 'face' is that the heart of Levinas's phenomenology of ethics. When we encounter the face of another [our relationship] is 'straightaway ethical.' When I encounter another person, I find myself responsible for them - I find myself unable to do anything other than to respond to them &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; another person - whether I like it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the question of whether a fish "has a face" is about whether our interactions with a fish have this phenomenological character: Do we treat a fish as a subject of ethical experience?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Experiences on this tend to differ, both by person and by context. Many people are vegetarian precisely because they experience animals as ethically relevant, and I know one person who as a child became vegetarian in a way that they literally framed as not wanting to eat anything with a face, a category in which they included fish.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Personally, I don't consider fish to be all that ethically relevant (oddly, I consider animals more ethically relevant than fish and yet I eat animals and mostly don't eat fish. This is primarily for environmental reasons though). I will not mourn the death of a fish. And yet, encountering a fish out of water, gasping on dry land, it is hard not to feel sorry for it.
In the abstract, I don't care about the fish, but confronted with the actual reality of the fish and its suffering, it is hard not to experience it as ethically relevant, as having a face.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Almost (I may have been subconsciously inspired in my choice of book) entirely coincidentally, yesterday I was listening to &lt;a href="https://www.preposterousuniverse.com/podcast/2019/02/18/episode-34-paul-bloom-on-empathy-rationality-morality-and-cruelty/"&gt;the Mindscape podcast episode with Paul Bloom&lt;/a&gt;, the author of &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2xCBEYd"&gt;Against Empathy&lt;/a&gt; (which I haven't read).
His essential argument is that this empathic experience leads us astray from good ethical behaviour. It causes us to overfocus on the individual in front of us - this empathy is what causes us to treat the fish as ethically relevant even if we don't "rationally" believe it to be. It's what causes us to be kind to our neighbour but ignore millions of people living in poverty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also what causes us to overvalue people like us and undervalue people different to us - it's much easier to be empathic to someone whose lived experience we can easily understand, and if we tie our ethics to our empathy then we will tend to prioritise those like us and neglect the Other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, one can bite this philosophical bullet and say that yes we should be rational in our ethics but also we should consider fish as ethically relevant. This is how you end up with things like &lt;a href="https://concepts.effectivealtruism.org/concepts/wild-animal-suffering/"&gt;Effective Altruists who are very concerned about wild animal suffering&lt;/a&gt;. It's possibly they're right - I don't agree with their concerns, but I don't think they're in principle invalid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think he has a point, and that a certain amount of rationality and deliberation in ethics is important, but I think too much of that will drive us towards utilitarianism, which is more like &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-18-11:10.html"&gt;policy&lt;/a&gt; than the sort of living ethics that I think improves our behaviour in day to day life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's worth using rationality as a tool to improve our ethical behaviour, but &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-14-13:56.html"&gt;emotion is key to effective rationality&lt;/a&gt;, and empathy and the experience of the other is a crucial tool in navigating any sort of rational ethics.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-21-08:02.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-22-08:31.html</id>
    <title>Power, baby, power</title>
    <updated>2020-04-22T14:08:40+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Power, baby, power&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-22&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm continuing the theme of notebook posts prompted by random passages from books. I've also decided to deliberately do this on books that aren't from my daily rereading practice to try and use it to integrate some of the books I read less often into my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-13-11:35.html"&gt;memetic domus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today's reading comes from "I'm very into you", which is a collection of correspondences between &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kathy_Acker"&gt;Kathy Acker&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McKenzie_Wark"&gt;McKenzie Wark&lt;/a&gt;. This section comes from Page 59. I also randomly selected a line (line 8) because Acker apparently hates paragraphs and this made it hard to select a passage manually.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember going to some Pomo conference Sylvère had a hand in, the early days, and that creep [Bernard Henri] Levy gives a speech (after Sollers has done his usual blather) all about Eve coming out of the rib of Adam, and therefore and therefore... So XXXXXX, very beautiful, asks him a question. Then she disappears. An hour or two later, she reappearing, we ask XXXXXX where she's been. "With Levy." "Why?" "Power, baby, power."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two things most strike me about this exchange:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; unsurprising, despite how nice it would be to imagine that human nature doesn't work this way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It strikes me as very gendered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm interested in unpacking the gendered nature of it. I can just about imagine (possibly inaccurately) the script playing out this way if both people involved were women, or both people involved were men, but the thing I can't imagine is it playing out that way if the speaker was a woman and XXXXXX was a man.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specifically what I can't imagine about it is not that a male XXXXXX wouldn't have been attracted to the powerful woman, but that he would so freely admit it. I genuinely don't know whether it's typical for men to experience power as attractive in a woman (my guess would be yes, but I don't really understand either men or attraction well enough to predict this confidently), but it definitely feels off script for men to &lt;em&gt;admit&lt;/em&gt; that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My impression is that the official cultural script for men being attracted to powerful women is that it's a shame/submission thing. The domme is the official script for the powerful woman who wields power in a sexy manner, and an intrinsic part of the sexiness of this script is partly that you're going off the official gendered script.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have at least two easily available hypotheses for why this is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power is coded masculine (perhaps because of a mix of patriarchy and more general &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/09/gendering/"&gt;gendering&lt;/a&gt;), so power intrinsically feeds in to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-27-08:18.html"&gt;competent performance of a masculine aesthetic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power is just attractive in general and men are supposed to pretend it's not because of masculine bullshit about how we're supposed to be the ones having power over others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A third possibility is that I'm just wrong and this would have played out exactly the same way when gender flipped. I don't &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; this is the case, but even if it is I'm interested in where I've got these scripts from.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One reason power might be intrinsically sexy is its streamlining nature for a lot of the process of generating attraction. In the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-31-09:52.html"&gt;mutual escalation&lt;/a&gt; that is flirting, one of the things that slows it down is a safety aspect - not so much physical safety (also that, but that's not the thing that's directly relevant here). People are hesitant in escalation because of fear of rejection and consequences, and power acts as a certain shield to that. Power essentially lets you take shortcuts in the flirting process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of those shortcuts are bad but work, because they involve violating boundaries because you know you can get away with it. Violating boundaries is another of those things which it would be nice to pretend doesn't work but actually does - the reason not to do it is &lt;em&gt;unethical&lt;/em&gt;, not that it doesn't work. e.g. just kissing someone fairly early on in the process whether they want you to or not is a pretty effective way of polarizing and finding out if they're into it. You shouldn't do it, but if you're powerful you can probably get away with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may partly explain the gendered nature of power as sexy - in gender training women get trained not to enforce their boundaries, and men get trained to enforce them too rigidly and interpret anything as an attack. If you do this to a woman, you might get away with it. If you do this to a man, you might get punched.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also, perhaps, explains part of why so many men with power end up turning out to be sexual predators - they've essentially learned that violating boundaries will get them sex. My guess is that many of these men didn't &lt;em&gt;start out&lt;/em&gt; rapey, their sense of appropriate behaviour just gradually eroded over time. This doesn't absolve them of responsibility - their actions were still ultimately unethical - but it puts an interesting spin on it. Are we actively training people with power to be ethically worse? If so, what can we do about it? Relying on people with power to be virtuous enough to resist that training doesn't seem like a good solution.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-22-08:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-23-07:48.html</id>
    <title>Proportionality and identity</title>
    <updated>2020-04-23T12:08:45+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Proportionality and identity&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today's reading comes from &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2VMdTVs"&gt;Random Justice: On Lotteries and Legal Decision-Making&lt;/a&gt;, page 75-76:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;random selection is intended to provide defendants and litigants with the opportunity to be tried by a representative cross-section of the population. The idea here is that fair and democratic social arrangements require that people be accorded the chance to be tried by juries drawn from a cross-sectionally representative pool. That a randomly selected jury will provide the opportunity to be tried by a representative cross-section of the population is, however, by no means guaranteed. [...] a perfectly representative sample is the average ideal of many random samples of a population and is not to be expected in any particular randomly drawn sample - or on any particular petit jury. Perhaps most importantly of all, even if random selection were to yield a jury perfectly representative of the population, the appropriateness of the outcome might still be contested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is actually a really excellent point for tying together a number of my interest areas.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular it prompts me to think about:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The difference between statistical fairness and individual fairness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What "representative" really means.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is representativeness good?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The interplay between justice and identity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The role of legibility in diversity initiatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As is well known &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2013/09/towards-a-more-perfect-democracy/"&gt;I'm rather a big fan of random selection&lt;/a&gt;, and one of the reasons for it is the guaranteed proportionality properties of it. However, there are some major distinctive features of juries compared to the situations I've focused on that I'd not previously appreciated until reading this passage just now (despite having read it before!).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First off, consider the difficulty of representativeness. Say we've got 12 jurors. Any group whose prevalence in the population is not a multiple of \(\frac{1}{12}\) will not be perfectly represented in the jury - they'll either be over or underrepresented.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a particularly big deal for minority groups. For example, consider Muslims. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islam_in_the_United_Kingdom"&gt;Wikipedia tells me&lt;/a&gt; that 4.4% of the UK population are muslim. Therefore the correct number of muslims on a jury of 12 people is 0.528. This is, obviously, hard to achieve.
Random selection achieves this on average by assigning one muslim to the jury 32% of the time, no muslims 59% of the time, and more than one muslim 9% of the time (these numbers are all rounded). That's all very well, but if you're a muslim and you consider it important to have muslims on your jury, it's of small comfort if you're one of the 59% who doesn't get any. Statistical fairness is all very well, but an individual up for trial might quite reasonably expect that it should be fair in their individual case too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This leads further to the question of which groups you want represented.
For example, it might be important to consider ethnicity.
Again, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_British"&gt;according to Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, 81.9% of the UK population is white. This means you want 9.83 white people on your jury. Depending on whether you round that to 9 or 10, that gives you 2 or 3 people of colour on your jury. But which racial groups do you want in those 2 or 3? People of colour have certain unifying experiences, certainly (e.g. being on the receiving end of racism), but they're very far from a unified group.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This gets worse when you consider intersections. For example, one can be representative of both ethnicity and gender without being representative of their intersection. Does it matter if all three of your people of colour are men but you make up the gender balance by including more white women? It probably does. Intersectionality tells us that the interplay of racism and sexism is significant in ways that are more than the sum of their parts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's take a step back and ask why this matters. It matters because how we form judgements about people is significantly affected by how legible they are to us, and identity is a big part of this.
I've &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/06/the-ethics-of-false-negatives-in-interviewing/"&gt;previously written about how this affects interviewing&lt;/a&gt;: The heuristics we use for judging people are based on those that are reliable for people who we are familiar with, a group that is generally heavily biased towards people who are like us. These heuristics are not necessarily prejudicial outside that group, but they may be wildly inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This suggests one obvious modification to the principle of representativeness in juries: Where the speaker is part of a minority group, we should aim to err on the side of overrepresentation of that group in the jury.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, this is tricky, and risks falling afoul of what Amartya Sen, in his book &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3cDC1jV"&gt;Identity and Violence&lt;/a&gt; calls the &lt;em&gt;assumption of singularity&lt;/em&gt; - the idea that we all have a single immutable identity that has primacy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A particularly ironic example of how identity can affect our judgement comes from Miranda Fricker's book, &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3cGXfgG"&gt;Epistemic Injustice&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that a hearer responsibly judges a speaker to be untrustworthy (because insincere) owing to the fact that the speaker avoids looking her in the eye, frequently looks askance, and pauses self-consciously in mid-sentence as if to work out his story. The speaker’s behaviour justifies the hearer’s judgement inasmuch as it fits an empirically reliable stereotype of insincerity. In fact, however, this individual is speaking entirely ingenuously, and his shifty manner is simply due to the rather idiosyncratic manifestations of his extraordinary personal shyness. This speaker, let us agree, constitutes an exception to an empirically reliable rule, and thus the testimonial injustice he suffers is caused not by prejudice but simply by bad luck. What should be said about such an example?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we were to consider this shyness example to be an instance of testimonial injustice, then it would be a case of non-culpable testimonial injustice: clearly the hearer has done nothing for which she is blameworthy, either epistemically or ethically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What should be said about this example is that somehow Fricker has managed to be either unaware of or indifferent to the existence of people with autism. She has taken a generally (but not wholly! Difficulty with eye contact may also result from e.g. trauma) reliable heuristic on neurotypical people, and declared that because the error is not based on an identity group that she recognises as valid, the error is not culpable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is almost an example of what I've previously described as &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-23-09:37.html"&gt;legibility privileges&lt;/a&gt;: The relevant features of identity are ones that are, apparently, illegible to Fricker (autism as a feature identity is perfectly legible, but &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-02-09:31.html"&gt;legibility is a relationship&lt;/a&gt;), and so are discounted from consideration.
If you have an autistic muslim woman on trial and the jury selection carefully is carefully padded out with muslim women in order to give her a fair trial but you end up with a jury of 100% neurotypicals (which is highly likely due to the relatively low prevalence of autism) then the selection would potentially be completely missing the point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As with many seemingly intractable problems, this admits a relatively feasible solution: You have to ask them. People have choice over what aspects of their identity have primacy, and we have a moral duty to respect those choices.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the case of the jury, what seems like a natural solution to me is to start the process of jury selection with a negotiation between the prosecution, the defence, and the judge, about some criteria that the defence would like to ensure is represented in the jury, and then ensure that (say) three out of the twelve jurors satisfy those criteria. Both those three and the other nine would still be randomly selected, but they would be selected from within fixed subsets of the population.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You'd need careful guidelines for how this is to be implemented in practice, and I'm not at all an expert in law or jury selection, so it's likely that I'm missing important features, but I do think some principle like this is worth considering every time you're making a decision about someone - whether it's a jury, as in this example, a hiring panel, or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-23-07:48.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-24-09:38.html</id>
    <title>Democracy isn't just voting</title>
    <updated>2020-04-24T12:42:29+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Democracy isn't just voting&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-24&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This post's reading comes from Amartya Sen's "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2XYL8aP"&gt;Identity and Violence&lt;/a&gt;", page 55, although actually it mostly comes from Nelson Mandela's "Long Walk to Freedom" (which I haven't read).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his autobiography &lt;em&gt;Long Walk to Freedom&lt;/em&gt;, Nelson Mandela describes how influenced he was, as a young boy, by seeing the democratic nature of the proceedings of the local meetings in his African hometown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone who wanted to speak did so. It was democracy in its purest form. There may have been a hierarchy of importance among the speakers, but everyone was heard, chief and subject, warrior and medicine man, shopkeeper and farmer, landowner and laborer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In context the point that Sen is making is that the idea we have of democracy as a "western" ideal that we've inherited from the greeks and imposed on the rest of the world is bogus, and in fact democracy taken in the general 
as any form of collective decision making that involves its participants equally in the process is found in my cultures.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd like to highlight something else: The democratic ideal that he is describing is actually quite far from the western one, and it's better.
These days in a lot of the west we have this very anemic idea of democracy, where we've basically reduced it to voting,
and voting is in many ways supposed to be the thing you do when better ways of doing democracy have failed.
Reducing democracy to voting is already failure, even before you get into the question of what voting system you should use.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Really the starting point for democracy is not the vote but the discussion (not the debate!) - people getting together to try to figure out the best solution, in a way that respects everyone's needs and viewpoints. Everyone speaks, everyone listens. You don't necessarily have to all agree at the end (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consensus_decision-making"&gt;Consensus-building&lt;/a&gt; is sometimes a good idea, but it's hard and not always worth it), but everyone has the option to be heard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't to say that voting is never a good feature in democracy. Voting has a lot of advantages when what you want is a relatively low cost way of deciding between a small number of options, but most decision making isn't like that (and the decision theorists who tell you it is are lying to you). Most of the interesting parts of the democratic process consist of getting to the point where you can reduce things to that small number of decisions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly useful for &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2016/11/democracy-for-lunch/"&gt;decisions that don't matter very much&lt;/a&gt;, because it lets you get them out of the way quickly, but for more momentous decisions it largely comes at the end when you've exhausted the possibility of agreement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the big limitations of voting over discussion is that it cannot put new things on the table. You can vote for &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/None_of_the_above#Re-open_Nominations_(RON)"&gt;RON&lt;/a&gt; (the only candidate that can promise change!) in some systems, but most voting in practice does not meaningfully allow that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This, I think, suggests a feature that is important and absent from most voting systems: They need to be able to fail. One possible conclusion of voting should be that it concludes that you weren't ready for voting yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Consensus seeking votes are the easiest example of such a thing: Unless 100% of people agree on an option, the vote fails and you have to go back to discussion. You can do similar things by requiring supermajorities: If \(\frac{2}{3}\) of people approve some outcome, you select that, otherwise back to the drawing board.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think one reason we overfocus on voting is that it's easier to do at scale (lotteries are also easy to do at scale, but we don't like those for various reasons - some good, some bad). The democratic ideal of discussion really only works with small groups - even our parliaments are too large to really manage it, let alone our populations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel like there are probably systems that solve this by essentially patchworking together many small democratic groups, but perhaps the biggest problem with getting there is how little small scale democracy there is in most people's lives. The overwhelming majority of small group interactions we have result in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:27.html"&gt;someone basically taking charge&lt;/a&gt;, and because people are increasingly atomized most of us don't seem to be part of any communities that could be or would benefit from being democratically run (maybe this isn't true? It's certainly my impression).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think one part of that is the absence of good &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/the-missing-social-technology-sector/"&gt;social technology&lt;/a&gt; for this. John Gastil's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3ePnt2m"&gt;Democracy in Small Groups&lt;/a&gt; describes how small group democracy is actually implemented in practice in some of the communities where we do have that, and frankly I'm a democracy fan and I still think it sounds &lt;em&gt;awful&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe what is needed is something like &lt;a href="http://www.liberatingstructures.com/"&gt;Liberating Structures&lt;/a&gt;? A toolkit of easy to use small group democratic processes that people can just plug in to their lives and use where appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-24-09:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-25-10:40.html</id>
    <title>The conditional love of a small town</title>
    <updated>2020-04-25T12:12:56+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The conditional love of a small town&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From bell hooks's "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2W0Q9gk"&gt;All About Love&lt;/a&gt;", Page 100:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like living in small towns precisely because they are most often the places in our nation where basic principles underlying a love ethic exist and are the standards by which most people try to live their lives. In the small town where I live (now only some of the time) there is a spirit of neighborliness [...] We protect and nurture our collective well-being. We try to make our home place a positive environment for everyone. We all agree that integrity and care enhance all our lives. We try to live by the principles of a love ethic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the book she defines love based on the work of Erich Fromm as "The will to extend one's self for the purpose of one's own or another's spiritual growth", which is a definition I quite like (with perhaps mild quibbles about the word "spiritual"), although given how into personal growth I am (it's practically a love language), I would.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So a community that lives by a love ethic is one where everyone is committed to contributing to each other's personal growth.
Such a community is &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; appealing to me, and I often fantasize about finding or creating it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, the idea of finding such a community in a small town? Not just no, but hell no.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing I think this illustrates is how non-transferable experiences of marginalisation are.
bell hooks obviously has more experience of marginalisation than I do - she is a black woman in the US, while I am in most regards a fairly privileged white man. But I am also a queer neurodivergent person, and the experience of small towns for people like me is literally the worst.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you're sufficiently "weird" and live or go to school in a small town, chances are pretty good you know almost nobody like you, and it's awful.
In a large city you may still struggle to find people like you, but those people are at least there and once you've found a few you will find more through them. It is possible to build a community of people like you, and to build a love ethic within that community, in a way that I don't think people like me are ever going to really find in a small town.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been reading James C. Scott's "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Kzllyc"&gt;The Art of Not Being Governed&lt;/a&gt;" recently (a book I suspect has never previously been linked to bell hooks's "All About Love"), which is about the hill people of Zomia, a large region of South East Asia, and their relationship to the states. In particular it points out that that rather than being some sort of "living ancestors" of the people of the valley states, the hill people are typically the descendants of refugees who fled the state.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things that this has been making me think about is the use of marginalisation as an enabling technology. Many schemes for organising humanity along legible lines work much better if you can just get the people who don't fit to leave. Otherwise you'd have to force them to conform to the system (hard, probably causes rebellions), kill them (same. Also ethics I guess), or adapt the system in order to accommodate the actual richness of human experience (yeah right).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the case of Zomia this is a flight from the large to the small - from the big states to the small isolated communities of the hills - but when it comes to towns there's an equal flight from the small to the large. The people who are weird and don't fit in nope out of the small towns and go find somewhere where they're less constrained. Small communities enforce their own sort of legibility on the people within them, and those who are illegible to them flee to the cities.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It may well be that small towns do exhibit the sort of love aesthetic that bell hooks describes, where everyone living in them promotes each other's spiritual growth, but if so they do so by driving out everyone who tries to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html"&gt;grow in ways that are not approved&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-25-10:40.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-26-07:28.html</id>
    <title>Fixed and growth relationships</title>
    <updated>2020-04-26T09:14:44+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Fixed and growth relationships&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today the successor group to our Rewriting the Rules reading group is meeting, and we're talking about daily habits we've tried to implement over the last couple of weeks. My habit has been rereading - dropping into books I've already read and reading at least one page from them (usually more, but the success criterion is one page). That habit lead more or less directly to the current "Today's reading" style of notebook posts, so I thought I would honour it with an appropriate choice of book today.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3eQhfQ3"&gt;Rewriting the Rules&lt;/a&gt;", Page 207:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, fixing or objectifying yourself is extremely common. It comes back to the sense that we're lacking, which we explored in Chapter 2. Much of the power of falling in love comes from the fact we find ourselves fixed in the gaze of another person in a wonderful way. This person dancing opposite me in a nightclub, sitting across from me over a candlelit dinner, or lying next to me in bed, gazes at me in adoration. The vision of myself that I see reflected in their eyes is a person I'd dearly love to be. It's like they see all the good stuff and none of the bad. As long as they look at me like that perhaps I can pretend there &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; any bad in me. Maybe they're right and I really &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; that loveable through and through. No wonder love can feel like a drug we can't get enough of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In context "fixed" is meant to mean "set" or "frozen", not the opposite of broken. MJB is talking about the tendency to want to see ourselves as singular, well-defined, identities rather than, to use their term, plural and in progress. This is in a chapter about conflict, and follows on from talking about how Sartre considers us to be unavoidably in conflict with each other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Things that immediately come to mind in response to this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Naturally, thinking about conflict makes me think of Thomas Schelling's book about nuclear war, &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3bGnLXp"&gt;The Strategy of Conflict&lt;/a&gt; where he defines conflicts as positive-sum games with imperfectly aligned incentives. This is a perfect way of looking at relationships, romantic and otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thinking about relationship problems inevitably makes me think of my own post &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-24-09:46.html"&gt;Trust beyond reason&lt;/a&gt;, because it has become my explain-everything theory for relationship problems: Relationship problems exist because you do not trust someone at a level that is needed for their importance to you to be safe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relationships as fixing you contrasts interestingly with bell hooks's notion of love as growth that I mentioned in my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-25-10:40.html"&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, putting me in mind of a relationship version of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindset#Fixed_and_Growth_Mindset"&gt;fixed vs growth mindset&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have roughly two experiences of romantic love. In one, it was definitely quite in line with this idea of fixing each other into ideal versions of our selves. In the other (the current one), it is much more in line with bell hooks's notion of love as growth. The latter is much better, let me tell you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sartre is correct, people are unavoidably in conflict, at least in the Schelling sense: Our relationships are positive sum games, in which our incentives are perfectly aligned. What we want out from the other is not exactly the same as what the other wants for themself. That doesn't necessarily mean that we would ever want to force them to do what we want instead of what they want, it just means that we have preferences and feelings about what they do that are somewhat separated from their own.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In and of itself there is nothing wrong with this, but one thing that I think goes wrong is that we are terrified of our partners rejecting us, and we fear that going against their preferences will cause them to do so. We may not believe this, but we certainly &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;alieve&lt;/a&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One strategy for conflict is to credibly threaten to punish the other party for going against your interests. Even if the punishment is costly, this can be worth doing. Mutually Assured Destruction is an example of this - once you know the other side has launched nuclear weapons at you, there is literally no benefit to you launching nuclear weapons back. It's a purely vindictive act that will not save you but will destroy them. However, the fact that you were able to credibly commit to doing this makes it very unlikely (unless they fuck up, which is always the concern) that they will ever launch those nuclear missiles in the first place. By making the threat you have changed the pay off matrix, so that the option where they launch nuclear missiles at you is no longer high payoff for them (because it results in their obliteration as well).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this analogy, the fear of rejection is the nuclear threat.
While rejection is not quite as bad as having your country obliterated and millions of lives lost to atomic fire, from the inside it can be hard to remember that, especially if you're &lt;a href="https://www.rewriting-the-rules.com/self/trauma-and-cptsd-101/"&gt;traumatised&lt;/a&gt; by a history of being treated badly (whether by family, peers, or in relationships).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You may argue that one should note be adopting manipulative tactics in a relationship (you certainly shouldn't be &lt;em&gt;threatening&lt;/em&gt; your partner!), and you would be right, but unfortunately it's not that simple: Generally speaking tactics we adopt are not the result of deliberate forethought, they are the result of our behaviours being shaped over time in response to feedback and incentives. Many of our behaviours are &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;legacy code&lt;/a&gt;, and many more of them are &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-28-06:33.html"&gt;contingent cultural effects&lt;/a&gt; that we have learned in response to each other in a given context.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The nice thing about mutually assured destruction is that, generally speaking, nobody dies in atomic fire. That's good. It is strictly better than people dying in atomic fire. Good outcome.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; nice thing about mutually assured destruction is that &lt;em&gt;everybody is constantly stressed out about the possibility of dying in atomic fire&lt;/em&gt;. This is still vastly better than dying, but is quite a lot worse than not being stressed out about dying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The same is true in relationships. Not being rejected is good, but being constantly afraid of being rejected as a way to achieve that is bad. This fear of rejection is a major part of what causes us to fix ourselves into a version seen by our partner: We try to fix ourselves as the version that will not be rejected.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;bell hooks defines love as "The will to extend one's self for the purpose of one's own or another's spiritual growth". But growth &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;requires safety&lt;/a&gt; - if you are living in fear of rejection, you will not feel safe, and you will not be able to grow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means love in hooks sense requires us to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-06-15:20.html"&gt;be safe for others&lt;/a&gt; who we are to be in a relationship with. If your partner is to express themselves honestly, it needs to be safe for them to do so. This means you need to:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not react with judgement or blame when they tell you how they're feeling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also&lt;/em&gt; not automatically change your behaviour to accommodate everything that they're feeling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is a form of rejection, and is exactly what people are afraid of. The second is often an overreaction and, because your partner loves you, may cause them to avoid telling you things for fear of causing you harm.
After all, if you know that someone you love will react as if they're a terrible person because they caused you some mild discomfort, are you going to share that discomfort with them?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once you have this safety, it becomes possible to build trust to a much greater degree, because you know that that trust building will not be met with rejection. This is the extending of one's self that bell hooks is talking about: You are putting yourself into the relationship, in a way that allows the other to know you, and gives them &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-17-11:40.html"&gt;permission&lt;/a&gt; to be known by you in turn.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also allows you to know yourself in a way that is almost impossible to achieve on your own.
Self-awareness allows us to know many things about our selves that are not visible to others,
and that this fear of extending ourselves into the world causes us to deliberately hide from them,
but we discount how many things about ourselves that we have no idea about are visible to others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3cOWfXU"&gt;Mindfulness in 3D&lt;/a&gt;" Peter Nobes talks about &lt;em&gt;Faulty Sensory Appreciation&lt;/em&gt; - the idea that our image of our self, especially of our posture, is often completely wrong in ways that are really obvious to others. He goes into this less in the book, but talking to Peter makes it clear how broadly he thinks it applies, and I agree. Often our moods are more obvious to those around us than they are to ourselves. Certainly how we come across to others is often invisible to us, and is often reflective of underlying learned reactions that we are not consciously aware of.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When our reactions in a relationship are safe, it becomes possible not only for our partners to tell us about their selves, but also for them to tell us about ourselves, and through this reciprocated love we can grow together.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-26-07:28.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-26-12:07.html</id>
    <title>78 Thinking Hats</title>
    <updated>2020-04-26T13:22:08+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;78 Thinking Hats&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This post is breaking the trend and is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; based on a random passage from a book, so is a bonus post for today, though it will contain multiple references to books.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2VCBSYa"&gt;Six Thinking Hats&lt;/a&gt;" Edward de Bono talks about the idea of there being six "directions" that you can pull thought in, each of which is best characterised by a coloured hat. Because he's de Bono, and thus a self-important asshole, the book opens as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Six Thinking Hats method may well be the most important change in human thinking for the past twenty-three hundred years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Uh huh.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He goes on to say:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That may seem a rather exaggerated claim but the evidence is beginning to point that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No it isn't, shut up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Despite my intense dislike for de Bono as a human being, the book isn't bad, and has some moderately useful ideas in it, and each of the different directions of thought &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; one that is useful to push your thinking in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To quote his description of the hats (page 13):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;White Hat&lt;/strong&gt; White is neutral and objective. The white hat is concerned with objective facts and figures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Red Hat&lt;/strong&gt; Red suggests anger (seeing red), rage and emotions. The red hat gives the emotional view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Black Hat&lt;/strong&gt; Black is sombre and serious. The black hat is cautious and careful. It points out the weaknesses in an idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yellow Hat&lt;/strong&gt; Yellow is sunny and positive. The yellow hat is optimistic and covers hope and positive thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Green Hat&lt;/strong&gt; Green is grass, vegetation and abundant, fertile growth. The green hat indicates creativity and new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blue Hat&lt;/strong&gt; Blue is cool, and it is also the colour of the sky, which is above everything else. The blue hat is concerned with control, the organization of the thinking process and the use of other hats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hats pair as White and Red, Black and Yellow, Green and Blue, each defining an opposite direction.
The idea is that people adopt a hat at a time, with the hats giving them &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-17-11:40.html"&gt;permission&lt;/a&gt; to pull their thinking further in that direction than they otherwise would.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do de Bono's ideas work? Yeah, I think they do. Certainly I've got some good use out of some of his ideas from another of his books, "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/355DAVj"&gt;Lateral Thinking&lt;/a&gt;", but I think his ideas work for a very simple reason: It's &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard to come up with things that don't work.
The main thing de Bono's ideas having going for them is that de Bono is very good at marketing his ideas in a way that only causes &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; people to dismiss them instead of everyone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;His books are short and kinda interesting, so I don't recommend against reading them and might read a few more in future, but I think most of the value they bring comes from the fact that not enough people are doing this sort of thing because it would be &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html"&gt;too weird&lt;/a&gt;,
and if you want to use de Bono's work for groups you're better off looking at something like &lt;a href="http://www.liberatingstructures.com/"&gt;liberating structures&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Basically, I think that almost &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; you can do that pulls your thinking in a direction that it doesn't naturally gravitate will prove interesting. We've been seeing that with the recent use of random readings from books to prompt posts - I'm still finding my feet on that a bit, but I think it's been very positive and it's certainly caused me to write things I would not otherwise be writing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which ties in to something I've been thinking about for years but have never really got around to doing, which is Tarot reading.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tarot obviously doesn't let you foresee the future, except insofar as you can already foresee the future because brains are causal reasoning machines that are fairly good at predicting the future on their own. Instead, tarot cards are a tool for randomised prompts for narrative construction, but having those randomised prompts causes you to construct narratives or think about things in ways that you wouldn't necessarily otherwise do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Learning Tarot "properly" is something I keep putting off, so given the success of the randomised prompts from books, I thought it might be worth integrating some of it into my writing practice.
How exactly this plays out will be something to experiment with, but if nothing else it will drive familiarity with the cards.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For convenient linkability I'll use the cards descriptions from &lt;a href="http://www.learntarot.com/"&gt;www.learntarot.com&lt;/a&gt; (the author of that site also has &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3aD3zo7"&gt;a book that I'll be consulting&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I drew a pair of cards:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.learntarot.com/maj02.htm"&gt;The High Priestess&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.learntarot.com/p2.htm"&gt;The Two of Pentacles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A core theme of the high priestess is intuition and mystery, paying attention to the subconscious. Actions listed include "Using your intuition" and "Seeking guidance from within". She is described as "the guardian of the unconscious".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The two of pentacles is, among other things, about fun and flexibility. Actions include "going with the flow" and "doing something you enjoy". The two of pentancles is described as "There is nothing quite like the feeling of being graceful and effective at the same time."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This puts me in mind of Focusing and Alexander Technique, two things which are fairly central to my current pursuit of emotional awareness and embodiment work. Focusing is using your bodily sense to learn about your emotional state, while this sort of graceful and effective movement is a key feature of Alexander Technique.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other thing that is interesting in this link is the idea of "having fun". How do you know when you're having fun? This isn't a rhetorical question. What does "fun" feel like? &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know either to be honest. I'm not very good at fun. I can do interest, I can do spontaneity, I can enjoy things, but &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt; is weird for me. I'm hoping Focusing will help me unpack that a bit, by paying more attention to the phenomenological character of enjoyment and leaning into it a bit (and yes, I am aware that the fact that "How do I have fun? Let's learn more phenomenology!" is very much part of the problem. I am &lt;em&gt;not good&lt;/em&gt; at either of these cards, which is part of why they are interesting).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suspect that fun is only visible to you after the fact. If you're too self-conscious about the fact that you're having fun, you'll forget to have fun. Overthinking is a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-20-10:52.html"&gt;brake&lt;/a&gt; on your ability to have fun.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is part of why the two of pentacles puts me in mind of Alexander Technique. If fun is primarily an embodied state, then &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-21-12:35.html"&gt;the half of you that is embodied&lt;/a&gt; is much more able to have fun than your cognitive half. Peter Nobes (my Alexander Technique) teacher relates a story of a standup comic: "Are there any intellectuals in the room? Raise your hand." (nobody raises their hand) "Good. Intellectuals don't know how to laugh. They just sit there and stroke their chin and go ah yes I see that's very funny". Highly relatable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the ways I have been deploying both sides of this recently - Focusing and Alexander Technique - is to try to have more fun doing exercise. Doing exercise not because I think I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; exercise, but because my body invites me to do so and to enjoy it. Using exercise as a way to engage with my embodied self, and to drop into a flow state. So far it hasn't resulted in a massive amount of exercise, but I've done some most days, and the amount I am doing seems to be going up over time rather than down, and at no point have I done any exercise and resented it.
This is pretty amazing, and makes me think there might be something to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-14-13:56.html"&gt;this human notion of "fun"&lt;/a&gt; you people are always going on about.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-26-12:07.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-27-07:57.html</id>
    <title>Telling each other stories</title>
    <updated>2020-04-27T08:52:02+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Telling each other stories&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today's Tarot prompt is "&lt;a href="http://www.learntarot.com/maj06.htm"&gt;The Lovers&lt;/a&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been writing a bunch about relationships recently, so I thought I'd investigate some of its other actions: Establishing personal beliefs and determining values.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This naturally leads me to revisit "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3cObm3Y"&gt;Finding Our Sea-Legs&lt;/a&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 141:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this telling of tales, I do not entirely lose the story that I pass on; but neither do I keep hold of it in the same fashion as before. There is a gain and a loss. Both are inevitable, and a strict accounting of the two is impossible. Even if I sit in silence and listen to the stories of others, although at first glance it may seen that in hearing I only make gains, there are also losses, subtle losses: as I hear about another's sister-perhaps about her expertise in cooking aubergines-my own sister seems a greater or lesser aubergine cook than before; when I am told about the wolf, the traveler to my side once encountered on a lonely hillside, the wolf with which I exchanged glances one day in the municipal zoo transforms into a different wolf; and through these subtle, perhaps imperceptible changes in my sister or my wolf, so too I am changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Funnily, having gone from the lovers to values to finding our sea legs, we're back at a different meaning of the lovers: Relationships.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finding Our Sea-Legs is a book about stories, and their interplay with ethics and our experience of others. I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-21-08:02.html"&gt;previously wrote about its focus on the phenomenology of ethics&lt;/a&gt;. This passage is more about the other "side" (in fact, the two are intimately related).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It makes me think about a couple of things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The mutability of memory. When we recall our memories, we fundamentally change them, overwriting details. We think of memory as a fixed record of facts, but it's more like stories we tell ourselves and others, over and over again, subtly mutating each time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way all observation is theory-laden. It's hard to separate facts from our interpretation of it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As we tell each other stories, we each give each other new ways of looking at the world, and we cast other experiences in that light.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One way I have seen this happening over and over again is when we tell people how we conceptualise our lives, we give them new tools for interpreting theirs. There's the "There's a word for that" moment where you give someone a new hermeneutical resource (a tool for interpretation, such as a new word or conceptual framework. For example, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2018-11-12-06:24.html"&gt;information about trans or non-binary people&lt;/a&gt;, or learning about the link between ADHD and &lt;a href="https://www.additudemag.com/rejection-sensitive-dysphoria-and-adhd/"&gt;rejection sensitive dysphoria&lt;/a&gt;), but you also see that in more subtle ways. For example, when you tell someone about an abusive behaviour in a relationship, this can cause them to recast similar things &lt;em&gt;they've&lt;/em&gt; experienced as abusive. The story didn't give them the concept of abuse, or teach them a new thing about their life, but it gave them the permission to recast the story of their life in new terms that they would not previously have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When these sorts of events happen, they &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; change our relationships with people - both past and present. Sometimes these changes are for the worse, realising how bad someone is for you, sometimes the are for the better, helping you realise how much someone means to you. Sometimes they give you new realisations and new directions to grow the relationship in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wrote previously about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-26-07:28.html"&gt;growth relationships&lt;/a&gt;. I think many of my closest friendships are growth relationships in this sense, to some greater or lesser degree, and several such relationships have ended up as the foundation of our &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-25-16:02.html"&gt;mutual support group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of back and forth is in many ways essential to support group. I've found many of the most useful conversations in support group for me have not been ones centered around problems I've brought to the group (though those have been helpful too - in a few cases, literally life changing) but the conversations we've had around other people's problems - both where I've helped them, and listening to others' advice. Hearing and understanding their stories has given me a new framework to look at my own life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In one sense, support group consists of getting together and helping each other solve our problems. In another, it is getting together and telling stories about our lives and building a shared interpretation of them. A great deal of why it works so well, and why relationships in general are such a great platform for growth, is that we are building a kind of shared canon of stories that we can build on - the Support Group Cinematic Universe so to speak - with which we can build our interpretive tools together, constantly deepening our understanding of our lives and the values we hold.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-27-07:57.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
