<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2021-10-02T08:53:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-25-12:50.html</id>
    <title>You can solve your problems, but you don't have to</title>
    <updated>2021-07-25T13:30:23+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You can solve your problems, but you don't have to&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Before I start, let me tell you some important truths:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because you can solve a problem, does not mean you are obliged to solve it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because you choose not to solve a problem, doesn't mean you don't care about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because you don't care about a problem you think is important, doesn't make you a bad person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because other people think a problem is important, doesn't mean you have to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are a small and finite human being, and you only have so much capacity to deal with the world,
and the world can absorb all of that capacity before you engage with the tiniest fraction of its problems.
There are more than seven billion people out there, every one of them has problems,
and even trying to solve all of &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; problems is probably going to overwhelm you.
Among the billions upon billions of important problems you could devote your efforts to, you've probably got the capacity for at most a few dozen at any given time, and you're probably doing less than that because running permanently at full capacity will make you miserable (and eventually reduce your capacity anyway).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I hope you know these things intellectually, but I bet you don't believe all of them emotionally,
and my evidence is this: There are a lot of problems that I could tell you how to solve that would cause you to immediately get mad at me for suggesting that you can solve them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know what they are, they very from person to person, but most people are walking around with easily solvable problems that they are steadfastly maintaining that they can't solve, because if they could solve them they would still not want to, and then they would feel guilty about that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People are very good at maintaining a set of beliefs that allow them to not feel guilty,
and the easiest way to do this is to believe that anything you think you should do but don't want to is impossible.
If you argue this belief convincingly enough, often other people will believe you and stop trying to get you to solve the problem you don't want to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's a genuinely good strategy, as long as you don't mind (or mind less than the alternatives) walking around in constant fear that you might one day discover the truth.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One way this comes out is that every time I offer generic advice on Twitter, I get people mad at me for suggesting that they could solve the problem I'm advising on.
They're very insistent that it's literally impossible this advice will work. Usually their reason is one that the advice was specifically designed with in mind. e.g. I hear a lot of my advice is terrible because it doesn't work for ADHD. This is particularly funny because it's often developed by listening to or talking with people with ADHD, and developed further to work with my own more ADHD tendencies given that I'm only just below the diagnostic thresholds myself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not every problem in your life is solvable, some really are immutable features of reality, but I am almost certain that vastly more of them are than you're pretending. I fully endorse your right and respect your choice not to solve them. I even fully endorse your right to not listen to me when I tell you that they're solvable. But I do not endorse your right to give me a hard time for talking about solutions, because many people are helped by trying to solve the problems they want to solve, and I have no desire to be complicit in maintaining a shared lie that hurts those people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Options exist. If you want to choose to believe otherwise, that's on you, but don't make your self-protective strategies an excuse to sabotage others.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-25-12:50.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-26-09:00.html</id>
    <title>The edge of the familiar</title>
    <updated>2021-07-26T16:40:53+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The edge of the familiar&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm reading "Why Poetry?" by Zapruder.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why why poetry? Well, why not?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"I don’t know what writers of stories and novels and essays eventually discover for themselves, but I can say that sooner or later poets figure out there are no new ideas, only the same old ones", he says.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He is wrong. This is a poet's problem. The ideas are there, but you cannot do poetry to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We are awash in new ideas, if we let ourselves listen for them. Generally we do not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Zapruder later cites Shklovsky, "Art as technique".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Shklovsky talks about "defamiliarization", or as Zapruder prefers, "strangeifying". The role of art is to trace the contours of the familiar, drawing your attention to it in ways that make it strange.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, if that's what you're doing, how could you have new ideas?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How can you strangeify that which is already strange to you?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think, perhaps, the role of art can never be to create the new.
It shows us what is already there, in a new light, allowing us to imagine that it could be different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It draws you to the very edge of the familiar,
and then tells you: Here we are. This is as far as I can take you. The rest is up to you.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-26-09:00.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-27-04:25.html</id>
    <title>You have to do the easy bits first</title>
    <updated>2021-07-27T05:33:47+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You have to do the easy bits first&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was helping a small child with a jigsaw puzzle the other day. We were assembling a map of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point she asked me "Why is this so easy for you and so hard for me?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was a good question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The easy answer is just "I'm 31 years older than you, I’ve learned a few tricks".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't say this, but I do think it's important. She's seven. There's no reason she should have figured out everything by now. She's still learning. That's what seven year olds do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But really there was only one trick, and it’s well within the reach of a seven year old if they can learn how.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Well, I’m doing the easy bits" I answered.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I explained a bit further, but I don’t think it quite landed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So here is what I would say with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%27esprit_de_l%27escalier"&gt;the wit of the staircase&lt;/a&gt; upon me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What you are doing is picking up a piece, and trying to figure out where to put it. Or you see a space that needs filling, and look for the piece that will fit it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is much too hard. Of course you're struggling, I would struggle too if I tried to solve the puzzle that way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is what I do instead: I do the same thing, and if it's hard, I stop. Then I look elsewhere. I put the piece aside, I look at another space, hoping that that one will be easier.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are many pieces, and many spaces, on the puzzle board, and some of them are hard, and some of them are easy. A blue square in the middle of the ocean is hard, a country boundary with distinctive colours is probably easy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can get good at spotting which ones are likely to be easy, but you mostly don't need to. You just try to place a piece, and if it works, it was one of the easy ones. If it doesn't, you try something else.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually you'll get good at spotting the easy pieces first, but you don't have to. Just be persistent, try them all. It usually won't take long to find an easy piece.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And when you've placed an easy piece, something funny happens: Pieces that were once hard, suddenly become easy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You fill a space, and now you have one less piece to place, and new spaces to place it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bit by bit, the picture takes shape, and as it does the problem becomes easier, because you have more to work with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you've only got a few pieces, you can just try them all, and one of them will work. When you're down to a handful, there are no hard pieces left.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can solve the hardest puzzles this way. All we need is a bit of persistence and some good tactics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't just about puzzles. You do the same with sudoku.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When we play sudoku together, you get stuck on a square. You look at it, trying to figure out what numbers go there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often you get frustrated. "I can't figure out what should go there".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well of course you can't. You've picked one of the hard squares. Pick an easy square.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is what's happening when I point to another square and say "Do you know what goes in this square?" - I look at the board until I find the easy square, and then I show it to you, and you find it easy, because you're perfectly able to solve the sudoku if you look in the right place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And once you've solved the easy square, now you know more about the other squares. A three went there, so there can't be a three in these squares, which means that one must be a two, which means that that one must be a four...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As soon as you've done the easy bit, everything around it becomes easier. This is the way we solve the puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is also the way we fix the world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a story about a seven year old, but it's not really a story about a seven year old, because people far older than me seem to miss this too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People often ask me how I know so many different subjects, or write about so many different things, when they struggle to do a tenth that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, I'm doing the easy bits.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If I run into a problem I can't solve yet, or I encounter a subject that's too hard for me, I go "Huh, interesting", and save it for later, or leave it to someone better suited to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't &lt;em&gt;give up&lt;/em&gt;. This is important. I just move on to something else, often something nearby.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I find a problem I can solve, and then I solve it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And everything else becomes easier.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-27-04:25.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-28-04:40.html</id>
    <title>You can't write life down</title>
    <updated>2021-07-28T06:04:42+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You can't write life down&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From "Trickster Makes this World", pages 313-314:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of the nineteenth century, a certain Father J. Jetté, Jesuit missionary to the Athabascan Indians, lived among the Ten’a in the lower Yukon. In those days the Ten’a told the old stories in the dead of winter, from early December to the middle of January. The group with whom Father Jetté lived would go to bed in the early evening, a dozen or more rolling themselves in blankets on the floor around the cabin, their heads to the wall. The last one blew out the light, throwing the room into complete darkness (every chink and crack was caulked against the cold, and gunnysacks hung outside the windows to keep the window panes from frosting over). Before long, someone would start a story—“In old times, it is said …”—the listeners responding anni! anni! to keep the voice going. “A strange thing had occurred: the sun had disappeared, and all was in the dark. What was to be done? the old women asked. Who will get back the sun for us?” Peals of laughter as Raven is lured from seclusion by the promise of dog meat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Father Jetté wanted very much to make a collection of tales, but there were difficulties. The Ten’a were reluctant to let the Raven stories be put in writing, for one thing (though another group of tales “the inane stories,” Jetté calls them—could be had for the asking). Jetté tried to transcribe tales as they were being told, but the utter darkness frustrated him. Nobody would repeat the stories in daylight, and at night whenever he struck a match to light a candle, the storyteller fell instantly silent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In case it needs be said, Jetté was in the wrong in this piece, and the Ten'a in the right.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not for intrinsic reasons. I take no stance on whether writing down the Raven stories would have been good or bad,
but from a moral standpoint the Ten'a had the right to refuse Jetté's desire to write those stories down,
and Jetté had an obligation to respect that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I confess my sympathies are with Jetté.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I often feel significant distress at the sheer amount of the past that we will never know about.
Depending on who you ask and how you count, modern humans have been around for 50,000 to 200,000 years,
with (necessarily imprecise) estimates of the total numbers of humans who have ever lived being in the region of 100 billion.
So many lives we'll never know anything about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They're probably mostly fine with that. This is my problem, not theirs. Nevertheless, I feel it as a loss.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But really, what would be gained by writing it down? Sure, I would know about them, and that's not nothing,
but it's not really a rendition of what happened either. You write &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; what happened, but you can never capture the actual event.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Peals of laughter as Raven is lured from seclusion by the promise of dog meat." - would I have laughed at the same story? Perhaps it might have elicited a chuckle, or a wry smile. Perhaps if I had been in the room with the Ten'a I might have shared their laughter. I doubt a written account would really convey it though. Maybe you have to be there?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or maybe you have to be them. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-04-12:52.html"&gt;Humour is a test of expertise&lt;/a&gt;, but the ultimate expertise is the full context of a life. There are always jokes that only work in context, and are hilarious but too specific to be able to extract.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first wrote about jokes, I thought of dividing them into the pure ones and the conditional ones. A conditional joke is one that can work only with certain audiences, and typically is meant only for those audiences. The audience must supply something in order either to get the joke or to be amused by it. That something is the condition on which the success of the joke depends. It is a vital feature of much joking that only a suitably qualified audience—one that can meet the condition—can receive the joke, and the audience often derives an additional satisfaction from knowing this about itself. A pure joke would be universal, would get through to everyone, because it presupposed nothing in the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It now seems clear to me that there is no such thing as a pure joke. It is a kind of ideal, but it doesn’t exist. At the very least, the audience will have to understand the language of the joke, and probably much more. But even if all jokes are conditional, it is still useful to note just how strongly conditional a particular joke is, and just what kind of condition is presupposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For something like this, the condition seems deeply cultural.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The idea of writing it down anyway is not, I think, intrinsically bad (except in that the Ten'a don't want you to), but the version of it that you have written down is not the version that the Ten'a told, and there is no way around this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Walter Ong, in the subtitle of his "Orality and Literacy", calls writing the "technologising of the word", and Albert Borgmann in his "Technology and the Character of Contemporary Life" talks about how the role of technology is &lt;em&gt;commoditisation&lt;/em&gt;. You take "things", complex objects with rich history and context, and replace them with "devices", which are largely interchangeable objects whose purposes is to provide some good as an equally interchangeable commodity. A fireplace is a thing, a space heater is a device.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This feels like a good summation of what's happening here: We're treating these Raven stories, and the context in which they are embedded, as if they have a neat, singular, purpose that we can capture by writing it down. The "commodity" that the word provides is its content.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I learned about Cohen's book on Jokes from C. Thi Nguyen's &lt;a href="http://schwitzsplinters.blogspot.com/2021/07/the-philosophy-of-art-technology.html"&gt;The Philosophy of Art is the Philosophy of Technology&lt;/a&gt;, where he says:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This observation [about how a change in the way people went tothe movies changed their contents] teaches us a few things. First: what’s most important about a medium for communication often isn’t in the raw material at the center, but in its social embeddedness. Much of what is crucial to the medium of film isn’t just in the images and sounds — it’s in the social process of theater-going. It’s in the fact that showtimes are, or aren’t, published in the newspaper. Second: tiny changes in the medium can have enormous social repercussions and shift the whole pattern of how people relate to an artform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing down the Raven stories would have utterly transformed them. Even if they had been preserved, the way people engaged with them would be different, and the results would be something new and probably lesser.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But now I will end with a confession: I still half wish someone had written those Raven stories down. I fully respect the right of the Ten'a to refuse this, and would not have pushed and would not push them to choose otherwise, but I am still sad about their absence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The role of the word may be to commoditise knowledge, but everything feeds into everything else, and by writing things down, no matter how disconnected they are from their source, we can provide the seeds of new things that would not otherwise have existed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We will then, of course, also fail to write those things down in a way that preserves them, but I am at peace with that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-28-04:40.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-29-16:22.html</id>
    <title>The changing nature of sick days</title>
    <updated>2021-07-29T16:52:38+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The changing nature of sick days&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting things about the COVID pandemic is that it very much changes the dynamics of sickness (if you're dealing with reasonable people anyway, which I acknowledge many of us are not).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Previously, if you called in a sick day, I feel like this was treated as a moral failing. You should just tough it out, come to work anyway, anything else is weakness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has helped highlight the fact that actually no, the reason to call in sick is to avoid giving people a virus. COVID-19 is a particularly bad virus to give people, but it's not like the other ones floating around are much fun either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The flip side of this of course is that although there's a stronger case to call in sick, when you're already working from home the fact that you just feel a bit grotty doesn't really stop you from working. It just reduces your capacity - unless you're really badly off you still &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do some work, you just would rather not. As a result, you take both more and fewer sick days, depending on how one interprets the term.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you're not noticeably ill, this has no effect. If you're very ill, this also has no effect (or minimal - you need to convincingly demonstrate that you're very ill). In the middle it has the odd effect of making things better if you're not ill enough that you would previously have stayed home, and worse if you are ill enough that you would have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not that too many people are going in to the office right now anyway, so this is mostly hypothetical, I'm just interested in thinking about what impact COVID will have on our social norms. Maybe none.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For my part, the big differences are just that I'm more willing to cancel social events when I have a cold. I don't know if that will last when there's no longer a pandemic on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm essentially self-employed, so COVID didn't make much difference to my attitude personally. I tend to do what I can, such as write a very mediocre post about sick days, when ill, and stick to coaching sessions I've committed to unless I'm utterly nonfunctional, but otherwise don't worry about it too much.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general I feel like modern life is not well set up for the intrinsic unreliability of humans, especially humans as awash in different virus sources as modern life also brings us, but I'll leave musing further on that for some time when my brain is working better.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-29-16:22.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-30-09:52.html</id>
    <title>Can you throw money at the Collatz Conjecture?</title>
    <updated>2021-07-30T18:41:30+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Can you throw money at the Collatz Conjecture?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-30&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Warning: Inside baseball, very much a set of notes rather than a coherent point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For context, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collatz_conjecture"&gt;the Collatz conjecture&lt;/a&gt; is the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For any given natural number \(n\), if \(n\) is even, move to \(\frac{n}{2}\), otherwise move to \(3n + 1\).
The Collatz conjecture is that no matter which \(n\) we start with, we will eventually reach \(1\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is, as far as I know, no particular reason to care about the Collatz conjecture except that it's interesting and that we don't know how to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1421051043266408449"&gt;I claimed on Twitter that you could probably solve the Collatz conjecture in a decade, given $1 billion of funding&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bpgbcg/status/1421057248365776899"&gt;Ben Gunby disagrees&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think we disagreed a lot. My estimate was something like "this would probably work", and I think his is something like "this probably wouldn't work". As far as I can tell neither of us thinks the other's position is ridiculous, we've just got moderately different views on the problem. That being said, having written all of this up, I've concluded that he's right and I'm wrong, because I had significantly underestimated how hard the Collatz conjecture is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the following is a fair summary of his argument that this is likely to be very hard:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are likely quite far away from techniques that would allow us to tackle the Collatz conjecture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If this is the case, there is likely a long dependency chain in which we have to develop tools to develop tools to develop tools etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If this is the case, this likely passes through many fields unrelated to the Collatz conjecture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$1 billion is a lot but it's not enough to literally bend the whole of mathematical research to your whims.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To look at this from another perspective, one can think of this in terms of two questions:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many direct mathematician-years of work do we need to solve the Collatz conjecture? i.e. if you add up all the mathematician-years of work spent on the proof and things it depends on, what do you get?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many mathematician-years of work do we realistically need to do in order to actually achieve that? This would be the same if you could just linearly proceed from A to B, but if you depend on unrelated fields you need to take into account work done in equally plausible unrelated fields that you couldn't have known in advance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much of that work is intrinsically sequential? e.g. if we decided that it will take 1000 mathematician-years, can we do that in 10 years with 100 mathematicians or are you going to have to do a full 1000 years of work with one mathematician building on the results of another, etc?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;("mathematician-years" of course depends on how good the mathematicians in question are. I guess I'm assuming reasonably top end mathematicians)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Ben and my intuitions on these differ as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His estimate of the number of mathematician-years required is much higher than mine initially was.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think you probably can cut out a lot of the unrelated work with a bit of work on focusing people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe this is more parallelisable than he does.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On further reading up on the difficulty of the literature I think that he is right and I am wrong about the first one,
and I've significantly underestimated how hard the Collatz conjecture is. In particular "The Ultimate Challenge" by Lagarias has a good survey that made me realise I'd underestimated the problem. &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.03562.pdf"&gt;Terence Tao made good progress on the problem in 2019&lt;/a&gt; and this good progress established a &lt;em&gt;substantially&lt;/em&gt; weaker result than the full conjecture. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For comparison, I think reasonable estimates for how many mathematician years went into solving Fermat's Last Theorem are somewhere in the region of 1000 to 10,000 mathmatician years, taking 1900 as the starting point (Most of the work on it that got real traction happened in the 20th century, I think). If on average 100 mathematicians were working on it full time at any given point of that century, that gets us to 10,000. If it's only 10, that's 1,000.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is that realistic? I don't know. I could also make a convincing argument that it was less than that (e.g. a lot of the last stretch was Wiles working on his own for 7 years, followed by Wiles and Taylor finishing it off...). But lets say 10,000 mathematicians years is about how much FLT took. It's a nice round number.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is the Collatz conjecture about as hard as FLT starting from 1900? I don't know. Based on my reading since Ben and my initial disagremeent... yeah, probably. Possibly even harder. We've got a number of partial results and angles of attack on it, but certainly nothing resembling a convincing story. It might be that it's actually amenable to some easy attack, but I don't think we've got any reason to expect that to be the case, and people who have studied it more than me seem to think it's probably too hard for us right now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose now that we could just turn money into mathematician-years. A high end mathematician salary seems to be about $100k. Because we want the best, and also need support staff and infrastructure, lets double that and say that one mathematician year costs us $200k. $1 billion now gets us 5,000 mathematician years.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, based on these (admittedly somewhat pessimistic) estimates, even if we could make a perfect beeline for the Collatz conjecture, if it's about as hard starting from now as Fermat's Last Theorem was starting from 1900, we should not expect to be able to solve it with a mere billion dollars.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is before we even get to the harder questions to quantify. What if exploring all the dead ends means we actually need 100,000 mathematician years?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, what happens with the dependencies problem? Can we, realistically, do even those 10,000 mathematician-years in 10 years even if we had infinite amounts of money to throw at it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't have a good handle on this but think the answer is a resounding "Maybe". If we again use Fermat's Last Theorem as a benchmark it doesn't seem unreasonable to me to think that we could do this - that's only one order of magnitude reduction, and I think if we had the relevant parties in a room together and were able to more aggressively speed up the collaboration, offer them support, etc. I don't think this is &lt;em&gt;ridiculous&lt;/em&gt;. Wiles worked on FLT for 7 years on his own, and I wouldn't be surprised if he could have done that in half with a collaborator to discuss things with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is all speculative though, I genuinely don't know, and I don't have any way to know. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polymath_Project"&gt;The polymath project&lt;/a&gt; gives me some hope that hard mathematical problems are parallelisable, but as far as I know it's never been tried on anything nearly this hard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, in conclusion, Ben is probably right. You probably can't solve this is in a decade with $1 billion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; think you could probably make meaningful progress on the Collatz conjecture, up to and including solving it, with a mere $1 billion, but I think if I were to do that it would look more like trying to build resources and community around it in the broader mathematical community.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, for this sort of price tag one could fund:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some sort of ongoing "residency" arrangement where a rotating group of mathematicians get together and work on the Collatz conjecture and related problems for a year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many small cash prizes for Collatz adjacent conjectures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put together a small team whose primary job was to essentially shore up results, generate conjectures, and write up the state of the art of current Collatz research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many post grad positions for getting people working on the problem for a period of time early in their career&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An alternative approach would be to just hire Terence Tao and Jeffrey Lagarias, and any dozen or so other mathematicians they care to name, and let them go wild on the problem. I doubt it would work, but it might produce something interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-30-09:52.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-31-09:29.html</id>
    <title>Unlearning</title>
    <updated>2021-07-31T22:03:23+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Unlearning&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-31&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I got distracted, and it got late, so here's a short piece on how schools are terrible, as &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1421488767257518081"&gt;this seems to be the thing I'm talking about today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From "How Children Fail", page 259:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The confused and hopeless children that I have worked with naturally never test as well as their abler classmates; but they are never much more than a year or two behind. This year, according to the tests, my worst pupils had the mathematical knowledge and skill of an average child entering the fourth grade. In short, they presumably knew addition, subtraction, place value, multiplication, and easy division. But this is utter nonsense. These children know &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; about arithmetic; in any &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; sense they don't know what first-graders are suppsoed to know. An accurate test, if there could be such a thing, a measuring instrument that really measured something, would give them a score of one point something [compared to a peer average of 5.5].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. Much closer to the truth to say that an accurate test, if there had been such a thing, would have given them a &lt;em&gt;minus&lt;/em&gt; score. After five years of school - in one of the "best" schools - they were worse off, in terms of arithmetic (and not just arithmetic), than if they had never been in school at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How are these high scores achieved? A week or two before the tests, their teachers begin an intensive drilling on all the kinds of problems they will have to do on the test. By the time the test comes along the children are conditioned, like Pavlov's dog; when they see a certain arrangement of numerals and symbols before them, lights begin to flash, wheels begin to turn, and like robots they go through the answer-getting process, or enough of them to get a halfway decent score. Teachers are not supposed to do this; but they all do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things that I often end up arguing about with regards to schools is whether it's good that they teach the things they do. Surely it's better for people to learn a bit of writing, mathematics, etc. that they can build on later, even if they're taught less well than they could be?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I think it's not, because this assumes that "taught less well than they could be" is like "taught as well as they could be" but less so, but that's mostly not the case. Instead people are &lt;em&gt;taught things that they shouldn't be&lt;/em&gt;, in the sense that the things they are taught are wrong and/or useless, and stand in the way of them later learning things properly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of this is the sort of "emotional lesson" I talked about in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-20-00:32.html"&gt;The trauma model of talent blocks&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/made_in_cosmos/status/1412862625516507139"&gt;Maria has a good thread of such lessons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also extends to more practical things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The above anecdote about mathematics education is I think a good example of this: Even if you could help those kids unlearn all of their traumatic associations with mathematics, they've had their head filled with nonsensical rules and rituals they've memorised that are going to actively get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also happens when people are "good" at the subject, because people can learn to pass tests to a really very high grade on this kind of rote memorisation. I once had to explain to someone doing university physics that the expression \(f(x)\) didn't mean \(f\) multiplied by \(x\), but instead evaluating the function \(f\) at the value \(x\). It's literally impossible that she had gotten to that point without having to apply functions, but she'd just learned the rules to follow and had no working model of mathematics on which to base those rules. She &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; got this untangled OK without having to unlearn everything (I wasn't much help, and honestly probably wasn't very nice about it, but in my defence I was 18 at the time).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mathematics has the advantage that at least if you're able to figure the subject out you can pass it well by actually being good at mathematics. Some skills, this is harder. Being actually good at writing doesn't help unless you're also school good at writing, and school good at writing produces really boring writing. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vtIzMaLkCaM"&gt;See Larry McEnerney's critiques for details&lt;/a&gt;. Most people have writing habits they need to unlearn from school, and they'd probably have been better off spending their English classes writing fanfic and arguing on tumblr.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This isn't a dig exactly, those are both very good ways to learn to write)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also notice that people very much need to unlearn reading habits. Most people I know who were book worms as kids struggle to read as adults, and my advice for this is basically &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1418610947107823626"&gt;read badly&lt;/a&gt;. I don't &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; that this one is a school leftover, but it sure feels like it to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1421530364552482820"&gt;I don't set educational policy&lt;/a&gt;, so I don't know what the solution to this is. My personal bias is that when we simultaneously have a problem where we don't have enough school resources, and also most of what we teach is actively harmful, we could solve the former by just teaching way fewer subjects to a higher standard, but there's probably some bad consequence downstream of not ruining most subjects for most people that I'm not currently seeing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I guess my main advice is to notice that this is a thing. When you're trying to learn something you've previously struggled with, you don't just need to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-16-10:12.html"&gt;overcome hurdles in learning&lt;/a&gt; where you previously got stuck, you probably need to back up from the wrong turn you took when trying to work around those.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-31-09:29.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-08-07-08:15.html</id>
    <title>Notes towards a social technology R&amp;D lab</title>
    <updated>2021-08-07T13:51:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes towards a social technology R&amp;amp;D lab&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-08-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I mentioned on Twitter that I'd like to run a "small R&amp;amp;D lab where we mostly do low budget weird social technology nonsense".
This was not something I mentioned as a serious plan, but a throwaway comment about escapist fantasies.
There was a surprising amount of interest in the idea though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;I should maybe mention that if you want to spot me about £2 million over a 3-4 year period to change the world, I'm all ears and we should definitely talk. &lt;a href="https://t.co/EvHd5tcDXh"&gt;https://t.co/EvHd5tcDXh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— David R. MacIver (@DRMacIver) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1423669891345813507?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 6, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In response to this, people have quite reasonably be asking what it is I actually &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; by this plan, because it's not obvious.
So I thought I'd try to articulate this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is not really a proper pitch document, more of a sketch of the idea, but if you've got some spare cash and &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; a proper pitch document it could definitely turn into one).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What's social technology?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think people might have the wrong idea about what I mean by "social technology", which is fair enough as it's not a particularly commonly used term. By "social technology", I don't mean a type of software, I mean something more like sets of practices that people can do together, that have the character of technology, in that they are a well defined thing that benefits from research and development.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I talked about this in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/the-missing-social-technology-sector/"&gt;The missing social technology sector&lt;/a&gt;. My definition from there is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social technology is “technology” built out of groups of people following rules, maybe with assistance from simple props, rather than software, machinery, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've since read Nguyen's "Games: Agency as Art", which I think has helped refine my thoughts on this subject more. Social technology is technology built out of &lt;em&gt;group agency&lt;/em&gt;. It builds a structure to constrain and support the sort of actions that a group can take together, in a way that helps them achieve some desired end.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of a social technology:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pen and paper roleplaying game. Dungeons and Dragons is the classic example, but I think lightweight games like &lt;a href="http://www.onesevendesign.com/laserfeelings/"&gt;Lasers and Feelings&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://img.fireden.net/tg/image/1491/35/1491350819880.pdf"&gt;Four Sherlock Holmes and a Vampire. (Who Is Also One of the Aforementioned Sherlock Holmes)&lt;/a&gt; where the rules fit in a page are a more interesting set of examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed dating.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://agilecoffee.com/leancoffee/"&gt;Lean Coffee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coaching and therapy type arrangements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are designed with the following ends in mind:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A roleplaying game has a &lt;em&gt;ludic end&lt;/em&gt; (the thing you are trying to achieve in the game - uncover the vampire, prevent Zorgon the Conqueror from building a quantum tunnel that will rip a hole in reality), but the ultimate end is to have fun, and you are adopting the ludic end in order to achieve that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed dating you are looking for people to date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lean Coffee you are trying to have a productive discussion across a range of topics, and the structure supports you in picking interesting topics and keeping the meeting on track.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coaching and therapy provide someone with a space to work through a particular problem of interest to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of other examples, both explicit and implicit. For example, &lt;a href="https://www.liberatingstructures.com/"&gt;Liberating Structures&lt;/a&gt; is an entire group of people designing social technology for meetings, and every interviewing pipeline is an ad hoc and buggy piece of social technology. The academic field of social choice theory (which mostly designs voting systems) is a really interesting area of social technology that to within rounding error of nobody uses.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course in a certain light almost everything people do is social technology. There isn't a hard and fast line that makes some things social technology and some things not social technology, in the same way "But is it art?" is an unanswerable question. As a concept, "social technology" is useful less for categorising things and more as a lens through which to view them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular viewing something as social technology starts from asking two questions:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is this practice trying to do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we do that better?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Why do we need social technology R&amp;amp;D?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the most common pieces of social technology that I've encountered outside of games is meeting facilitation.
Liberating Structures is one of the best examples of meeting facilitation social technology that I'm familiar with,
and mostly seems to be very good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, most other social technology I've encountered for meeting faciliation are quite bad, and leans heavily on the skill of the meeting facilitator rather than the technology, and the technology itself is often quite clunky.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Take lean coffee for example. A lot of people really like lean coffee. I attended some lean coffee sessions and they were awful. I loved the idea, I loved what it was trying to do, and the execution has obvious glaring flaws that I feel would have been obvious and easily fixable if they had ever done any sort of playtesting. I cannot imagine they did.
In response I designed &lt;a href="https://github.com/DRMacIver/systems/blob/master/tempo.md"&gt;TickTalk&lt;/a&gt;, which I think is pretty good. It could certainly use more play testing itself, but it's had some and I really do think it's &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; better than lean coffee.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Brainstorming is another example. Brainstorming doesn't work. We're pretty sure of this now. It produces results that are worse than not using it. Many things &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; brainstorming work, and work well, but brainstorming itself very much doesn't.
A little bit of development and experimentation could have revealed this early on, but instead as far as I can tell people just had an idea, slapped a name on it, and declared it the hot new thing that everyone should be doing, and it worked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The common theme here (and why liberating structures tend to be Actually Good) is obvious I hope: &lt;em&gt;Playtest your social technology&lt;/em&gt;, and learn from it and improve it.
People don't do this enough, and are using really bad systems as a result.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Social technology R&amp;amp;D is the solution to this problem. You treat these systems as a piece of technology like any other, and you develop them as such. You try things, you see what works, and you refine based on that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't a novel idea in social technology, everyone who designes games knows this. If you make a game and don't playtest it, you'll get a game that isn't fun and nobody plays. In contrast, when you design a meeting facilitation system, it only has to be less bad than an unfacilitated meeting (this isn't hard), and also you can usually impose it by fiat, so there's much less direct incentive to be good. This is ridiculous though - meetings are expensive and potentially high value, so anything that increases that value or decrease that cost is obviously good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Weird low budget social technology nonsense?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I'm interested in has two defining features:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing social technologies for a broad range of problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...that can be implemented easily and cheaply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, take speed dating. Has anyone actually ever done any speed dating R&amp;amp;D? Speed dating doesn't seem to work particularly well for people, and some of that is because dating is intrinsically awkward, but a lot of it does seem like the structure is just very poorly designed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm pretty confident nobody has ever done a detailed user experience analysis of speed dating and tried to improve it in a principled way. Someone just had the idea, people tweaked it a bit, and it mostly works well enough. For the same reason meeting design lacks a strong incentive to improve (because meetings are so bad that anything helps), speed dating has little incentive to improve (because there's no shortage of single people who would really like some help with dating).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, speed dating is primarily a low value proposition. People don't pay a lot for speed dating, so where would the budget for improving it come from?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(People &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; use speed dating for research, but it seems to be primarily using speed dating as a methodology for studying romantic interactions. i.e. it's people taking the social technology as read and using it to do social science)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Taking something like speed dating and improving it for its intended purpose, and also finding other interesting applications of those approaches (for example, what would a "Speed dating, but you're there to make friends" event look like? How should one do bi/poly speed dating? Could one do a speed dating event to start up a co-coaching network?), is the sort of low budget social technology I'd like to develop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another example of a problem I think would be interesting to study is this: &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2016/11/democracy-for-lunch/"&gt;How do you decide where to go for lunch?&lt;/a&gt;. Or where to go to the cinema. Or what to cook tonight... You get the idea. Collective decision making is common, but I don't actually know how common, and I don't know what the best way to do it is.
I have a history of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:27.html"&gt;solving this for people by just telling them what to do&lt;/a&gt;, but it sure would be interesting to study this class of problem and how to do it better, wouldn't it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, the sort of thing I would like to do is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify reasonably common social problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop social technologies to improve them that can be explained in one or two pages, and implemented with cheap and/or commonly available tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of low hanging fruit of this nature, mostly based on the fact that the individual examples that gain traction don't seem like they're still very much picking low hanging fruit, and it shouldn't be hard to find others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What would this look like in practice?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Gosh, that's a great question, this has turned from a vague idea into something resembling a structured plan remarkably quickly, so this is the bit underspecified, so please bear in mind that I wasn't planning to do this for a while and part of the thing that this would look like in practice is getting a bunch of people together to figure out the details.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The general procedure we'd want to use for developing social technology is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create or identify a prototype piece of social technology with a Version 0 document describing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Playtest it amongst ourselves, then with random members of the public, until we're happy with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish a Version 1.0 version of the social technology in public, probably under a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt; license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over time publish updated and improved versions of it in response to subsequent usage and feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Both (1) and (2) are the bits that need a lot of trial and error. The following are probably the two main sources of prototypes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Study what people actually do in the wild and extract it into something standalone.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often this can start from existing literature. e.g. speed dating comes pre studied. The "teaching open ended style" protocol from Vaughn Tan's The Uncertainty Mindset that I talked about in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-teach-the-local-style"&gt;How to teach the local style&lt;/a&gt; is another example where you can just get it from books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often you can get paid to find this out! Going into a company and consulting with them is a great way to find out what they actually do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting from problems people have (e.g. we could find this out by offering coaching and consultancy services) and then trying to generate solutions to those. This would probably need us to work a bit on the social technology that supports generating these solutions, but I expect we'd be using Liberating Structures or the like as starting points for that rather than trying to invent new ones from scratch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Actively work on the social technology underpinning how the group runs itself, and try to extract this into reusable standalone features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as producing the actual final products, there would probably be:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of writing about the things we learn along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various professional services built on top of this. I think there is quite a lot of scope for this to lead into a lucrative consulting and training business around these things, as a lot of it would be quite useful to companies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What would this need?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My dream version of this where I get to run an actual R&amp;amp;D institution looks something like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Staff would be:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A small team of about 5 for the actual R&amp;amp;D.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone to do admin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probably someone to do sales and marketing? Certainly this would be needed eventually.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of this would need to be done in person (at least post COVID...). This would require an office and a studio space for running events.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that there would need to be budget for:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the usual company stuff. Computers, paying for software, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quite a lot of training, partly for people's personal growth, partly because it's important research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hiring people on one off contracts, for a mix of:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consulting specialists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paying people to do initial playtesting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A flexible group of people who we could bring in to do various research tasks (e.g. send out a bunch of interns to learn more about different meetup groups).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm expecting the professional services arm of the group would do quite well (it's potentially very high value for corporate customers). Initially (and to some degree ongoing - it's a good habit to keep your hand in on) this would be done by the R&amp;amp;D team. With increased demand, it would be necessary to bring on more staff to keep up with it, and eventually I would expect us to transition to having a full training arm.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;How plausible is all this?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly pretty plausible. Some of it is stuff I could do today, and may well start doing as I start providing more consulting and corporate training options built in to my existing work. It's possible that in five years time I may be doing exactly what I describe given no external intervention, assuming I still think it's a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The big questions are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there as much low hanging fruit as I think there is? (I'm reasonably confident there is)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I underestimating the amount of work playtesting takes? (I don't think so, in the sense that the amount of work people currently do is so low that even modest amounts would be an improvement)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there really enough demand for this to fund it? (I'm genuinely unsure about this one, but I think it's likely that there is if it's pitched right).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would this end up a niche thing used only by corporates and weirdos? (This is a totally plausible failure mode. Certainly I expect many of the things we develop would never see wide adoption. But I figure worst case scenario we make a lot of money improving various work environments and maybe make one or two useful prosocial innovations)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All told I'd be very surprised if &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; in this space couldn't be made to work, and also very surprised if what ends up working looks exactly like I've outlined in this document, because technology startups never work out that way, and that's ultimately what this idea is.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-08-07-08:15.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-08-08-12:28.html</id>
    <title>how to write like this</title>
    <updated>2021-08-08T12:59:15+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;how to write like this&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-08-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drossbucket.com/"&gt;Lucy&lt;/a&gt; and I were talking about the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-27-04:25.html"&gt;You have to do the easy bits first&lt;/a&gt; piece, and she asked me how I wrote it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's a good question. I didn't answer it very well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here, let's have another go.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way to write like this is to write like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That isn't a very helpful answer, huh.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One more time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way to write like THIS is to write like THIS!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the way to write&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;like this&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;is to write&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;like this&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;thewaytowritelikethisistowritelike this&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You see?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way to change how you write is to change how you write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The best part of the answer I gave Lucy earlier is that the thing where the paragraphs are short (I said one sentence, but actually looking again they're not) is more important than you'd think.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way to change the voice you write in is to write in a different voice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the voice of your writing is&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;determined by its form. As you shift&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the layout&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the format&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the literal physical way the words appear on the page&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the sound of what you are writing changes, and with it the voice in which you write moves to match.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I write like this, in long discursive paragraphs, in which I patiently explain the thing I am doing to you, that is one voice. I can fuck with it if I want, right? Code switch mid paragraph. I don't have to write like a tedious book, but this is the tone that I naturally fall back into, because habits of writing are entrained ways of being, that one grows comfortable in. If you try to do a thing that is well served by a particular mode, you have to actively exert effort to avoid falling back into that mode. It's entirely possible, especially if you have other modes that you're used to and can borrow from, but without the clarity that those modes provide, it is difficult to avoid. It is hard to write differently without first deciding what that difference is, and the easiest form of difference is to be able to say "More like &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you fuck with the form&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;you instantly break the habit&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;because&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;the habit can no longer serve you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Will the result be good? Nah, probably not. That's OK.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/arts/english/currentstudents/undergraduate/modules/fulllist/first/en122/lecturelist-2015-16-2/shklovsky.pdf"&gt;Viktor Shklovsky thinks that art is about defamiliarisation&lt;/a&gt;, and I think this is even more true for the artist than for the viewer of the art.
In order to create art, you must first break out of your habitual mode of engaging with the thing you are depicting.
Anything that breaks the habit by forcing you outside of what it can do will help you to achieve that,
by pushing you into a mode where everything is strange, and giving you a space in which to learn that strangeness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;but if you do what you also do&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;you'll get what you always get.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is uncomfortable at first, of course it is. You're learning a whole new way of engaging with the world through writing.
Stay with that discomfort, and write through it, and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or, in short:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way to write like this is to write like this.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-08-08-12:28.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-02-08:53.html</id>
    <title>On feeling blocked, redux</title>
    <updated>2021-10-02T08:53:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;On feeling blocked, redux&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-10-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ages ago, when struggling to write, I wrote &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-20-10:33.html"&gt;On feeling blocked&lt;/a&gt;, in which I describe the phenomenology of writer's block.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been really struggling with writing my newsletter recently, so I've decided to solve this with resuming daily writing, and it seemed natural to start by returning to the subject. A year and a half on I have a very different perspective on writer's block.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's this: Writer's block is not wanting to write, or wanting not to write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may seem overly simple, but it's not. It just moves the complexity. Wanting is complicated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular, often some parts of you will want to write, and some parts of you will want not to write, and the resulting inner conflict leads to writer's block.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In "On feeling blocked":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being blocked feels like this. It's not that there's an actual block, it's that you reach for a part of your brain where the words come from and it's not there. You can't run out of ideas and you know this, but you try to follow the steps of the idea generating process and the world glitches and you realise you cut off mid-sentence and have been reading Twitter for the last half hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That sort of distraction is exactly what (at least one type of) an inner conflict feels like. A part of you drives you to write, a part of you resists with some emotional judo and redirects you somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3l08rfl"&gt;On Writer's Block&lt;/a&gt; by Victoria Nelson is a good book about the emotional dynamics of writer's block which, ultimately, boils down to a long discussion of reasons why you might want not to write. Typically they're some variation on wanting to write something that you don't feel able to, or that you feel scared about in some way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular they often come down to trying to adhere to a standard that you don't feel you can be good enough for, or feeling that you should write in a way that isn't actually very good.
e.g. a lot of people get blocked because they're trying to write like they learned to in school and everything comes out boring.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm blocked on my newsletter at the moment. I don't entirely know why, but the symptom is that I have lots of unfinished posts. The solution is probably to write the newsletter more like I do the notebook. I don't feel able to do that, I don't know why yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I'm going to get back to writing even if I can't write the newsletter. Life is much better when I write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The fundamental principles are the same as they always are. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-05-08:59.html"&gt;Make success trivial&lt;/a&gt; then apply &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/05/how-to-do-hard-things/"&gt;the fully general system&lt;/a&gt;. The fact that in this case the hard thing is something that I already in theory know how to do doesn't matter, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-12-08:19.html"&gt;things can be hard for lots of reasons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-02-08:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
