<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2021-07-22T01:05:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-11-11:03.html</id>
    <title>You open one of the 999 boxes on this floor and find...</title>
    <updated>2021-07-11T12:53:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You open one of the 999 boxes on this floor and find...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening I was, for reasons, talking to someone and coming up with strange and unsettling things you could do with surplus rooms in a house. Here are some of my entries:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One room has all the walls mirrored but one of the mirrors is secretly a screen and doesn't flip the image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One room is perfectly normal but for some reason the ceiling is a map of England. There is a "You are here" label on it. The label is, confusingly, pointing at a completely different city.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a pool room. We couldn't decide whether this was the sort with water or the sort where you hit a ball with a stick, so it's both.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room with a microphone and speakers that generate an artificial echo that is on very slightly too long a delay to be comfortable, and also sometimes you'd swear there's another voice in the background.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An entire room which is just a giant playground for cats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls are an ant farm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could keep going pretty much indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One room has many cupboards, but all the cupboards doors look identical to doors to other rooms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room with a window in it that on closer inspection looks out on the wrong side of the house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A perfectly normal living room in which all the furniture is for some reason clad in brightly coloured padded foam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room with central heating that automatically adjusts to a temperature the current occupants will find uncomfortable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room where all the walls are lined with drawers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room that generates a slightly unpleasant noise every time someone talks, gradually training people into silence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room that is perfectly normal but all the wall sockets are that of a different country.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Each of these took me no more than a couple of seconds to come up with, and I feel like I could do this for longer, though I expect I'd start to get a little repetitive at the 100 mark.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls are all different colours. When the room is occupied and nobody is looking at a particular wall, its colour changes very slightly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls "wrap around" visually so that looking at a wall you see the view from the opposite wall, stretching out into infinity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's only so much you can do with walls.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A reading room with several comfy chairs. Next to each is a small table with a pile of books on it. When you take a book off the pile, another one emerges from underneath to replenish the pile. Putting a book back on the pile does not cause any books to disappear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two identical rooms in separate parts of the house that are "sound linked". A cunning arrangement of microphones and directed speakers means that not only do you hear everything happening in the other room, you also hear it as if it were coming from the corresponding place in this room.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm using screens and speakers a lot, but that's because they're so versatile. I'm sure I could do without.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls and floors are a giant jigsaw puzzle. The pieces are lightly magnetic so they stick to the wall easily. The puzzle is of the view you would see from the outside of the house looking in that direction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room where all the furniture is metal and is very gently electrified so you get a light tingle when you touch it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room filled with tiny ballerina dolls. As long as the lights are off, they will dance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason I'm able to do this is that this sort of idea generation is something I just practiced a lot as a child. It's easy to the point of being slightly surprising that other people can't do this so easily.
"How do you come up with all of these things?" "IDK I just think about the subject matter and reach for the place where ideas come from".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of example is particularly easy because "normal" is so tightly constrained. Everyone does most things in broadly the same way - there's variation, but even the variation is within pretty tightly defined bounds. As a result it's easy to generate interesting ideas by moving at right angles. It's easy to make weird things - you just do something that makes people go "Sure, you could do that, but why would you?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of where I learned a taste for this sort of thing and developed this skill is, I think, in &lt;a href="http://basement.warehouse23.com/"&gt;the Warehouse 23 basement&lt;/a&gt;. Someone on Twitter described the Warehouse 23 basement as a kind of proto &lt;a href="http://www.scpwiki.com/"&gt;SCP&lt;/a&gt; and that's not wrong but I think misses something important about it: The things in the Warehouse 23 basement are really quite low effort, and that's part of their virtue. It's seconds or minutes of work, not hours, and so you can iterate on the skill of generating them quite easily.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of idea generation is what Edward de Bono calls "lateral thinking". As with all Edward de Bono books, his book of the same is quite annoying, but it is genuinely useful. I'm particularly a big fan of his suggestion of making lists of a fixed size. Committing to generating, say, 100 ideas, forces you to come up with things that you wouldn't otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lateral thinking is foundational to a lot of creative processes, because often the way to come up with a good idea is to generate many bad ones and see what resonates, then improve on some of the best or most interesting parts of it, and practicing the ability to do it in a generalised sense is useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often when I think about developing useful general skills I think in terms of very sensible reasonable exercises that develop the skill. The warehouse 23 basement is a nice reminder that you can also just develop skills by having fun.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is an elevator room. It doesn't contain an elevator, it's just got lots of pictures of interesting elevators. A low voice is playing in the background, telling you endless interesting facts about elevators.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a room in which every time you say something a small child's voice plays, asking you "But &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;?"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a room in which anything is possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-11-11:03.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-12-17:36.html</id>
    <title>A library of recurring ideas</title>
    <updated>2021-07-12T18:10:35+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;A library of recurring ideas&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-12&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is a quick piece that I am writing because I realised I'm not going to finish the long piece I was writing today)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A thing I notice that I do more than many other people is that I just have a lot of ideas in my head that I pattern match to new situations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Like e.g.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Market_for_Lemons"&gt;Market for lemons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satisficing"&gt;Satisficing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Positive_deviance"&gt;Positive deviance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pluralistic_ignorance"&gt;Pluralistic ignorance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2010/07/26/a-big-little-idea-called-legibility/"&gt;Legibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodhart%27s_law"&gt;Goodhart's law&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuart_Kauffman"&gt;The adjacent possible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These seem to come up time and time again. I'm only mentioning these ones because they're all things that have come up recently,
I'm sure there are dozens if not hundreds of others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are also plenty I've come up with too. e.g. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-04-11:18.html"&gt;Skirting the edge of disaster&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/a-fractal-of-lies"&gt;Fractal of Lies&lt;/a&gt; have both come up recently.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't really have any good evidence that I do this more than other people, but it sure feels like it. I think I even do it more than other people who have some of the same ideas - a lot more people know about the market for lemons than go "Oh, a market for lemons" whenever they encounter the pattern in the wild. I talk about "Things that you can't unsee" but really I might just mean "Things I can't unsee".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of my evidence that I do this to an unusual degree is that I am unusually good at explaining things (at least, I think so, and other people seem to agree), and I think having this sort of library of recurring ideas is part of that: When presented with something to explain, I probably have a ready tool to hand to reach for to take it apart and reveal interesting things about it (&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/fragments-intellectual-diy"&gt;Intellectual DIY&lt;/a&gt; of course being another of my recurring ideas).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another recurring idea that doesn't have a catchy name or something I can refer to, but which I think about a lot, is that anything someone can do is a skill that almost everyone can learn to do better (this doesn't deny talent, although I'm a low-key talent sceptic in a number of ways, I just have a lot of faith in people's ability to learn skills given the right environment).
So if this &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; something I do to an unusual degree, how can people learn to do it better?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2017/02/thinking-through-the-implications/"&gt;Thinking through the implications&lt;/a&gt; I suggested a couple of things that might work:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When learning by doing, write down interesting things you learned so you remember them later explicitly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you learn new things, try to come up with at least one application of them outside the context you’re learning them in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you encounter a new problem, see if anything you learned recently applies to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you re-encounter a problem that you previously believed was hard or impossible, spend at least 5 minutes thinking about why it is hard or impossible and if anything you’ve learned since then changes that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is all good advice, but discounts the explanatory aspect of it. Perhaps the real thing to do is to just use them a lot - building up a conceptual framework in the way I discuss in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-05-10:30.html"&gt;Why do we need new terminology?&lt;/a&gt; by writing things that they enable you to write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, maybe writing is just the best way into this. Perhaps the reason I'm unusually good at this skill really is just writing? Or at least, writing in the way I write. In which case, perhaps the key to developing this skill is contained in:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/10/how-to-explain-anything-to-anyone/"&gt;How to explain anything to anyone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-02-09:29.html"&gt;People are bad at defining things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-03-13:55.html"&gt;No shortage of things to write about&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-08-10:11.html"&gt;A guide to starting a daily writing practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By writing about things as we encounter them, and connecting them to our library of ideas, we train ourselves to recognise these patterns as they occur.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-12-17:36.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-13-11:49.html</id>
    <title>Source: The noosphere, impersonal communication</title>
    <updated>2021-07-13T12:54:01+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Source: The noosphere, impersonal communication&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-13&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently writing a newsletter issue in which I'm explaining a lot of stuff.
Very little of it is original to me, although a lot of it is my own idiosyncratic conception of it, but instead something that I have synthesized from many sources.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What sources?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly, beats me.
Could be anything.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Kirsten3531/status/1412896229378379777"&gt;a recent conversation with Kirsten&lt;/a&gt; in which she'd made a popular tweet and was trying to figure out where she got the idea from, and thought it might be me. Could have been, we're not sure. I've certainly not said exactly the same thing as she did, but I've said a number of things vaguely in that space.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't much care, honestly. The idea isn't mine. If it did come from me, I would have put it together out of ideas I'd picked up from other people. I might have combined some things, I might have tweaked it a bit, but ultimately I'm just a conduit for the flow of ideas. Words come in, at some point later words come out, and there's some relationship between the two but I can't really say that I got the latter from specifics of the former.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example in the piece I'm writing at the moment (probably out some time next week) I'm talking about a bunch of ideas about how learning works. Are they original to me? No, absolutely not, I've read probably a dozen different books that have informed them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But the way they informed them is mostly not traceable to a particular book. I read some books, they informed my practice, and I then wrote something based on that practice and my conception of it. The books left a significant trace, and some of them have been a significant influence on me, but I couldn't necessarily tell you what that influence was any more than I can tell you exactly when and how I learned English, I just did.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What to do in these cases?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well I can mention some of the books I read, but even at a dozen there's no real chance of me remembering all of them (I recently bought a copy of "How children fail" only to discover I'd read it more than a decade ago. I still plan to reread it, and revisit it in a new light, but it's definitely ended up influencing me in ways I have no chance of recreating).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I'll often be saying things that are at odds with those books, or frame things in a different way, or which you'd have to go through the entire multi year long process of digesting the contents of the books before you can squint at them the right way to see that they're deeply instrumental to what I'm saying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And what to do about the books that are even less connected to the topics I'm writing about? My thoughts on education have definitely been influenced by reading anarchist and ethnographic writings from James C. Scott, but it would probably take an entire extra essay to unpick those links.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these problems are soluble. I could keep a detailed log of books. I could go through any books I've read that seem relevant an pick out the connections. I could carefully trace out the lineage of every thought I had in the essay and where its influences come from. None of this is unachievable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It does, however, have one crucial problem: It's hard and boring and I don't wanna.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also not that useful. The reader doesn't care, and the authors I'm citing probably don't care either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may sound like excuse making, and perhaps it is, but I think it's an important consideration. If you raise the bar to writing, many pieces that were previously worth writing no longer are, and this loses out on significant value. Having to carefully attribute everything or else you're bad and you should feel bad will inhibit me, and others, from writing many things that would improve the world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Norms of scrupulously crediting all your sources mostly come out of academia, where they're largely important because credit for ideas is a key part of the academic status game, and publications are supposed to be very clear about what their novel contribution is as a result.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Outside of academia you can just... not do that. It's mostly fine. There's no need to tie credit-assignment to citation like our lives depend on it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead I propose the more modest set of citation norms:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you already clearly know where something comes from, obviously you should cite it and give credit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not explicitly claim ideas as your own unless it's really overwhelmingly clear when in possession of the full facts that they are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If someone attributes an idea to you that is not yours and you notice, politely correct them (for example I'm often credited for the term "life-complete problems" due to my article of the same name, but credit is due to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mechanical_monk"&gt;Mechanical Monk&lt;/a&gt;, as I explicitly highlight in the piece).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recommend sources that you have found valuable, both casually and in your writing, regardless of whether they're directly the source of the idea you are writing about. For example I thought &lt;a href="https://summerbrennan.substack.com/p/discourse-person"&gt;Discourse Person&lt;/a&gt; was an excellent piece about related issues recently - I don't know if it informed this piece much, but it's worth a read either way!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Everything is a remix, we're all riffing off each other, and worrying too much about the credit assignment game within that ruins the flow.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-13-11:49.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-14-11:44.html</id>
    <title>A lack of shared projects</title>
    <updated>2021-07-14T19:07:29+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;A lack of shared projects&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been visiting my parents out in the country recently,
and as a result I was &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1414139777654431744"&gt;talking on Twitter the other day&lt;/a&gt; about an idea I have from a book called "The Art of Frugal Hedonism" (though the idea is hardly revolutionary and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-13-11:49.html"&gt;definitely isn't something I feel like I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to cite&lt;/a&gt;) that a great and commonly underrated way to spend your time is to have a mundane task to do with your hands while sitting around a table with your friends and loved ones chatting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Their example was podding peas, in our case the event that prompted me thinking about it was picking and processing red currants with my family. Honestly, I think they're spot on. Having the shared task to focus on made the conversation flow very smoothly, and there was a satisfaction to doing a task that would have been slightly tedious without the company. They pair very well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This got me thinking how few things in modern life look like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that's interesting about it is the physicality of it, and indeed we don't do a lot of work with our hands.
Much ink has been spilled talking about this sort of thing. I too have read Shop Class as Soulcraft (and I suppose recommend it, maybe, sortof), and various takes in this space. I won't be talking about that today.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead the thing that struck me as anomalous is that we were doing something useful together,
and that's surprisingly rare. We do it at work, we do it when living together as a family. Those honestly seem like the main widespread examples to me. I can think of a few others, but they all feel in some way unusual to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not saying nobody does practical projects with their friends, obviously people do, but it seems anomalous to me? Like it's a relatively rare thing, and it so easily gets coopted by work. e.g. open source projects are kinda this, but they sure mostly feel like free work rather than a practical project with friends done for our own sakes.
Sometimes you ask friends for favours and they help you achieve something, but even that feels rare and socially discouraged.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doing things with friends is certainly a thing, but when we do things with friends it tends to be leisure activities.
We mostly do things because we want to spend time together, not because we're trying to achieve something.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wonder if this is related to the longing some people have for community? In &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/communities-construct-a-sense-of"&gt;Communities construct a sense of purpose&lt;/a&gt; I suggested that a lot of the function of communities is structure our emotional evaluations of what matters, and thereby construct a sense of purpose. This certainly seems related to that - trying to achieve things in tandem with people you care about feels like an almost central example of purpose.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't really have a firm conclusion here. I just find I'm staring at this in vague incomprehension going "No, this must be a thing, right? What am I missing?", and feel very strongly like something weird is going on here.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-14-11:44.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-15-10:56.html</id>
    <title>Spiraling outwards</title>
    <updated>2021-07-15T11:12:58+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Spiraling outwards&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to describe a problem that I have. I have not yet found a good solution for it, and this is why you are getting a very nominal post today in which I describe that problem and think out loud about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is this: I start with something small, and then I think "Oh this is really good, I should do it justice". &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doing it justice makes it... not small. Often it increases the work of doing it by a factor of ten or more. Suddenly it becomes a thing that I need to spent much longer on than I had time allocated for it, and moves it up a project size category.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In concrete terms what happens is that I now have two pieces that started out life as notebook posts and are going to be newsletter issues that I need to finish. They should be pretty easy to finish but I probably won't have time to do so prior to the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often they languish unfinished. This was very much my problem with writing papers. It felt like in order to write an academic paper I had to publish something that was substantially worse than the state of the art that existed in my head, because in order to get to the point where it was publishable I either had to stop thinking about the problem (impossible if I were to be interested enough to finish writing it) or publish something that I felt was worse than I could have done.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't really a problem for many things which feel like I can just snip off a thread. The notebook is good for that, but often I end up wanting to write things which have a certain minimum size without which they would end up incomplete.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think part of the problem here is really not that things become large, but that I need a better way to work on large projects. The paper problem felt like a mismatch between the sort of incrementalism I wanted to do and the sort of incrementalism that academia wanted me to do. The newsletter issue problem is more manageable, and I think I just need to get better at managing my draft backlog and allocating more time to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I can treat drafts as an inbox problem and apply the &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/triage-your-inboxes"&gt;How to triage your inboxes&lt;/a&gt; method to it?&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-15-10:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-16-10:12.html</id>
    <title>Clearing hurdles in learning</title>
    <updated>2021-07-16T10:51:31+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Clearing hurdles in learning&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-16&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The following is not true, but it's often close enough to true that it's worth using as a working model.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When learning a skill, the level of effort required to get to a given point typically looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/effortskillgraph.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This corresponds to the following difficulties of improvement at any given point:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/difficultyskillgraph.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(These numbers are made up imaginary units, obviously)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is, the difficulty of getting better is usually pretty easy, but occasionally there are spikes where the difficulty rapidly increases. The gentle bits are the places where the way to improve is to just do the thing, the spikes are the bits where &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-do-everything"&gt;there's some insight you need to figure out to progress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A very simplistic model of human behaviour is that people do things that are worth the effort of doing. As a result, what often happens when people are learning a skill is that they progress as long as it's easy, and then they hit a part where it's difficult it's no longer worth it to them to keep progressing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result what you end up with is people who stall out particular points in their skill progression, thinking they have reached the limit of their talent, when in fact all they needed was a sustained period of effort at which point they would have started getting better again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think people generally solve these problems in one of three ways:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being smart tends to lower the effort in one of these spikes. I don't know how much of this is "intrinsic" smartness and how much is having already learned the right skills of learning, but if smartness is a thing at all it certainly reduces the effort of generating insights when you're blocked on skill development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being very into the subject makes more effort seem worth it, so someone with exactly the same level of "talent" but more interest will often get better because they reach a spike in difficulty and it's still worth it to them to overcome it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a good teacher &lt;em&gt;hugely&lt;/em&gt; reduces the difficulty level of these spikes, because they already know the insights you're struggling to come up with and can help you discover them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believing in this model will often motivate you to put in more effort than seems reasonable until you've overcome the hump, banking on the promise of future reward (I think, to the degree that they do, this is a lot of why "growth mindset" interventions work).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is what I tend to mean when I say that almost nobody is bottlenecked on talent. They're probably just at a point in their skill development where it wasn't worth it for them to get better on their own, and nobody provided them with the right external support they needed to overcome the current spike in difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is then compounded by the fact that the messaging they get about skill tends to convince them that this is evidence that they lack talent and will never be good at the thing, when in fact they're probably not substantially less talented than many people who end up way better than them due to a mix of luck, privilege, and motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-16-10:12.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-17-14:20.html</id>
    <title>Would you like some advice?</title>
    <updated>2021-07-17T14:45:55+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Would you like some advice?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you wouldn't, too bad. You're here reading my writing, advice is one of the main things my writing is for. If you don't want my advice, don't read my writing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Conversation, however, is different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is a good rule of thumb: When a wide variety of people get annoyed at you for the same behaviour, it's more likely that you are behaving in an annoying way than that there is some bizarre conspiracy in which everyone has decided to behave irrationally for no good reason.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems obvious to me, and yet people persist in offering advice in contexts in which it's obviously unwanted and then getting surprised when people get annoyed at them for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/you-should-complain-about-it"&gt;Complaining about things is good&lt;/a&gt;, and has many virtues above and beyond problem solving. People complain to process their feelings. People complain as a bonding activity. People complain because they're angry and want something to direct it. Sometimes people complain because they're mentioning something annoying in passing as part of a broader point. Complaining is normal, and it is not intrinsically a request for advice on how to solve the thing you are complaining about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Notably: Often people complain about things where they have thought a great deal about the solution space already.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And then people offer advice anyway, and are surprised when this is &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/no-backseating"&gt;just as unwelcome as unrequested advice usually is&lt;/a&gt;, and get all huffy about how they were just trying to help.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The prompting incident that made me think of this is that I was in a situation where someone was describing a problem they had. It was a category of problem I was pretty familiar with and was pretty sure I knew how to solve, but they hadn't asked for my help.
This happens to me a lot, as you might imagine, because I listen to a lot of people and also problem solve professionally.
Must be frustrating, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No it's not, the solution to this problem is very simple, to the point of being blindingly obvious.
I said "I might have some useful advice on this if you'd like it?",
to which he politely thanked me and said he would love some advice, and we had a good conversation about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is what usually happens. Sometimes people say "No thank you", and I respect that, and we have a good conversation about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You know what never happens when I ask something like this though? Nobody ever gets mad at me. Because it's an &lt;em&gt;obviously reasonable thing to ask&lt;/em&gt;, and everyone is pleasantly surprised that I asked rather than leaping in with my opinion, and thanks me not only for my advice but also for checking if it was welcome.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this is my advice: If you want to give someone advice in response to something they said which was not clearly a request for said advice, ask them if it would be welcome, and if they say no then respect that. Also if they're obviously going to say no, don't bother asking and just stay quiet about it rather than wasting their time and yours.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-17-14:20.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-19-09:20.html</id>
    <title>Making life less irritating</title>
    <updated>2021-07-19T14:28:02+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Making life less irritating&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me start by telling you two recent things that happened to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is that I &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1416310982943645696"&gt;was complaining on Twitter about how annoying closing many windows is on Windows&lt;/a&gt;: If you click on the X for a window while in the window switcher then the row lays itself out centered so the next window's X is not under your cursor, wasting an entire second. A second I say!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This may not seem like much but I like to deal with my windows &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/triage-your-inboxes"&gt;Triage your inboxes&lt;/a&gt; style so this does add up to a moderate amount of time and a significant amount of annoyance)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Various people ignored my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-17-14:20.html"&gt;injunctions against offering advice in response to complaint&lt;/a&gt; but honestly I didn't mind that much (they were nice about it - more interested than telling me what to do - and I'd have happily taken advice on this front beside), and their advice didn't quite work but pointed me in the right direction and fairly soon I'd figured out two ways to solve this problem:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you hold down alt tab to get to the window list, keep alt pressed down to keep it open, switch to the window of interest using tab and shift-tab to navigate, and then press delete while still holding tab down, the window will close close and the window list will remain open so you can close more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you go to the other window display (there's probably names for the different displays, I don't know them) by pressing windows+tab or triple swiping up, you can navigate it with the arrow keys and delete also closes a window there too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Knowing this genuinely improves my life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also I've been low grade irritated by this for years, and I had a solution within about 15 minutes of complaining about it on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's another thing I've been annoyed about for a while.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The bins for my flat where I have to take rubbish and recycling to are in the basement car park. The only way down to the basement is by a lift. What with there being a pandemic on, I'm not a huge fan of this. It's mostly fine, but it makes me a little anxious each time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that, it's extra stupid because there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; stairs, but there's a door at the top which is one way - it's just a fire exit, and opens with a bar from the inside. You can't go in the other way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway right now our lift is broken - the heavy rain last week flooded the basement, got into the lift pit, and damaged the lift. Which means that I can't access the bins. Particularly with the current heat, this is a Problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I took another look at the outside of the door and spotted that although there wasn't a door handle, there was a keyhole.
Also it looked like the type of key for the deadbolt on my flat door. Nothing to lose in checking, so I gave it a try, and indeed it worked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This problem has been irritating me, and indeed fractionally (I doubt it actually matters that much - I was never in the lift with other people, and I always wore a mask) increasing my statistical risk of COVID, for about 10 months now, and it took me about a minute of actually looking at it in a very obvious way to solve it once I actually had to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have any number of other examples of this I can think of this over the last year, some of which I've now solved, some of which I still haven't. It appears to be a fairly persistent trend that when there is some persistent annoyance that I could solve in five minutes I &lt;em&gt;don't solve it&lt;/em&gt;, and I don't know why.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This looks like, but I think is distinct from, another class of problem, which is the thing you keep putting off that takes five minutes. That tends to be some sort of fear based procrastination. This isn't that. This is instead a persistent irritation that is solvable almost as soon as you think to genuinely try to solve it. It's not an aversion, it just doesn't seem to register that it's a thing I can solve until something finally causes it to shift.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have a couple of theories, and some possible avenues to try, for why this happens, but for now I'm just going to start with a simple recognition prompt: When I notice that I am annoyed, I'll try to think whether it's something I could easily solve. If it's not, that's fine, I'm certainly not committing to solve the irritations that are hard and difficult work to solve, but it seems worth trying to learn to be better at making the world less irritating.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-19-09:20.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-20-00:32.html</id>
    <title>The trauma model of talent blocks</title>
    <updated>2021-07-20T02:30:57+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The trauma model of talent blocks&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something very important you learn as a result of doing a mathematics degree. It's this:
People &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; didn't like studying mathematics at school, and they are keen to tell you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something like a 50% hit rate when you talk to normal people (people in tech don't count) that when you tell someone you did mathematics at university they say "Oh god I hated mathematics at school". Sometimes they say it in different words. "Oh.", in a very flat tone of voice. "You must be very clever". They look at you with the wary look of a gazelle facing off with a lion, fearful and ready to bolt at the slightest sign of you baring your teeth and trying to do an equation at them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, I've historically found this quite irritating, but as time has gone on I've started looking at it differently.
Instead of treating this as an attack on my interests, when people say this to me my first thought is more along the lines of "I'm sorry your mathematics teacher hurt you."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't usually say it that way, that's a good way to get punched. Instead I wince sympathetically and say "Yeah, it's often taught really badly."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I add "Sorry about that".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-16-10:12.html"&gt;clearing hurdles in learning&lt;/a&gt; I talked about how often what happens is that people hit a block where the they require help to progress and think of this as their natural talent limit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The detail this missed out on is what happens next, which is that you get stuck and we do two things, in order:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tell you to try harder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blame you for not succeeding and then tell you it's your fault and is an intrinsic feature of you and your abilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A distinction I find quite useful is that between guilt and shame. Guilt is when you feel bad about what you do, shame is when you feel bad about who you are. "I did a bad thing" vs "I am bad". It's not a perfect distinction but it's a pretty good rule of thumb.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another principle I find useful (see &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/jiminy-cricket-must-die/"&gt;Jiminy Cricket Must Die&lt;/a&gt;, or "Voices: The Educational Formation of Conscience" by Thomas Green) is that moral emotions are the internalised judgement of others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A third principle I find useful is that emotional reactions we learn tend to stick around until we find a way to actively engage with them and change them by recognising that our situations have changed (see &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;Emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html"&gt;Your emotions are valid but probably wrong&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sure &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; like having kids spend a substantial fraction of their entire childhood in an environment in which they are praised or punished for their academic achievement, then telling them that their failure to excel is the result of an intrinsic feature of themselves and punishing them for it anyway might have some uh lasting negative emotional side effects, huh?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let me tell you about my experience learning to drive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My attempts to learn to drive went as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had driving lessons when I was 18. I was bad at it. I stopped driving lessons and went to university in a town where I could cycle everywhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I moved back in with my parents for about six months post university, and used this as an opportunity to practice driving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I took a few more driving lessons to fill in some gaps, I was fine, and I passed my practical test first time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm absolutely fine at driving, and am comfortable enough doing it that I've done multiple long road trips.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What made the difference between my first attempts at learning to drive and my subsequent attempts?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, my first driving instructor was a very angry person, and tended to shout when I made mistakes. The result was that I was so anxious learning to drive and so afraid of making errors that I was unable to drive to any degree of competence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's certainly not the case that I'm a natural driver. My physical coordination and spatial awareness are on the poor side. It's possibly genuinely true that I was dangerous and needed correcting in my first driving lessons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And yet, somehow shouting at me about that didn't help, because it turns out that experiencing intense negative emotions every time you make an error is not &lt;em&gt;remotely&lt;/em&gt; conducive to the acquisition of complex skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't expect feeling shame every time you think of a subject is much different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear: This is, for the most part, not teachers' fault. There are definitely individual teachers who make the problem worse (e.g. by behaving like my driving instructor), and there are individual teachers who make the problem less bad, but fundamentally this is a function of the system. It arises from the system of grading, and is compounded by the fact that when you hit a block you need individually tailored help to overcome it, which our systems of teaching are absolutely not set up to provide unless your parents are rich enough to hire a tutor for you. While a great teacher can ameliorate the worst of this problem, attempting to solve it will break them because the task is too big.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But regardless of whose fault it is, it seems to hurt a lot of people pretty badly, because they end up hitting their "talent limits" - the bits where they needed help - and instead of either helping them progress or telling them that their current level was good enough, the education system chose violence and made their attempts to improve &lt;em&gt;harder&lt;/em&gt;, not just now but effectively forever until they unlearn the incorrect emotional lessons that they got instead of the lessons they should have been getting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suspect that above and beyond the specific subjects that we fail to learn as a result of this dynamic, it has a much broader impact on our conception of ourselves, because we think in terms of subjects we are good at and subjects we are bad at,
when instead we should be thinking more in terms of how good we want to be a subject and how much help we need to get there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also suspect that many people would find it really helpful to get some one on one tutoring in subjects they struggled at at school where they feel bad about that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, suspicions aside, one thing I'm reasonably certain of is that there are a lot of adults walking around with lingering low-grade trauma from school that they think of as their "lack of talent", and would benefit a great deal from the following reframing: It's not that you're bad at it, whatever "it" is, you were just never given the sort of help you needed.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-20-00:32.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-22-01:05.html</id>
    <title>Learning from the real</title>
    <updated>2021-07-22T01:05:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Learning from the real&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-22&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-04-11:18.html"&gt;Skirting the edge of disaster&lt;/a&gt; I pointed out that most complex systems that have been running in production for a while (e.g. a legacy software system, the London underground, humanity) have the form that they do as a result of the following two rules:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If an important system is broken, we fix it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a system has spare capacity, we place more demands on it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can tell from the title of the linked piece, I was mostly framing this as a bad thing: The consequence of being at a stable balance of these two things is that the system is constantly almost but not-quite broken, because every time it gets too far from broken it gets loaded more, and every time it breaks it gets fixed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there's another side to this that I think is interesting: If you encounter a reasonably stable complex system in the wild (and you do, very regularly), this reliably means:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It does a lot of things, because capabilities kept accreting over time, and they're often not things you would have thought of without that infrastructure because it changes what's easy and cheap to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything that would have stopped it from doing those things has been solved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of time, work, and ingenuity has often gone into getting it to that state, much of which would have been impossible to figure out from first principles because you had to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;try things and see what happened&lt;/a&gt; before you could even learn that you needed to solve the problems, let alone how.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Gall_(author)"&gt;Gall's law&lt;/a&gt; is "A complex system that works is invariably found to have evolved from a simple system that worked. A complex system designed from scratch never works and cannot be patched up to make it work. You have to start over with a working simple system."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But this then leads to the question: OK smart guy, how do I make a working simple system?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And I think the answer is often this: Go find a complex system that does what you want, and study it until you understand it well enough to extract a simple system from it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-22-01:05.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
