<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2022-12-08T20:25:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:53.html</id>
    <title>Getting to know the right people</title>
    <updated>2022-06-05T14:58:24+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Getting to know the right people&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-06-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's a draft bankruptcy piece about how you solve the problem of finding good people in areas you lack expertise in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;It's hard to find good people these days&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you find a good plumber?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Easy. You ask a good plumber who they'd recommend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No, you can't just google for a good plumber. You'll find a plumber
but they probably won't be a good one. Good plumbers mostly don't
advertise, they've already got far more work than they need. Also
there's a market for lemons problem with unknown tradespeople - most
tradespeople are bad to OK (because most people in any job are bad to
OK), the ones that are good are worth their weight in gold, but you
don't know which you're getting and you don't want to pay the latter
like the former and the latter don't want to work for the rate you'd
be willing to pay the former.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Why do you need a good plumber if you already know a good plumber? Well
because they're a good plumber, and thus they're probably too busy for
you, or because you live on a boat and they don't do boats, or because
you live in a house and they don't do houses, or...)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This makes it sound harder than it is. You can also e.g. ask a good
joiner who they'd recommend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you find a good joiner? Well you find a good plumber and ask them
who they'd recommend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you make new friends? Just go to parties and find people you hit
it off with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you go to parties? Well, ask your friends to invite you along to
them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you find someone to date? Meet people through your friends.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you make those friends? Well if the parties option isn't working
out for you you can always find someone to date and make friends with
their friends.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you find a good plumber? Well you make friends with the sort of
people who need plumbers and ask them for their recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This mostly doesn't work in reverse, especially in the city. You
probably can't make friends with your plumber - not because it's
intrinsically impossible, but the interactions you have with trades
people are not necessarily conducive to this. I'm sure it works for
some people from time to time, but it's not a reliable strategy)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;It's all about who you know&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, the way to find the right people is to know the right
people, and the right people generally form a network of similar right
people, so as soon as you know some it becomes much easier to find many.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finding the first couple of right people can be almost impossibly hard.
For some of these things (e.g. plumbers) you can solve this problem by
throwing enough money at it - if you try 10 plumbers eventually one will
probably be OK. You might even have the skill to be able to tell
they're OK. For finding friends in a new city, you can't really buy
friendship, that's not how it works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Your relationship with a network goes in roughly the following levels of
strength:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can be completely disconnected from it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can be &lt;em&gt;tenuously connected&lt;/em&gt; to it - you know a small number of
    people in it, but not necessarily particularly robustly. It's
    difficult to ask favours of them because you're in a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-24-09:46.html"&gt;low trust /
    high
    importance&lt;/a&gt; scenario.
    You need these people to transition to stage 3, but also if you lean
    on them enough to do that they might get upset with you and
    disconnect you from the network entirely, putting you back in
    stage 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are &lt;em&gt;well connected&lt;/em&gt; to the network - you have no trouble
    accessing it, and can use it in the way that you need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of the network - you don't just have access to it,
    members of it consider you one of them in some way, and people
    access you through it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Moving from weaker to stronger connections to a network is what I think
of as the &lt;em&gt;network bootstrapping&lt;/em&gt; problem. Your future strength is built
on your current strength.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Transitions from (1) to (2) and (2) to (3) are both very hard, and
require quite different skillsets. I'm still myself only really figuring
out what those skillsets are, but I'll do my best to explain.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being in stage (4) is complicated and tends to vary with types of
network - with networks of friends there's a well defined transition (3)
to (4). With networks of plumbers the way you become part of the network
starts with being a plumber. I'm mostly not going to talk about stage 4.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Meet the network&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you want to connect to a network that you are completely
disconnected from. What do you do?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, first off, bear in mind that you might not be able to do that.
Many networks are Not For People Like You - you're the wrong race,
class, or gender. You didn't go to the right schools. Your family's
ancestors didn't subjugate the right people three generations back along
with the other members of the network. Or maybe you're just too weird
and the people in the network don't want to put up with that. Some
networks are just exclusive and nothing you can do will gain you access
to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is bad, obviously. I want to be clear on this: This is bad. It's a
major source of inequality. I mention it not because I think this is how
networks &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; work, but because prejudice is a real thing that
exists in the world and it's important to recognise that this problem is
linked in with that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But assuming the network is one that you could, in principle, connect to
if you knew how, how do you actually do that?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The common solution for the initial connection to a network is to
bootstrap it from another network. Ask your friends about plumbers, ask
your friends in one city about people to connect to in another. Turn
Twitter friends into IRL friends. This works great if you already have
networks you're well connected to, and those networks are ones that are
well connected to other networks. It requires going out on a limb and
asking for favours from people, which can be socially tricky and anxiety
provoking, but most people are happy to help in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specific tip: It's better to ask for introductions one on one rather
than e.g. posting a message on a shared group. You're more likely to get
an honest response that way, and often what will happen in a shared
group is that the least trustworthy member of the group will post a bad
answer and other people won't find it worth the effort of arguing with
you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If meeting the network via one of your other networks is not really an
option (e.g. because you don't really have any other networks, or
because nobody in your networks knows a good plumber), you need to work
harder.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've got to be honest, I'm still figuring out how this works. Here is my
very sketchy understanding of how things work:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have access to existing networks you are well connected to,
    you really really should be using them. Ask for favours and
    introductions. It's scary, but it's mostly fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some networks are in some sense "open entry" in that you can gain
    access to them without knowing people. If you have a job, your work
    network is like this (Unfortunately &lt;em&gt;finding&lt;/em&gt; a job is quite network dependent. Chances are if
    you don't have good social connections your first job won't be very
    good, but you can use it to bootstrap to a better one. Recruiters are
    also a way of getting what is basically paid (by the company) access to
    a network and are less good than personal connections but cast a much
    broader net). There are also e.g. churches, activity groups
    (these haven't worked very well for me), professional networking
    events. These are often a good grounding for finding other higher
    value local networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often you can find people in the network you want to connect to and
    just cold approach them. This doesn't work for the plumber problem
    (because if you could find them without a network you wouldn't have
    the problem), but it does work for many other networks. e.g. if you
    want to know people in an academic discipline you can just find and
    follow some people on Twitter in that field who seem nice and start
    talking to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many networks are connected to other more visible networks. e.g. I
    have a hunch that if you walk up to a random house boat and say
    "Excuse me, I have an odd question", pause as they brace themselves
    for the inevitable "what's it like to live on a boat?" question and
    then ask "Can you recommend me a plumber?" they will be utterly
    nonplussed and then recommend you an excellent plumber because
    they're a house boater and they &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; know or know someone
    who knows a good plumber as a result. I suspect going into a
    builders' merchant (which tend to be more visible) and asking one of
    the staff members will have a similar result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general I think this is a problem that requires a level of
systematicity that people often feel uncomfortable bringing to bear on
social problems, and requires you to think about people in fairly
strategic terms. My recommendation is to treat every individual you
interact with as respect, and to otherwise suck it up and deal with it.
It's unpleasant, will result in a fair bit of low-grade rejection, but
generally nothing actually bad will happen and the problem is fairly
amenable to hard work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Starting from zero&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is... harder if you don't have any well connected networks,
which many people don't. It's been about 15 years since I've had this
problem, so I may not be the best to advise on it, but here is how I
understand the process to work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is that some networks are essentially "open entry"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In that case the solution is to build some networks from scratch and
just accept that everything is going to be much harder than it needs to
be until you solve this problem, but also accept that things will become
&lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; easier after you have solved this problem and thus that it is
worth doing (I think a lot of people get trapped assuming that they will
forever be isolated).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the solution is to essentially start with easier to join
networks. A lot of networks make it easy to attach to, because you have
a natural entry point into them. For example:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting a job gets you a professional network, which you can try to
    turn into a friend network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making friends on Twitter is much easier than making friends
    offline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joining a church is supposedly a good way to connect to a
    pre-established network, although this didn't work for me (it was a
    UU church, which may not be representative of the general
    experience).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are a lot of professional meetup groups that are basically
    explicitly networking events. Software development is particularly
    good for this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People always recommend activity groups for this. This maybe true,
    but it didn't really work out that way for me. I think there's a
    skill to using them this way that I lack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's more support for bootstrapping a romantic partner than a
    friend network, so you can always find people to date using the apps
    and steal their friendship
    network (Personally I found online dating the absolute worst and cannot recommend this strategy at all, but I do know people for whom it's worked).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Connect to the network&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had an empty section here. No idea what I was going to write here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;So what?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm interested in this pattern for a couple of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is just that sometimes I need to actually find a good plumber,
or the equivalent thereof in some other field of expertise. e.g. I've
been vaguely intending to find a good singing teacher and didn't have
the faintest idea of where to start until one happened to attach to my
network of friends (I don't yet know if she's good or not - I start
next week), and I'd like to develop some general skills for doing this
better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think some of those general skills consist of just being better about
noticing this is a thing and asking for introductions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second is that I think it's a really underappreciated form of
inequality. Having a rich set of networks that you are well attached to
makes life &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much easier, and almost by definition we don't really
notice the people on the fringes or who are not well connected to our
networks. Such people are both experiencing a much harder life than
people with better social connections, and also are deprived of an
environment where they can learn those skills of network bootstrapping
because they're not connected to anyone who can teach them!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This also scales way further upwards than I have access to - the
networks you get access to from having the right families, the right
wealth, etc. are things of immense power that I have only the vaguest
conception of)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One consequence of this is that if you're well connected to a network,
helping other people join it is almost certainly &lt;em&gt;hugely&lt;/em&gt; life improving
for them, much more so than you realise. Looking out for people who need
help being onboarded into a network that they might not even know
exists, and helping them connect to it, is one of the most
transformative things you can do for another person, and people should
do a lot more of it than they do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not really sure why this piece was abandoned. I think it was too large and I didn't quite know what I was building up to, partially because I was theorising about a problem that I haven't had a huge amount of success with personally.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-15:04.html</id>
    <title>Knowledge and justice</title>
    <updated>2022-06-05T15:06:40+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Knowledge and justice&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-06-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was an abandoned attempt to introduce the ideas of &lt;em&gt;Epistemic Injustice&lt;/em&gt; in
an accessible manner.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You should need approximately zero philosophy to
understand this, though I'll occasionally refer back to the relevant
philosophical terminology to connect it up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Credit&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The idea of Epistemic Injustice comes from the philosopher Miranda
Fricker, who wrote &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2OB2HYH"&gt;a book of the same name&lt;/a&gt;
about it. My understanding of the subject has been heavily informed by
Kristie Dotson's "&lt;a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5250/fronjwomestud.33.1.0024?seq=1"&gt;A Cautionary Tale: On Limiting Epistemic
Oppression&lt;/a&gt;".
I'll also be drawing a little bit on Elizabeth Anderson's &lt;a href="https://philpapers.org/rec/ANDEJA"&gt;Epistemic
Justice as a Virtue of Social
Institutions&lt;/a&gt; and Rittberg et. al's
&lt;a href="http://philsci-archive.pitt.edu/15133/1/Epistemic%20Injustice%20in%20Mathematics%20%28to%20appear%29.pdf"&gt;Epistemic Injustice in
Mathematics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, I'll be synthesising a little bit with some broader themes.
I'll be drawing on some of the work of James C. Scott in &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/30ktRbu"&gt;Seeing Like a
State&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2DSR7py"&gt;Domination and the Arts of
Resistance&lt;/a&gt;, and Jean-Francois Lyotard's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/32vPDfj"&gt;The
Postmodern Condition: A Report on Knowledge&lt;/a&gt;.
I'll also be drawing on some of CN Lester's book &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/32zHUN8"&gt;Trans Like
Me&lt;/a&gt; for an example of epistemic injustice that
I've not seen discussed in the literature.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because of this synthesis I won't necessarily be explaining any of this
in the terms that the authors would use, but I'll do my best to
highlight all the places we differ explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Knowledge is Social&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you know what you know?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't a trick question. I'm not going to probe deep into the nature
of knowledge here. I mean it much more literally: You, presumably, know
things. How? Where did you learn them?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, mostly, you learned them from other people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of it of course you will have learned through direct experience, or
figuring out on your own, but even that tends to blur in with the bits
you learned from other people - I know that I am typing this newsletter
on a laptop, and that is knowledge I have from direct experience, but
the fact that I know what "typing" is, or even "a laptop" is is
knowledge that, ultimately, came from someone else. Although the
&lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; is mine, the knowledge that allows me to interpret and
understand it is part of a shared canon that I have learned from and
with the people around me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Don't get me wrong, a lot of my knowledge is of my own making: I'm
clever, I've figured things out. I'm sure you have too. But even for
people a lot cleverer than me it's a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; easier to figure things out
with others' help.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This help both with the knowledge that we have learned from them, and
with their direct help when we have a problem to solve that we need to
figure out. Knowledge isn't just collective in the sense that we learn
things from other people - we go to other people with our problems, talk
them out, explain them and solve them together. At the end of the
discussion changes are that &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; involved has learned something
about it, and you have a little more shared and common knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What is Epistemic Injustice?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As with anything involving more than one person, this process of
constructing knowledge together can be done in ways that are unjust.
This is what Fricker calls &lt;em&gt;Epistemic Injustice&lt;/em&gt; (Epistemic just means
"Concerning knowledge"): An injustice done to or by you in your capacity
as someone participating in the process of constructing knowledge
together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Examples of epistemic injustices include:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unjustly dismissing someone's testimony. e.g. "You would say that,
    you're a woman". By doing this you are refusing their contributions
    to the process of collective knowledge. Fricker calls this a
    &lt;em&gt;testimonial injustice&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unjustly denying someone the knowledge they need to solve their
    problems. e.g. Fricker cites the example of women needing the term
    "sexual harassment" to explain an aspect of their lived experience,
    and previously lacking it partly due to a prejudicial environment
    that prevented them from identifying it. Fricker calls this example
    a &lt;em&gt;hermeneutical injustice&lt;/em&gt; but she means something slightly more
    specific than denial of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unjustly refusing to acquire (or acknowledge the validity of) the
    knowledge that allows you to engage properly with someone else's
    worldview. e.g. white people refusing to engage properly with people
    of colour's views on racism. Dotson calls this &lt;em&gt;contributory
    injustice&lt;/em&gt; (though again means something slightly more specific).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spreading lies about a particular subject (e.g. about trans people,
    their behaviour, their medical treatment) so that when people of a
    particular group try to tell the truth about their lives they are
    dismissed because "everybody knows" things that contradict that.
    (This is what CN Lester calls "The production of ignorance")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What makes it injustice?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tend to differ from a lot of the canon on some of the details of
epistemic injustice, and you're reading my newsletter so you're going to
get my view on the subject (sorry). Here I'll spell out some of those
differences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For Fricker, Epistemic Injustice is tied to a very specific conception
of justice, and in order to count it has to be an injustice that is
specifically &lt;em&gt;identity prejudicial&lt;/em&gt;: That is, it's done to you based on
some stable aspect of your identity (e.g. race, gender).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tend not to insist on that for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is that it ties you concepts of justice to whatever way you
happen to bucket people into categories. Unless you are &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
confident that you understand the myriad ways in which humans can vary,
tying your notion of justice to your particular favoured labelling
scheme is itself prejudicial (I wrote about this a bit before in
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-23-09:37.html"&gt;Legibility
Privileges&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fricker herself makes significant errors in the book as a result of this
- e.g. she has the example of treating someone as dishonest (and thus
discounting them as a source of knowledge) because they don't want to
make eye contact as &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an example of an injustice because it's based
on an individual trait of e.g. shyness rather than their identity,
completely ignoring that it might be because they're autistic.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second reason I tend to discount this view is that it's just weird
and obviously wrong. Although many injustices &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; identity prejudicial
in nature, by no means all are (e.g. you can do someone an injustice
just by behaving like an asshole to them when they've done nothing to
deserve it, just because you don't like them). It puts us in the
situation where something might be obviously epistemic in nature,
obviously an injustice, and yet not an epistemic injustice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So if not identity prejudice, what makes something an epistemic
&lt;em&gt;injustice&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Pass, sorry.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In all of my examples of epistemic injustice I just said "This thing
happens, and also it's unjust" and that's about the level of specificity
I'm willing to get into. I think trying to pin down when exactly
something is an epistemic injustice is a very hard problem and will
depend on your theory of and feelings about justice more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is somewhere where Fricker's focus on identity prejudice based
injustices does a lot of work, because it allows her to focus on cases
where you can just say "Yeah obviously this is bad". e.g. Dismissing
someone's mathematical work because they're black is &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt; an
injustice (unless you're really extremely racist), and you don't have to
do much work to justify this. Dismissing the same person's mathematical
work because they are telling you they have a one page proof of Fermat's
last theorem on the other hand is entirely justified because you'd do
exactly the same if they were white.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I assume you have your own conceptions of justice, and I do not plan to
solve the problem of justice in this newsletter issue (maybe a later
one...). Instead I think understanding epistemic injustice will come
down to understanding how things play out in the field of collective
knowledge, and then carrying over your normal beliefs about justice to
that field. What is distinct about epistemic injustice is not that it
requires its own notion of justice, but that it requires paying
attention to and understanding how we relate to knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Different Types of Epistemic Injustice&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another way I differ from the canon is that I find this attempt to
pigeonhole epistemic injustices into different categories (testimonial,
hermeneutical, contributory...) &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; uninteresting. There are always
going to be more ways to do an injustice than we can conveniently label,
and having all these labels feels like an instance of &lt;a href="https://notebook.lisamcnulty.co.uk/2020/05/28/the-fallacy-fallacy/"&gt;the Fallacy
Fallacy&lt;/a&gt;
- labelling something doesn't necessarily help you explain why it's bad,
and explaining why it's bad removes the need to label it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also had the following two section titles, completely empty:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding the Epistemic Playing Field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structural vs Individual Epistemic Harms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not very surprised I abandoned this piece. I hate this type of summarisation work, not so much because it's unimportant as because I never know where to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-15:04.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-15:15.html</id>
    <title>You don't learn in a straight line</title>
    <updated>2022-06-05T15:15:41+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You don't learn in a straight line&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-06-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's another abandoned draft from the newsletter archive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd like to talk about learning things, and how the way we learned as
children&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Learning things in order&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Have you ever thought about what determines the order you learn things
in? Some things you learn at the same time of course, but you're
learning throughout your life and so inevitably you learn some things
before others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes there's no particular rhyme or reason to the ordering. I
learned to play the bassoon before I learned to program, but likely
plenty of people do it the other way around, and that's not not
particularly surprising, and many people learn only one or neither of
them. There's no dependency between the two, the only thing determining
the order is the particular details of my life story. Call that a
&lt;em&gt;coincidental ordering&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But other things the order feels more intrinsic. You have to learn to
walk before you have to learn to run. You have to learn to read before
you learn to write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an order where there is some sort of &lt;em&gt;dependency&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;ordering&lt;/em&gt;
between the two. It might in theory be logically possible to learn to
write before you learn to read, or to learn to run before you learn to
walk, but it's pretty hard to imagine there being common circumstances
under which that makes sense (Not completely impossible, mind. I learned to swim before I learned to
walk, and I can imagine that there might be effective ways of teaching
that teach reading and writing simultaneously).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But do you have to learn to run before you learn to read? It's clearly
not logically necessary, and it's also not universally the case. Some
people will never run at all, due to physical disabilities. Presumably
some people will have developmental delays in their gross motor skills
but not fine motor skills, delaying when they learn to run, so it's
fairly likely that there are people out there who learned to write
before they learned to run, and maybe even before they learned to walk.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can think of this particular type of dependency as a &lt;em&gt;typical
ordering&lt;/em&gt;. It's one that's determined by the normal developmental
development of children: Most people are ready to learn one thing before
they're ready to learn the other, and it's good (or we think it's good)
for them to learn it as soon as they're ready.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Teaching things in order&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a little bit of a sleight of hand up there, did you notice? What
does it mean to learn to write?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, let me give you a clue: I was in my mid teens before I learned to
write to the standard that we expect most kids to write before they're
10, and arguably I'm still not there. Also, before I was 10, I was
writing very well (by the standards we'd judge someone of that age).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How does this work? Well, "writing" means two different things here.
When we talk about teaching kids to write, we primarily talk about
teaching them to &lt;em&gt;handwrite&lt;/em&gt;. This is bottlenecked on the development of
their fine motor coordination, not on their verbal ability, and my fine
motor coordination lagged considerably behind my verbal development
(this is part of something called dyspraxia). As a result, my "writing"
in the sense of "handwriting" was terrible, but if you put me in front
of a keyboard I could write pretty competently.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I honestly don't remember the details of how much trouble this caused me
in school. After a while of struggling I just refused to write in
anything other than block capitals (I eventually learned to fix this, no
thanks to the schooling), and this "solved" the problem by aging out of
the period where any teacher thought it was their job to comment on my
handwriting, but the period up to that point was I think pretty
stressful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More importantly, it was a stress that permeated &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;, because
every class I was in expected me to be able to handwrite my answers (I
could at least type homework in some cases).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can think of this perhaps as a &lt;em&gt;normative ordering&lt;/em&gt; in how we learn
things. It's not that there's actually any logical necessity to learn to
handwrite to any reasonable standard before you learn, say, history or
physics, but the entire system is set up to give you a pretty bad time
if you don't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't really consider this a great injustice perpetrated against me -
at the time computers were more expensive and generally less widespread
than they are now. It would have been genuinely hard to computerise
everything, and there are still major challenges to that today. But it
was still a problem I experienced that I wouldn't have with another way
of teaching (There's a whole complicated story with me getting special permission to
use a laptop at school that I won't get into here because it's besides
the point, and I compensated OK by being otherwise good at the subjects
I cared about, so I don't know that I suffered much in the way of
lasting consequences from this, but it was at best unpleasant at the
time.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This problem gets worse with people who have reading difficulties (e.g.
because dyslexia). A lot of subjects could in theory be taught purely
orally - you don't actually need to be able to read to do philosophy for
example, and many classic philosophers were actively against reading and
writing - but the way we teach them is intimately tied up with reading
and writing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I'm not saying this is bad. I'm saying this is a trade off,
where we have adopted a particular style of teaching that works for most
people, and some people get a worse deal under this trade off than
others because of their specific difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Typical orderings become normative&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I apparently never wrote this section, but the basic idea feels fairly obvious to me: If it's super convenient to teach in one set order, then that order becomes widely adopted, and it's not long before failing to learn in that order is treated as a problem with the student instead of the system.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No idea why I abandoned this one. It feels like it's only a short section away from being complete. I may just have got distracted.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-15:15.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-15:16.html</id>
    <title>Consensually treating people as things</title>
    <updated>2022-06-05T15:24:22+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Consensually treating people as things&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-06-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's a section from a post that I didn't manage to get any of the real meat of written:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"There's no greys, only white that's got grubby. I'm surprised you
don't know that. And sin, young man, is when you treat people like
things. Including yourself. That's what sin is."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"It's a lot more complicated than that--"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"No. It ain't. When people say things are a lot more complicated
than that, they means they're getting worried that they won't like
the truth. People as things, that's where it starts."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Oh, I'm sure there are worse crimes--"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"But they &lt;em&gt;starts&lt;/em&gt; with thinking about people as things..."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- the Reverend Mightily Oats and Granny Weatherwax, in conversation
in Terry Pratchett's "Carpe Jugulum"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this post I will be going "Yes, people as things, very bad. Quite
sinful. But... sure is useful, isn't it?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Moreover, if we take this definition seriously, I think most of modern
civilization can reasonably be considered a technology of sin. The whole
&lt;em&gt;point&lt;/em&gt; of markets and supply chains is that we can treat these complex
systems that are made mostly of people as things to achieve a particular
purpose. A supermarket is a thing for acquiring stuff we want, and we
get to mostly ignore the fact that it's made up of people. Sure, we
interact with supermarket staff a bit, and we hopefully treat them well,
but this ignores the giant invisible mass of people behind them -
delivery, warehouse workers, factories, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've written about this before in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/the-usefulness-of-bad-people"&gt;The usefulness of bad
people&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core of this problem is is that the price system works as a black
box, hiding the implementation of where things come from from its
consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern supply chains and commodity markets are an incredibly intricate
system of interdependent parts that is far too complex to really
understand. This complexity is, in fact, part of the benefit, because
it grants us plausible deniability around the ethics of our actions.
If everything is too complex to track then we don't have to notice all
of the bad people downstream of our decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, as with the sales people, we never &lt;em&gt;ask&lt;/em&gt; those people to
be bad, we just say "I want this thing at this price, the details are
up to you" and get to be shocked, shocked I say, when the only way to
provide the thing at that price is slavery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And yet, for all its flaws, I'm not quite prepared to say "Well, modern
civilization is built on sin, burn it to the ground". I &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; modern
civilization and, more importantly, don't actually think this is a net
increase in treating people like things. The past was pretty bad for
this too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, for the most part, being treated as a thing in this way can be
perfectly fine. A lot of the nice thing about a job is that you &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt;
have to bring your whole self to work. You can narrowly act in a
specific capacity for achieving a well defined goal, without your
customers having to worry about what you get done outside of the job, or
you having to worry about the whole giant tangled mess of your life
there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But this is only true if you got to choose that. Being a thing that is a
high priced software consultant is a very different experience than
being a thing that is an exploited worker in a cocoa plantation. The
latter might theoretically have consented (in that it's better than the
alternative), or they might be literal slaves who have no choice but to
be there, but either way&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the moral resolution to this is something along the following:
The problem with treating people as things is not that you are treating them as things, it is one of consent. When your conception of someone as a thing combines with your power over them, you force thingness upon them. It's quite literally a form of objectification.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was in fact meant to be a post about the use of "Focus" in Vernor Vinge's novel "A Deepness in the Sky", and what this tells us about group dynamics. But I didn't write any of that bit, because I got too caught up in justifying that the thing I wanted to write about wasn't morally bad, honest.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-15:16.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-10-02:24.html</id>
    <title>Rules as moral training wheels</title>
    <updated>2022-06-10T02:34:50+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Rules as moral training wheels&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-06-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's the final draft bankruptcy piece. It's a pity, because I think it's a good piece,
but it turns out that I absolutely do not want to write about ethics right now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's definitely not going to hold together as a cohesive whole, sorry, this is in a stage
where I was pulling a bunch of disparate pieces together and haven't yet done the work to
join the dots. Hopefully the individual bits will be interesting though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Good people don't need rules&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One response I got to &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/learning-to-walk-through-walls"&gt;learning to walk through
walls&lt;/a&gt;
was surprise that I didn't talk about ethics in it. Many things become
easier when you let go of your ethical rules, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it's a mistake to think of it this way, and ethics should be
treated not as part of the rules you operate under, but instead about
the goals you are trying to achieve. Being a good person isn't about
only doing good things, it's about wanting to do good things and not
wanting to do bad things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One place this comes up is in the strawman version of a common argument
between religious people and atheists, where the religious person asks
what stops you going around murdering people without god, and the
atheist's response is that the thing that stops you from murdering
people is &lt;em&gt;not wanting to murder people&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not suggesting that this is a fair and accurate summary of the
argument. The strawman version of it is usefully illustrative in the
same way that our opening anxiety loop parody was.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ideally, ethics shouldn't be about a set of rules that must be obeyed,
but instead baked into your motivations and view of the world. This is
hopefully fairly intuitive. Would you really e.g. think well of your
someone if you knew that they really wanted to go out and do some murder
and the only thing stopping them was their sense of ethics?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Rules as a necessary developmental stage&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, in order to get to this ideal state, you sometimes have to
pass through non-ideal ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a great section from &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bhRNMj6UNYY"&gt;an interview with Robert Kegan (a famous
developmental psychologist) I watched a while
ago&lt;/a&gt;. Here's a cleaned up
transcript of it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was talking with a social worker the other day who works with
adolescents who have come out of the court system and who've
committed crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was talking about a young man maybe 16, 17, years old who had a
record of auto theft, and she told me about a session she had with him
where he he came to her and said "you know you'd be proud of me
because, I know I shouldn't, but I do still hang out with a number of
rough friends who could easily get me in trouble, and just this
weekend I was hanging out with them and they wanted they wanted me to
join them in stealing a car, and ordinarily I might have just gone
along with that, and because of our work together I didn't."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And she said "I'm really glad to hear about that. Tell me a little
bit more."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said "well they wanted me to steal this car and I was going to and
I stopped and I thought to myself that if I steal this car there's a
very good chance we're gonna get caught, and if I get caught, because
I'm on probation, unlike these other friends, they're gonna get let
off but I'm gonna go back to jail."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said to him "well, I'm really glad that you didn't steal the
car, but I have to be honest and say that I wished the reason you
chosen not to steal the car was not just that if you did you might go
to jail, but because you gave some thought to how that person would
feel and the fact that his car's not your car and then he would
naturally feel bad."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And she said he just looked right at her and he said "yes, but I'm
not there yet", and she she sat back and she thought that was a
beautiful answer that he was being absolutely truthful and that her
hope for him was a little further ahead of where he was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was kind of telling a story on herself kind of saying how you know
you can learn from your clients, even from your 16 year old clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because it's Robert Kegan, he naturally (and probably at least partly
correctly) interprets this as a developmental psychology stage
transition:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he said "I'm not quite there yet", from a developmentalist
point of view we would also feel like he was telling a very important
truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What he was saying was "just give me credit for the fact I didn't
steal the car, but my underlying logic is still about what's in my
best interest and the reason I didn't steal it was because I had at
least enough foresight to consider that I could get caught, I could
get sent to jail".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is itself a given stage of development. It is the stage that
comes before the socialized mind. What she was hoping for was a
qualitatively different stage where people live not only to pursue
their own interests and look at others as sort of opportunities to get
their own needs met, or obstacles to getting their needs met, but
where you actually begin to internalize something of the the values
and beliefs of others around you. It starts with your society, as that
make it conveyed through your immediate family, or your faith
community or others beyond it, and eventually there's the possibility
that I start relating to others - family members, friends, society not
just in terms of getting my own needs met but where I actually become
more a part of society, because society has become more a part of me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I begin to internalize the values, beliefs, and expectations of
important people around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We call that the socialized mind, because you begin to develop the
internal psychology that permits socialization, that permits you to
become a member of a tribe that permits you to become a part of a
community of interest larger than one, larger than your own
self-interest where you will be able to actually subordinate some of
your maybe short-term interests on behalf of enhancing the
relationship, and when that stage evolves, typically in adolescence,
it is a cause for relief and celebration on the part of parents and
the community at large who live with this adolescent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It enables employers of fast-food businesses who want to hire
teenagers to feel they can hire a person who's begun to make that
transition because they become trustworthy you can kind of count on
them they may be able to keep their agreements not just because
they'll get into they don't but because they want you to continue to
trust them and to respect them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/teenager-ethics.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Credit to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/made_in_cosmos/status/1465806900256194568"&gt;Made in Cosmos&lt;/a&gt;
for the original teenager meme)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to get to the point where your ethics is properly integrated
into your motivations, you probably need to pass through a period where
you hold very tightly to ethical rules. This is a good learning tool,
but holding onto it too tightly or for too long is bad for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Think of it like training wheels: They're very useful when learning to
ride a bike, but if you never take them off you'll never actually become
a proficient bike rider.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The non-composability of ethical rules&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The big problem with rules is that they conflict, and then what do you
do?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The big central rule based ethical philosophy is called deontology, and
is often associated with Immanuel Kant. In deontology there are
inviolable rules that you are supposed to follow in order to be ethical.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Where those rules come from varies. I think the most common place to
find real deontologists in the wild is in religion, which has the nice
simple answer that rules come from god. I think, in practice, even
religious people tend not to be pure deontologists, but there is a
strong deontological component to their beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Kant instead believes that rules are derived from the "categorical
imperative", a term that definitely doesn't mean "whatever Kant made up
based on his prejudices as a 18th century middle class Austrian
philosopher", but instead is about acting in accordance with
universalizable principles. e.g. you shouldn't lie because a world in
which everyone lied freely wouldn't function.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem with having hard and fast ethical rules is that sometimes
they will contradict each other. For example, suppose you're in Nazi
Germany and, as a good person, are hiding a Jewish family in your attic.
A Gestapo officer comes to your door and asks if you've seen any Jews
around. You know full well that the fate in store for them if caught is
a concentration camp. Do you lie to the Gestapo?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Kant thinks you should tell the Gestapo the
truth.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Kant is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are many points of ethics on which I think reasonable people can
disagree, but this is not one of them. Anyone who claims the correct
thing to do is to tell the truth to the Gestapo agent is a bad person
(or at least claiming ot be one) and is not to be trusted.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem here is that we have two conflicting duties: To protect the
lives of the family sheltering with us, and to tell the
truth. We are not able to follow both
(Or, at least, the path to following both is not obvious to us in the
moment - possibly a sufficiently clever person could come up with a
workaround, or possibly you could apply your mad Jiu Jitsu skills and
punch out the Nazi, or possibly a time traveller from the future
could... The point is that we work with the resources available to us in
the moment), and thus must choose between them, and much of the time
even if there is &lt;em&gt;theoretically&lt;/em&gt; a path available that resolves the
contradictions, in the moment we must navigate the fact that we see no
such path. This isn't solvable by pre-gaming every ethical conundrum we
find ourselves in, because the world is complex enough that we cannot
anticipate everything), and this leads us to ask the question we probably
should have asked at the start: What do we mean by &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;? What
actually happens if we break one of these ethical rules?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(It's unclear to me whether Kant thinks this is an example of a
contradiction in rules (mostly because I haven't checked too hard
because the more I read Kant on ethics the more I want to not read Kant
on ethics and also the more I wish I had a time machine so I could go
back in time and slap Kant), but to me it is reasonably clear that at
least one of two things are true: a) There is a moral duty to protect
the Jewish family in this example or b) Duties to follow rules are not
sufficient to describe the ethical requirements on being a good person,
and those duties must sometimes be overruled.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's part of an answer: You should feel guilty about it, regardless of
whether it was the correct thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The feeling of guilt&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So you did something slightly wrong. Honestly, you knew it was wrong,
why did you do it? Only a monster deliberately does wrong things.
Therefore you're a monster. You know it. You're the worst.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But wait! Maybe you were forced into it! Or maybe you in fact had a
&lt;em&gt;very good reason&lt;/em&gt; for doing the thing. Maybe it's completely justified
and not wrong at all, and therefore you don't have to feel guilty and
are not a monster after all! Yes, this must be the case, you've done
nothing wrong and you will continue to argue that you've done nothing
wrong until the part of you insisting that you have stops trying to make
you feel guilty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;fact&lt;/em&gt;, it's the people who forced you into this situation who are at
fault. They're the real monsters. You should punish them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, a huge exaggeration of the thought process most
people go through, but it's not as much of an exaggeration for everyone
as you might hope, and many of us go through some smaller version of it
on a pretty regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's talk a bit about what's going on here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For many people, guilt is one of the worst emotions they regularly
experience.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This essay had some huge footnotes, and they don't really make sense integrated into the main text, so here they are as a subsection.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;The Doctor on virtue&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In one of those oddly memorable scenes from otherwise forgettable media,
here's The Doctor on the subject of good mean not needing rules:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/O5JnqPSzSLo" title="YouTube video player" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Madame Kovarian: The anger of a good man is not a problem. Good men
have too many rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Doctor: Good men don't need rules. Today is not the day to find
out why I have so many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Kant on lying to murderers&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Naturally Kant didn't use the Gestapo example because it was a bit after
his time. In his original conception it's a murderer. The Gestapo
example seems to have become widely used though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was worried that I was being unfair to Kant and that his actual
opinion is likely to be more nuanced, so I looked up the original.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, here is his argument, from "On a supposed right to tell lies from
benevolent motives":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, if you have &lt;em&gt;by a lie&lt;/em&gt; hindered a man who is even now
planning a murder, you are legally responsible for all the
consequences. But if you have strictly adhered to the truth, public
justice can find no fault with you, be the unforeseen consequence what
it may. It is possible that whilst you have honestly answered Yes to
the murderer's question, whether his intended victim is in the house,
the latter may have gone out unobserved, and so not have come in the
way of the murderer, and the deed therefore have not been done;
whereas, if you lied and said he was not in the house, and he had
really gone out (though unknown to you), so that the murderer met him
as he went, and executed his purpose on him, then you might with
justice be accused as the cause of his death. For, if you had spoken
the truth as well as you knew it, perhaps the murder while seeking for
his enemy in the house might have been caught by neighbours coming up
and the deed been prevented. Whoever then &lt;em&gt;tells a lie&lt;/em&gt; however good
his intentions may be, must answer for the consequences of it, even
before the civil tribunal, and must pay the penalty for them, however
unforeseen they may have been; because truthfulness is a duty that
must be regarded as the basis of all duties founded on contract, the
laws of which would be rendered uncertain and useless if the least
exception to them were admitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be &lt;em&gt;truthful&lt;/em&gt; (honest) in all declarations is therefore a sacred
unconditional command of reason, and not to be limited by any
expediency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, to be blunt, a really fascinating combination of blatant
motivated reasoning and sheer moral cowardice. Kant's argument is that
you should do the action you know is likely to get people killed because
&lt;em&gt;then you will not be blamed for any negative consequences?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On the subject of blaming Kant for negative consequences of his actions,
when I complained about this passage on Twitter, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mbateman/status/1527320119633797127"&gt;Matt Bateman sent
me&lt;/a&gt; the paper
"&lt;a href="https://www.csus.edu/indiv/b/bellonc/fall14/117/kantsuicide.pdf"&gt;Maria von Herbert's Challenge to
Kant&lt;/a&gt;"
which is an exchange he had with a devout Kantian, who was looking for
moral guidance about a situation in which she had told the truth (to a
new lover, about the fact that he was not her first) after concealing it
initially. She is distraught, and seeking not so much abstract reasoning
as guidance:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herbert writes that she has lost her love, that her heart is
shattered, that there is nothing left to make life worth living, and
that Kant's moral philosophy hasn't helped a bit. Kant's reply is
to suggest that the love is deservedly lost, that misery is an
appropriate response to one's own moral failure, and that the really
interesting moral question here is the one that hinges on a subtle but
necessary scope distinction: the distinction between telling a lie and
failing to tell the truth, between saying 'not-p', and not saying
'p'. Conspicuously absent is an acknowledgement of Herbert's more
than theoretical interest in the question: is suicide compatible with
the moral law?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After several letters in exchange she does, in fact, commit suicide.
While I don't think it's entirely fair to blame Kant for this outcome, I
think his behaviour throughout definitely doesn't suggest he has any
practical insight into how to be a good person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason this draft got abandoned is pretty clear to me right now because
I was literally in the process of writing it when I abandoned it: I just
don't want to write about ethics right now. I'm tired and grumpy and depressed,
and this whole subject makes that worse rather than better, because I don't
have the energy for a proper righteous anger which is the actual useful emotion
that can drive me to write about ethics. I'm going to go find something more fun
to write about.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-10-02:24.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-07-14-10:44.html</id>
    <title>How you should have learned mental arithmetic</title>
    <updated>2022-07-14T10:46:27+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How you should have learned mental arithmetic&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-07-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Draft bankruptcy is over, but I got about a quarter of the way into writing this post before I realised that it was going to be much longer than I expected and also that I had no fucking idea why I was writing this post, so this is the point I stopped at.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had a conversation the other day with a small child and her father, in which I opined that the eight times tables was one of the easy ones because you could just multiply by two three times. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was apparently confusing. “How would you do 7 times 8 by multiplying by two three times?” “14 28 56, done.” “Huh I wouldn’t have thought of that”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The father in question is certainly decent at mathematics, although not a mathematician,  so this is probably a relatively common point of confusion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;7 times 8 is pretty easy in general. For example 7 times 7 is 49, so you can just add 7 to that to get 56 (because 6 is 7 - 1). Also really sometimes when multiplying by 8 it’s easier to go the other way and remember that 8 is 10 - 2, so 7 times 8 is 70 - 14, which is 60 - 4, which is 56.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But no, you’re not supposed to do any of that, you’re supposed to just know that 7 times 8 is 56. If you work it out you’re not doing the task of learning your times tables properly. That’s cheating that is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Desire lines in the mind&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For developmental reasons it probably does make sense to start kids off with learning their times tables. I’m not sure, I’m not actually very good at teaching small children, but the fact that people don’t then go on to learn how to do mental arithmetic properly is, I think, one of the injustices at the core of how we teach mathematics. Not because mental arithmetic is particularly important, but because it’s one of the easiest places to learn to think about mathematics like a mathematician does - rather than trying to memorise a bunch of information, you see how it all fits together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve talked about this before in the context of learning ROT13, but I think the non-serious nature of that post hid this somewhat (mental arithmetic is of course very serious). There is a specific technique of learning that works very well for mathematics in particular (but is, I think, general): Rather than trying to memorise the information, you instead learn how to work it out from first principles or other remembered information. This, in turn, will usually allow you to memorise a bunch of information, but it will be the right information - that which you actually use.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way this works is simple: Being able to work out the information means that you have a reliable feedback loop for learning it, because every time you use it you will access it by the fastest method readily available to you - whether that’s simply remembering it, or working it out from scratch, or skipping steps that you remember the results of… Each time you use it, your access to it will get faster and more fluent, until the things you use most commonly are readily to hand. But even if you don’t memorise it, you’ll be able to get there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can think of this approach to memorisation as that of building desire lines. Desire lines are those lines in the grass that you see on parks where people have clearly decided it’s more efficient to walk across the diagonal than follow the paved path the long way round. People build a path by walking it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In addition, by giving people the ability to build desire lines, you give them the ability to explore. Someone who has learned a large body of information this way has not only learned that information, they’ve learned how to learn new information like it. Memorising your 8 times table by brute force is not easier for having memorised your 7 times table, but the more mental arithmetic you learn to do “properly”, the more you start to understand how numbers work, the more other types of mental arithmetic and related mathematics are accessible to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;How to do addition&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m now going to teach you arithmetic from scratch. This will start out with me spelling out some things you might find either confusing or painfully obvious. Sorry. It’s important I promise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you start from the absolute basics of how mathematicians define addition (of natural numbers. If you don't understand this aside, please ignore this aside), it comes down to the following rules:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;m + 0 = m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;m + 1 is the next biggest number after m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;m + (n + 1) = (m + 1) + n&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or, in words:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you take any number (which we will call m), and you add zero to it, you get the same number (m) back. So e.g. 7 + 0 is 7.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add 1 is just counting upwards to the next number. So e.g. 2 + 1 is 3, because 3 comes after 2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you take any number (which we will call m), and you add some number to it that is bigger than 0 (which we will call n + 1, which we can do because there’s at least one rock in it, so it’s just the number before it plus one), then this is the same as adding the number right before the second number (n) to the number right after the first number (m + 1). e.g. 8 + 6 = 9 + 5. We “move” a single object from the second number to the first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you think of numbers as representing counting objects (which you should), you can think of addition as saying “If you have this many objects on the left, and this many objects on the right, how many are in the combined pile?”. I find it’s particularly helpful to think in terms of counting piles of rocks if you want a concrete example. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our rules combined says that you can count the combined pile by moving rocks from the right pile to the left pile one at a time (which always preserves the number of rocks), and then when the rightmost pile is empty you’ll have all the rocks in the pile on the left.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or, to see this with numbers, suppose we want to to calculate 9 + 7. We can do this by moving one from the right, one step at a time. So 9 + 7 = 10 + 6 = 11 + 5 = 12 + 4 = 13 + 3 = 14 + 2 = 15 + 1 = 16 + 0 = 16. Done.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Using this method you can now calculate any addition. Great! So easy, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I will admit, there are one or two downsides. Mostly, it’s extremely slow if the number on the right is large. So we probably don’t want to use this as our main method of calculation, but nevertheless, it is our starting point, and we now have our first reliable slow method for doing mental arithmetic.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first thing to notice is that even through we don’t always want to follow it the whole way, it’s often a pretty good tactic to deploy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, what’s 99 + 37? Well, it’s 100 + 36 (moved one from the right to the left), and 100 + 36 is easy it’s just 136.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This leads to the most important thing to understand about how to do mental arithmetic (and mathematics in general): Mental arithmetic is done by figuring out tactics to change your problem into an easier one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a more general version of this tactic, which we can represent as m + (n + k) = (m + k) + n. That is, we if we have our left pile (m) and our right pile (n), we can always take away some number of rocks (k) that is no larger than the pile on the right, and move that to the pile on the left, we’ve now got k more rocks on the left and k fewer rocks on the right. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often this is useful for making there be more multiples of 10 or other nice numbers to add together. For example, suppose you wanted to figure out 96 + 13. You could do this by noting that 13 = 9 + 4, so 96 + 13 = 96 + (9 + 4) = (96 + 4) + 9 = 109.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another tactic we could use here that looks very similar is this: We could write this as 96 + 13 = 90 + 6 + 10 + 3 = (90 + 10) + (6 + 3) = 100 + 9 = 109.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-07-14-10:44.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-08-07-00:51.html</id>
    <title>Notes on the design of a conference scheduler</title>
    <updated>2022-11-02T16:15:57+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes on the design of a conference scheduler&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-08-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;NB: This post is unfinished but it accidentally got added to the index and people keep asking about it, so I decided to publish it as is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of my lesser known but surprisingly impactful contributions to the world is the talk &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OkusHEBOhmQ"&gt;Easy solutions to hard problems&lt;/a&gt;, which is about mixed integer linear programming (MILP) and in particular about how to use integer linear programming to schedule conferences. Off the back of this, several conferences, including &lt;a href="https://www.emfcamp.org/"&gt;Electromagnetic field&lt;/a&gt; have scheduled their conferences using MILP.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I now think that was a mistake. Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are roughly three problems with this approach:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's actually really slow. Not as slow as scheduling it by hand maybe, but the EMF scheduler apparently takes most of a day to run.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It gives totally opaque error messages when things go wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time I've attended a conference scheduled this way I'm left with a vague sense that the schedule is just not very good. It's a bit all over the place in a way that I feel like a human scheduler would have done better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Set against this, you really &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; want a computer in the loop because scheduling things by hand is such a nightmare that this is still preferable for the organisers despite the trade off.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway I was thinking about this recently and realised that there's probably a nicer way to do this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic design is to follow the model from &lt;a href="http://oro.open.ac.uk/3275/4/Can_a_machine_design.pdf"&gt;Can a machine design?&lt;/a&gt; for human-machine collaboration, which is that it is the job of a computer to propose solutions and for the human to correct them. So instead of designing a &lt;em&gt;scheduler&lt;/em&gt; we are effectively designing a &lt;em&gt;schedule editor&lt;/em&gt;. The computer proposes an initial schedule, which is expected to not be especially good, and then maintains the schedule and all its constraints as the human makes edits to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This solves the problem of the schedule missing the human touch, because the human can make changes until they're happy with the schedule, and it's the job of the computer to make those changes work. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The UI I'm imagining this is essentially a version of the schedule, in which a user can drag things around and have everything reorder itself to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic operations I'm imagining are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lock a talk into the slot it's currently scheduled in, so it will not be moved in future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move a talk into a new slot, replacing the talk that's currently there. This will either succeed, or the software will say that it's forbidden (because the talk is not allowed into that slot because of e.g. constraints on when the speaker can manage), or that it has to unlock the following talks in order to make it work (with an explanation of why).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Many more operations are implementable (e.g. you could easily implement a "Move this talk somewhere else, I don't care where as long as it fits the requirement" operation), these are just the obvious basics. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Implementing the UI for this should be relatively straightforward for anyone who is actually good at UI. I'm not, and I'm not invested enough in this problem to want to pick up the relevant skills. If you're interested in this problem and already good at UI, feel free to drop me a line and talk about collaborating on this, because I pretty much know how all the algorithmic details should work!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Implementation&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These operations are relatively easy to implement, and the basic algorithmic toolkit for this is to use &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hall%27s_marriage_theorem"&gt;Hall's marriage theorem&lt;/a&gt;.
Hall's marriage theorem says that if you have some set of items (talks) you want to put into boxes (slots in the schedule), and each item can only go in some boxes (each talk can only be scheduled in certain slots), and each box can only hold one item (each slot can only have one talk), then either you can find an assignment that works, or you can find some set of items which is strictly larger than the number of boxes that are allowed to hold those items. e.g. there are three slots but four talks that all have to go in one of those three slots.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hall's marriage theorem is relatively easy to implement an efficient algorithm for if you have access to an implementation of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hopcroft%E2%80%93Karp_algorithm"&gt;Hopcroft-Karp algorithm&lt;/a&gt; (and fortunately &lt;a href="https://docs.scipy.org/doc/scipy/reference/generated/scipy.sparse.csgraph.maximum_bipartite_matching.html"&gt;scipy has just such an implementation&lt;/a&gt;).
You use this to find the largest possible assignment of items to boxes. If this assigns every item to a box, great you're done. If not, you can use the unassigned items to construct a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hall_violator"&gt;Hall violator&lt;/a&gt; - a set of items that cannot possibly be put into distinct boxes because there aren't enough boxes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a side note, one nice thing about this algorithm is that it has the opposite efficiency characteristics to using MILP for this: The more constrained your problem gets, the faster it runs. As a result, it should (I think) be viable to use it the way I need to use it for this design, because we'll mostly want to run it with quite constrained problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(You can also use MILP to solve the maximum matching problem and it may under some circumstances me more efficient to do that. This is something that would require experimentation. Certainly using a MILP gets you more flexibility than using Hall's theorem, because it lets you handle things like "these two talks shouldn't clash" natively)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it's easy enough to use Hall's marriage theorem for the initial schedule: You just run it on your constraints, and it either gives you a schedule or tells you that you e.g. have too many talks that have to go into a particular day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's how to use it to power what should be a pretty good schedule editor:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You always have a current schedule that you are working on. In response to requests from the user, the scheduler makes (ideally small) edits to the schedule by rearranging sets of talks.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Each talk has an epoch, which is the last time it was moved. The goal is to have the schedule converge to stability, so we always prefer to move talks that are from a more recent epoch. Initially, all talks are given a random distinct epoch. A talk may also be locked (as marked by the user), in which case it will not be moved without the user asking. We will also sometimes temporarily lock talks as part of a rescheduling.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When a user moves a talk to a new slot, the following happens:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First, check if the talk is allowed in its new slot (i.e. it satisfies the constraints as to which rooms, times, etc the talk is allowed in). If not, complain to the user and don't move it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Second, if the talk that is already there is allowed in the slot you're moving out of, swap the two. Similarly if the slot is empty because you don't have a full schedule, just move the talk there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally, if&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-08-07-00:51.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-10-02-06:24.html</id>
    <title>There are a lot of irreducible finite partial orders</title>
    <updated>2022-10-02T07:19:04+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;There are a lot of irreducible finite partial orders&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-10-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Advance warning: You don't care about this post. Tersely written notes about a question you've probably never wondered about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A problem I've been thinking about on and off for a month or two is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let \(A\), \(B\) be partial orders. You can combine them with the following operations:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\(A \sqcup B\) is the partial order on the disjoint union of \(A\) and \(B\) such that no element of \(A\) is comparable to an element of \(B\) (and elements of \(A\) and \(B\) compare as usual).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\(A // B\)  is the partial order on the disjoint union of \(A\) and \(B\) such that \(a \preceq b\) for \(a \in A\) and \(b \in B\) (and elements of \(A\) and \(B\) compare as usual).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\(A \times B\) is the partial order on the product of \(A\) and \(B\) such that \((r, s) \preceq (u, v)\) iff \(r \preceq u\) and \(s \preceq v\).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Say a partial order is irreducible if it cannot be expressed as a combination of two non-trivial smaller partial orders with one of these operations (note: non-trivial means "non-empty" for the first two and "more than one element" for the third).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can think of the irreducible finite partial orders as a sort of building block for the finite partial orders, and something I've been wondering is if irreducible finite partial orders have a nice characterisation and how many there are. I now think the answers are: Probably not, and lots.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some vaguely negative results in this space.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are irreducible partial orders of size \(n\) for every \(n &amp;gt; 3\). There are no irreducible partial orders of size \(2\) or \(3\).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are at least \(O(2^{O(n)})\) non-isomorphic irreducible partial orders of size \(n\).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a warm up let's see why there are no irreducible partial orders of size \(2\) or \(3\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;\(2\) is easy. Let \(P = \{a, b\}\) be a partial order of size \(2\). If \(a \preceq b\) then \(P = \{a\} // \{b\}\). Similarly the other way round. Otherwise, \(P = \{a\} \sqcup \{b\}\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;\(3\) is slightly more complicated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's helpful to think about this in terms of the level decomposition. The level of an element \(x \in P\) is the length of the longest chain ending in \(x\). Call that \(l(x)\). The height of \(P\) is the maximum level of an element of \(P\) (equivalently, the length of the longest chain in \(P\)), which we will call \(h(P)\). A level of \(P\) is a set of the form \(\{x \in P: l(x) = k\}\) for some \(k\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose \(P\) were an irreducible poset of size \(3\). If it has \(3\) levels, then it's a chain, so can be decomposed with \(//\).
If it has \(1\) level, it's an antichain so can be decomposed with \(\sqcup\). So it must have \(2\) levels. Thus we can write \(P = \{a, b, c\}\) with \(a \leq b\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If \(c\) is in level \(2\), then \(a \leq c\) (because \(a\) is the only element of level \(1\)), and so we can write \(P = \{a\} // \{b, c\}\). If \(c\) is in level \(1\), then if \(c \neq\preceq b\), we can write \(P = \{a, b\} \sqcup \{c\}\), so \(P\) is reducible. Therefore \(c \preceq b\), and so we can write \(P = \{a\} // \{b, c\}\). Thus, \(P\) could not have been irreducible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now to see that for \(n &amp;gt; 3\) there is always an irreducible poset.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Construct a poset as \(P = \{a_1, \ldots, a_{n - 2}, b, c\}\) and order it as follows: \(a_i \leq b\) for all \(i\), and only \(a_ \leq c\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is irreducible. It's clearly not reducible by \(\sqcup\) because every element is connected to every other by some sequence of comparisons. It's clearly not reducible by \(//\) because not every element of the bottom level is comparible with every element of the second level (this is where we used \(n &amp;gt; 3\) - we need an \(a_2\) for this to be true).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To see it's not reducible by \(\times\), we need to know that \(h(A \times B) = h(A) + h(B)\). This is true because you can basically create a maximal length chain by moving up each coordinate's chain in a zigzag fashion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thus if \(P = A \times B\), we must have \(h(A) + h(B) = 2\). This requires both \(A\) and \(B\) to have height \(1\), which would make them antichains, so \(P\) would be an antichain, but it's not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact a stronger result holds: If \(h(P) \leq 3\), then if \(h\) is reducible by \(\times\), it's reducible by \(\sqcup\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We saw the \(h(P) = 2\) case above. If \(h(P) = 3\) and \(P = A \times B\) with \(A, B\) non-trivial then we must have one of \(A\) or \(B\) have height \(1\). Say it's \(A\). Then \(A\) is an antichain and because it's non-trivial has more than one element, so we can write \(A = X \sqcup Y\) with \(X, Y\) non-empty. Then \(P = X \times B \sqcup Y \times B\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we can extend the idea behind this as follows to construct families of lots of non-isomorphic irreducible partial orders as follows.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let \(k &amp;gt; 0\). Construct a partial follow out of elements \(P = \{a_1, \ldots, a_k\} \cup \{b_1, \ldots, b_k\} \cup \{c_U: U \subseteq \{1, \ldots, k\}, U \neq \emptyset\} \cup \{q\}\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rules are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\(a_i \leq b_j\) iff \(i \leq j\).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\(a_i \leq c_U\) iff \(i \in U\).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\(b_j \leq q\)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The idea of this construction is that there are \(O(2^k)\) elements in this partial order, and all of them are distinguishable up to isomorphism. i.e. the set has a trivial automorphism group.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To see this, let \(f : P \to P\) be an automorphism. Then \(h(f(q)) = h(q) = 3\), so \(f(q) = q\) because \(q\) is the only level \(3\) element. Thus \(f(\{b_i\}) = \{b_i\}\), because they're the only elements directly below \(q\), and we can distinguish the \(b_i\) by how many elements are under them. Thus \(f\) must also preserve the \(a_i\), and thus also the \(c_U\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;\(P\) is irreducible by our above result, but more importantly now let \(X \subseteq \{c_i\}\). Define \(P_X = P \cup d_X\), where \(d \leq c_U\) iff \(c_U \in X\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is still height \(3\), and still clearly not reducible by either \(\sqcup\) or \(//\), so is an irreducible set.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More, for \(X \neq Y\), we have \(P_X \neq P_Y\), because any isomorphism betweem them would have to preserve the \(C_U\), and so would fail to be an isomorphism because \(d_X\) and \(d_Y\) are below different \(c_U\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This gives of \(O(2^{O(|P|)})\) non-isomorphic irreducible partial orders of size \(|P| + 1\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For general \(n\), construct the largest version of \(P\) such that \(|P| + 1 \leq n\), and just add in a bunch of extra elements more or less any way that works, and you'll get the same bounds.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It may still be that there's some interesting deep structure to look at for irreducible finite partial orders, but I think these examples show that there's probably not: There are just too many of them, and it's all a bit messy.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-10-02-06:24.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-11-02-15:46.html</id>
    <title>Examples of missing support networks</title>
    <updated>2022-11-02T16:13:52+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Examples of missing support networks&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-11-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did a popular tweet:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;The modern condition is mostly trying to do things on your own that people have historically achieved with a large support network and wondering why you're tired all the time.&lt;/p&gt;— David R. MacIver (@DRMacIver) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1586850511726206983?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;October 30, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People are, quite reasonably, asking me for examples beyond the really obvious one of parenting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In truth, I do think my tweet is overly simplistic, and there's a lot more going on. I wrote it partly because I'm living on my own at the moment and really don't like it, and I'm soon going to be living in a much more extended household and very much looking forward to it, and just the general ease of being relied upon and being able to rely on other people for the little things, and the changes I'm expecting (not, I think, to an unwarranted degree - it's different, but it's far from the first time I've lived with others) are many and small, so pointing at specific examples feels almost beside the point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, here are a few big examples. It's not a terribly well thought out list, this is just off the top of my head. It feels more pervasive than these examples would suggest, as I think this is often an aggregate of many small things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the examples that often comes up that makes me think about this is that if you look at a lot of past (and to some degree current) examples of extremely successful scientists etc. who published a million books, it turns out the "trick" behind their productivity was that they certainly had their wife acting as their personal secretary and possibly an entire household because they were aristocracy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a super privileged position of course, but when you look at people trying to achieve similar things today they certainly aren't in that super privileged position but are trying to achieve the same things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You see this at work too - e.g. most positions you would previously have secretaries, admin staff, etc. helping you out, and you would be able to rely on your housewife keeping home for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't a "feminism is bad" take don't worry. But it's important to bear in mind that the workload and assumptions of most jobs are designed around the idea that keeping house, life admin, etc. is something someone else is doing for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also on the work front there was much more in the way of apprenticeships and mentorships, and the expectation that you would have a long-term career at a given place got you (in theory, and sometimes also in practice) a lot more support from a network of people at work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The gig economy in which everyone is an independent contractor is the ultimate version of stripping this community of support away at work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From the consumer side, companies were often part of your support network in a way they no longer are, with increasingly large amounts of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shadow_work"&gt;shadow work&lt;/a&gt; where things that you could previously get help on are now your responsibility, increasing your workload.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of this, there's plenty of absent general community support stuff - having friends you can call on to help you out with a task (e.g. my "&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1564603678484566019"&gt;oh shit how do I get a table upstairs?&lt;/a&gt;" recently), or who will check up on you when you're ill, or whatever is much harder than it should be and historically often was (and to some degree still is in smaller communities, but my impression is that even there it's much less of a thing now).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general one of the big functions of support networks is that they absorb variance - even things that you're fine to do on your own 90-95% of the time, you sometimes need someone else to pick up the slack when things go bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Emotional support is like this too. "Go to therapy" is a way of making an individual responsiblity of emotional problems that often need a whole community to support you. Often historically (and perhaps currently? I'm not very familiar with religious culture except second hand, but my impression this is at least &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; true than it used to be) this would be a religious community. You'd have your priest, but you'd also have other members of the congegration to help you out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the religious content, when you're having a bad time you should be able to draw on a community of people who have your back, and heart emojis on social media when you sadpost doesn't quite cut it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Distributed trust is another one. I've complained about the problem of e.g. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:53.html"&gt;how to find a good plumber&lt;/a&gt; before, but historically this is something you solve by asking your community. Communities maintain social knowledge and help you figure out how to navigate the world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the discussions in the replies to my tweet is about housework and cooking and such. I think this is ambiguously an example - an extended family living under one roof does absolutely count as a support network for doing this, but in the middle class UK/USA cultures I'm most familiar with the lack of these is only "modern" in the sense that it's a 20th century trend. The actual solution we've had more recently which is now also gone was generally housewives again. With both partners working, or someone living alone or with flatmates with whom they don't really share a life, you're implicitly trying to do the work of two people. Not a "large" support network, but support nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of these have "replacements" from technology or the market. I think it's good that those exist, and it's good that people can do more as individuals, but they are far from a complete replacement for a full support network, and based on the slightly overwhelming amount of responses this tweet got, it seems like other people feel similarly.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-11-02-15:46.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-12-08-20:25.html</id>
    <title>Notes on shaking</title>
    <updated>2022-12-08T20:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes on shaking&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-12-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other night I was failing to sleep, feeling very physically agitated and generally unable to relax.
So I followed through on the muscle tension, basically started shaking and shivering, and spent about 10 minutes writhing around on my bed, seemingly in agony (I wasn't, but I think an outside observer would very much have thought I was).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;About a month ago now, I was doing the washing up, and had a bizarrely strong emotional reaction to it, and ended up curling up into a ball on the floor right there in front of the sink.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is all a bit odd, but right now it's actually pretty normal for me. I'm hoping it will calm down as I work out whatever is going on, but so far it seems a moderately unpleasant and very weird but basically harmless and often quite helpful set of practices.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let me start from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Dear penthouse, a funny thing happened to me in bed recently&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A few months ago at the time of this writing, I had a scary conversation with my girlfriend, Lisa.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I knew it was going to go fine, intellectually, but it was about something I have a lot of insecurities around, and that it was very easy emotionally to imagine it going badly. It was quite hard for me to even get out the words for my end of the conversation. I had to bring out the big guns: Having the conversation while cooking and pretending to myself it wasn’t a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It went fine, obviously. Lisa’s great and it was never not going to go fine. We had dinner, and then went to bed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Shortly after we went to bed my legs started shaking. It started as a pretty comically stereotypical knees knocking type motion and gradually progressed into more full blown shakes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I then spent the next two hours doing this, some of it shaking pretty hard. I’m reasonably confident I wasn’t having a seizure, but it's hard to describe what happened in a way that doesn't make it sound an awful lot like having a seizure. The main difference is that it felt like I could stop at any moment by just getting out of bed and calming down, although it did feel like that was what it would take - it wasn't uncontrollable, but it certainly wasn't easy to control.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually that’s what I did - it didn’t stop because the shaking stopped on its own, it stopped because after about two hours I decided that I was entirely worn out by this and wanted to stop, so we got out of bed, I had a chamomile tea and calmed down.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;During all of this, Lisa did a mix of holding me, telling me I was safe, and telling me to stop making jokes about it and just let it happen. “You can stop any time you want to, but you have to choose to stop, I’m not going to let you deflect.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lisa handled all of this very well. I was and still am impressed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point in all of this I curled up into a ball. “Everything’s fine, I just need to curl up into a ball for a bit, as one does.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was one of the points at which Lisa told me to stop making jokes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how long I was curled up for but eventually I had to uncurl because I’m nearly 40 and not all that flexible. Some time after that I realised that I was apparently not done and needed to curl back up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that I should mention here is that this whole process was &lt;em&gt;boring&lt;/em&gt;. My conscious mind just found the whole thing weird and vaguely confusing and not that interesting. This is almost certainly a deflection. But there was no conceptual content and very little emotional content.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point I mentioned this and Lisa said that I seemed terrified. There was definitely a bit of an emotional response to that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did cry a few times during the whole ordeal, but it still felt very inhibited.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I slept reasonably well after this (I think Lisa slept less well. This was probably more stressful for her than it was for me).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next day I had DOMS (muscle soreness). One interesting thing is that I had it much more in the leg I normally have chronic pain in, but the actual chronic pain was significantly reduced. This didn’t last, and I’m not sure it was real, but it sure was interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;War never changes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Such a dramatic incident should, naturally, result in a period of reflection and exploration and generally integrating the experience and learning from it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead I spent the next two weeks on a war footing, engaged in a major dispute with my landlord, gearing up for a long protracted legal battle.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This then immediately evaporated when I got sufficiently serious that my landlord backed down, leaving a lot of fighty energy with nowhere to go.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This then was followed by about two weeks of depression in which I was basically nonfunctional. Very tired, spent most of the day watching videos and playing games. No ability to read at all except for very trashy fiction. I think of this as being stuck in a Freeze state, although I’m not sure if that’s strictly accurate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also was a period in which I was having really bad insomnia. Lots of physical agitation at night that wouldn’t go away.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did use the big guns (watching Slay the Spire videos and very occasionally sleeping pills) and that helped a bit but the problem kept getting worse, and the mitigations helped less and less.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One night when I was having a particularly bad night I started paying attention to the physical sensations of the agitation and trying to see what sort of actions they “wanted” to do, and the result was more shaking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was watching a Baalorlord slay the spire video at the time and that felt quite helpful. It gave me something to focus on in between shakes and generally felt like it helped make the whole experience feel safer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It felt quite different from the previous incident with Lisa. They weren’t the same motions particularly, and it was much more voluntary (it’s not exactly voluntary, but the previous incident it felt like I had to actively work to stop it, while this it felt more like I had to actively choose to lean into it in order to get anything to happen).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other big difference is roughly... where the motion starts? Before it started from my legs and spread upwards, while this feels very focused on my upper body and sometimes spreads down into my lower. There’s also a lot more almost writhing around feeling out the right motion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing about this is that after every shake that I felt calmer. It was very specifically a place for the physical agitation to go. As a result, after about half an hour of this, I was able to fall asleep despite previously feeling very far from being able to do so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then the next day I was out of my Freeze state. I wasn’t feeling amazing, but I could think and read and generally function for the first time in weeks.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since then I’ve found most nights have at least some of this. Not necessarily a huge amount, but often when I’m in bed there’s a bit of shaking and writhing around as part of getting relaxed enough to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What the fuck is going on?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's talk about Trauma Releasing Exercises.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Trauma releasing exercises (TRE) are a therapy tool the basic idea of which is that the natural response to traumatic events is to shake it off once you’re safe, and that we habitually suppress these shakes because they seem weird, and this causes a build up of trauma stored up in the muscles that we have to shake off. Their evidence for this shaking phenomenon is how people in shock behave and that various cultures do have more common habits of shaking after big events (the former seems true to me, I don't trust amateur anthropology so I'm somewhat reserving judgement on the latter, but it certainly could be true).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m a bit sceptical of this story but it certainly seems more plausible to me now than it did before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do basically subscribe to the theory that emotions are experienced bodily, and that the way to better understand your own emotions is to learn to pay attention to your own body.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think also that muscle tension is often a way to regulate emotions. Certainly when I'm having a strong emotional reaction, I can literally "keep hold of myself", in a way that feels very physical like I'm tensing the appropriate muscles for control.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The "trauma is stored in the body" school of therapy seems to be about habitual patterns of muscle tension like this. If you're always holding yourself very tightly, keeping control of your emotions, then you'll build up habitual patterns of tension in your muscles, and learning to relax that tension is required if you want to have proper access to those emotions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;TRE are exercises designed to tire out your psoas muscle and trigger the shaking response that you see after a triggering event, in an attempt to "release the trauma" that you are storing in these patterns of muscle tension.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve done them before and they’re super weird and interesting, but I didn’t notice much therapeutic effect. That being said, the initial leg shakes in my first night of this seemed a lot like the shakes from doing a TRE. I thought I’d try them again and see what happened.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t feel much like the shaking I’ve been experiencing. There’s definitely a similarity in the leg movements, but it feels more purely physical.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing I did notice doing these is that I could almost feel the shape of things in my body and patterns of muscle tension from where the shakes were. In particular the shakes seemed to avoid my injured knee.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think that having done these in the past was an interesting reference point that made the spontaneous shaking feel safer, and they’re a good work out so I may try them some more, but I’m sortof convinced that these exercises are just coincidentally replicating the shape of something useful without being therapeutically useful themselves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do recommend them giving them a go though. They're interesting and worth trying at least once.
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WZOtBY4RTLo"&gt;This is the guided video I use&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I really don't think they work, except by accident. Possibly they provide a good basis for creating a space in which to do the real thing, but they are not themselves the real thing and can't force it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Interpretation as a barrier to right action&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a principle I tried adhering to for a while. It's very sensible, seems theoretically well grounded, and is all round good advice except for the fact that as far as I can tell it doesn't work. Worse, it's so close to something that does work that it distracts you from the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The principle is this: If you would describe your feelings as "I feel like I want to just curl up into a ball", why not just curl up into a ball?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The answer is because if you do that then now you still feel the same way but also you feel kinda dumb. It doesn't help.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's the corrected version of the principle: If you want to curl up into a ball, why not curl up into a ball?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The difference is annoyingly subtle. It's in the lack of an interpretive layer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me give you an unrelated example. You know the thing where doctors tap your knee to test your reflexes? I was quite bad at it as a kid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How can you be bad at a reflex test?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, the first time the doctor tapped my knee I was like "Ah yes, I know what this test is, I'm supposed to kick" and kicked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as being on a significantly longer delay, the kick was much more exaggerated than the reflexive jerk would be. It was very clear to the doctor that this was Not The Thing. He laughed and told me just to let it happen.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next time he tapped my knee, I knew I wasn't supposed to kick, so my leg didn't move at all. Turns out, the reflex response is pretty easy to suppress if you try, it just requires holding your muscles tightly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I assume we must have got the exercise working eventually but I don't remember for sure. This was like 30 to 35 years ago now, my memory is a bit fuzzy on the details.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if someone throws a ball at you, and you see it, and you think "Ah, a ball, I should catch it", and move based on that thought, you'll probably fail to catch the ball.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are two different ways you can respond to external events. One goes as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Observe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpret the observational data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Act on that interpretation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other goes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Observe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Act on that observation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The former isn't bad, in that it inserts a great deal of intelligence into the loop that allows you to figure out things you wouldn't otherwise and act beyond your current capabilities, but it's also not exactly good. The results are awkward, and often poorly suited in detail. They tend to be clumsy and unnatural seeming, often poorly timed, overly strong, overly weak, or otherwise not quite fitting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The same holds with acting on internal observations I think.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When doing Focusing, in the Gendlin sense, you are trying to put a description on a "felt sense", a physically felt bundle of sensations that capture some crucial feeling. You follow the felt sense until you find a description that feels right.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The most important sensation to pay attention to in Focusing is "no, that's not quite it". The difference between not quite right and the right thing is, to quote probably-not-Mark-Twain the difference between lightning and lightning bug.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Following through on your interpretation of the felt sense rather than the felt sense itself feels very much like a lightning bug, as do Trauma Releasing Exercises.
Acting on the motion feels like lighting. Based on what actually happens, it probably looks a bit like being struck by lighting too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Is this good?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Having borderline seizure-like episodes and randomly having tic-like symptoms or curling up on the floor in the middle of washing up the dishes seems bad, but I think this is good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Certainly my quality of sleep has massively improved since figuring out how to do this. There's a lot of physical agitation that I sometimes experience on bad nights that this allows me to release that agitation in a way that makes sleep possible on nights when it would previously have been a massive struggle.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It also seems to allow me to get out of Freeze states, in a way that nothing I've previously tried behaviour ever has.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If that was all it did, this would be a huge massive win, but it also feels something like... this is what it's supposed to be like?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think all the random shaking is supposed to be normal, but it feels like I'm clearing out a massive backlog of things that I've been suppressing for years.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also made me far more sensitive to certain sensations I think I've historically ignored. I'm much more aware of certain emotional states that were previously a complete mystery because I couldn't really put words to them. I still can't really, certainly not a good Focusing handle for them, but it turns out that some feelings are better expressed as motions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know where this is going - it feels like I've unlocked a missing piece of how things are supposed to work, and I'm still building out the foundations of that before I can even properly integrate it into the rest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Tracing my steps&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't want this to sound like I know what I'm talking about. I'm just reporting on a bunch of weird-ass experiences and my interpretation of them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But given that I think this is probably good, if you've got similar problems to me it might be worth trying to figure out how to do it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How? Uh... excellent question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The particular mental motion that triggers something like this is something like... notice a particular pattern of muscle tension, and stop stopping it from doing what it wants to do, then do whatever comes naturally next.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I expect that this explanation is completely unhelpful if you can't already do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something that's helpful for triggering it more clearly is to notice the tension, tense it up further, and do a sort of "follow up on the rebound" - when you release the clench, your muscles move in a particular way, just let them keep doing that, and if any sort of movement naturally completes from there, let that happen.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I find this works particularly well for tension in my shoulders, and that often once I've started the motion, it often works downwards from there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another thing I've found helpful is being cold and then warming up. Literally being in a cold room, then covering myself in a fuzzy blanket, seems to be a great way to unblock access to this when in a Freeze state. This is I think consistent with how shock works - people start shivering when you cover them in a warm blanket.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think that giving the trauma releasing exercises is probably a good starting point for learning what it feels like to just shake uncontrollably. As I say, I don't think it really triggers the same effect, but I do think having done them made all of this more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Probably experimenting with just noticing muscle tension, and trying out movements and seeing which ones feel appropriate, and which ones trigger that "not quite right" sensation, is a good starting point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I expect though the only way to learn to do this is to just do it, and that anything that lets you achieve it makes it easier the next time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you do experiment, please let me know what does and doesn't work for you. I'd also be up for any reading recommendations if you already know about all this and have recommended tools for working with it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-12-08-20:25.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
