<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-03-07T15:59:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html</id>
    <title>Nerding</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T08:47:25+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Nerding&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Definitions are gauche, but I'm going to attempt a definition of "nerd".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Prompts:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1234959895486660609"&gt;Me getting mad on the internet&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am utterly baffled by the question "What are some things you love that aren't nerd-related?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you mean things that are not nerd related? Everything is nerd related. Nerd is a way to relate to a subject, not a property of the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another prompt is the recent run of &lt;a href="https://www.egscomics.com/comic/party-126"&gt;El Goonish Shive&lt;/a&gt; where this is a topic of conversation (yes I read EGS, no I'm not embarrassed about this. It's fun. Shush).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the definition I would like to propose is this: Nerding is being interested in a subject for intrinsic reasons, rather than for anything that that subject can bring you.
It's a way of engaging with the subject where if someone asks you why you're spending so much time on it, any answer you give other than "Because it's &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt;" would be a rationalisation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to use &lt;em&gt;grounding&lt;/em&gt; as the antonym for nerding - that is, engaging with a subject as interesting for &lt;em&gt;extrinsic&lt;/em&gt; reasons. Grounding is what you do when you want to get shit done with the subject. The strategy I outlined in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2013/08/how-did-you-get-started-so-quickly/"&gt;how to quickly become effective&lt;/a&gt; is a grounding strategy - you don't avoid learning about the subject, but your learning is very much directed towards a specific goal,
and the subject is secondary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I'm not at all happy with "grounding" as a term and reserve the right to replace it with something better later)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My interest in cooking is grounding, because it's primarily driven by a need to eat and a desire to eat tasty things. My interest in voting systems is about 90% nerding, because although I occasionally use it in practical ways it's primarily driven by the fact that voting systems are intrinsically interesting to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, the distinguishing feature of nerding about a subject is that you know far more about it than is reasonable for what you need.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Virtually everyone nerds at least a bit. Unless you are fundamentally incurious about the world, you're going to find out stuff just because you find it interesting. In the same way that you can write without being a writer, you can nerd without being a nerd. Nerds are just those of us with a strong tendency to nerd, and for whom that is an important part of our identity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People think of some subjects as nerdier than others, and it's probably true that some subjects are intrinsically more suitable for nerding about, but people nerd about all sorts of things. I'm nerding about communication and emotional processing skills at the moment. I have a friend who is a dedicated sex nerd. Sports nerds are everywhere. The best bartenders I know are drinks nerds. Chefs are &lt;em&gt;certainly&lt;/em&gt; food nerds. It's &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard to find subjects that nobody nerds about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nerding often arises after grounding. You pick up a subject because you need it for stuff, and then you find some aspect of it &lt;em&gt;fascinating&lt;/em&gt; and you're just kinda hooked. Again, voting theory was this for me - I got interested because of the UK referendum on electoral reform. Test-case reduction is another one. Actually &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; of my nerding arises this way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing about being a nerd about a subject is that it often unlocks levels of practical functional capability that are useful to everyone, even when they're grounding.
Because you spend so much time thinking about it, your personal (or social) ecosystem of thoughts and ideas around the material is so much richer than that of someone who is just functionally interested in it.
It means that when you have a concrete problem to deal with, you have a whole set of tools that are ready to hand that you can apply to it that nobody who wasn't intrinsically interested in the subject would have bothered to acquire.
This means that nerding is often a necessary step to making real, practical, progress.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Of course, someone whose interest in a subject is 100% nerding will often go off in a weird useless direction that has no practical applications. That's fine too, but progress requires a certain mix of grounding and nerding).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because of this I often do what I call &lt;em&gt;nerd raiding&lt;/em&gt; - when I have a subject where my interest in it is mostly grounding, I still go seek out the subject nerds so that I can steal their good ideas, because often there's enough material in there that they arrived at the hard way that I can just package up and use without doing the same level of work.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-09:44.html</id>
    <title>You can't actually run out of ideas</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T13:38:18+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You can't actually run out of ideas&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can't actually run out of ideas, because ideas are generated not found.
The way to get more ideas is just to work at it, and if you're struggling it's probably because you're approaching the problem wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let me tell you about two books.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first book is de Bono's "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/38y5E3H"&gt;Lateral Thinking&lt;/a&gt;". This book is annoyingly good. By which I mean this book is good, and that's annoying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second is Steven Johnson's "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2TvxGIV"&gt;Where Good Ideas Come From&lt;/a&gt;", which is about innovation in the world but also works just as well at a more personal scale.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;De Bono's argument is that there are essentially two types of thinking: Lateral and vertical. I tend to think of the split as more lateral and critical: &lt;em&gt;generating&lt;/em&gt; ideas and &lt;em&gt;ensuring that your ideas are good&lt;/em&gt; as separated tasks.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Steven Johnson's argument is that ideas are an evolutionary process.
Ideas build on other ideas, through combination, mutation, variation.
Exaptation happens and ideas are borrowed from other contexts.
Selection pressure happens when ideas hit the real world and you find out if they actually &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt;.
At any given point, you have the ever growing adjacent possible - the set of ideas it's currently possible to have, based on the set of ideas that have already been had and developed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is how it works on the inside as well: You have your own personal version of the adjacent possible, which is ever expanding, and which contains all the potential ideas you could have.
Having ideas is about exploring that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you are failing to explore the adjacent possibly to your satisfaction, there's probably a very simple reason for that: You're trying to not have bad ideas, when you should be trying to have good ideas.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bad ideas are great. Having bad ideas is &lt;em&gt;super&lt;/em&gt; fun. You can toy with them, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html"&gt;nerd out about them&lt;/a&gt;, and you can &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;learn from them&lt;/a&gt;.
You need to be careful about &lt;em&gt;implementing&lt;/em&gt; them, especially at scale, but &lt;em&gt;having&lt;/em&gt; them is a harmless and necessary part of the idea generation process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is especially true because they provide grounding for your adjacent possible. Bad ideas can generate good ideas, because they act as &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-05-11:27.html"&gt;existence proofs&lt;/a&gt; that show you what a solution &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; look like, and you can riff off that to generate good ideas.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You will never get the benefit of this if you are integrating critical thinking too early in the process, because you are &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-06-07:46.html"&gt;censoring&lt;/a&gt; a critical part of the process.
Reproduction and selection are &lt;em&gt;separate parts&lt;/em&gt; of the evolution of ideas, and if you try to integrate them too tightly your idea generation process will feel unneccessarily difficult.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recommend both of the books I mentioned, but especially de Bono's lateral thinking book.
However, I can tell you the most useful idea in the book in one sentence:
When you want to generate ideas, give yourself a prompt (ways to do X, Y, Z), decide how many you want (fifty is a good number, but start with ten if you're unsure), and write down that many ideas. They can be ridiculous, they can certainly be bad, they don't have to be things you'd want to do or even could do, they just have to be ideas attached to the prompt.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After you've done that, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; is the time to mine through the ideas to see if there's anything interesting there, but until you've actually generated the ideas there's no point being too critical.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-09:44.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-11:33.html</id>
    <title>COULDDO vs TODO</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T11:41:42+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;COULDDO vs TODO&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know about you, but I have TODO list anxiety. TODO lists feel like a giant pressure on me of endless and painful grind. I do not like TODO lists though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;COULDDO lists though? Those are great.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1235991023383347200"&gt;asked on Twitter the other day about my coping strategies for depression&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmm... So roughly it's:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Grind certain skills so that you can do them more or less on automatic. It's particularly important that you can do them without feeling emotionally engaged with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) Use non-depressed periods to fill pipeline with ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for example I can read reasonably well while depressed. I can write these daily notebook posts even on my off days because it's stuff I've thought about quite a lot and I've got an ideas list. I can cook decent food while depressed because I've got a good library of basics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The daily notebook posts were getting to be a bit of a struggle until I implemented &lt;a href="https://github.com/DRMacIver/notebook/blob/master/ideas.md"&gt;ideas.md&lt;/a&gt;, a list of possible things I could write about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I wrote earlier &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-09:44.html"&gt;you can't actually run out of ideas&lt;/a&gt;. I can keep that ideas.md file much fuller than my actual mental bandwidth and available time for writing posts, because putting entries in it is just idea generation and idea generation is easy.
Here I have to do the hard work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;ideas.md is an example of a COULDDO list: It's a list of things that I could do, but that I have no obligation to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;COULDDO lists are very good because they ensure that you avoid pipeline stalls, they help you maintain momentum:
When you're feeling listless and not really sure what to do and nothing sparks joy, or you find yourself staring into space, you can look at the list of things that you put together and see if there's anything in there that you currently feel up to doing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also use this for dealing with brain fog days: I have a day plan which I write out on paper of things that it would be useful to get done. It's OK if I get to the end of the day and haven't done all those things. It's even &lt;em&gt;intended&lt;/em&gt;. The paper goes into the bin. The purpose is to ensure that when I find myself in that "Oh god what should I do?" state there is a ready procedure to hand to fill that gap, rather than a default of staring into space or checking Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-11:33.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-11:43.html</id>
    <title>Stuff just happens and you probably don't know why</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T12:02:47+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Stuff just happens and you probably don't know why&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I get ill a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why? Who knows. It's always happened to me. There are any number of theories. Maybe I have a weird immune system. Maybe I touch my face a lot. Maybe I'm a bit too stressed and not breathing properly as a result and that makes me notice mild illnesses more. Maybe it's a consequence of bad diet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is almost certain not monocausal and is because of a number of independent things that don't actually interact but each just up my chances of getting ill, because getting ill is a highly nondeterministic process that is an accumulation of many different things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, you know that big 20th century crime wave? Due to social breakdown, modernity, changing demographics, toxic masculinity responding to the different gender roles in an increasingly feminist world, the consequences of multiple wars, globalisation, and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lead%E2%80%93crime_hypothesis"&gt;oops never mind it was probably just lead&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While we're on the subject of toxic masculinity, you know how every woman has experiences of being cat called in public by men?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No, that's not true actually. It's definitely the &lt;em&gt;majority&lt;/em&gt; experience, but there are multiple women I know who have cautiously said to me "It's really weird. This just doesn't happen to me. Other women talk about how this is some ubiquitous thing and I've just never seen it". It's not an attractiveness thing - the women I've heard this from are mostly very attractive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That's not to say that cat calling isn't a problem. It's a problem, of course, a major one. But somehow it's one that some women don't experience, and it's fairly mysterious as to why. It's easy to generate hypotheses, but it's hard to say which of them are accurate because it's &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; unlikely that it's monocausal, and if it is monocausal it's probably caused by something completely random like preferred colour palette or getting enough sleep or something.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Seemingly almost everyone in London is tired. Seemingly almost everyone in tech has a sleeping disorder. Why? Who knows. It's probably not monocausal, and if it is it's probably something random like the design of the tube network or homophily along shared social traits of people who sleep badly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rival Voices has this idea of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nosilverv/status/1205082282979184640"&gt;secret handshake theory&lt;/a&gt; as implicit ways of groups signalling compatibility, and secret handshakes control what parts of the world you have access to, but I think this if anything &lt;em&gt;understates&lt;/em&gt; how weirdly specific our lived experiences are, and how many areas of life are opened to or locked away from us by seemingly inconsequential choices and behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We like the idea that the world makes sense and things happen to us for reasons, but this greatly underestimates its complexity, and the number of things that are indirect consequences of seemingly unrelated things that just change the numbers enough to completely shift our lived experience into a different pattern from other people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because we focus on this idea that the world makes sense, we tend to fit our experiences to simple narratives, and this causes us to assume they are much more shared than they are. We talk about the typical mind fallacy, but the typical lived experience fallacy is if anything more pervasive. Your lived experience is probably less universally shared than you think it is, and where it's shared it's probably not for the reasons you think it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Questions like this are frustrating because they're in some sense purely empirical and &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be answerable by empirical and logical means, but you're probably never going to know the answer until the nature of the world shifts and the problem fixes itself and becomes obvious in retrospect.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-11:43.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:12.html</id>
    <title>If a task is impossible, try making it harder</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T12:18:55+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;If a task is impossible, try making it harder&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If a lecture is a struggle, try speeding up the video.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you struggle to read fast enough, try using a speed reader app that just scrolls the words by at 1000wpm.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If a book is too hard, try making it harder by reading it aloud. Maybe do weird balancing acts while doing it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often the rate limiting factor on difficult tasks is not actually that they're too hard, it's that we are failing to engage our full attention on them. This is particularly true if you're very smart and/or ADHD or somewhere vaguely in its vicinity. The world is literally moving too slowly for you, which means that you cannot bring your full attention to it, and as a result you never enter flow and the entire thing becomes a painful exercise which you can't help but fail.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This creates the paradoxical solution that impossible seeming tasks are not too hard for you, they're too easy for you.
If you make them harder, you might find that they become possible, because they become something that can absorb your full attention. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel like this is actually the true secret to success to a lot of productivity methodologies. They don't actually help, but by focusing on the methodology they become something that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html"&gt;you can nerd out about&lt;/a&gt; and because your nerding task is integrated with your grounding task, the two together can consume your full attention in a way that the mere task on its own could not. &lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:12.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:35.html</id>
    <title>Untangling moral concepts</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T13:33:55+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Untangling moral concepts&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The following are not the same thing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have an &lt;em&gt;obligation&lt;/em&gt; to do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;morally permissible&lt;/em&gt; to do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;morally virtuous&lt;/em&gt; to do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;morally required&lt;/em&gt; to do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Figuring this out is a process I call &lt;em&gt;untangling&lt;/em&gt;, which is essentially just a skill that you learn doing mathematics:
Finding a bunch of examples where the concepts separate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When untangling it's important that your examples pass the "c'mon, really?" test. They shouldn't be contrived or annoying, but should be points of separation that actually matter in daily life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Obey the laws of physics". This is definitely 1 and 4, and definitely not 3, 5, or 6. There's no real moral component to physics, so there's no real moral significance to it. It's certainly permissible, because if you literally have no option but to do the thing it would be bizarre to consider it forbidden.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Obey the speed limit" is an example where 2 through 6 apply to varying degrees, but 1 does not. People clearly &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; break the speed limit and do so all the time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More, it's &lt;em&gt;common&lt;/em&gt; to have examples like this where people behave low grade unmorally for convenience.
Moral norms are more like guidelines than rules, and almost everyone implicitly understands this and treats them as such.
So, when considering moral norms, don't consider them as ironclad rules, consider them as things you're going to &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; follow. Depending on how serious they are, you'll probably want to follow them more often than not (the moral norms against killing people are stronger than the moral norms against spitting. You would probably still kill someone in some circumstances, even ones you didn't consider morally justified, but they'd have to be pretty extreme).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Brush your teeth" is something you should do which mostly lacks an moral component, so is (2) without any of the others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you have made a promise to do something minor. Say, meet a friend for coffee. Suppose also that a major family crisis has occurred and they need you. "Meeting your friend for coffee" is an example of 3 on its own. You have an obligation (3) but you shouldn't do it, it's not permissible, it's not required, and it's not virtuous.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose someone is being a dick to you. You get angry at them. This is morally permitted, but it's not required or virtuous. Whether you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; do it is situation dependent (it might be tactically wise to do so), but lets say it's not a good idea. So this is an example of (4) without any of the others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So none of (1) through (4) imply anything else on the list. Now we get into the tricky bits where I'm not entirely sure how cleanly they separate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Staying calm in a heated situation where someone is being a dick to you is an example of (5) that is not (6) - it is morally virtuous without being required. Giving all your money to charity is another example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Are there things which are morally virtuous but not morally permissible? I'm not sure. I can come up with some contrived examples where the answer is "Maybe?" (trolley problem type stuff). I think in practice this is probably not an interesting category and all the details will be too contextual.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Are there examples which are morally required but not morally virtuous? Another maybe. I'd say "not committing murder" is definitely ethically required, but it's not particularly praiseworthy. Unclear that it's virtuous, but it's certainly more virtuous than committing murder.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My inclination is that for practical purposes we have (6) implies (5) implies (4), and the examples above show that these are the only implications possible.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:35.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-14:06.html</id>
    <title>Computer games as therapeutic tools</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T14:21:47+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Computer games as therapeutic tools&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think computer games are underrated therapeutic tools. Many people seem to know this, but it seems surprising to others, so I'd like to tell you about three that I find useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Celeste&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slay the Spire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Untitled Goose Game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They each have slightly different functions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Celeste is very good for inducing flow state. If I'm in a bad mood, or otherwise need to recover from something, Celeste allows me to drop into flow state almost instantly, because it's impossible to play Celeste and think at the same time, and it is a rich source of challenges that are right at the edge of my skill level.
This is why it works - it is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:12.html"&gt;hard enough to require full concentration&lt;/a&gt; but not too hard to be unachievable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another game in a similar genre to this is Hollow Knight. Hollow Knight does not work like Celeste for this. It's a decent enough game, but it's a bit too erratic in its pacing and the sort of decision making it requires to be a flow state on tap like Celeste is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Slay the Spire's function is very simple: When I need a break from my brain I can play it for however long I want. It's the opposite of Celeste, in that it doesn't require flow, it just requires very basic reactivity and can be played while half zoned out. If Celeste lets me dial up my level of presentness in the moment, slay the spire lets me dial it way down.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Playing Slay the Spire well requires more concentration and thought than that, but I never claimed I played it well)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Untitled Goose Game has an entirely different purpose. It's a diagnostic tool.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="https://shkspr.mobi/blog/2020/01/the-value-of-videogames-or-why-i-think-untitled-goose-game-was-a-rip-off/"&gt;edent has pointed out&lt;/a&gt;, when considered on its merits as a game, Untitled Goose Game doesn't really have any. It's a very weak puzzle based game with not much play time and not a great deal of challenge to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, you're a goose wreaking mayhem, and you can steal a man's slippers and drop them in the pond, then run around with his pipe in your beak, so there's that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Untitled Goose Game is great if and only if you are currently able to experience the emotion of &lt;em&gt;malicious glee&lt;/em&gt;. You are causing problems on purpose, and that's hilarious. As such I find it a very useful diagnostic tool for telling how depressed I am. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-06-07:46.html"&gt;Depression is in large part a restriction on emotional range&lt;/a&gt;, and having a tool that will reliably provoke a particular emotional response if I'm currently capable of experiencing it is very helpful for calibrating my current level. "Gleelessness" may lack the cachet of "Hopelessness", but it still seems to be a pretty reliable predictor of my depression levels. HONK.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These aren't the only games I play, but they're the main ones. And having a small library of them that I've played a lot of is helpful because they serve as a sort of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-11:33.html"&gt;COULDDO list&lt;/a&gt; where if I'm not sure what to do, I can pick one of these up, and play them more or less on autopilot, and the effect works reliably. I expect I'll add to the list over time, but for now these seem to be a good set of tools for my personal therapeutic toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-14:06.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-14:34.html</id>
    <title>Touch starvation and group responsibility</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T15:21:06+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Touch starvation and group responsibility&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to use this post to talk about the intersection of two things dear to my heart:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touch starvation, especially in men.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Group responsibility as distinct from the sum of individual responsibilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Touch starvation is also common in other groups. I've heard and read a lot about it in disabled women too for example. I'm talking about men primarily because that's the aspect I'm most qualified to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Touch starvation is a big deal. Regular physical contact, ideally with other human beings, seems to be fairly essential to our emotional regulation. This isn't a sex thing, people just really need to be touched.
I could probably cite studies etc for that but this is a notebook post, so I won't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Touch starvation is a very personal subject for me because I've spent a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time touch starved, mostly because I've spent a lot of time single (which I'm fine with) and society is weirdly precious about men and platonic touch (which I'm very much not).
I'm also a very huggy person (a fact which I think the overwhelming majority of my friends would be suprised to hear, for reasons), so this feels extra acute to me, but it's probably pretty bad for everyone in a similar situation.
Right now I'm in a great relationship so I'm getting plenty of touch in the official socially approved way for men, but that doesn't make me less grumpy about the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These norms are of course a thing done by men as well as to men. There are no conspiracy theories here about how this is somehow women's fault. Gender norms are a product of collective behaviour, and women are absolutely part of the shaping of norms around masculinity in approximately the same way that men are responsible for shaping the norms around femininity (if you find this a controversial point, I invite you to not argue with me about it), but it's at the very least a problem &lt;em&gt;primarily&lt;/em&gt; driven by men.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But setting aside who exactly is included in "we", I think it is clear that we are collectively failing men in this way.
Touch starvation in men is epidemic, and it's a major problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Set against this is the fact that no one individual is obligated to participate in fixing it.
I feel when we, society, are failing half of our members to such a large degree, we are &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:35.html"&gt;morally required&lt;/a&gt; to do something about that,
but that does not imply that any individual person is morally required to individually participate in the solution.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's certainly morally virtuous to go hug the men in your life if you want to do that. They'll probably be very grateful, unless &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/jiminy-cricket-must-die/"&gt;they've internalised the norm too heavily&lt;/a&gt; to accept, but it's in no sense morally required.
The moral obligation is at the collective level, and trying to address that at an individual level is so far into "I don't even know where to start" territory that I'm not even sure "morally virtuous" is enough to cover it.
The strongest moral requirement I would put forth here is that if you personally are actively enforcing these norms (which is distinct from being silently complicit in them), it is morally imperative that you should get in the sea.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Uh, sorry, I did say I was quite angry about this)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is another untangling: When men are upset about this issue, a number of bad things happen.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They conflate touch starvation with a need for romantic and/or sexual love, again because they've internalised the norms around touch too heavily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They confuse collective and individual obligations to them ("society is failing me, you are part of society, therefore you are failing me" is a very tempting trap to fall into)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Even if they successfully understand the problem&lt;/em&gt; people pattern match them into one of the first two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly (3) is my biggest concern in writing this piece. I'm kinda expecting to get told I'm a horrible patriarch who thinks he's entitled to women's bodies just for pointing out this problem (please note: Men are allowed to hug men. It doesn't have to be women providing the hugs. Although as someone who is mostly friends with women I would ideally prefer a gender neutral solution).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It would be nice to wrap this post up with a nice pithy call to action, but I don't really have one. Lets just pretend I asked you to normalize hugging men or something equally inspiring but unactionable like that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-14:34.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:27.html</id>
    <title>Be the more decisive person</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T15:51:21+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Be the more decisive person&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you an amazing favour you can do for your friends: Be the one to make decisions when nobody else is willing to step up. Especially unimportant ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I learned this skill the hard way. Getting a bunch of indecisive socially awkward nerds to decide where to go for a meal is worse than herding cats, because it's watching cats try to self organise,
so at some point I just started saying "Hey, why don't we go to $RESTAURANT. Any objections?" and observing how much easier the whole process became once I started doing that. Nobody minds you doing this, everyone is grateful, and a long annoying pointless dither is averted.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People don't want to be the one to make a decision for any number of reasons, but it's mostly anxiety, and they're mostly offloading anxiety onto everyone else. You can stop the cycle of anxiety through the simple realisation that 90% of the decisions that are causing this just don't matter that much. It doesn't matter that much where you go for a meal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you want to help people this way, go read &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;how to make decisions&lt;/a&gt; so that this is low cost for you, and then start making suggestions like this once it's clear you're stuck in an indecision loop that nobody involved wants to break out of.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Remember that the decision you're making is a &lt;em&gt;first pass&lt;/em&gt;. People can object to it, and that's fine. The system is working. This is a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;fastest way to learn something is to do something&lt;/a&gt; situation. By making a suggestion (doing something) you are learning about people's constraints, which you can then feed back in by making another suggestion, or by asking that person to make some more concrete suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For more important decisions you need to start looking into serious facilitation skills and techniques for running meetings and such, but that's a different problem. For now, just help people break out of indecision on the simple stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:27.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:59.html</id>
    <title>Install cut out switches in your mind</title>
    <updated>2020-03-07T15:59:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Install cut out switches in your mind&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you my favourite joke. It comes from Scott Aaronson's "Quantum Computing Since Democritus":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a joke about a planet full of people who believe in antiinduction: if the sun has risen every day in the past, then today, we should expect that it won’t.
As a result, these people are all starving and living in poverty.
Someone visits the planet and tells them, “Hey, why are you still using this anti-induction philosophy? You’re living in horrible poverty!”
“Well, it never worked before...”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A different Scott recently wrote about &lt;a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2020/02/12/confirmation-bias-as-misfire-of-normal-bayesian-reasoning/"&gt;Confirmation bias&lt;/a&gt;. His view is very Bayesian, which I'm not that into, but the basic premise is sound: If you come across a piece of evidence that contradicts your worldview, it's probably right to discount it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a recent discussion of &lt;a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5250/fronjwomestud.33.1.0024?seq=1"&gt;one of my favourite papers&lt;/a&gt; pointed out that the arguments depended in quite a critical way on certain values (obvious sensible ones like "racism bad" which he agreed with, but even so) and that this presented difficulties with how to use it properly for breaking out of your frame of reference.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The common thread here is that in all of these cases there is an underlying concern: "But what if my fundamental worldview was wrong in some critical way? How would I break out of that?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recently reread "Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance", which is a deeply flawed book that is much more interesting in its flaws than in the things people normally get out of it. One of the things I found fascinating was observing the author's thought process (the author is schizophrenic, and this was very obvious to me when reading it). This provoked the following thought process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes, this is a very familiar line of reasoning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now comes the bit where you stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...why aren't you stopping?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He was getting involved in thought loops that were obviously deeply unproductive, and he wasn't stopping. This was quite distressing to me to watch because of how carefully I have cultivated a series of cutoff switches in my thought processes to avoid this from happening.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The most basic one is this: If you are concerned with your worldview being fundamentally wrong in some way... Eh, don't worry about it. It's probably fine. Put that to one side and come back to it later if you really feel like it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; you do grounds out in basic premises about how the world works and what the appropriate values are, and those things are arbitrary and contingent and not even necessarily that consistent. If you allow yourself to reevaluate your worldview as part of every basic thought process, what will happen is that you will be constantly spiralling into unproductive areas of thought.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You should, of course, occasionally consider that your fundamental worldview might be wrong, but mostly the way to do that is by talking to people who are different from you and learning from them and how they see the world. Getting trapped in thought spirals will not do this, and you need to install cut off switches to block off those spirals when you run into them.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:59.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
