<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2024-01-20T11:18:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-10-07:48.html</id>
    <title>Showing people the door</title>
    <updated>2024-01-10T07:59:43+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Showing people the door&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another draft bankruptcy post. I think this was abandoned for a
fairly common reason for me to abandon posts: I tried to write it
because it was important, but it’s actually a fairly depressing subject
for me to write about and I didn’t particularly want to write it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I run a small&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Officially we’re about 400 people, with a regulars list
of about 100 people, of whom maybe half are regularly active.&lt;/span&gt; but fairly successful discord
server. &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/bY5XKnWMQj"&gt;You can join if you want
to&lt;/a&gt;. Nominally it’s about this newsletter, and occasionally we even
remember that, but mostly it’s just a bunch of nerds who hang out on the
internet, help each other navigate life better, and talk about stuff we
like. I think it’s pretty great.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I act as the sole authority figure for how the community works.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It’s not a cult, I promise.&lt;/span&gt;. This is a space on the internet I
manage to cultivate the sort of community and conversations I want to
exist. It’s what I’ve called &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-07-14-13:42.html"&gt;Living
Room Rules&lt;/a&gt; before - it’s the equivalent of people coming around to
my house to hang out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t mean the community do whatever I want. Truthfully, it’s
like herding cats sometimes. But it does mean that when the community
isn’t working, it’s my responsibility to fix it. Often in consultation
with others, but ultimately I’m the one who makes the call.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hardest part of this is that sometimes you have to show people
the door.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had to do this with someone yesterday&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Possibly he’s reading this. If so, sorry. Editor’s note:
Presumably not on the notebook. Also this “yesterday” was actually more
than a year ago.&lt;/span&gt;. He
wasn’t right for the community.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is only the second time I’ve had to ask someone to leave this
discord (I’ve &lt;em&gt;banned&lt;/em&gt; some people for outright terrible
behaviour, but that’s different), but I’ve seen it with other
communities in the past. Crucially, I’ve seen it with other communities
in the past because the community leadership &lt;em&gt;didn’t&lt;/em&gt; ask the
person to leave. This kills the community.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the key things you are there for in a community - what
&lt;em&gt;makes&lt;/em&gt; it a community - is the other people. A community is, at
its core, a group of people who do stuff together. Having someone who
fails to gel with the group and can’t easily be avoided around disrupts
that, because it adds friction to every interaction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What this means is that if some is disrupting the group’s ability to
interact, there is less of the thing that brings people there, and some
people who were already marginal stop showing up so much. This in turn
means that the people who were there partly to hang out with those
people stop showing up so much, which in turn…&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s not a complete death spiral even in the worst case. Usually some
subset of the community stays - those who don’t have any better options,
or who are still too attached to what the community used to be - but the
community turns into a shell of its former self.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More commonly, one person who doesn’t mesh with the others isn’t
enough to offset the rest of the benefits people are getting, but the
community contracts a bit and what’s left feels slightly less thriving.
If you add more such people, it may get worse, .&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Internet communities without a shared project are particularly
vulnerable to this, because there’s &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; bringing people
there except the other people, so if you ruin those interactions you’ve
got nothing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, communities built around something are a bit more
robust. e.g.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An open source project you have the motivation of the project itself
- you’re there because you want it for stuff. A sufficiently toxic
contributor can definitely drive you off, and someone you don’t get
along with can definitely sap your motivation to contribute&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Open source is pretty good at doing this on its own,
honestly.&lt;/span&gt;, but you’re at least there for some
specific purpose external to the people involved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volunteer-driven physical projects (e.g. charitable works,
maintenance of some space, etc) are the same but more so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communities built around access to some resource. e.g. you’re
probably not going to stop hanging out on the midjourney discord just
because you don’t like the people there, because that’s where you go to
use midjourney.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical communities with shared physical resources are even more
like this. The people at your local maker space or tennis club might be
super annoying, but if it’s the only place you can go to get access to a
laser cutter or a tennis court, you’re still going to keep going.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These places still can be harmed by people who don’t mesh well with
the group, and sometimes even outright ruined, but it’s much harder and
they’re more robust against it because of the additional draw to keep
coming back beyond just liking the people there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="who-needs-to-leave"&gt;Who needs to leave?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly, the person who I asked to leave wasn’t an asshole. He
was a bit hard to deal with, but he didn’t cross any lines where I could
feel good about just pressing the ban button. He just consistently
failed to mesh with the community in a way that made everyone else’s
experience worse when he was in the room.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Frankly, he was probably just of an age where relatively few people
would fit in with the rest of us - we’re mostly in our 30s, and he was
in his late teens or early 20s, and I think most people of that age
wouldn’t have fit. Certainly I can’t imagine a 19 year old version of me
doing well there. There’s just too large an experience gap.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of thing is, in general, the problem zone: People who have
not and probably never will do anything that lets you go “Right, you’ve
crossed a line” and kick them out, but you really wish they would.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you start feeling that way about someone, you probably need to
think seriously about asking them to leave. If you don’t, people you
want in the community much more will leave on their own instead.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="afterword"&gt;Afterword&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tapered out there partially because I don’t really have good advice
on how to navigate this. This is hard, and I’ve not got more than a
handful of personal examples of doing it, and I’m not confident that I
handled it especially well, or that I know what handling it well looks
like in full generality.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All I know is that I’ve seen communities die by not doing this, and
it’s a problem that needs solving&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-10-07:48.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-11-08:07.html</id>
    <title>Thinking in memes</title>
    <updated>2024-01-11T09:15:58+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Thinking in memes&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another draft bankruptcy post, though I’m going to continue this on
for a bit as it’s really more of the prompt for a post than a full
abandoned draft.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of you get annoyed when I write very culturally bound things
that rely on a lot of shared context. Like Shaka, when the walls fell,
you will not enjoy this post. You may or may not wish to bear with me
anyway.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is a post about memes. Mostly of the internet sort, not
the Dawkins sort, although a little bit also of the Dawkins sort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="all-part-of-the-pattern"&gt;All part of the pattern&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was indeed a garden, like a lot of other gardens you got in areas
like Clay Lane. The gray soil was nothing more than old brick dust,
elderly cat mess, and generalized, semirotted dross. At the far end was
a three-hole privy. It was built handily by the gate to the back lane so
the night-soil men didn’t have far to go, but this one had a small stone
cylinder turning gently beside it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The garden didn’t get much proper light. Gardens like this never did.
You got secondhand light once the richer folk in the taller buildings
had finished with it. Some people kept pigeons or rabbits or pigs on
their plots, or planted, against all experience, a few vegetables. But
it’d take magic beans to reach the real sunlight in gardens like
this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, someone had made an effort. Most of the spare ground
had been covered with gravel of different sizes, and this had been
carefully raked into swirls and curves. Here and there, some individual
larger stones had been positioned, apparently with great thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vimes stared at the garden of rocks, desperate for anything to occupy
his attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He could see what the designer had in mind, he thought, but the
effect had been spoiled. This was the big city, after all. Garbage got
everywhere. The main disposal method was throwing it over a wall. Sooner
or later someone would sell it or, possibly, eat it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A young monk was carefully raking the gravel. He gave a respectful
bow as Sweeper approached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The old man sat down on a stone bench.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Push off and get us two cups of tea, lad, will you?” he said. “One
green with yak butter, and Mister Vimes will have it boiled orange in a
builder’s boot with two sugars and yesterday’s milk, right?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s how I like it,” said Vimes weakly, sitting down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sweeper took a deep, long breath. “And I like building gardens,” he
said. “Life should be a garden.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vimes stared blankly at what was in front of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Okay,” he said. “The gravel and rocks, yes, I can see that. Shame
about all the rubbish. It always turns up, doesn’t it…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes,” said Lu-Tze. “It’s part of the pattern.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What? The old cigarette packet?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Certainly. That invokes the element of air,” said Sweeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And the cat doings?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To remind us that disharmony, like a cat, gets everywhere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The cabbage stalks? The used [condom]?*”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At our peril we forget the role of the organic in the total harmony.
What arrives seemingly by chance in the pattern is part of a higher
organization that we can only dimly comprehend. This is a very important
fact, and has a bearing on your case.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And the beer bottle?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first time since Vimes had met him, the monk frowned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Y’know, some bugger always tosses one over the wall on his way back
from the pub on Friday nights. If it wasn’t forbidden to do that kind of
thing, he’d feel the flat to my hand and no mistake.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not part of the higher organization?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Possibly. Who cares? That sort of thing gets on my thungas, it
really does,” said Sweeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This passage is one of various things the world has chucked over the
wall into my mind. I like to imagine that the garden has been raked
around the rubbish in the same way as it would any large rock or
intrusion into it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="/images/rock-garden.jpg"/&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Harima-ankokuji-sekitei01.jpg"&gt;Picture
of a Japanese rock garden by wikimedia user Jnn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is often how my mind feels to me. Things appear in it from the
world and stay there, patterns radiating outwards, interfering and
interacting and creating something unique and sometimes beautiful
patterns, but it often starts from garbage.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="trekkies-watching-darmok"&gt;Trekkies, watching Darmok&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The “Star Trek: The Next Generation” episode “Darmok” is about a race
of aliens whose communication style does not correctly translate,
because everything they say is in terms of analogy to previous
events.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Editor’s note: I think I stopped writing this post because this
section was boring. Please insert any one of various standard takes
about how the way we communicate on the internet is like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="the-associative-value-of-memes"&gt;The associative value of
memes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because what I actually wanted to talk about was the use of memes for
thinking rather than about how we talk with them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of this is just the usual straightforward way that any language
is a tool for thought: Having a concept for a thing allows you to think
about the thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But memes have an unusual sticking power, because of the richness of
the concept. They usually have an image with a quite specific vibe
associated with them. Sometimes they undergo enough evolution that they
leave the image behind, but even there there’s a whole web of
associations that helps make them feel really accessible and live.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve talked about a related phenomenon in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/reading-philosophy-for-the-examples"&gt;Reading
philosophy for the examples&lt;/a&gt;, where having a whole rich example for a
concept makes it much more relevant.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="/images/duck-guy.png"/&gt; &lt;em&gt;Purple suited man riding a
rocket duck, as you do.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even in that post the images help. I’ve still got a concept for duck
guy that feels quite live,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I still don’t really know how to talk to him, though I
suspect I’m better at it than most.&lt;/span&gt; and Danny at the Grand
Canyon also sticks around, but I had to look up the rest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The particularly useful function of memes as a tool of thought though
is the way they spring unbidden to mind.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, a useful meme to acquire recently has been “Stop. Look.
Think. Are you eating yourself?”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ouroboros.png"/&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://topatoco.com/products/og-ouroboros"&gt;Buy the T-shirt
here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When stuck in unhelpful patterns, it’s helpful to remember this goofy
little guy and ask if I’m currently eating myself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another good related tool comes from catchy songs. Discord got a bit
obsessed with the song Diggy Diggy Hole for a while:&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I can’t imagine how this could possibly have happened
and definitely accept no culpability in it…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/ytWz0qVvBZ0?si=8JxlPuz0o1eb6dZw" title="YouTube video player" width="560"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It became a bit of an injoke for a while to come up with many
variations of this to the tune of verby verby noun&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I am on discord and I’m verbing a noun. verby verby
noun. verby verby noun.&lt;/span&gt;,
but the one that’s really usefully stuck is that when you’re caught in
that annoying state of endlessly browsing the internet, doomscrolling,
etc. you’re in a clicky clicky loop.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Clicky clicky loop. Clicky clicky loop…&lt;/span&gt; Having this concept
available is often enough to break you out of it when the music starts
playing in your head.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And of course, there’s the eagle that makes me go outside whenever I
think about it:&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This hasn’t actually worked very well recently, but in
my defence it’s been cold and dark and wet and I don’t like. Admittedly
this is also the eagle’s vibe so this isn’t much of a defence.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/stupid-little-walk.png"/&gt; &lt;em&gt;An eagle going on a
stupid little daily walk for it stupid physical and mental
health.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I partly think of these posts as my stupid little daily writing for
my stupid mental health.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="no-private-language"&gt;No private language&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think an important feature of memes is that they’re social. Very
few of these things would have stuck without a community of people
reinforcing them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Partly this is because talking about the meme makes it more salient,
part of this is because I think a group is much better at building memes
that are optimised to work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there are probably useful magical practices (sigil creation
etc) that do pull off this sort of trick privately, but personally I’ve
never got them to work. I think it’s important to me that eagle and
ouroboros are shared concepts for the things they represent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe this is something communities should do a bit more
intentionally though. Crafting and selecting memes for their common
problems. I’m not really sure what this would look like, but it’s worth
thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-11-08:07.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-12-08:42.html</id>
    <title>Working hours: A report on an anomaly</title>
    <updated>2024-01-12T09:55:12+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Working hours: A report on an anomaly&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-12&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of my most read posts is &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/people-dont-work-as-much-as-you-think"&gt;People
don’t work as much as you think&lt;/a&gt;. In it, I report:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my estimate of how much work I can get done in a day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most days I can do somewhere between one and two hours of hard
thinky work. Writing, programming, etc. Good days or easy tasks it might
be three. It’s rarely four, and over a week almost never averages more
than two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can probably do some low effort reading, not very high quality
code review (more at the level of “scan for obvious flaws” than “do an
in depth study of the design”) on top of that without it massively
eating into my energy levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Four hours of coaching in a day, i.e. face to face time in which I
have to be on and intelligently responding, is pretty close to my
absolute limit - I can do five in a push but I will not be very
competent for the fifth - and I cannot do this two days running. I have
estimated 20 hours to be my absolute upper bound for coaching I could do
in a week, and I’ve set my comfortable limit as 10 hours if I want to be
able to maintain little things like getting any writing done or having
remotely functional mental health1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can probably do 4-6 hours of very routine stuff (e.g. mostly
mechanical refactoring of code).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can sometimes do 4-6 hours of flow-state work (e.g. debugging a
hard problem). This requires a problem with tight feedback loops, no
interruptions, and a good physical and mental health day. I almost never
get this combination at the moment, and when I had normal jobs this
happened maybe a couple of times per year for a few days running at most
each time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Idlework, where I think about a problem in the background while
going for a walk or having a shower or the like, is mostly free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve got longstanding problems with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1711673235891257441"&gt;stamina&lt;/a&gt;
and energy levels that I want to improve. My health isn’t great, and I
suffer from something that isn’t really chronic fatigue but is certainly
chronic and certainly fatigue. It’s what the doctors dismissively call
“tired all the time”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of these things feel like very intrinsic hard limits where it’s
not that I don’t want to do more, it’s that I hit some sort of block
where my brain stops working and I couldn’t do more if I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, recently (last few weeks, plus a good chunk of December) I’ve
been working pretty solid six to eight hour days. I’ve also been ending
these days… mostly fine? I’m noticeably a bit tired, but it’s not like I
get to the end of the day and I’m dead. I’ve felt much worse on days
I’ve done much less.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if this will continue to be the case. I doubt it’s fully
long-term sustainable,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;and even if it is, it’s come with some fairly
significant downsides in terms of available capacity for non-work things
which is a problem.&lt;/span&gt; but it also doesn’t feel like I’ve
been pushing myself &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; hard to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As the rationalists say, I notice that I am confused.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this is definitely a mix of my schedule and the project I’m
on. Here’s roughly how that goes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wake up whenever I like&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Or at least whenever my body likes, which is not always
the same thing.&lt;/span&gt;. Sometimes to an alarm,
often not. This might be any time between 7AM (if I’ve slept well and
got to bed on time) or 10AM (if I haven’t or didn’t).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The morning is mostly not spent working. I check project Slack, I
check on any jobs that have run overnight, anything I want to be ready
for the afternoon I start running and write whatever I need to do to
enable that. On a busy morning or one that starts early this might add
up to two hours work. Most mornings it’s probably somewhere in the half
hour to hour region. Mostly though I potter around, do home things,
write, etc, and do whatever is needed to gradually become human.
Sometimes I eat breakfast, sometimes I don’t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At around noon through one I have lunch. This is usually a full
meal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At 1PM I switch into full on work mode. I work pretty solidly on
code for the next four hours until people in US time zones start waking
up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From about 5PM to 7PM I may still be working solo but I’m probably
in calls or meetings for at least half of it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As close to 7PM sharp as I can, I close my work computer and stop
working.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes I’ll do about another half an hour of work over the course
of the rest of the evening as I check on running jobs, etc. I try not
to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most of these details feel essential to how much I’ve been getting
done - the flexible mornings, the large chunk of flow state work, the
transition out of flow state work to work with other people, and the
hard cut off.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don’t &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; these are sufficient though. Certainly I’ve
had, you know, jobs before, and I wasn’t this reliably productive in
them. What I’m describing would be possible on a good day, but good days
were in short supply.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here’s a list of everything that might be being helpful about the
work itself:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It might be the nature of the work. It’s at a very good level for me
where it’s at the cutting edge of my skill but not beyond it. There’s
always something I can obviously do, but it’s never obvious that it’s
going to work and I’m constantly having to learn new things in order to
do it (while generally being able to learn them as I go rather than
having a huge amount of moving parts all of which I have to stand)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is the most consistently my primary focus has been on writing
code in a while and I’ve definitely spent the last few years starved for
&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/two-types-of-work"&gt;crunchy
work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There’s very little uncertainty in what I do next. The incoming task
queue is very well saturated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fact that I do not usually have meetings until the end of the
day helps a lot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And some tmore general things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I quit caffeine for a while and resumed in mid December, and my
caffeine intake has been gradually ramping up in line with this, so it’s
very plausible that I am currently in a period where caffeine actually
works for the first time in a while and that’s helping.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;My relationship with caffeine is so annoyingly
problematic. It’s both great for me and terrible for me.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am working in a room with a very bright corn bulb, which I started
doing to combat seasonal depression. I started this year &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt;
depressed before I got back into the swing of things, so clearly
something is working for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relatedly, I started daily writing again a little bit before my
productivity took off at the beginning of this year, and that too has
been very helpful for depression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My diet is OK at the moment (not great) and I’m taking a probiotic
pretty reliably.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’m doing regular pilates and jumping on a trampoline a lot&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;We made it for the child, but I’m the second biggest
user. Well, I’m the biggest user, but I’m the second most frequent
user.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pilates has significantly reduced my chronic joint pain
issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things are going pretty well in my personal life. Not perfectly,
everything is more than a bit stressful right now, but on balance
everything is trending in a good direction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here’s are some things that it probably isn’t:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-02-14-23:37.html"&gt;Inositol&lt;/a&gt;.
I’ve been forgetting to take it reliably recently. I should fix that but
it hasn’t felt necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other supplements. I was trying a whole bunch of things before and I
mostly lost the habit and haven’t resumed. I’m drinking &lt;a href="https://drinkag1.com/en-uk"&gt;Athletic Greens&lt;/a&gt; a couple times a
week when it feels like I’m lacking in something, but I don’t know if
that’s really doing anything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-caffeine stimulants. “Take amphetamines” is the most common
advice I’ve seen for this level of hyper productivity. I haven’t needed
to take amphetamines to achieve this. I experimented a bit with nicotine
lozenges in December but it mostly made me nauseous (I’ve had some luck
with it before and may try again).&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;That being said, my state of mind does feel a bit like
it used to when I took modafinil, a thing I definitely did legally and
with a prescription don’t do drugs kids. There’s a similar level of
singlemindedness of focus and slight irritability at things that intrude
on that focus. I’m even ending the day with my appetite feeling somewhat
suppressed. But this is genuinely without taking any stimulant stronger
than caffeine so no idea why.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some fundamental shift in the nature of my being. It doesn’t feel
unprecedented to have days like this, only to have them this reliably.
All of the sensations are familiar, it’s just unfamiliar that it keeps
happening.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don’t think I’ve actually fixed my health problems. They’re all
still there, they just feel less like bottlenecks right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My chronic headaches are still there and in fact I have a mild
headache most of the time right now.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Another thing that feels similar to taking modafinil.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another thing maybe worth noting is that there was a significantly
dip in this around the end of the holiday season. As mentioned, I
started the year massively depressed, and it took a little bit to get
back into the flow of it, and I had to gradually ramp up into this state
over a period of a few days.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My best guess is that the core of it is that spending energy is
actually energising rather than debilitating, as long as you can
experience the demands on you as eustress rather than destress. I’m not
sure I’ll be able to continue that, and it’s very very likely that
there’s some sort of hidden precondition that I’ve not identified, but
fingers crossed that it stays this way.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-12-08:42.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-13-08:28.html</id>
    <title>Writing good programming abstractions</title>
    <updated>2024-01-13T11:55:04+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Writing good programming abstractions&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-13&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was talking to &lt;a href="https://nelhage.com/"&gt;Nelson&lt;/a&gt; about
programming abstractions the other day, and how you identify a good
abstraction, and I hit on a heuristic that once I suggested it seemed
obviously correct to me but that is very at odds with how I think people
normally think about introducing abstractions in their codebase.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I don’t mean anything fancy by abstraction. Implementing
a new class or a new function for example.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s this: When you introduce an abstraction, it has to be an
improvement at each call site. That is, even if you never reuse it, it
should be make your code better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another way of thinking about this: If you implemented this, and then
you deleted all but one of the call sites, would you be tempted to
inline the abstraction? If yes, you shouldn’t do it. If you were in a
fresh codebase and wanted to do something similar to your previous uses
of the abstraction, would you inclined to copy the previous abstraction
into your codebase in order to make use of it? That’s a sign that it’s
probably a pretty good abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, I think most people’s intuitions about abstraction are
around reducing code duplication. You introduce a function when you see
duplicate code, because duplicate code is bad and you want to reduce it.
I think this intuition is almost entirely wrong. It leads you to create
bad abstractions, sometimes where you didn’t even need one at all, and
it also means you miss important abstractions that you could have
introduced even without any duplication.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, it’s not that duplication can’t be the &lt;em&gt;prompt&lt;/em&gt; for
abstraction. In the conversation Nelson and I were having, I’d
introduced a class that managed a bunch of state for gathering
statistics about some work in progress and doing cleanup when particular
conditions were met. Originally I wrote that logic and state inline in
the class managing those tasks. Then I needed it again, in a slightly
different way with slightly different constraints, so I extracted a
class for the common state and logic. This is a perfectly reasonable
example of abstraction in the classic sense of reducing duplication.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But also, even before I’d written the second call site, the code got
much cleaner, because doing this made me think about the actual
interface I wanted, and I replaced a bunch of raw calls to heapq and set
management with a nice API that declared what I was actually doing. This
was a big improvement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The repetition served the following purposes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was a &lt;em&gt;prompt&lt;/em&gt; to think “Can I abstract this?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the fact that I had needed it twice, I had a better idea of how
to abstract it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It &lt;em&gt;justified the work of making the abstraction&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The third is an important clarification of the heuristic: It’s not
that the abstraction has to be justifiable without the duplication.
There are two things to consider when making a change: How much of an
improvement it is, and how much effort it is to implement. An
abstraction that is a lot of work for only a mild improvement might not
be worth it for one call site but clearly worth it if you’re going to
use it in multiple places.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the best way to think about abstraction is that its purpose
is to &lt;em&gt;make programming less annoying&lt;/em&gt;. Writing the same code
over and over again is annoying, and abstraction can reduce that
annoyance, but it only reduces the annoyance if the abstracted code is
actually less annoying than repeating yourself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This judgement of annoyance does of course require developing a
degree of taste, which makes it somewhat uninformative if you’re just
starting out. Here are some ways code can be annoying that’s worth
factoring out:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’ve got multiple pieces of state that are always used
together, it can be worth putting them together into an object if you
can figure out a clean API for that object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similarly, if there are a lot of intermediate variables that aren’t
used outside of calculation, it might be worth extracting a function to
reduce their visibility - it means you don’t have to keep track of where
they’re used, and it’s harder to make stupid typos where you
accidentally refer to a different variable where you mean.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a function is really hard to follow, it can be worth extracting
parts of it into smaller functions. e.g. recently I refactored a
function to just extract the bodies of various branches of an if
statement into functions. Those functions will never be called from
anywhere else, but the control flow of the code was impossible to follow
in a way that had previously masked a bug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If code is irritating to get right, it can be worth thinking about
whether there is an abstraction that makes it easier to get right. For
example, it can be useful to factor out error handling into context
managers in Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes there is a sort of logical “abstract algorithm” to code
that is worth factoring out into a higher order function. e.g. I’ve
talked about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2019-04-30-13:03.html"&gt;&lt;code&gt;find_integer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
before, which I end up reusing all over the place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the other direction, it’s probably better not to introduce an
abstraction if:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It requires introducing a function with a lot of arguments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It significantly increases the number of lines of code when you
first introduce it at one call site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The abstraction is significantly complicated by different needs from
different call sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, I think it’s worth erring on the side of not abstracting.
If you’re not feeling the pain of not abstracting, it’s probably
fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, here’s some code I often write variations of&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I work on test-case reduction, so this sort of thing
comes up a lot. I’m aware that almost nobody else regularly needs to
write code that looks like this. Also yes I’m aware of the quadratic
nature of this code. It’s fine, I promise. It’s not &lt;a href="https://accidentallyquadratic.tumblr.com/"&gt;accidentally
quadratic&lt;/a&gt;, it’s intrinsically quadratic because the
&lt;code&gt;can_delete&lt;/code&gt; checks are already O(n) and have much higher
constant factors.&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="sourceCode" id="cb1"&gt;&lt;pre class="sourceCode python"&gt;&lt;code class="sourceCode python"&gt;&lt;span id="cb1-1"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb1-1" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;i &lt;span class="op"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="dv"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb1-2"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb1-2" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="cf"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span class="op"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bu"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;(ls):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb1-3"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb1-3" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="cf"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; can_delete(ls, i):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb1-4"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb1-4" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        &lt;span class="kw"&gt;del&lt;/span&gt; ls[i]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb1-5"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb1-5" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="cf"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb1-6"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb1-6" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        i &lt;span class="op"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="dv"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And this code is a bit fiddly and I could definitely do something
along the lines of:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="sourceCode" id="cb2"&gt;&lt;pre class="sourceCode python"&gt;&lt;code class="sourceCode python"&gt;&lt;span id="cb2-1"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-1" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="kw"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; DeletableListIterator:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-2"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-2" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="kw"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="fu"&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class="va"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;, ls):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-3"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-3" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        &lt;span class="va"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;.ls &lt;span class="op"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; ls&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-4"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-4" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        &lt;span class="va"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;.i &lt;span class="op"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="dv"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-5"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-5" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-6"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-6" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="kw"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="fu"&gt;__iter__&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class="va"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-7"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-7" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        &lt;span class="cf"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="va"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;.i &lt;span class="op"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bu"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class="va"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;.ls):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-8"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-8" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;            &lt;span class="cf"&gt;yield&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="va"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;.i&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-9"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-9" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;            i &lt;span class="op"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="dv"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-10"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-10" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-11"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-11" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="kw"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; delete(&lt;span class="va"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-12"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-12" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        &lt;span class="kw"&gt;del&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="va"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;.ls[&lt;span class="va"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;.i]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb2-13"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb2-13" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        &lt;span class="va"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;.i &lt;span class="op"&gt;-=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="dv"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And then I could use this as:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="sourceCode" id="cb3"&gt;&lt;pre class="sourceCode python"&gt;&lt;code class="sourceCode python"&gt;&lt;span id="cb3-1"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb3-1" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;list_iterator &lt;span class="op"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; DeletableListIterator(ls)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb3-2"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb3-2" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="cf"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span class="kw"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; list_iterator:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb3-3"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb3-3" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="cf"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; can_delete(ls, i):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb3-4"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb3-4" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        list_iterator.delete()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it’s not really an improvement. I find this if anything slightly
harder to follow than the original, though there’s not much in it. But
more importantly, sometimes I want to write code like the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="sourceCode" id="cb4"&gt;&lt;pre class="sourceCode python"&gt;&lt;code class="sourceCode python"&gt;&lt;span id="cb4-1"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb4-1" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;i &lt;span class="op"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="dv"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb4-2"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb4-2" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="cf"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span class="op"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bu"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;(ls):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb4-3"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb4-3" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="cf"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; can_delete(ls, i, i &lt;span class="op"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; k):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb4-4"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb4-4" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        &lt;span class="kw"&gt;del&lt;/span&gt; ls[i:i&lt;span class="op"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;k]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb4-5"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb4-5" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="cf"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span id="cb4-6"&gt;&lt;a aria-hidden="true" href="#cb4-6" tabindex="-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        i &lt;span class="op"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="dv"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And now I need to fiddle with the implementation to support this
too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is almost certainly an abstraction that would make support this
well - e.g. from what I know of C++’s iterator protocol it seems
probably actually quite good for this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But also… this code is fine without it? It’s a bit weird, and
slightly ugly, but it’s not actually hard to get right, it’s not a lot
longer than it needs to be, and once you’re familiar with the pattern
it’s pretty straightforward to work with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;None of this is to discourage you from creating abstractions in
general. I’m a big fan of well factored code. But it’s easy to abstract
too much, or abstract the wrong things, and I think paying attention to
what’s irritating about working on your codebase and fixing that is a
good way to prioritise.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-13-08:28.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-14-09:38.html</id>
    <title>Defining definition</title>
    <updated>2024-01-14T09:56:08+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Defining definition&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another abandoned draft, this one dredged up from an old Google doc.
It was meant to be part of a longer book-length project but I lost
steam, because that’s what happens when I undertake longer book-length
projects.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When we use a word, we might know exactly what we mean by it, but
unless other people know what we mean by it our use of it isn’t very
useful. If I wrote a long essay about the strengths and weaknesses of
incorporating scamprooft&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;These are of course all completely made up words.&lt;/span&gt; into our florbnoggle practices, this
would not be very helpful to a reader that doesn’t know what scamprooft
is and hasn’t ever practised florbnoggle in their life.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Of course, such a reader probably won’t benefit from
reading such an essay in most circumstances, but they might if you can
adequately communicate them that florbnoggling is basically the same as
bungipopping, a practice they are quite familiar with, except you zeft
when in bungipopping you would smork.&lt;/span&gt; We
can solve this problem by giving people &lt;em&gt;definitions&lt;/em&gt; of concepts
we are using that they might not be familiar with, in order to help them
understand what we mean by them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A definition, informally, is an explanation of what some concept
(usually labelled with a word or a phrase) means. That is, it tells you
how to apply the concept.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;“Definition” is used in a variety of other related ways.
For example, you can “define the problem”, you can “define the terms of
an agreement” etc. When I talk about definitions in this chapter, I
don’t mean those senses, I mean specifically defining the meaning of
some term.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The key thing that a definition lets you do is understand when some
item fits the concept. This provides you with &lt;em&gt;conditions&lt;/em&gt;
(things you can check) that allow you to tell whether something is an
instance of that concept or not. That is, a definition is supposed to
communicate to you some sort of decision procedure that you can use to
check whether the concept applies in a given instance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most definitions we use in practice are in some sense incomplete -
there will be some things that the definition gives you a clear yes to,
some that it gives you a clear no to, and a large class of states
(often, but not always, somewhere between the two) where it doesn’t give
you a clear answer. Sometimes that’s a limitation of the definition and
a better definition would decide between them, sometimes it’s just that
the precise boundary is just genuinely fuzzy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, some things are just extremely hard to define without
introducing some sort of circularity or non-linguistic explanation. We
explain the colour “red” by pointing to red things until you get the
pattern.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Defining things perfectly is hard to impossible, and often even
undesirable, but some amount of definition is necessary if we’re to be
able to communicate at all. This chapter is about how to use definitions
well, and to do that we’re going to have to dig in to what a definition
actually does, and how to take advantage of definition’s strengths while
compensating for its weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="necessary-and-sufficient-conditions"&gt;Necessary and sufficient
conditions&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;ideal&lt;/em&gt; of a definition is the sort of definition you
would see in mathematics, which takes some concept and provides strict
necessary and sufficient rules for when it applies. For example: a
square is a shape with four straight sides, all of equal lengths, and
each corner having the same angle.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What it means to say that these are &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; conditions is
that if something doesn’t satisfy all of them it is not a square. For
example, an equilateral triangle is a shape with three straight sides,
all of equal lengths, and each corner having the same angle. You can
tell that it’s not a square because it fails the condition of having
four straight sides even though it satisfies all the others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What it means to say that these are &lt;em&gt;sufficient&lt;/em&gt; conditions is
that if something satisfies all of them it’s definitely a square.
There’s no possibility of saying “Oh whoops I forget that there’s a
secret extra requirement”, these conditions lay out what it means to be
a square and anything that satisfies them is one. We will often write
sufficient conditions as an “if” statement. e.g. “A shape is a square
if…”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To look it another way: A necessary condition is something you can
check in order to show that an item of interest &lt;em&gt;isn’t&lt;/em&gt; the
thing. A sufficient condition tells you something you can check to show
that an item of interest &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the thing. We will often write
necessary conditions as an “only if” statement. e.g. “A shape is a
square only if…”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Having a set of conditions which is both necessary and sufficient is
very convenient because it gives you a precise&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s possible to have sets of conditions that are necessary but not
sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, you &lt;em&gt;weaken&lt;/em&gt; a set of necessary conditions by
removing parts and they’ll still be necessary, so e.g. “a shape with
four sides of equal lengths” is a condition that is necessary for being
a square (every square has four sides with equal lengths) but not
sufficient because e.g. a rhombus (a square which has been skewed so
that all sides have equal lengths but some corners are pointier than
others) satisfies these but is not a square.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly you can &lt;em&gt;strengthen&lt;/em&gt; a set of sufficient conditions
and still have a set of sufficient conditions. e.g. Anything satisfying
“a shape with four sides of length one and all angles equal” is a
square, but a square with sides of length two does not satisfy these
conditions so they are not necessary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Generally with non-mathematical objects we’re not so lucky as to have
simple necessary and sufficient conditions. Those that are tend to refer
to human-constructed concepts that are built as having necessary and
sufficient conditions deliberately. e.g. legal concepts tend to come
with a very explicit decision procedure for determining that they apply.
You’re “officially married in the country of X”&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Normally one would just say “married” here, but this
blurs multiple related but distinct concepts together, and also elides
historical marriages from before state records begin.&lt;/span&gt; if
you’re officially recorded as married in X or by some country whose
marriages are recognised by X (and if your marriage is of a type that is
recognised by as permissible by X due to e.g. constraints on gender).&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It’s almost certainly more complicated than this. I am
not a lawyer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For things that are more about describing things that actually exist
in the physical world, what you tend to find is that it’s easy to
provide sufficient conditions and it’s easy to provide necessary
conditions, but there’s a large gap in the middle. e.g. the sorites
paradox (how many grains of sand count as a heap?) can be thought of as
being about this gap: It’s easy to provide a sufficient condition
(e.g. if you’ve got between one and two million grains in a pile, that
counts as a heap), it’s easy to provide a necessary condition (e.g. you
need more than one grain to count as a heap), but somewhere in the
middle the question gets hard to resolve. You’ll have this problem with
most continuous quantities - how tall do you have to be before you count
as tall? How old do you have to be before you count as elderly? There
isn’t a clear boundary, but it’s easy to create necessary conditions and
easy to create sufficient conditions, it’s just not easy to create
conditions that are both.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Running into problems like this is often what stops people coming up
with good definitions for things: They are aiming for a mathematical
style set of necessary-and-sufficient conditions, this doesn’t work, and
then they give up on the whole thing as indefinable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact, definitions are perfectly possible for real-world concepts.
We have to give up on them being as nice as mathematical definitions,
but we can still use them to provide people with helpful handles on what
we mean, and it starts by recognising that we’re often going to want to
provide separate necessary conditions and sufficient conditions, and
we’ll almost always have ambiguous edge cases that any definition we
provide won’t cover. This doesn’t stop them being useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, a necessary condition for being a definition is that it
is an attempt to explain what a term means using language. This is not a
sufficient condition (e.g. talking about the history of the use of a
term satisfies this condition but is not really a definition).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sufficient condition for something being a definition is that it
has the form “A (term) is a (thing) which…”. This gives you something
very like the mathematical type of definition, and you can sure that
something that looks like this is, or at least can function as, a
definition.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Much of the interesting work of defining things lies between the
regions set by these two conditions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="ostensive-definition"&gt;Ostensive Definition&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One useful way of defining things is by &lt;em&gt;ostensive
definition,&lt;/em&gt; which means roughly “definition by showing”.
Classically, you point out a bunch of examples and define your term as
meaning “this sort of thing”. When you see it in writing it will often
look like “By this term, I mean things like…”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ostensive definition as defined this way is bad and I don’t like it,
but the thing that it is trying to point to is good, so I’m going to
shamelessly redefine the term (in a way that includes the original
usage) as meaning a definition which uses examples in some essential way
(i.e. not just as illustrations of some point).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The limitation of definition by just pointing at examples is this:
You can think of an example of a concept as being an &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt;
specific sufficient condition, and you need at least some sort of
necessary condition preventing you from generalising that condition too
far. “You see this thing? It’s a cat.” gives you a sufficient definition
for being a cat, but it doesn’t tell you what else is a cat. It would be
perfectly reasonable from this one example to assume that cat meant, for
example, animal, and start calling dogs cats as well.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This isn’t pedantry! It’s an actual problem in language
acquisition, both first language and foreign languages.&lt;/span&gt; At
the bare minimum, defining things ostensively requires you to point at
both examples of the concept and non-examples of the concept.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In theory, you can define anything you like ostensively as long as
you’re able to interact with the recipient. You give them a bunch of
examples, and then they point at more examples and you say whether they
are or aren’t an instance of the thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In practice, most of the time, this doesn’t work very well. Both
because you’re not necessarily getting to interact with the people
you’re defining things for (e.g. if you’re writing it down), and also
it’s very slow because it can take a very long time for them to figure
out the right decision procedure for the concept.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is that people are not necessarily generalising in the
way that you want them to. If you show them a bunch of examples and they
come up with a rule for distinguishing them, there can be many rules
that work.This means that they will consistently have errors in their
understanding of the concept.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Worse, often you won’t even be able to &lt;em&gt;tell&lt;/em&gt; what those
errors are, because either they’re in important but rare edge cases, or
the back-and-forth testing has blind spots because they’re looking for
examples that confirm their theory&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;There’s a classic experiment called the Wason reflection
task which asks you which cards you need to turn over to see if a rule
is satisfied. People very regularly fail to turn over the cards that
they would need to determine that the rule &lt;em&gt;isn’t&lt;/em&gt; satisfied. For
example, given the rule “if a card shows an even number on one face,
then its opposite face is blue”, you need to turn over red cards and
even cards, but instead people turn over blue cards, which can provide
no information. People don’t tend to show this error in subjects with
which they’re familiar, but they do show it with subjects with which
they’re not, which is exactly the situation you find yourself in when
learning a new concept.&lt;/span&gt;, and you don’t
understand what the examples you need to show their theory is wrong are
because you don’t know what their theory is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can solve, or at least mitigate this, by giving each of your
examples a generalisation - in the case of a positive example (an
example where the concept holds), a sufficient condition that that
example satisfies that makes it an instance of the concept, and in the
case of a negative example (an example where the concept doesn’t hold) a
necessary condition it fails to satisfy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, I’ve given you a couple of examples of definitions, but
I haven’t given you examples of things that &lt;em&gt;aren’t&lt;/em&gt;
definitions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here’s an easy example of something that isn’t a definition: A cat.
You can tell it’s not a definition because it’s not a use of language,
it’s a cat. A necessary condition for being a definition is that it
involves some degree of use of language (even if it’s just to say “This
is an X” when pointing at an X).&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;“Is a cat an instance of this concept?” is a
surprisingly good starting point in general, because it forces you to
define the boundaries of what sort of thing this concept applies to.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here’s a more interesting example of something that is not a
definition:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Priests are identifiable by their consistent attire and groomed
appearance. When not occupied with their official duties, they can be
spotted around town engaged in leisurely activities. They reside in
modest accommodations among the public. Priests dedicate time to
advancing their knowledge and serving the community. They make
themselves available to offer guidance. Though often solitary, priests
derive purpose from their vocation. During infrequent breaks, they
partake in simple enjoyments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;em&gt;description,&lt;/em&gt; not a definition. It tells you what
priests &lt;em&gt;are like&lt;/em&gt;&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn9"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn9" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;At least stereotypically. Very few of these things are
universally true of priests of course.&lt;/span&gt;, not what a priest &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. This
may be useful information about priests and how to spot one, but it
doesn’t tell you anything about what makes someone a priest, or really
even how to tell if they are a priest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Using examples like this is an important part of doing ostensive
definition well: If you only pick examples that are far from the
boundary between being instances of the concept and not being instances,
you don’t help people really learn how to make the decision in the cases
where it’s difficult.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another thing that can be helpful is to provide examples where it’s
genuinely ambiguous as to whether it’s an instance of the concept, or at
least it’s not a very good instance. For example, here’s an alternative
paragraph about priests:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Priests are people who wear special clothes and live in churches.
They spend a lot of time reading old books and talking to people about
being nice. Priests tell stories to children and sometimes help people
when they are sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is this a definition? I &lt;em&gt;guess&lt;/em&gt;? It tells you just enough
about what a priest is and what they’re for that I suppose I’d count it
as a definition. But it’s not one I’d be particularly happy with
giving.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of ostensive definition is often useful to provide even if
you’re providing a more direct sort of definition, because it greatly
helps the reader understand how the definition works to have examples
and illustrations of how they fit into the definition.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="working-definitions"&gt;Working definitions&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s one small defect with this view of definitions in terms of
necessary and sufficient conditions: It’s wrong. Or, at least, it’s very
limiting - it fails to cover many definitions that exist in practice and
serve a useful functional process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A nice example of this is from Bernard Suits’s book “The
Grasshopper”, which is about philosophy of games. He offers two
definitions of a game. The first is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To play a game is to attempt to achieve a specific state of affairs
[prelusory goal], using only means permitted by rules [lusory means],
where the rules prohibit use of more efficient in favour of less
efficient means [constitutive rules], and where the rules are accepted
just because they make possible such activity [lusory attitude].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He then offers the following “portable” definition:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a voluntary attempt to overcome unnecessary obstacles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These do not define the same concept - satisfying either of them is
neither a necessary nor a sufficient condition for satisfying the
other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, suppose you’re going somewhere and you decide to take
the long way around just to add some variety. You discover there’s a
road blocked for maintenance. You could backtrack, but you’re feeling
stubborn, so you instead try to find your way around the road block.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a voluntary (you’re doing it for no other reason that you
feel like it) attempt to overcome an unnecessary (you could always
backtrack) obstacle. It’s not a game in the full sense that Suits
defines it, because it lacks constitutive rules. The thing that is
stopping you from backtracking is not that it would be a rules
violation, it’s that you’re feeling stubborn.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You could argue that there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; constitutive rules that
you’re making up on the fly, but I think that’s cheating and requires
diluting the meaning of “rules” too much.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn10"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn10" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I think a better argument would be that Suits is
putting too much emphasis on “rules” and that the things that constitute
a game may not be rules in any sort of formal sense, and any sort of
taking on a restriction to achieve an activity that is constituted by
that restriction is at least somewhat gamelike. Under this view, this
example is a game but not a “Suitsian game” to use Nguyen’s term for
it.&lt;/span&gt;
This is particularly true because I think what happens when you violate
these putative rules is different than what happens if you violate the
rules of a game.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An example from C Thi Nguyen’s account of games is mountain climbing:
There you have the prelusory goal of getting to the top of the mountain,
and a set of constitutive rules about how to do it (you have to climb
the mountain). You could achieve the goal of getting to the top of the
mountain by travelling there in a helicopter. You would still have
achieved the goal, but in violating the rules you are &lt;em&gt;not doing
mountain climbing&lt;/em&gt;. In contrast, in our detour example it’s not that
you’ve failed to do something well-defined. There’s no game of “take the
long way around” that you’re now not playing. It’s just not what you
want to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the other direction, suppose someone threatens to kill you unless
you beat them at chess. Your playing of this game of chess is in no way
voluntary, but you’re still playing a game in the full definition.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, in the strictly idealised mathematical sense of definitions as
providing necessary and sufficient conditions, these aren’t the same
definition, they’re barely even related. And yet, it sure seems like
Suits’s portable definition adds something to your understanding of the
meaning of games on top of the full definition.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of what it adds is &lt;em&gt;convenience&lt;/em&gt; - the full definition of
games is somewhat unwieldy, and introduces many other terms as part of
its definition. It’s strictly a better definition in terms of giving you
the full concept in detail and making it easier to analyse something in
terms of Suits’s conception of a game, but it’s hard to get much of an
intuitive sense of.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast “a voluntary attempt to overcome unnecessary obstacles”
is pretty intuitively comprehensible and it is easy to see its gamelike
structure.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="afterword"&gt;Afterword&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And that’s where it randomly cuts off. Chalk this one up to another
victim of “things I wish other people understood but that I don’t find
worth the effort of explaining”.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-14-09:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-15-07:13.html</id>
    <title>Things I believe about ethics and personal development</title>
    <updated>2024-01-15T07:18:28+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Things I believe about ethics and personal development&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn’t exactly an abandoned draft, in that it’s more or less
complete as it is, but it’s pulled out of an old Google doc and I wanted
it to be somewhere more permanent and visible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a core to my self-work that I struggle to articulate and
that end up mostly showing up as empty space that I write around. I’d
like to articulate these, with a particular focus on providing clear
statements of belief that are easy for others to disagree with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Many of these probably require deeper articulation, I am trying to
resist the urge to articulate them. If there is one that you’d like to
discuss, I’m happy to elaborate as much as you need.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By self-work I mean “things that are sort of like therapy”. Anything
that is designed to in some way change your experience of yourself as a
person, your emotional responses, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can, and probably should, change your nature as a person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Self-acceptance” in the sense of not constantly beating yourself up
is important and you should do that one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Self-acceptance” in the sense that you’re fine as you are and don’t
need to change is bad for you and bad for others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can get better at things that matter with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things that make you unhappy or hurt others are problems, and you
can likely fix them or work around them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very little of the things that you think of as inherent features of
yourself are actually immutable. If you want to change or compensate for
them you probably can.
&lt;ol type="i"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But it’s sometimes going to be a lot of work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And sometimes you’re better off just leaning into them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What you do matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People will evaluate you based on your actions and they are right to
do so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-work fundamentally needs to start with acting in the
world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is important to change how you think and feel, but it is more
important to change what you do and change the others in support of
that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By this I mean change &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, not later when you’re done
healing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Self-work can and should be directed towards becoming a morally
better person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without this, it is doomed to fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attempting “ethics-free” self work will likely make you a morally
worse person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the central links between self-work and ethics is your
relationship with guilt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Becoming a morally better person does not usually mean feeling
guiltier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feeling easily overwhelmed with guilt is in fact a moral
failing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never feeling guilt is also a moral failing.
&lt;ol type="i"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Either you’ve suppressed the feeling of guilt, which means you can’t
tell when you’re doing a bad thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Or you’re over-scrupulously avoiding doing anything that makes you
feel guilty, in which case you are ineffective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Conversely, ethics is fundamentally grounded in self-work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is useless to ask what you should do in the abstract, because the
most important ethical question is “How do I become the sort of person
who does that?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making yourself miserable in the pursuit of ethics probably in the
long run produces worse results than learning how to be happy being a
good person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Community building is vitally important for both self-work and
ethical development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-work is fundamentally interpersonal, because being a person is
fundamentally in relationship to others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you do not have a community supporting your self-work you will
fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are leading such a community, your self-work needs to at
least be partly directed to being the sort of person who can lead a
community, or your community will fail and it will be your fault.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moral realism is clearly fake and distracts from the actual role
of realism in ethics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ethics shape actions and actions have consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ethics shapes relationships and relationships shape people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no objective point of view for ethics. Ethics starts from
subjects and their relationships to others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A core feature of ethics is “alliance building” - I behave this way
because you agree to also behave in a complementary way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But ethics goes beyond alliance building because of the way group
norms shape people. It’s not just about building alliances but about
&lt;em&gt;becoming the sort of person with whom explicit alliances are not
needed&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moral language is in one sense just expressing a personal
preference, but these preferences are not devoid of content, they are
rooted in consequences. e.g. engineering has many ethical judgements
around competence and care that are ultimately rooted in preferences
like “It is bad when bridges fall down”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When we use moral language we are expressing something that is more
than personal but less than fully objective - “X is good (bad)” means
something like “according to the sort of people who I would consider
good, X is (un)desirable, usually based on its outcomes, but sometimes
something intrinsic about it.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ethics is fundamentally about conflict in the Schelling sense -
the best thing for me is not the best thing for you and vice versa, but
there is an outcome where we cooperate that is better for each of us
than not cooperating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contra Schelling, we change our values each time we cooperate. By
cooperating with you we build trust and love, and I value your wellbeing
more, and vice versa, and this lowers the level of conflict because a
good outcome for the other is also a good outcome for us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By repeatedly cooperating we become the sort of people who value
cooperating.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is also important to value not cooperating with people who don’t
cooperate. Altruistic punishment when someone behaves selfishly is an
important part of this sort of interaction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Judging people is good and is an important form of altruistic
punishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many people fall short of their own standards, and it is right and
proper to note that and think less well of them for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should have standards for other people that are at least as
stringent as “Does not fail by their own standards”. e.g. Someone not
treating others as well as you feel they deserve, regardless of whether
they agree with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This judgement does not require an objective morality to be useful
and important. These are judgements by &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; moral
standards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These moral standards are how you decide what sort of person to
be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These moral standards are also how you decide what sort of
relationships to have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In many ways those are the same thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Helping people is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think most people are reasonably altruistic and will feel good if
they help others, and that if this is not the case they probably have
unlearned altruism somewhere along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regardless of whether you are intrinsically altruistic, being in a
community that helps others is selfishly better than being in a
community where people don’t help each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the ways you should help others is to help them live up to
their own standards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Punishing people is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When people fall short of your ethical standards, you can and should
make them experience consequences for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By default this shouldn’t go much further than expressing
disapproval and maybe downgrading the relationship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is how you express your preferences for what sort of person to
be in community with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes this will result in breaking the relationship. This is a
failure, possibly a big one, but it is usually better than not having
attempted correction, and often better than many “successes”
(e.g. having to put a huge amount of work into fixing a relatively
unimportant relationship).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For severe ethical failures it can and should go further (call outs,
getting them fired, reporting for crimes, etc. In some cases physical
violence may be appropriate though I’m not personally a fan)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without punishment for transgression of shared norms, communities
die.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideally punishment goes hand in hand with helping - “I will hold you
to high standards and help you achieve them” but this isn’t always
possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Competence is a moral issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s no good having good intentions if you won’t put in the work to
be able to act on them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helping people learn to competently act on your shared ethics is one
of the points of communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taking responsibility is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad things happen in part because people don’t stop them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People are over-focused on &lt;em&gt;not being blamed for bad
things&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People should focus more on &lt;em&gt;not wanting bad things to
happen&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is definitely possible to take too much responsibility but most
people do not take enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This will sometimes result in you being blamed more (because you got
involved and bad things still happen) and being OK with that is one of
the reasons you need to be comfortable with guilt if you are to be more
ethical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A common failure mode of this is feeling responsible for things
going badly without actually doing anything to stop them from going
badly. This is strictly worse than not feeling responsible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thinking about things is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of people in self-work space have had a very disordered
relationship with thinking in the past and so have decided that thinking
is bad. This makes about as much sense as “I was repeatedly punching
myself in the face, so I cut off my hands to stop myself doing that”.
Just stop hitting yourself, idiot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You shouldn’t ignore your feelings when thinking about things
(you’re not doing very good thinking if you are), and you shouldn’t
think to the exclusion of action, but thinking is an essential part of
the acting/feeling/thinking cognitive triangle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Done well, thinking is fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part of why people don’t like thinking about things verbally is that
they are conflict averse. If you express your thoughts too clearly then
people can disagree with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rumination is not a central example of thinking, and is an example
of the thinking/feeling part of the triangle going wrong together. You
can often break out of rumination by doing thinking better - e.g. by
writing down your thoughts as clearly as you can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Health is heterogenous&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a sort of “perfectly spherical idealised human in a vacuum”
generic version of health that a lot of spiritual and therapeutic
practices try to push you towards. This is probably bad for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The healthy versions of two different people will often look very
different from each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is possible to have a very healthy life that is dominated by
intellectual pursuits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is possible to have a very healthy life that is dominated by
physical pursuits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is likely that the optimal healthy life for you involves more of
the generic version of health than you are naturally inclined to
(e.g. more physical activity, more intellectual activity).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Health is not mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A healthy life is often something you should be pursuing, but it may
not be achievable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often it will be achievable but you correctly choose not to
prioritise it - it’s too much work, it’s in conflict with other
important things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even if it’s achievable, it may take a long time to achieve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also the world is better with broken people in it. Many of the most
important changes in modern history have come from people who are
clearly emotionally unhealthy, and who have given their lives to some
overriding obsession and made the world a vastly better place as a
result because e.g. they invented half of the vaccines we use today, or
popularised stainless steel. Maybe any given one of their lives would be
better if they were perfectly emotionally healthy, but their lives would
be worse if the &lt;em&gt;others&lt;/em&gt; were perfectly emotionally healthy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even to the degree that you treat working towards health as
normatively desirable, nobody is there yet, and punishing people for not
being perfectly healthy already is unlikely to achieve the desired
result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Allowing for heterogeneity is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is because people are heterogenous and don’t magically become
homogenous because you don’t approve of that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many people cannot and will not conform to your ideal of how people
should be, and you need to be able to coexist with them without a state
of total war.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideally you should be able to form friendships with people who are
very different from you (although not all differences are possible, or
desirable, to form friendships across)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should certainly be able to support people who are very
different from you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Exclusive communities are important&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communities should be more homogenous than the general population.
It’s important to have communities of people who are in some sense like
you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These communities should have a degree of gate keeping to them,
where people who do not fit the target demographic of the community are,
if not outright excluded, at least expected to expend more effort
fitting in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In particular these communities establish common knowledge within
them, and it is reasonable to expect people who do not share that common
knowledge to acquire it in order to participate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communities also allow people to establish norms that would not work
in the broader world. This can include both stricter norms of good
behaviour, and also weaker norms in which behaviour that would not be
tolerated between strangers is permissible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the functions of such communities is supporting people who
struggle with the broader world. Ideally by helping them navigate it
better, but in extreme cases by sheltering them from it and providing
them an environment in which they can nevertheless contribute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Loyalty is important&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People adapt norms for low-context low-trust environments to their
private relationships, and this makes them bad people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A prior relationship with someone is in fact a reason to maintain
that relationship and treat it as valuable and give them more leeway and
benefit of the doubt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’re not prepared to do that, you cannot maintain healthy
relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This does not mean that you should take arbitrary shit from people
you are in relationship with, but it does mean that by being in that
relationship it is reasonable to expect a certain degree of
collaboration in fixing the problems with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a degree of relationship failure past which this is not
reasonable, but that degree has to be pretty severe or chronic before
you break off the relationship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because loyalty is important, treating other people’s loyalties as
important is important. Just because you would not form a relationship
with someone does not mean you should punish other people for
maintaining such a relationship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Disagreement and conflict are good and important (disclaimer:
This section is something that I am currently still sorting my shit out
on. I’m not actually good at it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="a"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the advantages of a high trust relationship is that it should
be robust enough to support disagreement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One advantage of a low importance relationship is that if the
disagreement breaks it that’s no big deal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disagreement clarifies your thinking, and thinking is good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It also is the basis for understanding and improving your shared
norms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we cannot disagree, we cannot find the places where we
agree.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disagreement is foundational in being able to orient towards good
together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h1 id="afterword"&gt;Afterword&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This feels unsatisfyingly lacking in an ending that pulls everything
together, but I think that’s part of the point of writing it - I still
haven’t figured out how to pull all of this together. I still think it’s
mostly correct and important though.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-15-07:13.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-16-13:11.html</id>
    <title>Journaling as a foundational practice</title>
    <updated>2024-01-16T13:18:15+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Journaling as a foundational practice&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-16&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is another draft bankruptcy, excerpted from another abandoned
book project. Most of the rest of the project is very sketchy but this
is one of the more fleshed out chapters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Journaling is writing about your life, ideally every day, in a way
that helps you observe key things about it, understand them, and start
to improve them. It returns you to the question of what’s going on in
your life and how you can understand it and improve it over and over
again. It helps you figure out what matters to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If there is one thing that I wish I had kept up as a practice
throughout the last five years, it’s daily journaling. Every time I’ve
done it it’s been important and transformative and then for one reason
or another I’ve just… stopped.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Editor’s note: Don’t ask how well I’m doing on this
right now please…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Continuity of journaling practice is hard, and the design of the
practice matters both for feeling like you’re getting something out of
it and for making it robust against failure.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is what I currently consider an ideal journaling practice:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Journaling is done by hand, with a fountain pen, in an A5 notebook.
For reference, &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B0B8M88JW9"&gt;I use
this one&lt;/a&gt;, and I think it’s reasonably well designed for the purpose,
but it’s nothing special. Write on some flat surface, with your arm well
supported (note: I am still figuring out ideal writing posture, and may
need to update this advice). Pages in the journal should be dated. I
usually only add a date for the first page of every day (dating every
page is also fine, I just rarely bother). I have a dedicated writing
desk from which phones and computers are banned, but this may be hard to
find space for.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You should have a foundational journaling prompt that you use every
day. The idea of the foundational prompt is that it takes you straight
into just writing without having to make decisions about what to write
about, and it creates a diverse range of different starting points to
get you to examine things from many different angles.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mine is this: I draw a tarot card from a standard Rider-Waite-Smith
deck, I consult Joan Bunning’s “Big Book of Tarot” entry for that card.
I read the description of the card out loud. I then write two pages
inspired by it. “Inspired” can be anything that feels right. Often I
pick out some characteristic from the list of characteristics that
describes some problem I’m currently having. Sometimes the card lands
with a big “ouch, too accurate” and I know exactly what to write.
Sometimes the card completely fails to land and I instead describe the
&lt;em&gt;absence&lt;/em&gt; of the card’s qualities from my life. If the card is a
court card I often talk about what it would be like to be the person
represented.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you are comfortable with Tarot (this does not require attributing
any mystical significance to it. I don’t), I recommend adopting this as
your specific practice. If you want to try it out without committing to
buying a deck and the book, you can use &lt;a href="https://randomtarotcard.com/"&gt;https://randomtarotcard.com/&lt;/a&gt; for
your card draw and look up the card in &lt;a href="http://www.learntarot.com/cards.htm"&gt;http://www.learntarot.com/cards.htm&lt;/a&gt;
(which is by the same author as the book I use, but the book often has
expanded descriptions).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you’re not comfortable with tarot, I’ll list some alternative
prompts further down.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Note: In actual fact I currently do not my foundational journaling
in my journal, I’m doing it on A4 sheets, because I started it as a
project of working through the deck one card at a time without
replacement and introduced the journal midway through and want to
complete the deck before I switch over to the journal. This section may
be updated if I discover that the switchover doesn’t work, but I have
used a tarot deck this way in the past and expect it to work fine)&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Editor’s note: This project has now been completed. See
&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/completing-completable-projects"&gt;Completing
completable projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The goal is that the foundational journaling should be done by noon.
If you notice that it is after noon, you should treat it as a matter of
some urgency to go complete it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Immediately after you have done your foundational journaling, you
will ideally write another page of journaling about anything you feel
like writing about. If literally nothing comes to mind, don’t worry
about it. This page is not a requirement of the practice, it’s just a
point at which you are invited to journal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, you should try to journal in whole pages. Keep writing
until the page is full, and then stop. As you notice you’re coming to
the end of a page, try to sum up or fine some appropriate way to drop
the mic at the end.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something else I find useful is to light a candle while journaling.
The way the candle works is that it serves as a sort of anchor: If the
candle is lit, I’m supposed to be journaling. If I notice it is lit, I
should make a decision to go back to journaling or snuff it out. As long
as I’ve completed my foundational journaling, it’s fine to choose to
stop journaling, the candle just serves as a reminder to make the
decision.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Throughout the day if at any point you feel like you need to think
something through or want to express something, go write a page in your
journal about it. The ideal is to cultivate the journal as something you
&lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to use and keep going back to. There is no such thing as
too much journaling as long as most pages you write in your journal feel
productive to have written.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="debugging-notes"&gt;Debugging Notes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a good opportunity to practise debugging.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Editor’s note: This is partly a reference to a previous
chapter on debugging in this book attempt, but I never actually wrote
that chapter. I may attempt to turn its stub into a notebook post at
some point soon.&lt;/span&gt;
Chances are, if you try to copy the above verbatim, you’ll run into some
problems. I don’t know what they are (if you do run into some problems,
please tell me! I’d like to debug them with you)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I promise that the daily journaling habit is going to be worth it, so
it’s worth spending some time figuring out why it isn’t working for you
and changing that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some variants you can try for the physical form:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can, if you must, journal on the computer. I think it’s a bad
idea, but the best system is the one you can actually follow, so if you
hate handwriting and can’t bring yourself to do it, don’t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can reduce the volume of journaling, either by writing fewer
pages, switching to a smaller journal, allowing yourself to stop at the
half page mark, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You could journal on disposable paper - write it on an A4 sheet and
then shred it if you don’t want to keep it around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experiment with different pens and journals. Do you hate fountain
pens? Do you prefer squared over lined? etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For the content you could try different foundational practices.
e.g.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick some book of special significance to you (a bible for example,
but it could also be a favourite novel) and use that as a source of
prompts. Turn to a random page, read the page out loud, and focus in on
some passage that feels salient in some way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rather than having a special book, you could have a book that you
rotate. Pick some book of your shelves, use that for a while. When you
feel like moving on after journaling, switch it out for something
else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A variation on the above is that rather than random pages you could
work through the book sequentially - read a few pages before journaling
until you find something&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The core of the foundational practice is that it needs a random
prompt to get you started, and those random prompts have to have a
reasonable amount of range, and a lot of flexibility for interpreting
them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another common way the journaling practice is likely to fail is that
you just stop doing it. Usually you forget to do it one day, and it
makes it easier to forget to do it the next, etc. The practice I
described above has a number of features designed to offset that:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has a specific centre that is easy to return to (do your
foundational journaling before noon).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It makes that centre easy to achieve (it uses a random prompt)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has the candle as an anchor to help stabilise the practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similarly it has a physical book for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But these are all predicated on the fact that it’s relatively easy
for me to find time in the morning to do it, and I have a good physical
space for it. Your problems might be different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The core thing to do though is to decide:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When are you going to do your journaling?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are you going to do when you miss that slot?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where are you going to do your journaling?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are you going to do if you’re not able to do it there? (e.g.
because traveling)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For me the answers are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideally while I drink my morning coffee, but any time before noon is
fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As soon as I can after noon I go do my journaling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At my writing desk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’ll bring my journal with me and try to do some journaling on the
right schedule, but it often won’t be my foundational practice because I
don’t have the tarot deck I’m using with me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3 id="afterword"&gt;Afterword&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This excerpt was a good reminder that I should try to journal more
reliably again. I haven’t stopped doing it, but I probably average about
once a week.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Partly this is because this daily writing project is taking up the
time slot that would otherwise be used for journalling.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-16-13:11.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-17-09:02.html</id>
    <title>Cheeseburger Ethics</title>
    <updated>2024-01-17T10:50:05+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Cheeseburger Ethics&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another draft-amnesty post extracting a usable excerpt from an
attempted book length project, though lightly edited from the version in
draft. Originally based on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1557717189159010304"&gt;a
Twitter thread of mine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An important tool of ethical reasoning I use is the &lt;em&gt;cheeseburger
threshold&lt;/em&gt;: Asking whether an act is ethically better or worse than
eating a cheeseburger.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is useful because some bad things we do are bad like murder, and
some are bad like eating cheeseburgers, and the standards we hold those
different types of act to should be very different.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is not unlike the classic distinction between a
venial and a mortal sin, but I like making the distinction this way
better, both for the examples and because I’m not that interested in
whether your action counts as turning away from god.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The key distinguish factor is that something is murder-bad if the
ethically correct amount to do of it is zero, while it is
cheeseburger-bad if some amount of it is morally permissible and
incremental reductions are morally virtuous even if they don’t - and
aren’t intended to - get you to zero.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;There are of coure strict vegetarians who would hold
that eating a cheeseburger is as bad as murder, but even most
vegetarians who believe that the correct amount of cheeseburgers to eat
is zero will generally treat it as being in a different reference class
to murder.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why cheeseburger-bad?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are clearly negative consequences to eating a cheeseburger -
the meat industry has many ethical problems, and even the most ethically
produced cheeseburger in which everyone in the pipeline was well paid,
all the animals were well treated, etc. has significant environmental
costs. Probably even if not vegetarian one should assign some ethical
significance to the life of the cows killed in making the cheeseburger
(both for the meat and for the cheese), and that too should be factored
in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But also cheeseburgers are convenient and delicious and widely
culturally accepted as permissible to eat and so, despite the harms, we
eat cheeseburgers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Possibly you’re vegetarian, or vegan, or hindu, or keep kosher. In
which case I encourage you to substitute your own similar badness act
for the cheeseburger. I like the cheeseburger example because the harms
are so clear - as much as we like to ignore them - and eating it is so
clearly culturally permitted. But you could consider, for example,
driving a car as another cheeseburger style act (environmental cost,
noise pollution, risk of injury to others, etc).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another cheeseburger-bad act might be pirating movies or TV shows.
It’s on its own a “victimless” crime if you wouldn’t otherwise have
bought the thing pirated (of course, it’s easy to convince yourself of
that. Would you really not have?). Certainly the harms of pirating a
digital good are relatively minor. And yet, in aggregate, piracy does
seem to cause a lot of harms, especially to independent authors,
publishers, and developers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I will continue to be using cheeseburgers as my example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The point is that cheeseburger-bad acts are things that we
acknowledge have harms, and that a maximally virtuous version of
yourself might choose to avoid cheeseburgers entirely. The current
version of you could, and possibly should, also choose to eat fewer
cheeseburgers, and we would acknowledge this as morally virtuous,
without requiring that you cut out on cheeseburgers entirely for it to
count.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the ethically correct amount of murder is zero. You do
not get points for saying “Yeah, I know murder is bad, I’m trying to cut
down”. Murder is bad enough that by the time “I’m trying to cut down” is
a consideration, you are already beyond the ethical pale.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although I’ve phrased it as a threshold for how bad an act is, using
this tool more a question of how (if at all) you can reform from
performing such an act.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I think this may be a sign that I’m framing this wrong
tbh. “Is it as bad as eating a cheeseburger?” is a useful framing
question, but really what I’m talking about is something more like
categories of ethical acts. Commensurability of acts is part of it but
not all of it.&lt;/span&gt; A habitual murderer doesn’t need to
cut down, they need to change their very way of being. A habitual
cheeseburger-eater just needs to cut down.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is again a subject on which many vegetarians would
differ because they would in fact regard cheeseburger-eating as
requiring a fundamental reform of your character. I suggest again
replacing this with another example.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it’s very hard for sufficiently many cheeseburger-bad acts to
add up to murder-bad. Someone who eats cheeseburgers for breakfast,
lunch, and dinner, is rude to everyone he meets, drives loud gas
guzzling cars everywhere, and generally goes out of his way to do every
pettily immoral and inconsiderate act he can think of is still not doing
something murder-bad. The correct approach here is still to cut down,
and every step along the way to doing so is morally praiseworthy.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although they may be enough of a jerk that you don’t
want to praise them. You can think of this instead as being
incrementally less morally blameworthy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, say, running a scam is murder-bad despite not being
nearly as bad as murder - you can’t think of reform from this as trying
to cut down on the scams you run, you need to become a person who does
not run scams.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why make this distinction?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The main reason is because it’s important to be able to acknowledge
that some things we do are bad without it being a big deal. Having a
class of actions which we acknowledge are bad but don’t consider
ourselves morally obliged to eliminate entirely allows us to make
incremental improvements, which has good effects. If we treated all
cheeseburger-bad things as murder-bad, this creates a very strong
incentive against recognising them as bad at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The cheeseburger example works very well here: Even from a strict
vegetarian’s point of view, it should be considered preferable for 100%
of people to cut out 90% of their meat consumption than for 50% of
people to go full vegetarian. Also, most people aren’t and are not going
to become vegetarian, and being able to view their actions as worth
reducing without having to&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being able to acknowledge the harms of our own behaviour without
being overwhelmed with guilt allows us to take a proper reflective look
at our own behaviour and, where we decide it’s worth it, improve it, and
where we decide that’s too much work, helps put it in perspective.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="afterword"&gt;Afterword&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;See also &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-15-07:13.html"&gt;Things
I believe about ethics and personal development&lt;/a&gt; and some of its
thoughts on guilt.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-17-09:02.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-18-10:00.html</id>
    <title>Something isn’t working</title>
    <updated>2024-01-18T10:24:43+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Something isn’t working&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-18&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Loosely based on a stub chapter from the same work as &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-16-13:11.html"&gt;Journaling
as a foundational practice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The core of my approach to a lot of things is embarrassingly simple:
If you’re getting outcomes you don’t like, that means something about
what you’re doing isn’t working, and you can fix that. A system is
perfectly designed to achieve the outcomes it achieves, so if you don’t
like the outcomes you have to change the system.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is in direct contrast to &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/dont-just-try-harder"&gt;doubling
down on the thing you’re doing&lt;/a&gt; because if it isn’t working then
clearly the solution is to try harder, or to get mad about the fact that
it doesn’t work and conclude it must be some failure of yours.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have a running joke that when I do coaching, a great deal of the
value I add is to listen patiently and then say “Yes, that does sound
like a problem. Have you tried solving it?”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I very rarely literally say this, but I do often say variants of
this. “What have you tried?” is a common one. Often the answer is that
they’ve not tried anything. Sometimes they have tried many things, but
they haven’t worked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“They” of course also often means “me”. Sometimes I need someone to
say “Have you tried solving the problem?” to me too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My approach to writing software isn’t that much different. I write
software. It’s software, so it has problems. I fix those problems. &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2013/03/what-the-fuck-are-we-doing/"&gt;Sometimes
I probably shouldn’t&lt;/a&gt;, but ultimately this approach has produced very
good results that would otherwise seem impossible, just by fixing the
problem in front of me repeatedly and seeing what happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fixing things that aren’t working consists of trying to understand
them, based on that understanding trying to change something that you
think will help, and learning from what happens then - either its
success or its failure.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this is a process of &lt;em&gt;debugging&lt;/em&gt;, and it feels very
much like debugging software, where you systematically narrow down what
causes a problem until it’s clear enough to fix.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Software and other &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/two-types-of-work"&gt;crunchy
work&lt;/a&gt; is very good for teaching this skill, because it provides you
with a very tight feedback loop that rewards systematically going
through everything. It’s a good type of work for learning &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-07-08:50.html"&gt;how to
be better at everything&lt;/a&gt; because of how much it rewards diligence.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is interesting contrast to my advice not to just
try harder, but I think they’re compatible. The unified advice is that
if you’re going to put in more work, don’t put it in by doing more of
the thing you’re currently doing, do it on things that you’re not doing
because they seem like too much work.&lt;/span&gt; A lot of these skills then transfer
reasonably well to other environments, as long as you’re prepared to
understand how crunchy work and squishy work differ. Nobody likes a
software developer who treats everything like a software problem, but
part of why that type is so common is that the basic attitude
&lt;em&gt;works&lt;/em&gt;. Treat things as understandable, and fixable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For me in particular I use “debugging” as a concept a lot in
emotional contexts. e.g. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-17:58.html"&gt;How I
fix anxiety triggers&lt;/a&gt; is very much a debugging process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the most important things to debug is when you get &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-give-good-advice"&gt;advice&lt;/a&gt;
from other people and it doesn’t work for you. It might be that you’re
doing it wrong, but it might also be that the advice is not well suited
for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1656631345165000704"&gt;said
before&lt;/a&gt; that the universal disclaimer of self-help books is “This
advice has a domain of applicability, and the author is not competent to
assess what it is”. i.e. This will help some people, but the author
doesn’t actually know who. This applies to all advice, really.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some (non-exhaustive) ways advice can fail to apply to you:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is some ideal middle ground, and this advice is designed for
people on the far side of that from you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This advice relies on capabilities you lack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This advice solves something that’s not your bottleneck.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But from a debugging point of view, this makes such advice actually
quite useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s a book called &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/How-Measure-Anything-Intangibles-Business/dp/1118539273"&gt;How
to measure anything&lt;/a&gt; that I am mostly&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I think that there is a target audience for whom it is
very good, and I am not that target audience.&lt;/span&gt;
indifferent to, but that had a fundamental premise that has entirely
justified the read for me: A measurement is anything that reduces
uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this sense, everything you try while debugging is a measurement.
Either it solves the problem, in which case you’ve solved the problem
and also learned something, or it doesn’t and you’ve learned something
through how it fails. Use that measurement to find out more about the
problem. Everything you try is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-26-09:43.html"&gt;a
forking path&lt;/a&gt; that tells you something about the system.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So here is my advice: Try more things, take more advice, but notice
as you do when something isn’t working, and then fix that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-18-10:00.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-20-11:18.html</id>
    <title>Shared frustrations</title>
    <updated>2024-01-20T11:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Shared frustrations&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am, it will shock you to know, annoyingly finickity about things
being done correctly. It hurts me somewhere deep in my soul when people
do things in obviously suboptimal ways.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Importantly I’m fine with people doing things less well
because it’s easier. What annoys me is when people are obviously failing
&lt;em&gt;by their own standards&lt;/em&gt;, getting worse outcomes for a worse
experience of doing the thing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I try to reign this in. I don’t actually like telling people off, so
I’ll often be silently frustrated rather than telling someone about
it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is a bad idea for anything recurring, because as a
result I sound super annoyed by minor things when I finally break and do
say something about it. I’m not saying I don’t do that, I’m just saying
I do that and I know it’s a bad idea. If you will, an obviously
suboptimal approach that is failing even by my own standards…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you two instances of this recently and something
interesting I learned from them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is this: We have an instant pot. Its pressure cooking mode
gets used for roughly two categoires of things: Making stock (usually
beef, sometimes chicken), and what you might think of as “normal
cooking” - stews, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Crucially, these take very different times. Stock takes about four
hours, normal cooking takes somewhere between 20 and 45 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Adjusting the time on an instant pot is very slow. This makes
switching between these two times irritating. Fortunately, the instant
pot has a feature for this: The pressure cooker remembers two previous
times, and you can press the pressure cook button to switch between
them. So you can have it remember a four hour time and a half hour time,
and everything is fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At least, everything is fine if people use this feature and don’t set
both timers to four hours, forcing me to do the slow adjustment process
every time I used the normal cooking mode. Very annoying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did eventually explain this feature to the others in my house, and
of course neither of them knew about this feature - it’s not like they
would have been maliciously setting the timer wrong, and it’s a pretty
non obvious feature until you know about it, and I only found out about
it relatively recently. Problem solved. But I’d been vaguely annoyed
every time I used the instant pot for the entire several month period
between discovering this feature and telling people about it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;To be clear I don’t use the instant pot &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;
often, so we’re talking about maybe 3 or 4 times at most.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More on this in a moment, but now let me tell you about another
kitchen irritation: Someone has been stacking the pots wrong. This means
that the cupboard doesn’t close properly because the pot stack is too
tall.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s a specific stacking order to the pots. If you get it right,
the pot stack is short enough for everything to work fine. If you get it
wrong, they don’t nest and it’s too tall. Someone had been placing pots
in a non-nesting order, and this was causing problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually we were in the kitchen together at the time when the pots
needed stacking, and I showed them how to do it. “Oh, that’s how you
stack them! I had no idea those nested, they look exactly the same size.
That’s been so annoying.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are two interesting things about this response:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They were in fact correct, it was slightly non-obvious. The pots are
&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; exactly the same size, but they do look pretty similar from
the outside, it’s just that one has much thinner metal than the other so
although they look similar in size the slightly smaller one nests easily
in the slightly larger one, because the interior of the slightly larger
one is much larger relative to the slightly smaller one than their
exterior would suggest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They’d been annoyed by this too, and I hadn’t shown them how to
solve their annoying problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This recontextualised some things for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That instant pot thing? Adjusting the timer to four hours from half
an hour is just as annoying as adjusting the timer from four hours to
half an hour. I shared it as a “this is a thing you do that is annoying
to me and here is how to not do it” but in actual fact it was probably a
thing we &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; were finding frustrating, and that I could easily
have shared as “Hey you know that annoying thing? I’ve figured out the
solution!”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing about being annoyingly finickity is that because I care
about doing things right, and because I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-18-10:00.html"&gt;debug
everything so reflexively&lt;/a&gt; is that “obviously suboptimal ways” is not
actually obvious to others. It’s obvious to me because I’ve &lt;em&gt;figured
it out&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes through careful problem solving and sometimes
because I accidentally pressed the button twice and noticed what
happened when I did.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I’ve done that, I can share this knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The silly thing is that I’m actually very good at sharing knowledge a
lot of the time. I have a sort of habitual attitude of teaching when
people ask me for help. e.g. a great habit of mine that you should
definitely steal is that when people can’t find a link and I find it
using search, I give them both the link and also tell them how I found
it. This is a great way of helping people be better at search, which is
a surprisingly deep and hard to learn skill.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;The downside of this habit is that it sounds a bit too
“let me google that for you” if you’re not careful. I usually &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/telegraph-your-moves"&gt;telegraph&lt;/a&gt;
why I’m doing this quite carefully, and am very explicit that it’s not a
problem if they apologise for not googling for it themselves.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I’m good at sharing information spontaneously - you’re
reading this on one of my outlets for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But volunteering information to someone specific, in response to
something that they’re doing wrong, feels different. Like I said, it
feels like telling them off, and I don’t like doing that. It feels bad
for me to do it, and I’m worried about people reacting badly to it. Most
people don’t like unsolicited advice. Not that I expect anything to go
terribly wrong from telling partners about minor things, but it might
hurt their feelings and I don’t actually like doing that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think this fear is somewhat real - a lot of the time people
don’t like being told they’re doing it wrong, and often wrong is
subjective. Sometimes &lt;em&gt;I’m&lt;/em&gt; wrong because the suboptimal way is
in fact optimising for some preference I don’t know about. I suspect
it’s exaggerated in my head, but it is a real possibility.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I think a lot of the time, the fear is largely the result of a
skill issue on my part, and I need to stop thinking in terms of “argh
you’re doing it wrong” and more “boy it looks annoying to do it that
way. Can I show you a thing?” and see how people respond.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-20-11:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
