<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-05-10T08:54:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-02-08:46.html</id>
    <title>Strategy, reliability, and impersonality</title>
    <updated>2020-05-02T11:08:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Strategy, reliability, and impersonality&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Three cards:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.learntarot.com/maj10.htm"&gt;Wheel of Fortune&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.learntarot.com/pkn.htm"&gt;Knight of Pentacles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.learntarot.com/w6.htm"&gt;Six of Wands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_construct_theory"&gt;Personal Construct Psychology&lt;/a&gt; we organise how we look at the world through a series of bipolar &lt;em&gt;constructs&lt;/em&gt;, axes around which we organise the world. For example Masculine/Feminine, Good/Evil, Strong/Weak. A construct is not necessarily a binary category (indeed usually is not) but is a line along which we can orient.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Kelly proposes we look for constructs by comparing three things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a construct is a way in which some things are alike and yet different from others. In its minimum context a construct would be a way in which two things are alike and different from a third. It should be kept in mind that the way in which the two things are like each other should be the same as the way in which they are different from the third. We do not explicitly express a whole construct if we say, ‘Mary and Alice have gentle dispositions but neither of them is as attractive as Jane.’ We would have to say something like this, if we were to express a true construct: ‘Mary and Alice are gentle; Jane is not.’ Or we might say, ‘Jane is more attractive than Mary or Alice.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;("The Psychology of Personal Constructs", Vol 1, p 79)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been finding using pairs of cards to define axes quite interesting in my previous posts, so I thought it might by a good way to look at a set of three cards, constructing a construct between each card and the pair defined by the other two.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Focusing first on The Wheel of Fortune suggests the construct Impersonal/Personal to me. The Wheel of Fortune seems to be intended to be more about destinty than chance, but as a non-believer in destiny I think destiny &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; chance, it's just the pretty face we put on it to try to pretend that it is more personal than it is. Both the Knight of Pentacles and the Six of Wands in contrast represent people, each of them striving against chance in their own ways: The Knight of Pentacles doggedly plugging away at it, persevering in the face of setbacks, while the Six of Wands rides it to success, but ultimately both are people, in contrast to the faceless nature of fortune and chance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This impersonality of random chance is one of the chief obstacles to using it in many contexts where it would be sensible to - there is no court of appeal against chance. If it was unfair, it was unfair. Them's the breaks.
Even if &lt;em&gt;statistically&lt;/em&gt; a random procedure produces much better results than a deterministic one, people find this impersonality daunting. In many ways, this is one of the big failings of atheism as a foundation for systems of human organisation (NB I am an atheist): We can no longer pretend that random chance is the will of the gods, putting a face on the faceless.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To pick a random page from &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2KRvRRh"&gt;Random Justice&lt;/a&gt; (p. 15):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the lottery has never been adopted as a general social decision-making tool, we shall see in due course that it has, in the past, bene used to resolve a fairly wide variety of matters. Yet, today, seriously to entertain the prospect of extensive social decision-making by resort to lot would probably strike most people as absurd. "To a modern educated man," Tylor remarked over a centur  ago, "drawing lots or tossing up a coin is an appeal to chance, that is, to ignorance." To argue that, in general, social goods and burdens ought to be distributed randomly is to take no account of criteria such as merit, desert, competence, and need. Why, when important decisions have to be made, should we place our trust in the luck of the draw?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This impersonality is, I think, key to this problem: We treat a person as knowledgeable, chance as ignorant. But individual &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;people's decision making should also be considered randomised&lt;/a&gt;, so the real question is not whether decision making should be personal or impersonal, but &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; personal should we make it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now focusing on the Knight of Pentacles, we get the construct Reliable/Unreliable. The Knight of Pentacles's determining feature is his doggedness - he is dedicated to a task, he stubbornly pursues it. He's not exciting, but you can rely on him doing the work. Both success and chance are somewhat out of your control - you can influence them, but you cannot rely on them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reliability makes me think of resilience, because it requires weathering adversity regardless of what comes your way.
Picking a random page from "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2VUQ4Mh"&gt;Resilience: The Science of Mastering Life's Greatest Challenges&lt;/a&gt;" (p. 183):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aerobic exercise can also help in reducing symptoms of depression. [...] Many other studies have found that exercise is substantially effective in easing symptoms of mild to moderate depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Exercise helps depression" is one of those pieces of advice that everybody knows is true and those of us who would benefit from it hates you telling them - partly because it doesn't feel internally valid, but mostly because it seems very victim blamey and doesn't suggest any way forward - if you're struggling to get out of bed you certainly don't want to go for a run, and telling you to do so will just make you feel worse about yourself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Cultivating reliability when &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; depressed (or at least less depressed) may partially be a way through that. Entraining habits and rituals that just get you to do the work come hell or highwater... may still not survive a severe depression, but may last into a deeper depression than mere motivation would.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally, focusing on the Six of Wands I think we have the construct Goal/Strategy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The wheel of fortune is in part about working with destiny and chance, both of which are key components to success. You need both care work (the knight) and fixing things (the wheel of fortune) to respond to and take advantage of circumstances, and to keep going until success happens. The Six of Wands is about what happens once you succeed, and is less concerned with how he got there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People are very bad at maintaining this construct, often to their detriment. 
I had a conversation with a friend a while ago which went roughly along the lines:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I'm really struggling to go to bed earlier."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"OK what have you tried?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I've tried going to bed earlier."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"No, that's a goal. What have you &lt;em&gt;tried&lt;/em&gt;?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Strategies here might be e.g. setting an early alarm and letting your sleep cycle catch up with you, taking a melatonin at 7pm and letting your body clock hit you when it's ready, creating an elaborate bedtime ritual. Just wanting the goal and forcing yourself into it against whatever habits and features of your life are currently causing you to struggle with going to bed is not a strategy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2VVfIAD"&gt;Thinking in Bets&lt;/a&gt;", p. 138:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On our own, we have just one viewpoint. That's our limitation as humans. But if we take a bunch of people with that limitation and put them together in a group, we get exposed to diverse opinions, can test alternative hypotheses, and move toward accuracy. It is almost impossible for us, on our own, to get the diversity of viewpoints provided by the combined manpower of a well-formed decision pod. To get a more objective view of the world, we need an environment that exposes us to alternate hypotheses and different perspectives. That doesn't apply only to the world around us: to view &lt;em&gt;ourselves&lt;/em&gt; in a more realistic way, we need other people to fill in our blind spots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Obviously I buy into this given my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-25-16:02.html"&gt;support group&lt;/a&gt;, but I think there are a couple interesting points to consider here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is that while it is definitely true that other people are incredibly helpful in this, I don't think it is true that it is almost impossible for us to get exposed to get the diversity viewpoints on our own that a good decision pod will provide (a decision pod in this case is something more or less like support group, but more focused on strategy and knowledge than personal growth and emotional health), and I think I've been demonstrating some of the techniques for that recently: You can draw on viewpoints from a &lt;em&gt;vastly&lt;/em&gt; larger number of people if you're drawing from a well curated library, you can use &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-26-12:07.html"&gt;tarot or other randomisation&lt;/a&gt; to drive your thinking in directions you can not otherwise see. You can figure out &lt;a href="https://www.rewriting-the-rules.com/self/new-year-new-zine-plural-selves/"&gt;your plural selves&lt;/a&gt; and deliberately enter into their roles.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Don't get me wrong, support group is very good, but the &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; it is very good is not necessarily the different viewpoints that we each bring each other, but the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-27-07:57.html"&gt;personal connection we have as a group&lt;/a&gt;. It's a specific feature of our support group that we are not there to argue with each other, and much of our perspective is shared and complementary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These approaches to acquiring different perspectives yourself are, in the "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Ss1rZY"&gt;Ritual and its Consequences&lt;/a&gt;" sense, rituals that let you enter a subjunctive world, where you look at the problem &lt;em&gt;as if&lt;/em&gt; you were someone else.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Random page from the bits of Ritual and its Consequences I've read so far gives us page 13:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its ability to play with boundaries - to see the dual role of boundaries as both separating and uniting - ritual action stands in opposition to modern forms of social organization, which most often tend to absolutize boundaries, either by doing away with them totally or by apotheosizing them into unquestionable and inviolable entities. We take up this issue directly in Chapter 4. There we open the discussion of how liberal modes of social organization - and of organizing the self, we might add - maintain interaction and solidarity by doing away with boundaries rather than by teaching how to negotiate them. The only boundaries maintained in such liberal visions are those predicated on instrumental distinctions, that is on the vagaries of the division of labor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm a little skeptical of the tail end of that but haven't read the chapter in question yet so will refrain from judgement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think there is something to this idea that we tend to either do away with boundaries or treat them as inviolate, and that part of this is that people tend to get stuck at various points in construct space that they've conceptualised as integral features of themselves rather than something they can fluidly navigate. We rely on other people in part because we cannot move ourselves into the way of being that they naturally access.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That's fine of course. Other people are good, and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-26-07:28.html"&gt;relationships are key to our growth as people&lt;/a&gt;, but sometimes our strategies could rely more on the impersonal than the personal, which helps avoid &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-28-06:45.html"&gt;exhausting others&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reliability is one where we often lean on others for it. Many people rely on others for care work (organisational, cleaning, emotional support). I'm very bad at it myself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is a key way in which we can move from the personal to the impersonal, by moving some of our reliability into the environment, finding ways to build physical constructs and rituals outside ourselves that help improve it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem with this of course is that it's &lt;em&gt;scary&lt;/em&gt;. We &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;alieve&lt;/a&gt; ourselves to be unreliable, and trying to strategies our way out of that seems like it's setting us up for failure.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing this post has kinda convinced me that I need to address this, so here are some things I'm going to try:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up a &lt;a href="https://howtosurvivementalillness.tumblr.com/post/162396810334/how-to-make-and-use-a-coping-board"&gt;coping board&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting couch to 5k.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beginning using &lt;a href="https://todoist.com/"&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt; again (I expect to fail on this one. I find TODO lists incredibly aversive)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-02-08:46.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-02-11:23.html</id>
    <title>Adoptive Identities</title>
    <updated>2020-05-02T18:43:03+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Adoptive Identities&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another extract from &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3fj10eH"&gt;Jonathan Strange and Mr Norrell&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stephen felt oddly disappointed, though he did not know why he should be. After all he did not wish to be king of anywhere. He was not English; he was not African. He did not belong anywhere. Vinculus's words had briefly given him the sense of belonging to something, of being part of a pattern and of having a purpose. But it had all been illusory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I often hear people use the word "liminal" to describe experiences similar to Stephen Black's, because they are at a threshold between two identities (English and African in his case), but I don't think that's quite right for him.
Stephen Black's problem is not actually that he's between two identities. It's that he has wholly embraced an identity, but it has not wholly embraced him, because a key part of that identity is regarding people like him as outsiders.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's a consistent theme throughout the book that Stephen is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; English, despite his African origins. He has fully embraced a very proper Englishness suitable for his role as a butler.
He has &lt;em&gt;adopted&lt;/em&gt; Englishness (albeit for reasons that are not entirely of his choice),.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He's also black, and is black in a very racist culture that will not allow him to succeed by its own standards. Stephen Black's problem is that he has thoroughly adopted a culture, but a key part of that culture is that he will never be judged according to his worth.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We see this elsewhere in the book:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that the cost of Stephen's clothes and boots could have bought the carrier's cart and horse twice over, the carrier assumed the cheerful superiority that white generally feels for black. He considered the matter and told Stephen that the first thing they must do was to arrange for the carcass to be removed. "She's a valuable beast - dead or alive. Your master won't be best pleased when he finds soom other fella has got t'horse and t'money."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"She was not my master's horse," said Stephen, "She was mine."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because Stephen is black, he is judged as inferior, despite the fact of his relatively obvious high status (compared to the carrier). The other aspects of his identity are judged irrelevant, to the stranger.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the book we see how Stephen is regarded by the other servants:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course in many households there is a servant who by virtue of his exceptional intelligence and abilities is given authority beyond what is customary. But in Stephen's case it was all the more extraordinary since Stephen was a negro. I say "extraordinary", for is it not generally the case that a negro servant is the least-regarded person in a household? No matter how hardworking he or she may be? No matter how clever? Yet somehow Stephen Black had found a way to thwart this universal principle. He had, it is true, certain natural advantages: a handsome face and a tall, well-made figure. It certainly did him no harm that his master was a politician who was pleased to advertise his liberal principles to the world by entrusting the management of his house and business to a black servant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other servants were a little surprised to find they were put under a black man -- a sort of person that many of them had never even seen before. Some were inclined to be indignant at first and told each other that if he dared to give them an order they would return him a very rude answer. But whatever their intentions, they discovered that when they were actually in Stephen's presence they did nothing of the sort. His grave looks, air of authority and reasonable instructions made it very natural to do whatever he told them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The butcher's boy, the baker, the lamplighter and other similar new acquaintances of the Harley-street servants showed great interest in Stephen from the first. They asked the Harley-street servants questions about Stephen's mode of life. What did he eat and drink? Who were his friends? Where did he like to go whenever he should happen to be at liberty to go anywhere? When the Harley-street servants replied that Stephen had had three boiled eggs for breakfast, the Secretary at War's Welsh valet was a great friend of his and that he had attended a servants' ball in Wapping the night before, the butcher's boy, the baker and the lamplighter were most grateful for the information. The Harley-street servants asked them why they wished to know. The butcher's boy, the baker and the lamplighter were entirely astonished. Did the Harley-street servants really not know? The Harley-street servants really did not. The butcher's boy, the baker and the lamplighter explained that a rumour had been circulating London for years to the effect that Stephen Black was not really a butler at all. Secretly he was an African prince, the heir to a vast kingdom, and it was well known that as soon as he grew tired of being a butler he would return there and marry a princess as black as himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this revelation the Harley-street servants watched Stephen out of the corners of their eyes and agreed among themselves that nothing was more likely. In fact, was not their own obedience to Stephen the best proof of it? For it was hardly likely that such independent, proud-spirited Englishmen and women would have submitted to the authority of a black man, had they not instinctively felt that respect and reverence which a commoner feels for a king!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To the degree that Stephen has succeeded (which is, remember, only the first among servants) in his adopted culture,
it was entirely in the form of an exception: He was an exceptional individual, whose presence was essentially mandated by a white man of high authority. Even then the white servants still had to construct an elaborate story as to why  he was one of the worthy ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We never see this in the books, but I think if Stephen ever &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; to go to Africa (he has never been - he was born on a slaver ship leaving there) he would find himself thoroughly rejected in an entirely different way, because he carries with him all the cultural trappings of the English. African culture would be alien to him, and they would see him, probably not entirely unfairly, as on the side of their oppressors.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think we see these sorts of adopted identities quite a lot, although usually not to quite the clear cut level of Stephen Black. Marginalised people in professional communities experience this problem - they norm to their profession, and take it on as part of their identity, but because the community is prejudiced against them they will often struggle to succeed by it, and consequently their own, standards.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another area we see is people who are part of marginalised communities without sharing that marginalisation.
Two common examples I see of this are straight people in queer communities and men in feminist communities (what counts as a feminist community is complicated - I'm using this as a shorthand for "primarily female and with a pervasive agreement that feminism is a good idea"). Generally these communities are not as hostile to such people as the dominant norms are to many marginalisations, but there's definitely still a pervasive sense of "not one of us".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't necessarily the reversal of the power dynamic it seems. Often these are people who are still themselves marginalised, often in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-23-09:37.html"&gt;illegible ways&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of reasons people do this. Ones that come to mind are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of marginalised identities overlap. You might be autistic, and hang out with a lot of autistic people, and a lot of autistic people are queer, so you implicitly hang out with a lot of queer people and the two communities just blend together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of communities have distinguishing characteristics. For example, the queer community I am loosely part of in London is minority male (not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; minority, and it's hard for me to judge exactly due to the loose sense of what the "community" is, but certainly it's culturally female), so by virtue of my queerness while also being a cis man I am a cis man in a queer feminist community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-25-10:40.html"&gt;experiences of marginalisation don't transfer that well&lt;/a&gt;, one that is shared of that of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-01-16:42.html"&gt;not being like the others&lt;/a&gt;, so if you don't have a community for your own marginalisation you're probably still going to be better off in another marginalised community than you are trying to fit into the mainstream.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People make friends through their friends, and marginalised people are often friends with people of similar marginalisations, so if you make friends with one you might make friends with many. e.g. I was part of poly communities long before I was poly. ("Are poly people marginalised?" you might ask. To which I answer "Lets not have that argument right now". Either way it demonstrates how the process work).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the consequences of being part of a marginalised community is that you tend to start to adopt their assumptions and norms about the world. I've tended to use "culturally X" as the term for this in the past.
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-27-07:57.html"&gt;We tell each other stories&lt;/a&gt; and those stories reshape and become part of how we view the world. I was "culturally poly" long before I was ever actually poly, just by virtue of how many people around me were and how much I had started to take on their worldview.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This leads to a problem where you are now culturally out of synch with everyone. In your community of choice, you are not one of them. In the mainstream community, you will feel out of place due to their differing cultural norms, and you will often be &lt;em&gt;seen&lt;/em&gt; as out of place due to &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; differing cultural norms.
It's not really just a question of whether you are culturally with them, they are &lt;em&gt;your people&lt;/em&gt;, you just lack the characteristic that unifies them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This often leads to people having big arguments about how expansive an identity label should be. I think &lt;a href="https://sexgeek.wordpress.com/2019/06/19/whos-queer-whose-queer-on-claims-identities-and-kink-among-other-things-at-pride-part-1/"&gt;the argument for making queer pretty expansive when it comes to self-identification&lt;/a&gt; is quite good, but even so you ar egoing to get people who are unambigously not queer (cis and straight but also monogamous, not kinky, etc), but all of their friends are queer, they are culturally queer, often they're even &lt;em&gt;aesthetically&lt;/em&gt; queer just because of how aesthetics tend to propagate in communities.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, one reason why it's a problem is that being a part of a community where you're not one of them is intrinsically precarious. There is very much a sense that you are there only on sufferance, only as long as people can be convinced that you are one of the good ones. In a dispute, you will likely be seen as in the wrong, and if you are in the wrong people are more likely to turn against you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is this actually likely in practice? I don't know. It's certainly not entirely false (I've seen this play out at individual levels, but not at community levels), and regardless of its truth it &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; that way to the people involved and the way people typically talk about the outgroup sure makes it sound true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel like I shouldn't really need to spell this out, but feeling constantly under threat of losing all your friends is &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Stepping back, an article I really like is "&lt;a href="https://conscienceandconsciousness.com/2018/07/11/transwomen-and-adoptive-parents-an-analogy/"&gt;Transwomen and Adoptive Parents: An Analogy&lt;/a&gt;". The argument is that in many cases "trans women" is to "woman" as "adoptive parent" is to "parent": Yes, the underlying biology does not match what we think of as typical for that role, but as a society we generally regard adoptive parents as obviously parents except for where there's a specific concrete reason for us not to (e.g. needing to know about medical history).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a similar way, I think we might want to start taking adoptive identities more seriously in some cases. I think there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a case to consider some people adoptive queers. It requires careful handling - it's not a thing to impose on someone, and it's not a thing that people should adopt for themselves without checking in with at least a couple of others (you'll never get consensus of course - there is no queer council who can make official rulings that you know about).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Whether this makes sense for other identities, I don't know. Some, it probably does (for example "neurodivergent" seems to make sense as a pretty expansive identity), some it almost certainly doesn't (I doubt "adoptive black" would ever be an acceptable identity for a white person to take on, and "adoptive disabled person" is probably almost as problematic, although disabled is by its nature a more expansive identity).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In all honesty, I don't necessarily know how any of this should, could, or would play out in practice, but this is the place for half-formed thoughts after all. Mostly I just want people to have communities in which they can be safe, and I want us to take the fluidity of identity more seriously, and this seems to be an important area where those two concerns overlap.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-02-11:23.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-03-09:09.html</id>
    <title>Numbers and Feelings</title>
    <updated>2020-05-03T14:43:13+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Numbers and Feelings&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Please note: This post is much more for me than these posts normally are. It's very stream of consciousness. You might find it interesting anyway, but I can't promise it will make sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Basically, I tried to do some maths, and I ended up mostly processing a bunch of feelings instead.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do you remember being able to concentrate for a sustained period on some work?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Neither do I, really, but I'm aware it must have happened at some point. A lot of my school reports are the usual smart kid thing to the tune of "David clearly understands the material but I wish he would do the work".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There were a few points in my life where I actually did the work, but most of the rest of the time the work was pretty invisible to me too. I clearly understood the material, but I'm not sure when I did that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On the other hand I also spent an entire summer during my A-levels studying a mathematics textbook that would have been a bit advanced a few years into university.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Imagine doing that. It's a struggle for me too. People think I read a lot, and I do, but it's not exactly uninterrupted, and reading a maths textbook is &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But why can't I do it? It feels like &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-20-10:33.html"&gt;being blocked&lt;/a&gt;. The capability is clearly there, you just need to do the work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is probably a feelings problem, isn't it? So today, it's time to do some maths and have some feelings about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to work through some of the exercises in "A Short Course on Banach Space Theory" by Carothers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why this book?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, it's small, cute, and based on material that I always would have found a bit hard but was once upon a time relevant to my interests.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also utterly useless. Why would you spend time on this material? I'm sure there's &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; application somewhere, but if so it's probably to things I also don't care about. I'm doing this for the pure joy of doing mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is there joy in mathematics? I feel like there used to be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let's do this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Page 1:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is a list of the &lt;em&gt;classical&lt;/em&gt; Banach  spaces. Roughly translated, this means the spaces known to Banach. Once we have these examples out in the open, we'll have plenty of time to fill in any unexplained terminology. For now, just let the words wash over you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do like Carothers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The opening chapter has a lot of "It's easy to see" and "Clearly" and "It follows". I think I'm supposed to be annoyed about those for politics reasons, but fuck it. You're not going to be reading this book unless you have a library card for &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-16-14:22.html"&gt;the ghost library&lt;/a&gt;. Why would you?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The funny thing is that it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; easy to see. It's been 15 years more or less since I finished my maths degree. I've done a little bit of maths in the meantime, but not much, and not particularly advanced. But this is just like riding a bike.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, enough feelings, lets do some mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't plan to do all the exercises, just the ones that spark joy. Here's chapter 1, exercise 14:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let \(H\) be a separable Hilbert space with orthonormal basis \((e_n)\) and let \(K\) be a compact subset of H. Given \(\epsilon &amp;gt; 0\), show there exists an \(N\) such that \(||\sum\limits_{n = N}^\infty \langle x, e_n \rangle e_n&amp;gt;|| &amp;lt; \epsilon\) for every \(x \in K\).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I stared at it for a little bit then went to have a shower. In the shower the answer was obvious:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let \(y_1, \ldots, y_n\) be an \(\frac{\epsilon}{2}\)-net for \(K\). Then for each \(i\) there exists \(N_i\) such that \(||\sum\limits_{n \geq N_i} \langle y_i, e_n \rangle e_n|| &amp;lt; \frac{\epsilon}{2}\) because these are just the tail sums for \(||y||^2 = \sum \langle y, e_n \rangle^2\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let \(N = \max N_i\). Then for \(x \in K\) we have some \(y_i\) with \(||x - y_i|| &amp;lt; \frac{\epsilon}{2}\) because the \(y_i\) are an \(\frac{\epsilon}{2}\) net.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now
[\begin{align*}
||\sum\limits_{n \geq N} \langle x, e_n \rangle e_n|| &amp;amp; = ||\sum\limits_{n \geq N} \langle y_i, e_n \rangle e_n + \sum\limits_{n \geq N} \langle x - y_i, e_n \rangle e_n|| \\
&amp;amp; \leq ||\sum\limits_{n \geq N} \langle y_i, e_n \rangle e_n|| + ||\sum\limits_{n \geq N} \langle x - y_i, e_n \rangle e_n|| \\
&amp;amp; &amp;lt; \frac{\epsilon}{2} +  \frac{\epsilon}{2} \\
&amp;amp; = \epsilon \\
\end{align*}&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;as desired.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;QED etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That was pretty easy. I wasn't exactly &lt;em&gt;surprised&lt;/em&gt; that it was easy, but I'm pretty sure I'm "supposed" to have forgotten that material.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How was the proof obvious to me? Well, "compact" means "small" basically, so I needed to use that smallness somehow. The construction of an \(\epsilon\)-net is the obvious way to use that smallness for something like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What makes it obvious? I don't know. Mostly that it tends to work I guess. It's &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-12-11:35.html"&gt;intuition&lt;/a&gt;. Once you think to try the approach it's relatively easy to see how it must work. I'm not sure what caused me to try the approach, my brain just said "Hey maybe an \(\epsilon\)-net?" and I checked it out and it seemed to work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is this result interesting? I don't know. I don't find I care about the result intrinsically. Maybe it will be useful later?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn't need to be useful though. Joy of mathematics, remember? I'm doing this to see whether I can, not because I care about this. Part of why I picked this book up is that I have no conceivable use for the material. There will be no obligation to carry on after.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I find I still don't &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;alieve&lt;/a&gt; I can concentrate on doing mathematics all day, but I'm prepared to try to suspend that alief for a while and see where the day takes me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's try another exercise. Exercise 2.1:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given a nonzero vector \(x\) in a normed space \(X\), show that there exists a norm one functional \(f \in X^*\) satisfying \(|f(x)| = ||x||\). On the othe rhand, give an example of a normed space \(X\) and a norm one linear functional \(f \in X^*\) such that \(|f(x)| &amp;lt; ||x||\) for every \(0 \neq x \in X\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just noticed that I was sitting at an extremely odd angle writing this, twisting my spine around. That can't be good for me. I should really use this to practice some Alexander Technique and pay more attention to unlearning those habits, but too much to try at once in think. For now I'll just notice and practice some basic posture unfucking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the exercise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first bit is just Hahn-Banach. Take the one-dimensional space spanned by \(x\) and define \(f(x) = ||x||\) there. This is a norm one functional and by Hahn-Banach you can extend it to a norm-one functional on the whole space.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This feels too easy. Does he want me to prove Hahn-Banach? I doubt it. But the proof is just blah blah blah Zorn's lemma blah.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the second bit was more interesting and took a bit more thought. The answer is to take \(l^1\) and to define \(f(x) = \sum (1 - \frac{1}{n}) x_n\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This satisfies the requirements because \(|f(x)| = |\sum (1 - \frac{1}{n}) x_n| \leq \sum |(1 - \frac{1}{n}) x_n| =  \sum |(1 - \frac{1}{n})| |x_n| \leq \sum |x_n| = ||x||\) with the last inequality being an equality only when \(x = 0\). This gives us that \(||f|| \leq 1\) and that \(|f(x)| &amp;lt; ||x||\) for \(x \neq 0\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Odd twist to my posture again).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To see that this has norm exactly one, note that \(f(e_n) = 1 - \frac{1}{n} \to 1\) as \(n \to \infty\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How did I spot this example?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well it was kinda obvious. You can't have such a space be finite dimensional (compactness of unit ball etc) so you need to make it so that the norm is closer and closer to \(1\) each time you extend it. Basically all this is doing is extending the functional for each unit vector one at a time, bringing it closer and closer to norm \(1\) with each step.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That's a bit of a retcon though. The intuition was there but I spent a while futzing around trying to make this work with variants on \(l^\infty\) where it doesn't work for a variety of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I find myself wondering why I'm doing this. What's the point?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I found I wanted to describe this feeling as wanting to check Twitter. I don't think that's accurate. It's more a feeling of... restlessness? A desire to get up and pace?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a definite sense that &lt;em&gt;I am not the sort of person who can do this&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Very well. I shall get up and pace. But I'll read chapter 2 while doing it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;OK, I've read chapter 2 now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If it seems odd that I was reading chapter 2 after doing the exercises, bear in mind that a) I've read the first couple chapters of this book before. It has been sitting on my shelves for well over a decade now after all and b) This is mostly recap stuff.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While reading this chapter I was definitely going "Blah blah blah proofs" for a lot of this. That will probably bite me later, but I think it's normal. Mathematicians mostly don't &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; proofs, we like nice, tidy theorems (unless we're into combinatorics in which case we like ugly technical theorems).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do notice that I still tend to think of myself as a mathematician despite it being objectively not true. I have a masters in mathematics, but I've never been a professional mathematician. Still, it's had a significant amount of influence on my thinking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wonder if that identification is part of the emotional noise around doing mathematics? If I'm over-identified with being a mathematician, realising that I'm not actually very good at it would be emotionally painful. Attempting to get better at mathematics is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;unsafe&lt;/a&gt; as a result, so it's no wonder that I tend to stall when I learn new things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn't help that most of the mathematics I've tried to learn in the intervening period has been stuff that at university I would have turned my nose up at. Combinatorics, statistics, graph theory. It's all stuff that is objectively very &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; but isn't something I find intrinsically interesting. There's no &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; there to drive the growth.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is stupid though. Statistics, for example, is just quantitative epistemology. I &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; epistemology. Maybe I'm doing it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, for now, that doesn't matter. I'm focused on something that I would have liked at university. Joy of mathematics, don't you know.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not that I'm feeling much joy right now. It's not &lt;em&gt;unpleasant&lt;/em&gt; though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's do another exercise. 2.6: Prove Riesz's lemma: Given a closed subspace \(Y\) of a normed space \(X\) and an \(\epsilon &amp;gt; 0\), there is a norm one vector \(x \in X\) such that \(||x - y|| &amp;gt; 1 - \epsilon\) for all \(y \in Y\). If \(X\) is infinite dimensional, use Riesz's lemma to construct a sequence of norm one vectors (x_n \in X) satisfying \(||x_n - x_m \geq \frac{1}{2}\) for all \(m \neq n\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;NB. there's a stupid error in the question, in that obviously \(Y\) has to be a &lt;em&gt;proper&lt;/em&gt; subspace for this to work otherwise \(X = Y\) is a counter-example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;OK, prove the first bit...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So we're all about the functionals right now, right? Suppose we had some norm one linear functional \(f\) such that \(f(y) = 0\) for \(y \in Y\). This would give us what we want, because we can find some \(x\) with \(||x|| = 1\) and \(f(x) &amp;gt; 1 - \epsilon\). Then for \(y \in Y\) we have \(f(x - y) = f(x) &amp;gt; 1 - \epsilon\). But \(|f(x - y)| \leq ||x - y||\), because \(f\) is norm one, so \(||x - y|| \geq |f(x - y)| &amp;gt; 1 - \epsilon\) as desired.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Can we construct such a functional?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to say that it's obvious that we can as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Actual desire to check Twitter just then. Apparently my brain wants to glitch out and stop me working on this)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can construct the quotient space \(Q = X / Y\), and there is a linear functional \(g\) of norm one on this space, which taking \(f = g \cdot q\) where \(q: X \to Q\) is the quotient map, gives us a linear functional of norm one on the original space.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not obvious to me that this has norm one though? It certainly has norm at most one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also prove the following result by more blah blah Zorn nonsense: Let \(X\) be a vector space, \(Y \subseteq X\) a proper subspace and \(x \in Y \setminus X\), do the usual Hahn-Banach extension shenanigans to get a functional on \(&amp;lt;\{x\} \cup Y&amp;gt;\) by adding in elements of \(y\) not in the span of what's already covered and setting them to \(0\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is more or less assuming what I'm trying to prove though. It's maybe simpler than this?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things I'm worrying about is that \(\epsilon\). Presumably we can't set \(\epsilon = 0\), so maybe there's some reason we can't expect to extend this with \(f(x) = 1\)?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently being reminded of Andrew Wiles on &lt;a href="https://mathwithbaddrawings.com/2017/09/20/the-state-of-being-stuck/"&gt;being stuck&lt;/a&gt;. This is, I think, another example of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-14-13:56.html"&gt;discomfort tolerance&lt;/a&gt; being very important for good epistemics, although I think the discomfort is net harmful here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I'd &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; is to cultivate some open curiousity and just sit with the problem. I'm feeling restless though. I'm going to read up on the proof of the Hahn-Banach theorem from Rudin's "Real and Complex Analysis" and see how I get on with that, then probably go do some staff spinning in the garden for a bit. I've been doing this for over an hour now, so it's probably time to take a quick break.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Weird posture again. Found I was twisted around and also sitting on one my legs)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I went to the bathroom instead and had some more thoughts, so writing these down before I go outside:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I found myself wondering... I've been quite blocked on PhD work recently. If I can just sit down and grind through it like this, can I deploy the same skill at my PhD? I should be able to, and I &lt;em&gt;do not like&lt;/em&gt; that thought. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-15-06:31.html"&gt;Capabilities can be coerced&lt;/a&gt; and self-coercion is a thing. If I can do it, then I should do it, and if I should do it, then I am bad for not doing it. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:35.html"&gt;This isn't true&lt;/a&gt; but it feels true. This almost put the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-20-10:52.html"&gt;brakes&lt;/a&gt; on the whole thing but I'm going to try to stay with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This whole thing feels &lt;em&gt;annoying&lt;/em&gt;. There are &lt;em&gt;details&lt;/em&gt; and I don't &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; details. The details are &lt;em&gt;stupid&lt;/em&gt;. Being annoyed makes me want to say "Fuck it, this is pointless, don't want to deal with it".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thought just now: Of course it's pointless. It was deliberately chosen to be pointless. Why am I doing this again?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feels like I have an ulterior motive that I'm not admitting to myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's difficult to distinguish between "can't do this" and "don't want to do this", especially when the latter is liable to cause my brain to glitch out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well I'm back from staff spinning now. That was interesting. The movements were energetic, violent, in a way that they usually aren't. I knew I was annoyed, but am I... angry? Does mathematics make me angry?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It would make sense if it did maybe. Anger is very focusing. Certainly some of my more productive coding sessions have been because I got angry about something and decided to just defeat it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In many ways, focus is the &lt;em&gt;point&lt;/em&gt; of anger. It lets you exclude everything but the problem in front of you, and raises the energy level you have to bring to bear on the problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not good at anger. Or rather, perhaps, the problem is that I am &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good at anger, and that feels unsafe. You've seen me cranky, but believe me that's not the same thing. Very few people reading this will ever have seen me in a proper rage.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of that is that I had a very angry childhood. I did not get on well with other children.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this was that I was a strange, poorly socialised, child who was quite hard to relate to. I hadn't really figured out how to human, and the people around me hadn't really figured out how to teach me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this was systemic failures of the school system.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A substantial part of this was that a significant number of kids around me were vicious little thugs and the teachers who were supposed to be responsible for protecting the children were culpable in a vast institutional betrayal of those in their care and they all deserve to die in a fire.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Huh, yes. Apparently I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; angry. I don't actually think they deserve to die in a fire. I understand adolescent development, I understand incentives, I mostly do not think the people involved were intrinsically bad people so much as part of a broken system. But normally I'm quite surprised at how inaccessible anger about the whole thing feels. I don't feel like I'm &lt;em&gt;allowed&lt;/em&gt; to be angry, because of empathy and understanding of systemic problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I saw a therapist briefly last year. She wasn't very useful, but she did get the ball rolling. We had a conversation at one point about how bad my school experience was and she said that I must be very angry about it. "Oh sure but blah blah systemic issues" I lightly answered. I thought I was telling the truth, but maybe I was lying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, enough about childhood trauma, lets focus on important things like irrelevant pure mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;...right after writing that the song that came on Spotify rotation was VNV Nation's "Illusion".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Opening lyrics:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know it's hard to tell how mixed up you feel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hoping what you need is behind every door&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each time you get hurt, I don't want you to change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because everyone has hopes, you're human after all&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feeling sometimes, wishing you were someone else&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling as though you never belong&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feeling is not sadness, this feeling is not joy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I truly understand. Please, don't cry now&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reader, I did not obey their request, and had to retreat to my room to have a little cry.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Accidentally &lt;a href="https://nibrasi.co.uk/the-lost-art-of-crying"&gt;NEDERAing&lt;/a&gt; myself with a textbook on some Banach space theory is some serious &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-24-10:37.html"&gt;everything is connected&lt;/a&gt; bullshit right there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's almost like there's some unprocessed emotions associated with the thing that I spent four years of my life on, the last one burning me out right to the edge of quitting before giving me a decidedly mediocre grade on something that I had connected a significant chunk of my identity to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No, seems fake. Lets do some maths.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The traditional approach on an exam when you're stuck is to go do some other questions, so lets try another one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First though, I have retrated to my room. I like my flatmates very much, but we do not have the sort of relationship where I particularly want to be crying in front of them, and apparently that's what's on the cards today.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course this presents its own problem, which is that I don't &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; spending time in my room. I don't entirely know why. I've been vaguely intending to do Focusing on the problem by spending a bunch of time in my room and seeing how it feels, and by "vaguely intending" I mean "I have absolutely no intention of doing this because it sounds &lt;em&gt;awful&lt;/em&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the drivers of this is that I'm very bad at maintaining my personal space. I've bought a copy of &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2yeCQ4i"&gt;Unfuck Your Habitat&lt;/a&gt; to try to offset that, but it hasn't arrived yet. Currently my habitat... well it's not &lt;em&gt;unhygienic&lt;/em&gt; or anything but it's cluttered as fuck and I really should do something about that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For now though I'm going to do some vacuuming. My new coping board tells me I should do that on the weekends.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Procrastinating? I'm sure I don't know what you mean. Next you'll be telling me that my sudden desire to rearrange all my furniture is procrastination.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have successfully resisted the urge to rearrange all my furniture. Time for some mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;2.7: Given linear functionals \(f\) and \((g_i)_{i = 1}^n\) on a vector space, prove that \(\text{ker} f \supseteq \bigcap\limits_{i = 1}^n \text{ker} g_i\) if and only if \(f = \sum a_i g_i\) for some \(a_i \in \mathbb{R}\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The if is easy: If \(x \in  \bigcap\limits_{i = 1}^n \text{ker} g_i\) then \(f(x) = \sum a_i g_i(x) = \sum a_i 0 = 0\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The only if...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I stared at a problem for a bit and did some work on it and then took a twenty minute WhatsApp break to chat to people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the problems with this is that the analysis bit I'm good at, the linear algebra, not so much.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose without loss of generality that the \(g_i\) are linearly independent. Then we can find \(x_i\) with \(g_i(x_i) = 1\) and and \(g_i(x_j) = 0\) for \(i \neq j\) basically by... the thing you do to to construct an orthogonal vector? &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gram%E2%80%93Schmidt_process"&gt;Gram-Schmidt elimination&lt;/a&gt;, right. You do it progressively, starting with any \(y\) such that \(g(y) = 1\) and \(y \not\in &amp;lt;\{x_j : j &amp;lt; i\}&amp;gt;\). Then you set \(x_i = y - \sum\limits_{j &amp;lt; i} g_i(x_j) x_j\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does this work? I don't think this works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ugh, the annoying thing I'm finding is that I've still got the right conceptual framework, but I'm no longer any good at the detail work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This might be a retcon though. I'm not sure I was &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; good at the detail work. I've always leaned very heavily on conceptual framework stuff.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lets go back to my first thought, which is that there's a dimensionality trick here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Feelings interrupt: Persistent internal exchange to the tune of "Ugh this is awful. I'm being &lt;em&gt;forced to do things I'm bad at&lt;/em&gt;." "Are you being forced? You can stop if you want. Do you want to stop?" "...no" "Well then lets keep going until you do.". Discomfort tolerance is hard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, dimension trick.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For finite dimensional \(V\) we have \(\text{dim}(V) = \text{dim}(V*)\). So if \(f \not\in \text{span}(g_i)\) then we must be able to find \(x_1, \ldots, x_n\) such that the restriction of the \(g_i\) to \(X = &amp;lt;\{x_i\}&amp;gt;\) are linearly independent. Necessarily \(f|_X \in &lt;g_i|_x\&gt;\), say \(f|_X = \sum a_i g_i|_X\). Let \(f' = \sum a_i g_i\). &lt;/g_i|_x\&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If \(f' = f\) then we're done. Otherwise there is some \(y\) such that \(f'(y) \neq f(y)\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to go have some lunch.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm back from lunch. I had stew. It was nice. I also now have a pot of genmaicha tea, and have taken some ibuprofen and theanine to go with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The caffeine/theanine/ibuprofen stack is a fairly productive one for me, but I do suspect part of that is &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/m_ashcroft/status/1246749019201732610"&gt;the suppression of feelings&lt;/a&gt; oh well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Over lunch I was thinking about three things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissociation, and how many behaviours are about avoiding feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anger, and the way we treat male anger as intrinsically dangerous and how much disservice this does to men.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linear algebra.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lets focus on the important one: Linear algebra.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had seemingly forgotten the obvious fact that a linear functional consists of a decomposition of a vector space \(V = &lt;x&gt; \oplus \text{ker}(f)\). I'm not sure if this helps here.&lt;/x&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I thought I might have a go at some of the chapter 1 exercises, see if I fare any better there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First, an easy one. 2.5, show that \(l^\infty\) is not separable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ugh, I've just realised that a lot of the mathematics in this post is invalid LaTeX. I've also remembered how much I fucking hate LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an area where the "optimised" workflow of my notebook is seriously lacking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, maths.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is easy. For any \(A \neq B \subseteq \mathbb{N}\), we have \(||1_A - 1_B||_\infty = 1\), so \(\{B(1_A, \frac{1}{2}): A \subseteq \mathbb{N}\) is an uncountable set of non-empty open sets. A dense set intersects every open set, so no dense set can be countable because it must contain at least one element of each of these.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is kinda what I meant earlier about being better at the conceptual work than the details. Things that are easily solvable with an intuitive leap are fine (although I might have remembered this one, I'm not sure), but things where there are multiple steps involved to figure out the conclusion are hard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm now trying 1.7: Let \(1 &amp;lt; p &amp;lt; \infty\) and let \(\frac{1}{p} + \frac{1}{q} = 1\). Show that for positive real numbers \(a and b\) we have \(ab \leq \frac{a^p}{p} + \frac{b^q}{q}\) with equality if and only if \(a = b\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm a little suspicious of that "equality if" part but lets see how this goes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First, lets check \(a = b\). Then the right hand side is \(\frac{a^p}{p} + \frac{a^q}{q}\). Sanity check, when \(p = q = 2\) this gives us \(a^2 = a^2\) as desired.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel like the claim that the two sides are equal if \(a = b\) just has to be bullshit in general though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Pick, say, \(p = 3\). Then \(q = \frac{3}{2}\). Then the claim that the two sides are equal is the claim that \(a^2 = \frac{1}{3} a^3 + \frac{2}{3} a^{\frac{3}{2}}\), which is just obvious nonsense (e.g. check a = 2). So I'm going to assume the "if" part is a mistake (a lot of the exercises in this book seem to be wrong).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let \(f(a) = \frac{a^p}{p} + \frac{a^q}{q}\). Then \(f'(a) = a^{p - 1} + a^{q - 1}\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd like to see how this scales. Without loss of generality, assume \(a \leq b\). Write \(b = x\) with \(x \geq 1\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This inequality now becomes \(a^2 x \leq \frac{a^p}{p} + \frac{a^q}{q} x^q\)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a joke that mathematicians are machines for turning coffee into theorems. If, as previously observed, it is helpful to be angry when doing mathematics, and coffee makes you irritable (it certainly seems to), is that the mechanism?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this point I moved to paper and the results were a mess, so I'm not going to bother to transcribe them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think, at this point, I have to admit that my skill in working with mathematics is severely degraded. This shouldn't be surprising, but somehow it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think because I've retained a lot of the conceptual machinery of mathematics, I've assumed I could still do this sort of thing reasonably well, when in fact a lot of what matters is the detailed fine grained machinery of doing the work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Equally, I'm not sure this was ever &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt; for me, so maybe I'm inferring more loss than was there. This is very focused on the nitty gritty algebraic manipulation bits which, frankly, I've always been crap at.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this point I did the standard thing I do when I get stuck in a puzzle game: Give up and look at a walkthrough.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is apparently called Young's inequality (I remembered it was a standard one, but not what it was called), and according to Wikipedia is an easy consequence of the concavity of the logarithm. I can kinda see how that works and I could probably work through the details, but I think this requires me to have a refresher course.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I looked at &lt;a href="https://www.math.upenn.edu/~brweber/Courses/2011/Math361/Notes/YMandH.pdf"&gt;these notes&lt;/a&gt; and they instead use the convexity of the exponential, which I think is a little nicer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway I see the details of this but also find I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don't want to work through them. The idea feels... disgusting? Beneath me?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think it is. I think it would in fact be very good for me to work through the details. But I &lt;em&gt;really don't want to do it&lt;/em&gt;, and I think I will respect that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to go outside for a bit and do some more staff spinning.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The earlier anger has passed. Instead I'm left with a kind of... despair? Despair isn't right. It feels &lt;em&gt;pointless&lt;/em&gt;, and it is. I deliberately picked it because it was a bit pointless. But I'm not actually struggling with any of those parts. I'm struggling with some really basic shit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This all, I think, ties in with a bunch of basic blocks I have around maintenance and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-30-15:20.html"&gt;care work&lt;/a&gt;. There's a kind of... what's the point of doing this when I'm just going to hve to do it again in future? I spent four years getting good at this sort of thing, but because I haven't maintained it, I've lost crucial skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could probabbly claim some of them back, but doing so feels... futile? Like I'd just lose them again, and then I'd have wasted more time of the finite time left before I eventually die.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bleak. The word for this mood is &lt;em&gt;bleak&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do feel like I would benefit from getting back into mathematics, but I don't think retreading old steps will get me there. I think it will just increase the level of negative pushback I'm getting from my emotions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the feeling that I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; do this is part of the problem. There's a huge internal response of "Shan't. It's pointless".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think picking something that I &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; to find interesting was a mistake. I have an ongoing problem where I find something niche interesting, lose interest in it, and then feel like I've wasted my time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given that that's how I'm starting to feel about my PhD I think that was a particularly big mistake here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; want to find my way back into being able to do the detail work of mathematics, I think perhaps the way in is through statistics. It requires careful going - there are a number of problems with getting myself interested in statistics, but it's the most immediately useful to me and it ties in to a bunch of things I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; still care about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it would be dangerous to try to push through this mood, so I'm going to call this post to a close soon, but let's try to end on a high note by seeing if my new book reading techniques work well for some things in this space.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's a random page from &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2z3KLBu"&gt;Reliable Reasoning&lt;/a&gt;, page 49:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Half of this result is that, if the classification rules in C do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have a finite VC dimension, then no matter how mnay data points are provided, there will be probability distributions for which enumerative induction will not select only rules with expected error close to the minimum for rules in C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hmm. I think I get what this is getting at, but it's been long enough since I've read this book that I'm honestly not sure, I'm going to just reread the book up to that point (not normally viable with a textbook, I'll grant!) and see where we are here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nope, I think I'm done, the ugh field has got too strong for today.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To end on a high note, I think I've learned a couple of important things today:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I actually &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; manage much more focused work on something like this than I thought I could. Admittedly I mostly ended up processing feelings around the work than doing the work, but I think that in and of itself is quite productive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's an interesting link to anger with that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stream of consciousness writing while I attempt work is actually quite productive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I should reread "Reliable Reasoning" as a possible next steps into regaining some skills I've lost.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's probably a very strong set of emotional ughs tied together around this, and I suspect sorting some of the other ones out might make a lot of this more accessible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I &lt;em&gt;haven't&lt;/em&gt; learned much about is Banach space theory, but oh well. It wasn't likely to be very useful anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-03-09:09.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-04-06:21.html</id>
    <title>Model Monocropping</title>
    <updated>2020-05-04T11:59:58+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Model Monocropping&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What is a model?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a good passage about models in the beginning of Cailin O'Connor's "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3c3Ap2Z"&gt;The Origins of Unfairness&lt;/a&gt;":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the book addresses many related phenomena these discussions necessarily vary in levels of carefulness. Some of the models presented are tied to the relevant phenomena quite tightly. Others are suggestive of the phenomena, but the details are not filled in as meticulously. This means that the explanatory role of the models will differ from case to case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, the models discussed can be thoguht of as providing "how-possibly" information. If something can evolve in an evolutionary model under basic conditions, we come to believe that these conditions are enough to possibly support the evolution of that behavior in the real world. In other cases, I take the models to have deeper explanatory power, giving us insight into how some patterns of behavior may have &lt;em&gt;potentially&lt;/em&gt; emerged. The difference here is not in the models but in the epistemic role they play. In the "how-potentially" cases, the models are intended to increase our confidence in the potential of a process to really have occurred. In particular, many of the examples of how-potentially modelling in the book will involve what Weisberg describes as minimalist  idealization, where the model pares away causally irrelevant factors to reveal candidates for the underlying causal variables responsible for a phenomenon. In still other cases, I will argue that the models discussed play an important epistemic role by outlining the minimal conditions for certain social patterns - especially inequitable ones - to arise, regardless of how those patterns were actually generated in the real world. This kind of "how-minimally" modelling is especially useful in thinking about intervention. For instance, suppose we intervene on real groups via implicit bias training. If inequity emerges under minimal conditions that do not include biases, we should not expect this intervention to fully solve our problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, sometimes the same model will play multiple epistemic roles. For example, I provide models of the emergence of gender roles that I think potentially illuminate how these patterns emerged in the real world. At the same time, they demonstrate how such roles can possibly emerge from minimal preconditions. Altogether, the explanatory picture that emerges echoes Downes (2011), who emphasizes the wide set of explanatory roles that models can play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Downes (2011) is &lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1747-9991.2011.00441.x"&gt;Scientific Models by Stephen M. Downes&lt;/a&gt;, who says:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The role of models in science has been a focus of philosophical discussion for at least a century. In what follows, I provide some examples of scientific models, introduce some of the relevant philosophical discussion about models and then focus in on issues arising from a specific view about what models do: all scientific models are representations of parts of the world. I side with an emerging consensus that this unified view is not tenable. Scientific models play a number of different epistemological roles in scientific inquiry and as a result, philosophical inquiry about models should be pursued in a number of different directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am reminded of a quote from Gelman and Shalizi's &lt;a href="http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/published/philosophy.pdf"&gt;Philosophy and the practice of Bayesian statistics&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social-scientific data analysis is especially salient for our purposes because there is general agreement that, in this domain, all models in use are wrong – not merely falsifiable, but actually false. With enough data – and often only a fairly moderate amount – any analyst could reject any model now in use to any desired level of confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A model is in some sense a &lt;em&gt;toy world&lt;/em&gt;. It captures some salient feature of the real world in a way that you can reason about more concretely. These toy worlds idealise the real world, typically to some very large degree, but in doing so they have a powerful advantage over the real world: They can be manipulated and tested, and reasoned about from the omniscient view. The models contain uncertainty, but the uncertainty is generally purely probabilistic, not &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knightian_uncertainty"&gt;Knightian&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of abstraction of the real world is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2019-02-18-08:58.html"&gt;how mathematics works in general&lt;/a&gt; - creating abstract objects that we can set up correspondences with, that are not themselves physically real, but that we can use to understand reality better through analogy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This can illuminate our understanding of the world in a purely descriptive way - the model as hermeneutic resource, a tool of interpretation, one of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-27-07:57.html"&gt;the stories we tell each other&lt;/a&gt; - but of course one of the key advantages of a model is that you can use them for decision support.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I've argued before, the way to think about decision making is not to try to imagine what an optimal idealised decision maker would do, but to think instead about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;doing a decent job under bounded resources&lt;/a&gt;. In this sense, models are clearly often going to be useful despite being "wrong", if they help you make better decisions than you would at random.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this sense you can think of models as members of a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-13-11:35.html"&gt;domus&lt;/a&gt; - abstract objects that we have domesticated to our service. When the models tend to result in bad decisions, they get culled, and new ones form in their place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It will rarely be the case that these models get selected for &lt;em&gt;truth&lt;/em&gt; exactly, because truth is complex and not always that useful. Instead they will be selected for whether the errors they make are inconvenient. A model that is more accurate on average but less accurate in cases where it causes a critical error will tend to be selected against.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Statistics, in this view, is a tool for model generation (especially parameter tuning) and selection (model checking lets you cull models that produce worse results).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, the passive voice there hides who is doing the selection. In a domus, evolution is no longer just a blind force, but is guided by intentional choices made by the people involved.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_models_are_wrong"&gt;As the saying goes&lt;/a&gt;, all models are wrong, but some are useful. But useful to whom?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We have a tendency in agriculture to monocropping: Finding the "best" crop and just doing more of that. The results are less interesting and fragile, and tend to ignore certain externalities in their endless optimisation (this is why storebought tomatos are boring). This sucks if that monocrop is less suitable for you - a society that bases all their diet on wheat sucks if you're gluten intolerance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We also tend to count "best" heavily weighted towards power, which tends to neglect the needs of those with less power, who are typically minorities. Therefore the errors in our models will tend to be heavily weighted towards minimizing ones that will affect those with power.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is one of the reasons it's important to seek out niche &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html"&gt;nerddoms&lt;/a&gt; - they will tend to provide you with models from outside the monocrop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often these models will be &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; in some sense. They will work less well if you're in the majority. Often they will be poorly thought through or optimised compared to mainstream models. This is because they are optimised for a smaller number of people for whom those mainstream models were optimised for.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, their inclusion in a healthy model ecosystem is vital, because they capture aspects of reality that we would otherwise ignore, because they come from people for whom those aspects are of vital importance. Further, often through synthesis they allow us to come up with hybrid models that work better for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was &lt;a href="https://letter.wiki/conversation/610"&gt;an interesting discussion on letter wiki&lt;/a&gt; that John Nerst linked to recently that contained the following gem:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Atheism, to my mind, never grappled honestly with this fact about human nature, often preferring a speculative "mind virus" theory, which disparaged religion as a kind of cognitive parasite and suggested that we could, if only we inoculated the vulnerable, rid the human species of the nasty pestilence of religious belief. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think this was dishonesty as much as a form of projection. There are people for whom an established and popular idea never makes sense and they believe that they worked this out rather than just had a psychology for which it didn’t work.  It is then easy for them to assume that they can bring other people into this mindset. I see this with queer theorists. They are often people who lie outside of norms themselves when it comes to gender presentation and sexuality and they then rationalise &amp;amp; moralise this and try to get other people to do it but other people don’t want to because they don’t lie outside the norm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I in fact think both the religion-as-meme and queer theory models are very useful ones that are worthwhile to have in a healthy, functioning, memetic ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I also think a lot of people who are mostly "in the norm" could benefit from at least a bit of queer theory, but it's true that most people are probably right not to bother)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do agree that both tend to get overapplied by their advocates, but I feel the world is richer for them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason they get overapplied is that we've all bought too heavily into the idea of the model monocrop. We don't just want our models to be useful, we want them to be &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt;, and that must mean that other people's models are false, and so we must argue our model into dominance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But this isn't healthy. The solution is not to replace the monocrop with a better one, it's to end monocropping altogether. If &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-24-10:37.html"&gt;all knowledge is connected&lt;/a&gt; then one consequence of that is that the problems we want to solve are too complicated to perfectly model with anything short of reality itself, which defeats the purpose of having the models.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead we need something closer to model &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permaculture"&gt;permaculture&lt;/a&gt;, holding a number of (potentially highly &lt;a href="https://notebook.lisamcnulty.co.uk/post/writing-20200504/"&gt;inconsistent&lt;/a&gt;) models, which we fluidly switch between as and when it seems needful.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-04-06:21.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-05-08:59.html</id>
    <title>Making Success Trivial</title>
    <updated>2020-05-05T17:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Making Success Trivial&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When trying to acquire some habit or perform some practice, it's worth making your bar for success &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; low. Essentially, if there's any question of whether you're able to do it at a given time, that should be a sign that you're significantly compromised (ill, depressed, dealing with a crisis, etc).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The classic example of this is in meditation practice: Success is putting your ass on the meditation cushion and closing your eyes for a breath. Maybe you'll do a two hour sit after that, maybe not. You can feel good about it either way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Other examples for me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have a rereading practice. Every day I try to reread something from a book I have previously read. The only requirement is that it is a book that I have previously read and I read at least a page from it. I usually read more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have (as of yesterday, so we'll see how this one pans out) committed to spending 10 minutes per day tidying my bedroom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general I expect to do a lot more than the bare minimum for the first most days, and I expect to be right on the edge of the bare minimum for the second (update: I was pleasantly surprised to discover that I actually wanted to do more today and did a full half an hour of cleaning). That's OK, both are success.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A daily writing practice can also be made trivial, but it requires a bit more setup work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is: The metric for success is that you have written something, in the place where you said you would write it. You probably shouldn't even set a minimum word count. You &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; shouldn't set a minimum quality count. All you need to do to succeed at writing is write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second is: If you can't make the task intrinsically easier, having a repertoire of strategies for achieving it can be very helpful. For things where the practice might require thought, it's useful to have tools for minimising that. For example, the approach of picking a random passage from a book, copying it out, and writing a few thoughts prompted by it, is one that guarantees that I can succeed at my writing practice if I feel like I don't have any thoughts to write about. The Tarot prompts work in a similar way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once you've made the practice trivial, a couple things can happen:
Everything can go great, you might discover that you don't want to do it, and you might discover that you want not to do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What you do if you don't want to do it depends a lot on the task. You might be getting paid to do it, or otherwise need to do it (I certainly don't &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to clean my room right now, but I want the clean room, so...). Or you might decide that actually this isn't worth doing unless you want to do it and abandon it. That's fine too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Wanting to not do it is different though. This is when you have a negative emotional reaction to the experience, possibly despite also wanting to do it. You're trying to do it and then &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-20-10:52.html"&gt;the brakes come on&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is generally a sign that you need to get debugging and figure out why you're having that reaction. In broad strokes there are two reasons why you have a negative emotional reactions to things: Something is actually wrong, or the situation looks like something that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;you've learned in the past&lt;/a&gt; is bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In equally broad strokes, there are two solutions to negative emotional reactions: You can change the emotion, or you can change the situation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(There's probably an interesting 2x2 to draw here but I haven't got around to creating a good way to add those to notebook posts)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Changing the emotion can be hard but roughly involves &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;figuring out where it comes from and bringing it in line with reality&lt;/a&gt; or acquiring a certain amount of discomfort tolerance. My recommendation is that for the goal of making success trivial you should not set out to do this. Instead, you should understand the nature of the emotional association, and try to find strategies that work around it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The one place where changing the emotional association &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; important for triviality is to add self-compassion: Making sure you understand that &lt;em&gt;this strategy is OK&lt;/em&gt;. That it is better to have a recurring habit of trivial successes that you elaborate on as much or as little as you want than it is to have no habit at all, and to avoid punishing yourself for not meeting a higher standard. Getting comfortable with the method of trivial successes is important to avoid putting an ugh field around the whole subject.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In terms of changing the situation, two things seem to be important and and common here:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-11-14:47.html"&gt;Removing trivial irritations&lt;/a&gt; - finding things which are easy to change and make the whole process much less irritating. e.g. listening to a podcast while cleaning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;Creating safety&lt;/a&gt; - finding ways in which the process feels unsafe. For example, writing in private rather than public, or under a pseudonym, until you are comfortable with other people reading your work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One non-obvious way that you might experience the process as unsafe is if it feels like an unbounded commitment. It's important to avoid the "Oh gods, I have to keep doing this &lt;em&gt;forever&lt;/em&gt;?" reaction, and keeping the level of commitment way down is helpful for doing that. In particular, you might be tempted to ratchet up the difficulty level - to say e.g. that once you're confident that you can read a page a day, you'll increase your minimum commitments, etc. I think it's probably a bad idea to do that, because you'll be aware that you're tricking yourself, and that you're creating a greater commitment for future you, and that might feel overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another emotion that can be difficult here is not wanting to start because you don't feel like you'll be allowed to stop. One way to deal with that is to give yourself explicit permission to stop. If it's awful, you don't have to keep doing it, you're just trying it on to see what it's like. If that doesn't work out, it's not a bad thing, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;you've learned something&lt;/a&gt;, and it doesn't imply anything permanent or bad about you, you can always try again later.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-05-08:59.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-06-09:51.html</id>
    <title>Cleaning up the fnords in your environment</title>
    <updated>2020-05-06T11:30:15+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Cleaning up the fnords in your environment&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A "Fnord" is a concept from the rather strange "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2SG4PRi"&gt;Illuminatus! trilogy&lt;/a&gt;". They are explained thus:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That calmed me a little, so I set out the toast and coffee and fetched in the New York Times from the hallway. I turned the radio to WBAI and caught some good Vivaldi, sat down, grabbed a piece of toast and started skimming the first page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I saw the fnords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feature story involved another of the endless squabbles between Russia and the U.S. in the UN General Assembly, and after each direct quote from the Russian delegate I read a quite distinct “Fnord!” The second lead was about a debate in Congress on getting the troops out of Costa Rica; every argument presented by Senator Bacon was followed by another “Fnord!” At the bottom of the page was a Times depth-type study of the growing pollution problem and the increasing use of gas masks among New Yorkers; the most distressing chemical facts were interpolated with more “Fnords.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly I saw Hagbard’s eyes burning into me and heard his voice: “Your heart will remain calm. Your adrenalin gland will remain calm. Calm, all-over calm. You will not panic. You will look at the fnord and see it. You will not evade it or black it out. You will stay calm and face it.” And further back, way back: my first-grade teacher writing FNORD on the blackboard, while a wheel with a spiral design turned and turned on his desk, turned and turned, and his voice droned on,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IF YOU DON’T SEE THE FNORD IT CAN’T EAT YOU, DON’T SEE THE FNORD, DON’T SEE THE FNORD …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I looked back at the paper and still saw the fnords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was one step beyond Pavlov, I realized. The first conditioned reflex was to experience the panic reaction (the activation syndrome, it’s technically called) whenever encountering the word “fnord.” The second conditioned reflex was to black out what happened, including the word itself, and just to feel a general low-grade emergency without knowing why. And the third step, of course, was to attribute this anxiety to the news stories, which were bad enough in themselves anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A fnord is a thing that you have learned not to see, but that still triggers anxiety. It is not actually harmful in and of itself, except through the power of the emotional associations you have developed with it. The fnord can't actually eat you, but you are sufficiently terrified of it that you have learned to completely ignore its presence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, not how operant conditioning works in reality.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you have learned not to see the fnords. What would happen if I put my finger on the page where the fnord is and told you there was a fnord there?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, you'd get annoyed at me. "Of &lt;em&gt;course&lt;/em&gt; there's a fnord there." you'd say "Everyone knows there's a fnord there. Why are you drawing my attention to it?" and then you'd get annoyed with me for having the bad taste to talk about fnords.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm a big fan of John Regehr's &lt;a href="https://blog.regehr.org/archives/861"&gt;Operant Conditioning by Software Bugs&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever used a new program or system and found it to be obnoxiously buggy, but then after a while you didn’t notice the bugs anymore? If so, then congratulations: you have been trained by the computer to avoid some of its problems. For example, I used to have a laptop that would lock up to the point where the battery needed to be removed when I scrolled down a web page for too long (I’m guessing the video driver’s logic for handling a full command queue was defective). Messing with the driver version did not solve the problem and I soon learned to take little breaks when scrolling down a long web page. To this day I occasionally feel a twinge of guilt or fear when rapidly scrolling a web page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Negative responses from our environment &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;install learned beheaviours&lt;/a&gt; which cause us to avoid them. It's not that we &lt;em&gt;can't see&lt;/em&gt; the fnords, it's that we &lt;em&gt;don't look at them&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The term "&lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/EFQ3F6kmt4WHXRqik/ugh-fields"&gt;ugh field&lt;/a&gt;" apparently comes from Less Wrong (the friend I got it from is not a LW person but maybe she got it from someone who was):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A problem with the human mind — your human mind — is that it's a horrific kludge that will fail when you most need it not to. The Ugh Field failure mode is one of those really annoying failures. The idea is simple: if a person receives constant negative conditioning via unhappy thoughts whenever their mind goes into a certain zone of thought, they will begin to develop a psychological flinch mechanism around the thought. The "Unhappy Thing" — the source of negative thoughts — is typically some part of your model of the world that relates to bad things being likely to happen to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've always had an ugh field around cleaning, and around &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-30-15:20.html"&gt;care work&lt;/a&gt; more generally. Reading "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2A4sFjg"&gt;Unfuck Your Habitat&lt;/a&gt;" recently has been quite helpful with coping with that, and I've added a daily 10 minute tidy of my room to &lt;a href="https://howtosurvivementalillness.tumblr.com/post/162396810334/how-to-make-and-use-a-coping-board"&gt;my coping board&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-05-08:59.html"&gt;prediction yesterday&lt;/a&gt; was that I would stick to that ten minutes to the letter. I was pleasantly surprised that this was not the case. I completed a full &lt;a href="https://www.unfuckyourhabitat.com/whats-a-2010/"&gt;20/10&lt;/a&gt; of cleaning and then did another 10 minutes to finish it off and restore some order.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specifically what I did was go through a giant miscellaneous pile of papers and mail, take everything out of its envelopes, and shred or otherwise recycle all of the bits that didn't need to be kept. I then return the pile to where it was in a slightly tidier and smaller form.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A friend asked whether being in a slightly tidier space felt different. My initial answer was that I hadn't really done enough to achieve that - the space looked pretty much as it was before, just with one corner of it slightly tidier.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I later realised this wasn't true, there was one signficant difference: The pile of papers was no longer vaguely scary, because I knew what was in it and that it was all stuff that I either didn't need to deal with or was entirely able to deal with.
It wasn't &lt;em&gt;tidy&lt;/em&gt; yet, and so visually speaking the room looked much the same, but the &lt;a href="https://focusing.org/sixsteps"&gt;felt sense&lt;/a&gt; of the room had changed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The pile of papers was no longer a fnord.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think this is all that's going on with me and cleaning, but I think it's a large part of it. A failure to care for the environment allows the fnords to breed, and once the environment is full of fnords, caring for it requires dealing with them, so the very idea of care acquires an ugh field.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2L1VcrS"&gt;Marie Kondo&lt;/a&gt;'s recommendation of learning to tell if an item sparks joy &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; genuinely an important skill for cleaning, but if you're not going to buy in to the full blown minimalism cult, maybe an equally important emotional skill is learning to see the fnords.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-06-09:51.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-07-07:57.html</id>
    <title>Easy changes and Uncomfortable Reflections</title>
    <updated>2020-05-07T09:36:19+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Easy changes and Uncomfortable Reflections&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I've talked about in my last two posts (&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-05-08:59.html"&gt;Making success trivial&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-06-09:51.html"&gt;Cleaning up the fnords in your environment&lt;/a&gt;), my bedroom is a mess. I'd like it not to be a mess, and I've recently made two changes that are enabling that:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using &lt;a href="https://howtosurvivementalillness.tumblr.com/post/162396810334/how-to-make-and-use-a-coping-board"&gt;a coping board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structuring longer cleaning around &lt;a href="https://www.unfuckyourhabitat.com/whats-a-2010/"&gt;20/10s&lt;/a&gt; (basically just pomodoros, but with some better ergonomics)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My room is not currently clean, but it's a little cleaner than it was a week ago, and I think in a month it'll probably be pretty clean and I kinda expect to be able to keep it that way (I'll need to make some more structural changes than this in order to enable that, but these changes will get me to the point where the structural changes that I should make become more obvious).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You may notice something important about these two changes: They're really really easy, and I could have done them at any time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What this means, is that a long-running problem of mine, something that I've been feeling bad about for well over a decade (and had for longer), is something that I could have trivially fixed any time I wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, should I feel guilty about not having done so? More, should I feel &lt;em&gt;ashamed&lt;/em&gt; about not having done so?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Distinction in case it's helpful: Guilt is "I did a bad thing", shame is "I am bad")&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I claim that the answer is no, and the answer is no for a variety of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The main one is that having negative emotional responses to success is maladaptive. It causes you to not want to succeed, and will tend to destroy the motivation to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;try things&lt;/a&gt;, and will cause you to feel bad while building the habit, which will tend to sabotage the habit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It might be right, in some circumstances, to feel a certain amount of guilt or shame over this, as long as they are proportionate (i.e. don't spiral out of control) and are more than counterbalanced by the positive feelings of success, but sucess does require confronting the honest truth that you are capable of succeeding, and that can be very unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you experience success as a negative, you will tend to discourage yourself from succeeding. This is relatively obvious when it's pointed out, but is a very easy trap to fall into. If you have this problem I'd recommend my previous &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/01/a-crash-course-in-having-feelings/"&gt;Crash Course in Having Feelings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that, I think it is &lt;em&gt;factually incorrect&lt;/em&gt; to feel guilt or shame about behaviour change, because it is the nature of change to be easy once it arrives: If you're having to force yourself through a gruelling process to change, you're probably just going to fail.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead what happens is that you gradually build up skills and relationships, or your circumstances change, or one of a dozen other possibilities occur and suddenly change is easy. The thing that makes change easy now wouldn't necessarily have worked if you'd tried it five years ago, or ten, and even if it had worked you wouldn't have necessarily known how to find it among the thousands of other equally easy things that seemed equally plausible but wouldn't have worked for you.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-07-07:57.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-08-10:06.html</id>
    <title>Separating Impulse from Action</title>
    <updated>2020-05-08T13:04:37+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Separating Impulse from Action&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's a trick I figured out yesterday. It solves quite a specific problem that I have, but you might have similar problems, and even if not I think it demonstrates some useful general principles that could be applied in other circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is this: I buy too many books.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not a &lt;em&gt;disaster&lt;/em&gt; because I also read a lot of books, but I buy books at a higher rate than I read them, and I often buy books that I later decide that actually I'm not realistically going to read.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is basically that when I encounter an interesting book whose ideas I would like inside my brain, I often impulsively buy it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of this is a problem of impulse control, for sure, and I could definitely fix it by being better at impulse control, but currently I'm trying to be &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; good at impulse control, so that seems counterproductive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An additional complication is that the correct amount of books for me to be buying is not zero. I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; just blanket ban myself from buying books. I would experience it as unpleasant, but it's manageable, but that would not result in my buying the right number of books.
I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; read a lot of books (typically between one and three a week, not counting fiction which are a separate category because I read them as ebooks), and I like having new books around, and I can definitely afford to spend a certain amount of money on books.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The additional complicating factor is that my bookshelves serve as a kind of... thoughts I want to have later? They're a TODO list for reading, and my experience is that I will lose track of digital TODO lists for reading - they will get too large, and I will forget about them and leave them to rot (I am even worse at digital &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-30-15:20.html"&gt;care work&lt;/a&gt; than physical).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, I:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a constant impulse to buy books, and suppressing it will be unpleasant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do actually want to buy a non-zero amount of books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need a way to keep track of the books I may want to buy later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, there's an easy solution, and it's &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-07-07:57.html"&gt;kinda stupid&lt;/a&gt; that it's taken me this long to realise it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The solution that satisfies all of these is to have:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a default Amazon list of books I wanted to buy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a scheduled task every Sunday to buy a book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now when I want to impulse buy a book I instead just click the add to list button instead of the buy now button. Then, every Sunday, I go through the list and decide which of these books is the one I want to buy the most right now. In the course of doing so, I remove any books from the list that I'm definitely sure I won't want to buy later.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This solution is actually very good, because it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;puts the rate at which I buy things under my conscious control independently of the impulse to buy things (a thing I learned the value of from years with &lt;a href="http://beeminder.com/"&gt;Beeminder&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gives a direct and (almost) equally satisfying replacement for the impulse activity by pressing a different and equally accessible button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fights the digital rot that lists normally have for me by coupling it to a regularly scheduled activity that I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to do because I get rewarded with a book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In addition I think it will significantly increase the quality of the books I do buy, because each book I buy will be a measured choice between alternatives where invest some effort in ensuring that my book this week will be a good one. I don't intend to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;avoid all error&lt;/a&gt; and I of course &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-17-10:16.html"&gt;can't ensure I always pick the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; one&lt;/a&gt;, but I'm pretty sure that investing about twenty minutes of thought into the question will result in me improving on impulse decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-08-10:06.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-09-11:26.html</id>
    <title>Initial Notes Towards a Manifesto</title>
    <updated>2020-05-09T13:57:51+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Initial Notes Towards a Manifesto&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mechanical Monk &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/i/status/1258738843630678016"&gt;invited his mutuals to write a manifesto&lt;/a&gt;. This is my response to that, though given that this is a notebook it's a more modest attempt to gesture in the direction of what a manifesto would look like when I'm a bit more ready for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So what do I want? How do I want to change the world?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well I'd like to be able to claim some high minded ideal like universal love and cosmic oneness but that's not what I'm about. What I'm about is this: Dear humanity, we are &lt;em&gt;fucking this up&lt;/em&gt;, and it's annoying me and I'm embarrassed to be a part of it. I really shouldn't be the one to have to tell people how to sort their shit out because I'm terrible at this but apparently nobody else is going to do it right, so &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by this?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I mean that we are universally lacking in the basic systems, skills, and ethics, of being functioning, healthy, happy, human beings, and we need to fix that, and instead we are making it worse. We do not have a society that supports the development of those, and in many ways &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html"&gt;we actively punish their acquisition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An incomplete list of things we are bad at include thinking, feeling, moving, communicating, decision making, organisation, and helping each other out more broadly. Some of us are good enough at some of these things, but essentially nobody is at what I would like to consider the bare minimum standard for all of them (I sure as hell am not!).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Currently I think we have roughly the following models for acquiring these skills:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dumb luck and/or privilege in having the right role models (unreliable).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School (monstrously bad at this, not really designed to do it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therapy and coaching (limited scope, expensive)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weird borderline cults (tend to overfocus on an aspect of the problem and convince you it solves everything. Also, are cults)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-help books (similar problems to cults, also mostly very bad)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these are grossly inadequate to the task.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I'm trying to push back on it. I cannot, at present, fix society and reshape it into a more pleasing image (though if you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; me to do that and can hand me the keys I uh have one or two ideas), but I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; provide people with tools that may help them under the current circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm acquiring the parts of these skills that I can figure out for myself, or with help, and I'm trying to be a model of how I think this should work. I'm helping other people around me take steps towards the same same, by writing about it, and by building relationships that support each other's growth.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And this &lt;em&gt;isn't going to work&lt;/em&gt;. You cannot rely on me to teach you all the skills you need for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The notebook is pretty good, and I hope to do better writing about this in future, but the really high value work is in personal relationships, and there's only one of me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My work is intrinsically built around my particular strengths and weaknesses - I'm a weird, queer, hyperverbal, nerd and so the problems I'm solving and the tools I'm using are designed with that in mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am, as alluded to, &lt;em&gt;not very good at this&lt;/em&gt;, and I'm going to miss things, get things wrong, or communicate them in unhelpful ways, and we need many different voices doing the same sorts of things if we are to have any chance of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-28-06:45.html"&gt;climbing out of the crab bucket&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(2) doesn't mean that you can't benefit from my writing if you're not like me, but it does mean that my tools are built in a very particular way for a very particular set of problems. They might or might not work for you (possibly with modification), but even if they work for you they might not solve all your problems because they're designed to solve &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; problems (and, to a lesser extent, the problems of people I know well enough to help). You need to build your own tools too! And then, once you have, I want you to share them with other people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And I want you to share them with other people while &lt;em&gt;understanding that their tools might not work for others&lt;/em&gt;.
When I wrote &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-08-10:06.html"&gt;yesterday's post&lt;/a&gt; I very clearly spelled out why this was a good solution for me, and that these might not be the same for you. All tools will be like this, but right now people tend to get very evangelical about how their tool is the one size fits all to all problems, and this is extremely wrong, both factually and morally.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm losing steam on writing more of this right now, so I'm going to just end with a list of things I want people to do:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut people some slack. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-06-15:20.html"&gt;Create&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety&lt;/a&gt; for those around you. Sign non-aggression pacts in the goddamn &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2019-06-04-09:58.html"&gt;legibility war&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Treat the problems in your life as interesting and worth solving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join and learn from &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html"&gt;nerd&lt;/a&gt; communities who can help you solve them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-26-07:28.html"&gt;growth relationships&lt;/a&gt;, where everyone involved helps everyone else be better versions of themselves. I'm particularly a fan of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-25-16:02.html"&gt;the support group model&lt;/a&gt;, but this is one of those tools that might not work for everyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/10/how-to-explain-anything-to-anyone/"&gt;Explain&lt;/a&gt; these things to others. Obviously I'm a fan of the notebook blog format, but again that might not be what works for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I understand that what I am asking of you is difficult, and I understand that for some of you it may not yet be possible, but I'm trying my best to make it possible, and easy, for as many people as I can, and I hope that some of you will do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-09-11:26.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-10-08:54.html</id>
    <title>How to be a better person</title>
    <updated>2020-05-10T08:54:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How to be a better person&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Shopping Cart test of Ethics" src="/images/shoppingcart.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/allenmmurray/status/1258954956473679873"&gt;Credit&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In response to my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-09-11:26.html"&gt;Initial notes towards a manifesto&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/joxn"&gt;@joXn&lt;/a&gt; quite reasonably asked how I would avoid falling afoul of the problem that, contra The Good Place, learning ethics doesn't actually make one more ethical. Eric Schwitzgebel has a lot of great research on this (see &lt;a href="https://faculty.ucr.edu/~eschwitz/"&gt;his publications&lt;/a&gt; and in particular the section "The Relationship Between Moral Reflection and Moral Behavior").&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of these, I think &lt;a href="https://faculty.ucr.edu/~eschwitz/SchwitzAbs/MoralMediocrity.htm"&gt;Aiming for Moral Mediocrity&lt;/a&gt; is perhaps the most important:
Schwitzgebel argues that most people probably aim to be about as moral as their peers, and that this is mediocre (neither great, nor terrible) to do, but that most people could manage to be better than they are with no great hardship.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Schwitzgebel's claim is basically right, and the paper is a very good one, with two major caveats:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He is underestimating the hardship, because (I think) he is missing one of the reasons why this happens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He has fallen afoul of precisely the reason why learning ethics does not make you a better person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there are approximately four reasons why people fail to behave ethically:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They do not care to do the right thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are discouraged from doing the right thing by external factors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They do not know what the right thing is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They do not know how to do the right thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Behaving ethically is a skillful practice, and most people are either not very good at the skill, not very motivated to practice it, or do not have an environment that enables them to practice it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ethicists primarily study what the right thing to do is, but I think for most people this is not the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-21-10:04.html"&gt;constraint&lt;/a&gt; on the skillful practice of ethics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I will, for the purpose of this post, assume that people &lt;em&gt;care&lt;/em&gt; to do the right thing. I think fixing that is a whole different question. This leaves the other three. Given that we know from Schwitzgebel's work that knowing the right thing to do is also not enough, lets assume for the moment that you, in most practical circumstances if not necessarily in general, know what the right thing to do is. Why don't you do it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, lets take a look at Schwitzgebel's theme of Moral Mediocrity: Why do people aim to be morally mediocre?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I propose that there's a very straightforward reason: Moral Mediocrity is the option that won't get you punished.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you behave badly, people will be judgemental towards you. But they will also react badly to you if you are especially moral. It's not just that you're not a saint it's that, in actual practice, we don't &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; saints, because they make us feel bad about ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the examples in the paper is vegetarianism. Suppose you were reasonably convinced that, ethically speaking, you should be a vegetarian or vegan. Now, all your interactions with people around you around food come with extra friction. Even if you never say anything judgy about it, it's impossible for people to not know you're vegetarian (if they're sharing meals with you) and many of them will respond defensively or aggressively about it. You'll experience a constant, albeit low grade, pressure of the people around you trying to drag you back down to their moral level.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You'll see this with other things too: Someone who is unusually ethical will constantly have people telling them to relax, take things less seriously, etc. Being unusually ethical is weird, and triggers the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html"&gt;social obligation to be bad at things&lt;/a&gt; in a big way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not, I hasten to add, a moral justification for being morally mediocre. It doesn't change what you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; do. If anything, the tendency of people to norm their behaviour to those around them creates a stronger moral obligation to be good, because it influences others to be good. It is a &lt;em&gt;practical barrier to ethical behaviour&lt;/em&gt;, and any theory of ethics that does not teach you to overcome such practical barriers will not result in more ethical behaviour any more than a detailed understanding of thermodynamics will allow you to build an internal combustion engine. A theory of ethics is all very well, but you need a &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; of ethics, which is what Schwitzgebel's paper.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's another practical barrier: If you realise that you are behaving badly, and decide to be better, you have to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-07-07:57.html"&gt;reconcile yourself to the fact that you could always have been better&lt;/a&gt;, which is very painful, so you would much rather rationalise your behaviour as just fine the way it is to avoid that pain.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And for another, consider the following scenario: Suppose you decide to be vegetarian, and you're really good about it for about a month, virtuously resisting the temptation to eat meat, and absolutely hating how bland all your food has become because you don't know how to cook interesting vegetarian food and the cafeteria where you mostly eat has awful vegetarian food. After about a month, you go out for a meal with some friends, and you look at the incredibly disappointing vegetarian menu and your eyes are drawn to the cheesburger selection... and after that you're no longer vegetarian.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This actually demonstrates &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; problems: Firstly, you don't know how to be vegetarian, and are trying to overcome that limitation with pure willpower rather than treating it as a practical problem you need to solve, and the second is that you don't understand behaviour change so you tried to go all in on the new behaviour and then gave up as soon as you failed once.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are the three main practical barriers to overcome: Social norms, emotional difficulties, and missing skills, and all of these are emimently solvable problems that you can learn to overcome, and that you will find personally beneficial to learn to overcome regardless of whether you use them to become more ethical.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More, I think once you have acquired these skills, you will naturally become more ethical (or at least, more in line with your own values): If you can change when you feel like you should, and you feel like you should behave a particular way, then you'll just do that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mostly, at least. You'll probably still be bad occasionally. That's OK. It's more fun to be a bit evil from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-10-08:54.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
