<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-05-30T13:17:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-21-09:32.html</id>
    <title>Against the Classification of Books</title>
    <updated>2020-05-21T10:25:24+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Against the Classification of Books&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-21&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2ylGMjz"&gt;How to Read a Book&lt;/a&gt;, p 64:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have already discussed a rough classification of books. The main distinction, we said, was between works of fiction, on the one hand, and works conveying knowledge, or expository works, on the other hand. Among expository works, we can further distinguish history from philosophy, and both from science and mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is part of a general section about how analytical reading should start with the question "What sort of book is this?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On page 60, they list this as the first rule of analytical reading:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must know what kind of book you are reading, and you should know this as early in the process as possible, preferably before you begin to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The authors do not, frankly, justify this very well. At the end of this chapter their argument is this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, just as there is a difference in the art of teaching in different fields, so there is a reciprocal difference in the art of being taught. The activity of the student must somehow be responsive to the activity of the instructor. The relation between books and their readers is the same as that between teachers and their students. Hence, as books differ in the kinds of knowledge they have to communicate, they proceed to instruct us differently; and, if we are to follow them, we must learn to read each kind in an appropriate manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To which I offer the following responses:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A book is not a person, and our relationship is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different to that of a person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The argument is nonsense for people too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can engage with a book however you like. There's no moral obligation to engage with a book as the authors want you to - if you want to read a book of science through a literary criticism lens, or a book of literary criticism through a scientific lens, you can.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even the practical vs theoretical distinction is dubious: I read a lot of philosophy. This philosophy is, for the most part, eminently theoretical, but I am reading it for practical reasons, to help me make sense of things. This requires me to do a lot of translation by doing the active work of framing practical situations using the tools provided.
This is not a style of engagement that a philosopher would generally be receptive to (it depends on the philosopher of course) and they would probably find it quite frustrating. A book can't be frustrated with me, so I'm free to use it however I like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's certainly true that treating a science book as a science book and a piece of literature as a piece of literature will result in results that are more... in line with the intent of the author I guess, and you should probably do that more often than not - it's useful to learn the norms before you violate them - but they don't necessarily produce more &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; outcomes, and different reads will tend to help you
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-24-10:37.html"&gt;bridge the gaps between different areas of knowledge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second problem is that the idea that coarse grained classifications are anything like enough. People have very individual styles and, yes, those are rooted in their communities of practice, but those communities of practice are only loosely defined by disciplines - they're often very different between subdisciplines, departments, individual teacher / student lineages, etc. You need to do at least as much work to identify those individual differences in engagement as you do to identify the genre.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead of asking "What sort of book is this?" I think the questions you should be asking are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can I engage with this book in a way that I want to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If not, where can I learn the skills for doing so?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Knowing what sort of book it is &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be helpful for answering the question, but often it is going to be much more about your relationship to the subject matter than it is about the type of book per se.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-21-09:32.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-22-09:34.html</id>
    <title>Feeling Good About Being Good</title>
    <updated>2020-05-22T10:52:49+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Feeling Good About Being Good&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-22&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently working through a (more or less) full reread of &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3g53ayI"&gt;Voices: The Educational Formation of Conscience&lt;/a&gt;, so you're going to get treated to a lot of extracts from it. Today's extract comes from page 41:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] normation just &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; this structuring of the emotions of self-assessment -shame, guilt, embarassment, pride, and the like-both in our self-assessment and in our judgements of others. It follows, of course, that it structures also the positive emotions companion to these that I have called the emotions of self-assessment. That is to say normation structures also the appearance of elation, pride, self-assurance, and the joy and hope that accompany these. By saying that normation structures these emotions, I mean to refer not to the logic of their composition, whether they presuppose some propositional content, as in one or another version of a cognitive theory of the emotions. I mean to refer rather to their focus or object. Normation gives content to these emotions inasmuch as it provides their object. It tells us &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; things are going to provoke such emotions. In short, normation makes these emotions specific. Structuring them in this way is precisely what mere compliance is powerless to accomplish. Again, absent these emotions and the norms themselves will vanish. Observance will deconstruct into mere compliance, governance into mere behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This continues to explore the theme of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-09:54.html"&gt;the connection between morality and emotional health that I highlighted before&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To unpack what Green is saying in this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Normation is the social process by which we acquire norms of behaviour - voices of conscience with which we reflexively judge whether behaviour is good or bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Observance" of a norm is distinguished from mere "compliance" when we feel the force of the norm internally rather than merely adhering to the behaviour it prescribes. e.g. we are observant to a norm of honesty if we feel guilty about lying, but we may still be honest (compliant with the norm of honesty) without internalising that norm if we think that honesty is the best policy for purely practical reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the general point of the quote is that this process of internalising moral norms is about structuring how we &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; about action: When we do something we feel is morally good, we feel good, when we do something we feel is morally bad, we feel bad. Observance to moral norms is defined by part of the structure of our emotional responses.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting things to me about this passage is its emphasis on both the negative &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; positive emotional responses to observing a norms (it also amuses me that he lists "pride" under both). I don't know about you, but I think of morality as primarily experienced through negative emotions - especially guilt and shame - but there are of course positive emotions associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of why I've been interested in &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-virtue/"&gt;Virtue Ethics&lt;/a&gt; recently is that it feels that this is the only one of the currently extant ethical frameworks that get this right (and, interestingly, although Green doesn't make this explicit, his voices of conscience sure sound a lot like virtues to me). If you are striving for excellence, there is a sort of joy in that. If morality is nothing more than a series of duties, or a number you are seeking to make constantly go up, then morality is purely a burden, a stick to beat ourselves with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I previously wrote about the use of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:35.html"&gt;fine-grained ethical distinctions&lt;/a&gt; - in particularly the distinction between it being virtuous to do something and being a duty to do something - and I think these track pretty well with emotional reactions. If you fail in your moral duties, it's proper to feel guilty over that. If you have a pattern of failing in your moral duties, it's proper to feel shame over that. But if you exemplify your moral virtues, it's also proper to feel joy in that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This brings the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; model into the question of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-10-08:54.html"&gt;how to be a better person&lt;/a&gt; - if we can take joy in our moral successes, then we will want to be better people, and this will drive us to become such.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-22-09:34.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-23-09:31.html</id>
    <title>Feet as a Foundational Skill</title>
    <updated>2020-05-23T10:41:21+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Feet as a Foundational Skill&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Fix a man's feet, and you will make him comfortable for a month. Teach a man to walk properly, and you will make him comfortable for life. Therefore denying people access to good foot education is key to monthly recurring revenue." - Ancient Capitalist Proverb.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently working on being good at feet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being bad at feet sounds ridiculous, right? Almost as ridiculous as &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-11-09:32.html"&gt;being bad at breathing&lt;/a&gt;. I am bad at both feet and breathing, and I'd wager that many of you reading this are too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons you can tell that I am bad at feet is that I've spent the last 10-15 years in semiconstant pain. Not, you know, a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of pain. Just a dull ache in most of the joints of my right leg that waxes and wanes but never really goes away. I've always been a bit reluctant to identify as someone who experiences chronic pain - it doesn't really match the definition of chronic pain, you know, other than being pain and being chronic - other people have it much worse than me (this is a bullshit line of thinking and I know it's a bullshit line of thinking. I have now more or less &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;reconciled the alief&lt;/a&gt; and recognised that, but it took a while).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another way in which I am bad at feet is that standing for long periods of time is painful. Walking is generally fine, but if I stand for more than about half an hour my legs will be very sad and probably hate me the next day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've at various points tried to get medical professionals to take these problems seriously, but it's never worked very well. The best I got is about a year and a half ago I got custom insoles made. They... maybe helped a bit? Not much.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But now, in one of the rare upsides of the world going to hell, my chronic pain is at the lowest it's been since my early 20s - it's not gone, but it's mostly retreated to a vague twinge in my hip (which is where all this started).
I attribute this largely to the almost total lack of wearing shoes, especially as it's accelerated since I've switched to barefoot shoes for running.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Standing for long periods of time is still a bit tricky, so I'm working on arch strength. I've switched to working standing in twenty minute stints recently, and doing a bunch of exercises for strengthening my arches, added a nightly (self) foot massage to my care routine, and I'm looking into toe straightening (one of the structural failings of my feet is that my outer toes curl inwards. I'm pretty sure this is related, because combining arch exercises with toe straightening is excruciating). These might or might not work, but I'm hopeful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this isn't really a post about feet. This is a post about being bad at things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At no point in the more than a decade that I've been dealing with this problem did I consider that the root issue of my chronic pain might be that I was using my feet wrong. I knew that the problem with standing was related to flat feet, but I thought of that as an intrinsic structural issue rather than something that I could work on by changing how I use my feet. At no point did it occur to me that feet were a foundational skill that I could just work on getting better at and that this would significantly improve my life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How much would it improve my life? Hard to say. Not being in constant pain is a pretty good improvement to start with but consider also...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am bad at sleep. Some of that is due to the aforementioned being bad at breathing, but some of it is due to the fact that being in pain makes it hard to sleep!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am bad at socialising in groups, especially parties. How much of that is because group social situations tend to involve a lot of standing, so I tend to be tired and in pain for a lot of them, which gives me fewer opportunities to get good at groups and also gives me negative associations with them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(As an aside, being bad at standing is something I've mentioned before as an &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-23-09:37.html"&gt;illegible marginalisation&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not saying that these are the only causes, because &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-11:43.html"&gt;very little is monocausal&lt;/a&gt;. I'm saying that among the weird and varied landscapes of life, these have exerted consistent pressure in some fairly negative directions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suspect there are a lot of foundational skills like this, and we currently don't have any infrastructure for identifying them, or learning to be better at them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly problematic because being bad at these foundational skills is something you can kinda get away with early on - you have more energy to power through them, and have not been subjected to the constant low-grade degradation of your body (or mind! Much of the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;emotions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt; model plays out this way too) that being bad at these skills causes, so by the time you start to notice the effects you're at the point where you feel like you should have life sorted out and you just treat these as the inevitable consequences of aging, when really they're a sign that you need to relearn a foundational skill.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-23-09:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-25-09:18.html</id>
    <title>Identity and Legitimisation of Knowledge</title>
    <updated>2020-05-25T09:55:20+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Identity and Legitimisation of Knowledge&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;PSA: Posts this week are going to be especially short because I need to focus on actual writing for my PhD this week. I'll just be copying out interesting passages from random pages of random books from my "canon" and making very short commentaries on them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3d3aby7"&gt;Epistemic Injustice: Power and the Ethics of Knowing&lt;/a&gt; by Miranda Fricker, page 9:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see that [a silencing of a woman by a man] involves an exercise of power, of of gender power in particular. But what do we mean by power? And how does gender power relate to the general notion of social power? In order to paint a portrait of testimonial injustice and to home in on its distinctive central case, we need to answer these questions about the nature of social power in general and the particular kind of social power (of which gender power is one instance) that I shall call &lt;em&gt;identity&lt;/em&gt; power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The "testimonial injustice" that Fricker is talking about here is a notion she introduces in this book, and is an injustice done to people in rejecting their testimony based on their identity - e.g. in the case she is talking about, rejecting someone's testimony because she is a woman.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've just finished reading Lyotard's "The Postmodern Condition", an experience which I cannot really recommend, and in it he talks about the role of &lt;em&gt;legitimisation&lt;/em&gt; in knowledge - i.e. if we think of a community of practice as telling each other stories about the world, what are the social practices involved in accepting some of those stories into our canon as legitimate knowledge. He argues that sciences in particular can be thought of as having a set of particularly stringent set of criteria for legitimisation, and tend to reject other modes of legitimisation as hopelessly fuzzy and informal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Read in this light, I think one interesting lens on Fricker's work would be this:
One of the roles of social power is control over the legitimisation process for knowledge. When social power is rooted in identities, this has the particularly pernicious effect of resulting in a community's canon of recognised legitimate knowledge that systemically underrepresents knowledge originating in marginalized groups.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, as has been pointed out before by &lt;a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5250/fronjwomestud.33.1.0024?seq=1"&gt;Kirsty Dotson&lt;/a&gt;, Fricker has badly misunderstood one aspect of the nature of knowledge in a way that this highlights: There is no single canon, but instead many loosely overlapping ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This misunderstanding is also present in her notion of identity power. In fact, identity power does not exist, because social power does not exist in individuals. Social power is a relationship between an individual and a community. The same identity that denies you credibility in one community may gain you credibility in another.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that the problems of testimonial injustice she is pointing out don't exist - they absolutely do - but that they need to be more carefully contextualised. "You're only oppressed by the dominant community who controls most of the economy" is not actually any more reassuring than thinking you're oppressed in some absolute sense, but the fine grained distinction is still useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly significant in another book I've read recently, which is James Scott's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2yzIMF8"&gt;Domination and the Arts of Resistance&lt;/a&gt;, where he introduces the idea of the &lt;em&gt;hidden transcript&lt;/em&gt; - essentially the canon of knowledge that is present within a marginalised group and is actively concealed (possibly by hiding it in plain sight) from the more dominant group.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Putting these together, one way of looking at Dotson's notion of contributory injustice, which is the refusal of dominant groups to take on the ideas of the marginalised (e.g. white people refusing to acknowledge the idea of racism), is that sometimes the transcripts of marginalised groups are hidden by the marginalised, but equally often they're instead ignored by the powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-25-09:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-26-06:22.html</id>
    <title>Attractive People on Magazine Covers as Hermeneutical Marketing</title>
    <updated>2020-05-26T07:40:18+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Attractive People on Magazine Covers as Hermeneutical Marketing&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3c0QDt4"&gt;Exuberant Animal&lt;/a&gt; by Frank Forencich, page 242:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The images we see on magazine covers are not authentic; they are manufactured. The models, beautiful as they might happen to be at the outset, are simply raw material for the digital hacks who do the ultimate make-over. What we see on the magazine rack are caricatures, not real human beings. They are not us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No wonder we are confused. No wonder our eyes are out of focus. No wonder everyone looks ugly. By comparison to magazine covers, none of us can come close to measuring up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Later, on page 243:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In each case, the subliminal message is the same: "Here is what you're supposed to look like. You don't, so now you've got a problem. But if you buy this magazine, and the products advertised in this magazine, you'll have a chance of looking this way, someday." Thus the magazines give a two-pronged marketing approach: create a sense of anxiety and offer a solution, all in one stroke. The strategy is nakedly, shamelessly manipulative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A couple thoughts sparked immediately from this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Magazines... those are a boomer thing, right?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Huh, visual hermeneutics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Huh, the supply of prototypes is a hermeneutic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hermeneutics is a great marketing strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's an interesting market coordination problem here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Hermeneutics" means "The Study Interpretation", and "A hermeneutic" is something you use to interpret the world.
Also I &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/life-as-nonproductive-act"&gt;did say&lt;/a&gt; that I see everything as being about hermeneutics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These were all surprisingly interesting thoughts for a book that I didn't feel like I really got that much out of on my first pass through.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The magazines thing: Magazines still exist, obviously, but this book is from 2006 and I can't tell how much I'm just completely oblivious to the consumption of magazines and how much the world has just genuinely moved on. I feel like social media and youtube and the like have plugged the gap a bit and our supply of visual prototypes of what people are supposed to look like are a bit better than they used to be - still very filtered and aspirational, but not quite the degree of total airbrushing than they used to be then.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The fact that there  were purely visual hermeneutics is not something I'd realised before. I tend to think of hermeneutics as quite a verbal thing, because I'm quite a verbal thing, but of course the way we literally look at the world has a huge interpretive element to it. You don't just look at something/someone and then judge after the fact that it's/they're beautiful, beauty is part of how you orient your visual experience of it in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The use of prototypes as a hermeneutic is also something that... I guess if you'd pointed it out to me I would have said "Yeah, of course" but it wasn't foreground information. A lot of how we interpret the world is going to be by comparison to other things in it, and so the supply of salient things to compare against are a huge part of my hermeneutic.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hermeneutics as marketing: If you can control how people look at the world it makes it much easier to sell them on your particular solution to the problems that you highlight.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Market coordination: There's something of an arms race here. Each magazine is made more competitive by advertising with pictures that are only slightly more attractive than its competitors, but they then catch up, which is how we end up with this hyperoptimised scenario where people are attractive to a degree that actual humans can't really manage.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel like I could expand any one of these into a full notebook post, but I'm supposed to be focused on other things this week, so I won't.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-26-06:22.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-27-07:21.html</id>
    <title>The Inner Pedestal of Tennis</title>
    <updated>2020-05-27T09:19:32+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The Inner Pedestal of Tennis&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2LUnchH"&gt;The Inner Game of Tennis&lt;/a&gt; by W. Timothy Gallwey, page 129:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been my own worst stressor. But slowly I have found that the demands I'm trying to fulfill when I'm stressing myself are not really my own, but ones I have "picked up" or "bought into" for perhaps no better reason than I heard them early in life, or because they seemed to be so generally accepted. Soon they begin to sound right - and are therefore easier to listen to than the subtle but insistent urging of my own being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this gets to the heart of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-21-12:35.html"&gt;my disagreement with Gallwey&lt;/a&gt;, which largely stems from the fact that in this paragraph almost every word he says is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I think this book is entirely a giant bait and switch: He makes the (mostly) useful distinction between (ugh) "Self 1", the teller, and "Self 2", the doer. This is a reasonable split which is useful in many circumstances. I don't necessarily think it's a &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; split, but it works pretty well for about 90% of cases.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately he then goes on to posit that:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self 1 is intrinsically dysfunctional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self 2 is intrinsically functional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every other binary split of your self, including "the bad bits" and "the good bits" also lines up with this distinction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every single one of these premises is badly wrong. It is certainly true for many people that Self 1 is dyfunctional and Self 2 is functional, but those dysfunctions are not intrinsic and treating them as such is actively harmful. The third is just intrinsically nonsense and is the sign of someone with an explain everything theory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these errors manifest in this paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, specifically what he is wrong about in this paragraph boils down to two important glaring errors:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost everything in you is learned from outside of you. That's not you listening to things that are "not really your own". That is how being a person works. We socially construct our knowledge and behaviours by engaging with the people around us. You are complaining about being a person, Tim.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The arising internally/learned externally split of your behaviour &lt;em&gt;in no way&lt;/em&gt; maps on to the self 1 / self 2 distinction. Self 2 &lt;em&gt;absolutely&lt;/em&gt; learns and internalises lessons from the outside world. That's what trauma, and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;emotional responses more broadly&lt;/a&gt;, are. This is why operant conditioning works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I mean FFS, really.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I listen to a lot of &lt;a href="https://www.therapistuncensored.com/"&gt;Therapist Uncensored&lt;/a&gt; and an interesting theme that keeps coming up listening to it is that they're also quite into a similar split to Self 1 vs Self 2 (they tend to neurowash it and refer to it by parts of the brain, but that's neither here nor there), but they think that &lt;em&gt;Self 2&lt;/em&gt; is the dysfunctional one and that a lot of the skills they're trying to learn are essentially trying to use Self 1 to help Self 2 heal from its entrained fear reactions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think here I must adopt my usual brand of fence sitting: Actually, both sides are wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Self 1 and Self 2 each have their own strengths and weaknesses, and you cannot operate as a fully healthy human being without:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A functional Self 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A functional Self 2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A functional relationship between the two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Self 2 needs to give Self 1 a hug, and Self 1 needs to help Self 2 to talk about its feelings. They're literally both in this together, and they should behave as such.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The relationship is the important part, and Gallwey's framing basically fucks up any chance of a healthy relationship.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Putting someone on a pedestal basically dooms any possibility of a healthy relationship with them, and this is what we are doing when we claim Self 2 is in some sense intrinsically whole and just needs to be let free. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html"&gt;Self 2 is wrong all the time&lt;/a&gt; and that's OK. It's wrong in ways that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;Self 1 is good at helping it resolve&lt;/a&gt;. Self 1 does tend to get a bit neurotic if left in control, it's true, but Self 2 just needs to give it a bit of a hug and tell it to calm down and let the body do its thing (I've not yet figured out a better tool for this than actual hugs unfortunately).&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-27-07:21.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-28-07:42.html</id>
    <title>Life is neither poker nor tennis</title>
    <updated>2020-05-28T09:18:29+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Life is neither poker nor tennis&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3deDz4N"&gt;Thinking in Bets&lt;/a&gt; by Annie Duke, page 10:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hindsight bias is the tendency, after an outcome is known, to see the outcome as having been inevitable. When we say "I should have known that would happen," or, "I should have seen it coming," we are succumbing to hindsight bias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those beliefs develop from an overly tight connection between outcomes and decisions. That is typical of how we evaluate our past decisions."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is from a chapter called "Life is poker, not chess."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Before I start, I'd like to say that I think "Thinking in Bets" is a very good book and I would recommend that most people read it. It is probably the most accessible practical manual of rationality that I know of (there may well be better ones, but I don't know of them), and most people's thinking would be improved by a good primer in that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which is why I now want to explain why it's also wrong about everything.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In discussions on Twitter about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-27-07:21.html"&gt;yesterday's diatribe against The Inner Game of Tennis&lt;/a&gt;, I made &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1265765964915904514"&gt;the following point&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem being that because he got his start in tennis where verbal intelligence mostly &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; need to get out of the way, and because most people don't have tennis-related trauma, his model works pretty there but has fatal flaws when you try to generalise it off the court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Gallwey is making a classic error: He is a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html"&gt;nerd&lt;/a&gt;, and he thinks his special interest is universally applicable. Most of the advice in the inner game of tennis is very good &lt;em&gt;if you only ever apply it on the Tennis court&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's absolutely a good thing to take ideas from a specific nerddom and try to generalise them. I love doing that, and claiming that it was bad would be the rankest hypocrisy on my part. The problem is not generalising his Tennis related learning off the tennis court, the problem is that having learned all these skills in a context where they are useful close to 100% of the time, you do not learn to understand the preconditions under which those skills are useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Annie Duke has made the same mistake: She has learned a skill set within the context of a game of poker, and is now viewing the relevant skill set as applicable to life as a whole. Unfortunately, Poker has some very distinctive features over life:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is intrinsically adversarial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is highly structured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The probabilities of different outcomes are well defined and easily calculable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has a single well-defined utility function (money made) describing success in the game.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you may or may not be aware I love to hate on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subjective_expected_utility"&gt;Subjective Expected Utility Theory&lt;/a&gt;, but poker is an example where utility theory is great because you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have a utility function and you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have probabilities. Regardless of whether you believe in SEU, life outside poker simply isn't like that because the probabilities and the utility function are at best much more complex and less well defined.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Note: Thanks to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelly_criterion"&gt;The Kelly Criterion&lt;/a&gt; the utility function of poker is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; just straight up money made, but its logarithm, but the point still stands).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Poker is an &lt;em&gt;excellent&lt;/em&gt; game with which to hone your skills for a particular type of technical rationality, but technical rationality will only take you so far.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;C. Thi Nguyen suggests that games are &lt;a href="https://philpapers.org/archive/NGUGAT-2.pdf"&gt;ways of experimenting with different structures of agency&lt;/a&gt;. In playing a game, you are entering a world in which your choices are constrained to follow the rules of the game, and so you learn to play &lt;em&gt;as if&lt;/em&gt; those were the only choices possible. As a result you will &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-21-10:04.html"&gt;learn skills that you are neglecting in other contexts&lt;/a&gt; where those constraints on your agency do not apply. Learning the inner game of tennis &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; teach you about embodied cognition, because you can't think your way out of the problem. Learning poker &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; teach you about technical rationality, because you can't sweet talk your way out of the problem. Both embodied cognition and technical rationality are very good skills that you can apply in life more broadly, but because life lacks that restricted structure of agency that the game had. The reason the game taught you that skill so well was precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; the skill is not universally applicable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;David Chapman has recently published an &lt;a href="https://meaningness.com/eggplant/introduction"&gt;updated introduction to his Eggplant Book&lt;/a&gt;, which is about what he calls metarationality, that I rather like. In particular:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[People with metarational skills] produce these insights by investigating the relationship between a system of technical rationality and its context. The context includes a specific situation in which rationality is applied, the purposes for which it is used, the social dynamics of its use, and other rational systems that might also be brought to bear. This work operates not within a system of technical rationality, but around, above, and then on the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This applies more broadly than technical rationality: The foundational skill of life is figuring out what other skills you need to bring to bear on the situation. You cannot learn that from a game, because games work precisely by removing the need for that skill.
Games are an excellent way to hone certain skills, but they intrinsically lack the ability to teach you the fundamental life skill of &lt;em&gt;knowing which game you are playing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of which is a very long winded way of getting around to a very basic point prompted by the initial quote: Hindsight bias is good, actually.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hindsight bias is generally bad in poker where you can have very well defined strategies and intrinsic quantifiable uncertainty in the problem, but in life more broadly hindsight bias serves several fairly important functions. For example:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It forces you to look at problems much more carefully than you otherwise would have, giving you incentives to improve your skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It lets you hold people accountable for actions even when they are individually harmless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An example of the first is that when writing it is generally worth assuming that any misunderstands are your fault. They may often not be - many people are very bad readers - but by treating them as your fault anyway your writing skills will generally improve.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An example of the second is something I often use as a moral test case and requires a bit more of an extended anecdote.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Near my parents' place there is a more-or-less blind bend in the main road with a small road that joins on to the main road right after that bend. It is very poor design.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Almost nobody comes down that small road. I've seen someone joining on to the main road from there maybe two or three times during many years of driving that road.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's entirely viable to take the bend at 60mph if you ignore the side road. It's not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; sharp a bend. However, the signage wants you to take it at 25mph in order to account for that basically-never-used side road.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, my question is this: How fast should you take that bend?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From a subjective expected utility point of view, it's actually probably fine to take that bend at 60mph. Slowing down at that point in the drive is quite annoying, and the chances of causing an accident are extremely low given the low usage of that side road (and it's not like an accident is inevitable at 60mph and more than it's entirely avoidable at 25mph, you're just increasing the likelihood and severity). Yes you're trading convenience for an increased probability of your own and/or someone else's death but of course you are, you're &lt;em&gt;driving&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, if everyone else makes the same calculation, driving in from that side road is now basically a death sentence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Subjective Expected Utility calculations often look &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different if you universalise them by assuming that everyone else will make similar calculations, but SEU calculations are hard enough as it is without reasoning this way, and there's an easy kludge to achieve much the same effect: Hindsight bias.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If we treat low-probability consequences as if we should have seen them coming, and punish them accordingly, then we change the incentives to shape individual behaviour away from creating outcomes that were inevitable in aggregate even if they were low probability in any given instance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is this unfair on the indidual who happens to trigger the low probablity consequence? Probably. But so is dying because everyone else was making individually rational calculations that decided a low probability of your death was an acceptable consequence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is hindsight bias always good? No, of course not. You have to figure out from context whether it is or not. But that skill of figuring it out from context is not, I'm afraid, something you can learn from a game.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-28-07:42.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-28-21:05.html</id>
    <title>Key Performance Indicators</title>
    <updated>2020-05-28T23:41:11+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Key Performance Indicators&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;TLDR: Drunk and more than slightly self-indulgent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have inspired &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/captain_mrs/status/1266063855018532865"&gt;the creation of a blog&lt;/a&gt; which is absolutely one of my victory conditions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This caused me to think about some others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every word I inspire someone to write.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time you curse my name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every comment by someone who is annoyed by my being right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time my perfectly reasonable behaviour seems impossible to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time someone sends a link to my writing to their therapist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time someone uses something I wrote to win an argument.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time I make someone happier for my presence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But also every time someone understands themself better because of me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time I change how you look at the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every conversation we have that you thought was impossible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every person whose life I make better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do these seems inadequately selfish to you? They do to me. We ground our values in the people around us, but if we don't &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/09/being-an-example-to-others/"&gt;learn to be a little bit selfish&lt;/a&gt; then those values result in everyone being miserable through trying to make everyone happy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of them are, perhaps, a little selfish, in that they allow me to embrace my inner villain,
but villains, too, are unselfish: We're the ones who want to change the world for the better.
The heroes are just there to maintain the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So what are my victory conditions for me?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every "Ah ha!" moment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every hug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time I get to uncomplicatedly enjoy myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time I figure out why I can't, and fix that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every time I get to act with my whole self, without holding back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every (redacted).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This doesn't seem enough. I can think of a few more, but I don't want to write them down,
and perhaps that's the problem: Admitting to wanting, let alone needing, things is vulnerable,
and I don't like being vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may seem surprising, as I share a lot, but what I share is in fact carefully curated. It doesn't count as vulnerability if by sharing it I rob it of its power, or if I do the work to become safe first.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, if I'm honest, I don't really feel like the ones for me count. They feel pointlessly self-indulgent, or like things I'm supposed to want to want. Where they don't the emotions don't feel exactly &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. I feel like the emotion associated with healing and growth should be something akin to joy, but that's not quite how it feels. It's more like a "Ha ha! Fuck you! You can't beat &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;!". It's still other-oriented.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been spending the last year or two trying to work on emotional skills, and that's been pretty good. I liked the bit where I figured out how to turn off social anxiety. But a lot of the drive for that has been other oriented too: I started a relationship, I realised my emotional baggage was now someone else's problem, and it caused me to prioritise it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1265585499500089344"&gt;I suggested recently to Luli&lt;/a&gt; that two good books about being selfish were "The Courage to be Disliked" and "Conflict is not Abuse". I feel it's kinda telling that both of my book recommendations about how to be selfish were about how to have healthier relationships with others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think perhaps the problem starts with how we conceptualise selfishness, and the idea of boundaries. Boundaries are things you put there to defend yourself. Defending yourself is good and proper and you have a right to do so,
so it's not hard to assert those rights. "You are hurting me. Stop." is not a complicated sentiment, and it's one that most healthy communities acknowledge a right to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But "acting to minimize suffering at the hands of others" isn't the hard part for me. I've had a lot of training in that one I'm afraid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The question is, what's next? Minimizing suffering doesn't lead to happiness, it just leads to non-suffering. Neutrality isn't that great. There's a reason "emotional blunting" is a diagnostic term.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think part of why I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-27-07:21.html"&gt;got quite so cranky at the inner game of tennis&lt;/a&gt; is the idea that you can just turn off the verbal self and the embodied self will rise to the occasion because it's fundamentally fine. The embodied self &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; fine sometimes. Sometimes you need to coax it out of its shell.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://clarissalittler.github.io/2020/05/28/feelings-of-being-final.html"&gt;Clarissa wrote about horizonal damage earlier&lt;/a&gt; and this feels fairly apt. My experience is different from theirs, but the space of the possible is constrained.
I can be selfish or unselfish in my interaction with others, but I can't really at present see how to be self-oriented.
I am aware of it as a theoretical possibility, but it does not appear as a practical orientation in the world that I can access.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had some more thoguhts but it's late and I should go to bed before this gets even more angsty, so I'm going to leave it there.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-28-21:05.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-29-05:46.html</id>
    <title>Defects are the responsibility of programmers</title>
    <updated>2020-05-29T08:34:06+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Defects are the responsibility of programmers&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This post is an elaboration on a &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1265967699743649793"&gt;Twitter thread about software I did yesterday&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hillel wrote &lt;a href="https://buttondown.email/hillelwayne/archive/defects-are-not-the-fault-of-programmers/"&gt;Defects are not the fault of programmers&lt;/a&gt;. It is a good post and I encourage you to read it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, the bigger issue with programmers create defects is an essential issue with the worldview. Its basis in facts is less important than its value as a lens we can use to understand defects. If we know where defects come from, we know what we need to do to manage them. To emphasize this: Our worldview on defects shapes our means of reducing defects. We measure the value of a lens by how useful it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does the defects are the fault of programmers worldview tell us about our means? It says that the only way to reduce defects is to improve programmer discipline. Either the programmer is sufficiently disciplined and nothing can cause defects, or the programmer is insufficiently disciplined and nothing can prevent defects. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd like to argue that Hillel is mostly correct, but bugs should &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; be considered the fault of the programmers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd also like to argue that the idea that bugs are the fault of the programmer, as implemented in practice, is in fact &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; worse than Hillel is making it out to be. The worst part of "defects are the fault of the programmer" is not that it doesn't help us to reduce defects, but that in fact that over time it virtually guarantees to increase them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A software development process is not just there to produce software, it's also there to produce a software development team, and in order to understand the effect of any given process you need to consider its effect on both. Systems which have positive effects on the software while having negative effects on the team, will, in the long run (which often is not that long - a year or two if often more than enough) end up backfiring horribly on the software as well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular, defects are a normal part of the software development process. People make mistakes, people misunderstand things. If you've never had a bug in production then that's probably because nobody is using your software or you spend &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; too long developing it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So independently of the question of whose &lt;em&gt;fault&lt;/em&gt; a defect is, the more important question is: When a defect occurs, does your software development team get better or worse?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd like to suggest that any system that relies &lt;em&gt;solely&lt;/em&gt; on personal responsibility will get worse in response to bugs, but so will any system that treats bugs as not the programmer's fault.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ideally we want people to take responsibility for shipping high quality software. The basic problem is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If people don't care about getting good results, there is no system that will get good results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If people do care about getting good results, basically every system works well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The system you choose determines which of these scenarios are stable states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular if a system &lt;em&gt;relies&lt;/em&gt; on people caring about getting good results, in the absence of support for that, you will &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;burn out the people who care the most&lt;/a&gt;, they will stop caring and/or leave, and you will end up with a team that doesn't care about getting good results.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the easiest ways to create this dynamic is to have a culture of personal responsibility for defects while pressuring people to ship, and providing no collective support for what to do in the event of failure.
If you treat "defects are the programmer's fault" as your guiding correctness principle, you will end up with a team whose response to that is "Yeah, but who cares?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; if you treat defects as intrinsically not the programmer's fault, you do this. "Human error" is a bad attribution in that you can always find a human to blame, but "System error" is also a bad attribution because you can always find a system to blame. Humans in the system are what create performance as well as defects, and if you treat humans as &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; the problem, what you end up with is &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/14773996.2018.1491147?journalCode=tphs20"&gt;safety clutter&lt;/a&gt; where people's hands are tied.
And, once again, people will tend to get frustrated ane leave. They won't necessarily be the same people as left in the other scenario, but having a team full of people who are entirely comfortable with plodding bureaucratic slowness at every step of the way is also not a great end state.
A key part of getting good results is that you have to get results.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I would suggest that a crucial part of getting to a system that creates a good team is that &lt;em&gt;guilt&lt;/em&gt;. When something goes wrong, the person responsible should feel appropriately guilty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem with this is that we are all very bad at guilt.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yes, I can hear you thinking "Oh don't worry David, I'm &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good at guilt". That is exactly the problem I am talking about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being good at guilt doesn't mean feeling a lot of guilt. It means feeling an appropriate amount of guilt, which can range from "Oops, my bad" to "Yeah that was a massive fuck up on my part. I'll make it right".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem we collectively have with guilt, both in terms of how we experience it and how we inflict it on others, is that we treat it as a binary with very little between no guilt and massive irredeemable shame. This is intrinsically unhealthy. Guilt, properly handled, is an acknowledgement that you have done badly and an impetus to do better. It cannot serve that function as we currently manage it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second crucial part of getting to a system that creates a good team is that "I'll make it right" part.
If people feel guilty but are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; empowered to fix it, then you once again end up in the situation where everyone who cares burns out and/or leaves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes that empowerment to make it right will consist of the programmer, as an individual, resolving and learning to do better. Sometimes it will be about changing the system. Sometimes they'll be able to manage it on their own, sometimes they'll need support.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is, sadly, no universal prescription that works. The world is messy and complicated. But if you give people the support they need to do better, and create a system that tends to improve rather than degrade the moral, emotional, and professional skills of its members, and responds healthily to the normal trials and tribulations that the world has to throw at it, it will probably go pretty well for you.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-29-05:46.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-30-13:17.html</id>
    <title>Knowing what to look for</title>
    <updated>2020-05-30T13:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Knowing what to look for&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-30&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(A short post today because I have run out of brain)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3d3M3vs"&gt;Finding Our Sea-Legs&lt;/a&gt; by Will Buckingham, page 69:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were to travel to Japan and stand before Mount Fuji, I would do so not with an attentiveness born of bare seeing, but with an attentiveness made keen by my love of Hokusai's prints. I would see the mountain with the care and the love that comes from knowing it is precisely &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; mountain, and not some other, before which I stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This ties interestingly in to my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-26-06:22.html"&gt;previous post about visual hermeneutics&lt;/a&gt;. Because Buckingham has prior context the mountain, that causes him to interpret it in a particular way - he feels certain things about it, but also he attends to it differently. He knows things about it, and his eye is trained to look for them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think we often have a broken intuitive model of how vision works. Vision is not actually us statically observing what is there. It is an active, engaged, process, where our eye looks for and tracks certain details. Your visual field is mostly incredibly blurry, outside of a very narrow range, but your eyes dart around picking out detail wherever you're paying attention to so you mostly don't notice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means that interpretation isn't just a matter of post-processing after you've seen an image, it determines where you focus your attention, so it literally changes what you see.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-30-13:17.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
