<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2024-01-11T08:07:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-02-12:56.html</id>
    <title>Is philosophy bad?</title>
    <updated>2024-01-02T13:05:54+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Is philosophy bad?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a draft bankruptcy piece. It contains a few interesting
things, but I abandoned it because it fundamentally didn’t work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I threatened to write “Contra David Chapman on Philosophy” as a
response to David’s repeated insistence that philosophy is bad. This
piece isn’t exactly that, but it’s not exactly not that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="chavid-dapman-on-philosophy"&gt;Chavid Dapman on Philosophy&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Allow me to introduce my correspondent for this piece, Chavid Dapman.
Chavid is a fictional character created by Claude to approximate David
Chapman’s opinions on the subject. Given real world David Chapman’s
opinions on AI, this is probably a very irritating thing of me to do.
Sorry, David.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to inform Claude when I think Chavid says something that
David wouldn’t, but this is an imperfect process. As Claude would put
it, “Chavid Dapman is a fictional character created for narrative
purposes. His critical opinions on philosophy should not be taken as
precisely representative of thinker David Chapman’s more nuanced
perspectives.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here is Chavid’s opinion on philosophy:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophy is an intellectual tradition that aims to find absolute
answers to questions about life, knowledge, ethics, and existence
through logic, thought experiments and reasoning. However, after
thousands of years, philosophy has failed to deliver definitive answers,
especially compared to the progress of science. Logic and thought
experiments have clear limits. And philosophy tends to neglect empirical
research and interactive empiricism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the deeper issue is that philosophy pursues misguided questions
based on false assumptions, such as: What constitutes a good life? What
is the meaning of existence? What is human consciousness? The search for
abstract absolute answers presumes these are coherent topics, when they
are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophy goes astray in seeking universal essences, rather than
understanding experience as an ongoing, embodied process. Contemplating
pseudoproblems based on flawed metaphysics cannot elucidate anything. We
should reject the search for absolute abstract answers and eternal
philosophical truths. Philosophy needs to engage the physical world
pragmatically and empirically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Editor’s note: I ran this by actual David Chapman and he doesn’t
think it reflects his views at all and is instead a generic and not
terribly well thought out critique. I agree.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="i-like-philosophy"&gt;I like philosophy&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let’s just get this out of the way: I like philosophy, and I get a
lot out of it. Reading philosophy has been significantly life improving
for me, and informed a lot of my thinking. This makes it hard for me to
accept a blanket “philosophy is bad” claim when a lot of philosophy is
clearly good for me, and I’m writing from that perspective.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s also plenty of philosophy I dislike. Frankly, it’s almost
impossible to like a thing without this being true, because almost
everything has good and bad examples, and also examples that are and
aren’t to your tastes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think one of the differences between Chavids opinions of philosophy
and mine are quite straightforwardly that I tend to think of the
examples of philosophy that I like as sufficient evidence that
philosophy is good, and Chavid tends to think of the examples of
philosophy that he doesn’t like as sufficient evidence that philosophy
is bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This disagreement is partly what Adam Mastroianni calls a &lt;a href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/science-is-a-strong-link-problem"&gt;strong
vs weak link problem&lt;/a&gt;. Some things are as strong as their weakest
link, some as their strongest. With science (in Mastroianni’s example),
progress doesn’t really depend on the worst science we’re doing but the
best. I think the same is true of philosophy: Although there are many
bad (both by my standards and theirs) examples of philosophy, there are
also many good examples, and you can get value out of the good examples
and mostly ignore the bad ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Chavid is basically right in saying that “a good life” is a
bad abstraction (although I’m sympathetic to what happens to the
question when you verb it, which is “How can you live well?” rather than
“What is a good life?” - I think this is hard to answer, but worthwhile
engaging with), but also this is almost never the sort of philosophy I
read.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, here are two examples of philosophy I’ve got a lot out
of:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“Games: Agency as Art” by C Thi Nguyen is a book about games, and
what the fact that we play games tells us about humanity, and defending
them as a distinctive form of art whose medium is constructing
structures of agency. This book isn’t “empirical” in the sense that it
gathers a lot of data, but is deeply engaged in the world by basically
centring its philosophy on many games Nguyen has played.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“Epistemic Injustice” by Miranda Fricker is a book about ethics that
consists of looking at a bunch of examples of things that are bad and
saying “these seem to have some sort of shared distinctive character.
What is it?”. Many of these examples are fictional, but even those feel
like they connect to plausible shared experiences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are examples for me of the sort of thing philosophy really
shines at: Pointing at something specific and going “There’s something
interesting here. What is it?”. They don’t go astray into big abstract
questions, but they use the same sort of methods that philosophers tend
to engage with big abstract questions on and focus them on something
specific and try to clarify our engagement with them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="where-was-this-going"&gt;Where was this going?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That was the point at which I abandoned this. I would still like to
write a pro philosophy piece, but I think arguing against David
Chapman’s views on it is the wrong way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I like Joe Carlsmith’s &lt;a href="https://joecarlsmith.com/2023/02/17/seeing-more-whole"&gt;Seeing More
Whole&lt;/a&gt; viewpoint, which is (in very brief summary) that philosophy is
about using logical reasoning to discover what sorts of person it is
possible to be. This seems an important viewpoint to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve previously ha-ha-only-serious joked that the fundamental
philosophical question is “That’s weird, right? You get that that’s
weird?”. I think the big thing that I get out of good philosophy is that
it forces you to actually look at the details of life and how it works,
rather than implicitly skipping over the bits that don’t make sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn’t the first time I’ve tried to write that piece. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:43.html"&gt;How to
use philosophy&lt;/a&gt; is another similarly brief draft bankruptcy piece
trying to do much the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/reading-philosophy-for-the-examples"&gt;Reading
Philosophy for the Examples&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-use-thought-experiments"&gt;How
to use thought experiments&lt;/a&gt; maybe capture this better. Perhaps part
of the problem is that I’ve tried to do too much with this topic and it
needs something larger if I’m to write the whole thing. Or maybe just
many smaller things.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-02-12:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-03-10:13.html</id>
    <title>Some Philosophy of Mathematics</title>
    <updated>2024-01-03T13:26:05+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Some Philosophy of Mathematics&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is another draft bankruptcy piece, pulled out of a random Google
doc. I think what I’ve got here is perfectly reasonable but it was an
overly ambitious project that I lost interest in finishing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s also my first attempt at moving my blog rendering over to
pandoc, so probably a whole bunch of things will break.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m going to be making a few sweeping generalisations about
philosophy of mathematics. I’m sure some of them don’t hold in complete
generality. I’m trying to convey the sense of what mathematics&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Especially modernish mathematics. I think most of what
I’m saying works as a description of historical mathematics, but it
certainly wouldn’t have been the way people thought about it prior to
some time in the 20th century.&lt;/span&gt; is typically like rather than
attempting to come up with a grand unifying theory of mathematical
practice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This piece comes out of trying to explain a bit about mathematical
incompleteness to a philosopher and realising that the core problem in
explaining this is that the way we typically&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I don’t know how reliable my sense of how we typically
present axioms is and was worried this might be a &lt;a href="https://www.lisamcnulty.co.uk/essays/phantom-opinions"&gt;phantom
opinion&lt;/a&gt;, so I checked and it’s not. I did some casual googling,
checked Wikipedia, and asked ChatGPT which is usually a pretty good
representation of the sort of the typical but oversimplified vox populi
opinion on things. I also &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1713814331224170566"&gt;did some
polling on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and I think most of the answers are confusing in
the relevant way. I think that my view is probably relatively typical
among working mathematicians, but not of how we talk about mathematics
to non-mathematicians.&lt;/span&gt;
present axioms philosophically is unhelpful for understanding what’s
going on in mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, let’s fix this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="what-are-axioms"&gt;What are axioms?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Axioms are things that we take to be true, but they are things we
take to be true in the sense that “a bachelor is an unmarried man” or “a
bishop moves any number of vacant squares diagonally”. They are not
taken to be true in the sense that they represent deep truths about the
universe that we have no way to prove but wholeheartedly believe&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is one potential source of axioms of course, as the
universe is one of the things we want to reason about, but it is not
what axioms &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;, they are taken to be true in the
sense that they represent defining properties of the class of thing we
are interested in talking about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For this to make sense, we need to realise that mathematics isn’t
really about proofs, it’s about &lt;em&gt;things&lt;/em&gt;, “mathematical objects”.
Proofs are for discovering properties of mathematical objects. They say:
“Suppose I’ve got some object and it has these properties. What else do
I know about it?”. Those properties are the axioms, but you’re not
“assuming” that the object has those properties in the sense that they
are things that might be false but you’re postulating for now, those
properties define the class of object that you are interested in talking
about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, most people think of axioms as things that are “self
evidently true” or, slightly more accurately, “assumptions”, but this
immediately invites the question “But what if your assumptions are
wrong?” or “How do you &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; your axioms are true?”&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;These questions are not meaningless or bad necessarily,
but they’re usually asked in the wrong place.&lt;/span&gt;. With axioms as picking out objects
of interest, these problems go away - you can argue about whether the
objects in question are interesting or whether any examples of them
exist (“exist” is complicated. More on that later), but not whether the
axioms are true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the easiest places to see how this works is with the
mathematics of games, because there the axioms are just the
&lt;em&gt;constitutive rules&lt;/em&gt; of the game. You can do mathematics around
games of chess (e.g. “From this position, can checkmate be forced in 5
moves?” is implicitly a mathematical sort of question), and in asking
this question you are restricted to the sort of moves that chess allows.
If you were playing with a different rule set, the conclusion might be
different, but that doesn’t mean that the two conclusions are
incompatible, they’re just about different games.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another, more historical, example is the parallel postulate and the
axioms of geometry. Simplified version: Euclid came up with a set of
axioms for geometry, describing how points, lines, and circles worked.
There were a bunch of perfectly sensible axioms, and then there was the
rather awkward &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parallel_postulate"&gt;Parallel
Postulate&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Note: This is all somewhat ahistorical and simplified
for illustrative purposes. Euclid’s account of geometry wasn’t fully
axiomatic, and the version of the parallel postulate stated is not
Euclid’s original and is only equivalent to it given the other axioms.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a plane, given a line and a point not on it, at most one line
parallel to the given line can be drawn through the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People spent ages trying to prove the parallel postulate from the
other axioms, and then someone pointed out that &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spherical_geometry"&gt;Spherical
Geometry&lt;/a&gt; demonstrated that you couldn’t do this: If you take a
sphere and interpret “line” as meaning “great circle” (a circle on the
surface of the sphere whose centre is the centre of the sphere. e.g the
equator, or a line of longitude, but not in general a line of latitude
because those are “off centre” for the sphere), you get something that
satisfies all the basic axioms of geometry but for which the parallel
postulate is false (because there are no parallel lines, because all
great circles intersect at two points on the sphere).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you think of geometry as trying to derive universal truths of
geometry, this information can be very distressing. How do you know
which axioms to use?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If, on the other hand, you instead think of there being such a thing
as &lt;em&gt;a geometry&lt;/em&gt; then all you’re trying to do is figure out
properties of particular geometries of interest, and you can pick
whichever one you want to work on. Sometimes you might want to work with
a Euclidean geometry, sometimes you might want to work with a spherical
geometry. It’s up to you! They’re both equally valid mathematical
objects for doing geometry on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="what-are-mathematical-objects"&gt;What are mathematical
objects?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If axioms pick out which mathematical objects we are talking about,
we need to follow this by answering a much harder question: What are
mathematical objects?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I need to start with a slightly slippery mathematician’s definition:
Mathematical objects are the things you can do proofs about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This definition is actually quite useful, because it highlights an
important point of this conception of axioms: It’s actually slightly
agnostic to foundational questions like this. As long as there is
something called a mathematical object and you can do proofs about it,
this notion of axiom is useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular, consider two&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Slightly strawman versions of these positions, but I
think morally accurate.&lt;/span&gt; conceptions of
mathematical foundations:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mathematics is reasoning about real entities that exist in some
sort of abstract platonic realm of ideal forms (&lt;strong&gt;Mathematical
platonism&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mathematics is a purely formal game of manipulating symbols
representing purely formal entities according to agreed upon rules,
which can be put in correspondence with real entities but do not
intrinsically correspond to things that “exist”. (&lt;strong&gt;Mathematical
formalism&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mathematicians often behave liked platonists but fall back on
formalism as a sort of philosophical justification.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A third competing view that I like is Reuben Hersch’s definition of
mathematical objects as “socio-historical objects”. Things that only
exist because we, as people doing mathematics, agree they exist,
similarly to other things like money, rules, games.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is mostly right, but I’d like to propose a slight
refinement: Mathematical objects are things that we agree to &lt;em&gt;behave
as if they existed&lt;/em&gt; because doing so allows us to do mathematics,
and mathematics is useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this makes sense of why, regardless of what they believe
about foundations, mathematicians in practice behave more like
platonists: Regardless of whether mathematical objects “actually exist”,
mathematics is done by behaving &lt;em&gt;as if&lt;/em&gt; mathematical objects
exist, and proceeding from that starting point to reason about what they
should be like.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In this view, mathematics is a ritual practice in the
sense of Seligman et al’s “Ritual and its Consequences”. It is the
creation of a &lt;em&gt;subjunctive world&lt;/em&gt; in which certain rules and
claims are treated as inviolable properties of the ritual space, because
doing so allows the ritual to occur, which is desirable for its
non-ritual consequences. e.g. politeness norms are viewed as a ritual in
this sense, because maintaining them allows for civil interactions which
everyone enjoys. In practice they are not inviolable, but if everyone
treats them as such they are not violated and thus you get to operate in
a world where you can trust them as if they were inviolable.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I sometimes joke that the formalists are right that mathematics is a
game, but it’s not a purely symbolic one, it’s an RPG set in the
Platonic realm. We are reasoning about some world that we agree to
behave as if it existed, contained certain objects, and was subject to
logical reasoning of the sort that we would expect to hold in the real
world.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is a nontrivial constraint on a hypothetical world.
e.g. fairy tales have a logic of their own, but it is not a simple if A
then B sort of logical reasoning you can count on. The realm in which
mathematical objects exist is posited to be one that makes sense.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This still leaves us to ask: What sort of mathematical objects do we
posit exist? Fictional worlds are very different depending on the world
building you’ve done for them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Generally mathematical objects are one of two types:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something we’ve built as an abstracted and generalised version of
something in the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something we’ve built out of other mathematical objects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often it’s both: When we build mathematical objects, we’re usually
doing them for some purpose, and that purpose is often to represent
something that in some way looks like the real world. This helps us
avoid positing too many “primitive” mathematical objects - the building
blocks of our mathematical world&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn9"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn9" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Which we want to do because every primitive mathematical
object is a sort of leap of faith as to whether the rules actually make
sense.&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The classic example of something which is purely built as an
abstracted and generalised version of something in the physical world is
a natural (counting) number. The numbers 0, 1, 2, … are mathematical
objects that we just assume exist&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn10"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn10" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In fact, in modern (i.e. dating from the early 20th
century) we construct these too out of other mathematical objects - sets
- but you can do the mathematics of numbers without doing the
mathematics of sets, and numbers are in some sense “more basic” to
mathematics.&lt;/span&gt; in our mathematical
world, according to the following rules for constructing them:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a number 0.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If there is a number n, there is a next number immediately after
it (n + 1, although we want to do this before we’ve defined addition so
this is usually written S(n), for successor of n).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We then agree that these mathematical objects satisfy what we think
of as the idealised rules of counting numbers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These counting numbers are abstract in the following sense: There is
no way to point to the number four. You can point to four rocks, four
caling birds, four tally marks. You can point to the arabic number 4, or
the roman numeral IV. These all in some sense “represent” the number
four (as does the word “four”), but they are not the mathematical object
four, they are a real object that in some sense has fourness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These counting numbers are also generalised, in that we posit the
existence of mathematical numbers that have no corresponding real world
counted quantity. Why? Well, it follows from the rules we have for
counting numbers (which I haven’t spelled out, but it does I promise)
that if n exists then so does 10n. But that means that 10 exists, 100
exists, 1,000,000 exists… &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(10^{10000000000}\)&lt;/span&gt; also exists, which is
vastly more things to count than there are atoms in the universe. In the
real world, you can’t count that high. In the mathematical world, no
problem at all.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn11"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn11" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And there are sometimes reasons to, even if you only
care about real world countable quantities! Sometimes you want to prove
a mathematical result and it requires you to e.g. look at all the
subsets of some set of a reasonable size. Although 1,000,000 is a
perfectly reasonable number, &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(2^{1000000}\)&lt;/span&gt; is again more than the atoms
of the universe. From a mathematical point of view, proving results that
use that number are completely legitimate, even if it has no physical
analogue.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another, more concrete, example of a mathematical object that allows
us to avoid concerns about infinity&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn12"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn12" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And concern ourselves with the merely very large.&lt;/span&gt; is the mathematical
objects corresponding to &lt;em&gt;game states&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Consider a game of chess, with the pieces on the board somewhere.
Suppose you nudge a piece slightly, keeping it in the same square but
just shifting it slightly to the left. In one sense, you’ve changed the
state of the board - a piece is in a different location. But, from the
point of view of a game of chess, you have not made a change&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn13"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn13" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In tournament rules you may have committed yourself to
moving this piece, but the point remains: If you moved this piece to
that square prior to nudging it, that makes no difference.&lt;/span&gt;, because all that matters is which
square the piece is in, not exactly where it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if you were to take another chess board and set and place
the pieces from that set in the same squares as they were in the
original board, this would represent the same game of chess. This is
true even if one board is physical and the other electronic. You could
even copy the chess board position onto paper by hand - either as a
picture, or as a list of positions in a standard chess notation. These
would all represent the same game of chess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although chess is a game whose state is represented by physical
objects (which might be a physical chess board, might be a computer,
might even be solely in the heads of the participants!), chess is played
as the &lt;em&gt;abstract game state &lt;/em&gt;- all that matters is the chess
position, which is represented by the physical object but not synonymous
with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One important feature of this is that not all physical arrangements
of a chess board have a corresponding abstract chess state. e.g. you
could have a piece halfway between two squares. You could have a board
with no kings. These are not valid chess states, they’re just things you
can do with the physical chess board.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, you’ve got the rules of chess which describe how abstract
chess states are transformed into each other. Nothing stops you
physically violating these rules - you can pick someone’s king up and
throw it across the room, you can steal their pawn while they’re not
looking, nothing stops you from doing these things, except the fact that
in doing them you are no longer playing chess. The rules of chess exist
precisely in order to enable you to play chess, and violating the rules
means that this is not a game of chess.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn14"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn14" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Some games do explicitly allow cheating as part of the
game, but that doesn’t change the basic point, it’s just a more
complicated ruleset.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These abstract chess states and the rules for moving between them are
mathematical objects that exist in the same sort of “mathematical realm”
as numbers. You can also do mathematics to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, the question “Is a checkmate guaranteed for white from
this position?” is a mathematical question. You are trying to reason
about whether white has a strategy that guarantees that all series of
moves from the current chess position result in a checkmate for
white.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although this mathematical question nominally answers a question
about real games of chess being played by the players, it differs in
several ways:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t describe anything about the game other than the
abstract states - you don’t know how the players physically move around
the board, their emotional states, etc. None of these are considered
relevant to or part of the mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has the same sort of unboundedness problem that counting
numbers do. This question actually does have a definite answer, but the
definite answer might require considering &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(2^{2048}\)&lt;/span&gt; different chess positions to
reach.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn15"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn15" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Actually much less than that, because not all of those
chess positions are in fact possible, but even a 100-order of magnitude
reduction makes this an impossibly large number of states.&lt;/span&gt; While in theory this is a finite
number with a definite answer, there’s no guarantee we can calculate
it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3 id="detritus"&gt;Detritus&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Editor’s note: This was a section with random cuttings that had been
removed from the text elsewhere because it didn’t fit the flow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the most important features of this explanation is that it
makes much more sense of the social role of axioms. If axioms are
universal truths then they arrive through some sort of deep a priori
knowledge or divine revelation or something, but if axioms just pick out
the objects you’re talking about they arrive in a much more
straightforward way: Someone picks up a mathematical object and goes
“Hey, look at this thing! Interesting, innit?” and then proceeds to try
to describe what’s interesting about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You have to do a bit of fiddling around to figure out which
properties of the object you do and don’t care about, and what a good
set of axioms to represent them are, but that’s just work, it’s not
anything particularly mysterious you just have to come up with a good
design. Once you’ve identified an object, or some objects, of interest,
you can just axiomatise them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This helpfully reduces the question “Where do axioms come from?” to
the much harder question “Where do mathematical objects come from?”,
which in turn first requires us to&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there are roughly two sources for mathematical objects:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We make them out of other mathematical objects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We abstract them from real things (which may be physical objects,
properties of such objects, processes, etc).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can do the first because (I have no idea how I was intending to
continue this sentence).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="reflections"&gt;Reflections&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I often find that there’s a large body of understanding that lives in
my head and that I think is more sensible than how other people seem to
view it, but when it comes time to try to explain it I find it’s all too
interconnected to be worth the effort of explaining unless there’s some
really clear goal to it. This was one of those times.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’d like a solution to this problem, but I’m not sure there is a
solution other than to accept my own mortality and finite energy
reserves and not worry so much about other people being wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-03-10:13.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-04-10:02.html</id>
    <title>Honesty is kinder than lying</title>
    <updated>2024-01-04T11:26:13+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Honesty is kinder than lying&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another draft bankruptcy post. This is one of those posts that I
started writing because I was annoyed about something (I forget what, I
don’t think it’s present anywhere in the text), and stopped writing when
I lost steam on that annoyance. I still think it’s important and worth
saying, but I lost the impetus to keep saying it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Advance warning: I am not pulling any punches in this post.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="do-you-want-impostor-syndrome-because-thats-how-you-get-impostor-syndrome."&gt;Do
you want impostor syndrome? Because that’s how you get impostor
syndrome.&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For various reasons I’ve been thinking recently about something I
helped a client with a while ago.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Details slightly altered and kept vague for
confidentiality reasons.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Roughly the scenario they found themselves in was this: Someone new
had joined their staff, and this person wasn’t &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; at their
job, but they were very slow at it, taking much longer to complete basic
tasks than seemed reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More, this person knew it, and was clearly very bothered by it, and
kept apologising for it. My client kept reassuring them that this was
fine and it was normal to take a while to get started. This didn’t seem
to help, and they kept being anxious about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, a couple of months of this had passed and my client now had a
problem: Their staff member was &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; too slow at their job. It
could no longer be written off as just slowness getting up to speed,
they actually weren’t fast enough at the job to keep up with the needed
workload, and weren’t showing any signs of improvement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m reasonably confident that the problem isn’t that the client’s
expectations were unreasonable. We talked a bit about it and it was a
set of requirements that it was perfectly normal to expect a person to
be able to do, nothing terribly out of the ordinary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I’m &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; sure about is whether in an alternate history
their subordinate could have been capable of doing the job at that
point. Certainly in this history they weren’t.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Unfortunately I also don’t know if they became so. Due
to a mix of funding changes at the client’s company and me winding down
that part of my business, this was only a month or two before my last
session with that client, so I don’t know how the story ends. It doesn’t
matter for the point I’m making though.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And part of why they weren’t is that my client had, bluntly&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Somewhat more bluntly than I put it at the time,
although I think I was at least clear about what they’d done wrong.&lt;/span&gt; spent the last couple of months
lying to them about their performance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t the client’s fault. It’s what we’re all trained to do.
When someone is expressing anxiety, you reassure them that the thing
they’re anxious about couldn’t possibly happen and everything will be
fine. When someone is expressing guilt about how they fucked up, you
tell them that it’s not their fault and there’s nothing they could have
done. There’s this deep seated cultural assumption that the way to be
kind to people is that you lie to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I hate this and think it’s a travesty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of honesty, I will admit that I do this sometimes. Much
much less than most people do, I think, but it’s hard not to. There are
a lot of forces pushing you to do it. When I find myself doing it, I try
to learn from that and do better in future.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a similar spirit of honesty, I know that you probably do this too,
and I’m &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/just-disappointed"&gt;disappointed&lt;/a&gt;
in you for doing so. I would like you to do better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason we all lie to each other like this is often framed as
kindness. I don’t think it is. I think it’s a form of cowardice. Honesty
has consequences that we have to own in a way that dishonesty would not.
If we speak the truth, we are responsible for any hurt inflicted, and
might have to face the other’s negative reaction to our words. If we
tell a nice lie we are not responsible when the problem we are lying
about inevitably has consequences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doing better requires both the courage to face those consequences,
and a sense of responsibility for events that are not our “fault” that
everyone is keen to disavow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The correct way to handle something like my client’s situation is, in
my opinion, to say something along the lines of: Yes, you’re
underperforming compared to what I’d hope for. It’s not a problem yet,
but if it continues it will become one. I’ve got your back in trying to
prevent that. Let’s figure out together what you need to solve this
problem and do our best to get it for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, taking on a lot of work, and it’s also taking on
a lot of responsibility. Now in the quite likely&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;A sad reality is that many people are in fact not good
enough at the jobs they’ve been hired to do, for reasons that are
outside of anyone’s power to fix, or at least to fix fast enough to be
viable. When this happens it’s important to treat them well, but it’s
also important to not retain them in that role.&lt;/span&gt;
event that their subordinate failed to perform and had to be let go at
the end of their probation period, it would be in part be because they
had failed to help them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Depending on how much capacity is available, that might not be an
option. I was talking to a friend recently about their company’s
situation and he was in a similar position but absolutely didn’t have
the capacity spare to help the person in question learn to perform at
the level he needed (and suspected that they couldn’t or wouldn’t
anyway).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In such a circumstance I honestly think the kindest thing to say to
someone is something along the lines of: Look, this is what we need, and
the fact that you can’t give it is a problem. If you’re willing to take
responsibility for stepping up, we’re happy to give you the space you
need to do that, and can make some changes to support that but cannot
commit a lot of resources. What do you want to do?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sucks to hear and it sucks to say. This is not going to be an
easy conversation&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And in this particular example and depending on where
you are can run into employment law complications. Not legal advice
etc.&lt;/span&gt;, but it is necessary, and the
results of not having it are worse. Again, this is why I think avoiding
conversations like this is a form of moral cowardice. Not having these
conversations allows you to pretend that the failure is not your
responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="you-shouldnt-lie-to-your-friends"&gt;You shouldn’t lie to your
friends&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I don’t care that much about the employment example right
now. It’s important, but it’s not why this has been on my mind.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was talking to some friends recently about the advice “when you
find yourself beating yourself up over something, imagine you’re talking
to a friend or loved one and ask if you would talk to them that
way”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the objections to this advice raised is that when talking to a
friend or loved one you will tend to lie to them in the ways I’ve been
discussing. You diminish the degree to which the situation is their
fault, you downplay the possibility of bad consequences. This feels fine
to do to a friend, but bad to do to yourself because you can see through
the ruse.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This objection is a commendable level of self honesty&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although I think self honesty of this form is often too
“brutal honesty”.&lt;/span&gt;,
but also reveals how much we let our friends down.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because here’s the thing: Your friends can see through the ruse too.
The thing about having a social norm of lying to people is that
&lt;em&gt;everybody knows you lie to people in this way&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recall the example of my client. One of the problems with lying to
his subordinate is that it didn’t give them the support they needed to
improve. But it &lt;em&gt;also didn’t make them less anxious&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And of course it didn’t. If people are going to tell you that
something isn’t a problem even when it’s a problem, you can’t trust that
reassurance at all, so why would it help?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you want to be able to reassure people that something isn’t a
problem when it’s not a problem, they need to be able to believe that
you would tell them that it’s a problem if it were one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can achieve this belief in one of three ways:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be true.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They can have poor judgement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They can lie to themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is, when you lie to people, you either fail to help them, or you
make them complicit in the lie, and at some level that’s hard to
maintain, and it’s bad for them and it’s bad for the relationship.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="the-problem-of-brutal-honesty"&gt;The problem of brutal
honesty&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honesty has &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-28-10:26.html"&gt;a
differing thresholds problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I often get accused of being brutally honest. It’s certainly
sometimes true - I think this post is erring on the side of brutal
honesty, partly because I’m fed up and partly because I don’t think a
softer version would land - but I think actually most of the time I’m
&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; brutally honest, I’m just honest in situations where other
people wouldn’t be, and this rounds to brutal honesty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But my primary association with people who self describe as “brutally
honest” is that they tend to care more about the brutal part than the
honest part, and that when you are being “brutally honest” with someone
it tends to be more because you don’t care about their feelings&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Or do care about their feelings, in that you want them
to feel bad.&lt;/span&gt; than it is because you care about
telling them the truth.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;That doesn’t mean you’re necessarily &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;
telling them the truth, but it does usually mean that you’re telling
them only the bits of the truth that hurt the most.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think brutal honesty has a missing mood. Something along the lines
of “It is regrettable that I must hurt this person but the truth is in
this instance more important than their feelings”. Instead, the attitude
seems to be much more “truth hurts, suck it up”. This is not an attitude
I want to encourage.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="you-probably-shouldnt-lie-to-yourself-either"&gt;You probably
shouldn’t lie to yourself either&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why I’ve been thinking about this recently is that
I was talking about self-help books the other day, and realising that
there’s really one fundamental message that underlies the vast majority
of self help books.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s this: You know that problem you’ve been having? It’s not your
fault. You don’t have to feel bad about having it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes this is a useful message for people to hear, because it
lets them get a bit of emotional distance from the problem that they
need to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And if it helps them achieve that, and they then solve the problem,
(Editor’s note: I apparently stopped writing this post mid sentence
here).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="postscript"&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I should revisit this theme at some point as honesty is
somewhere where my moral intuitions seem to sharply differ from other
people’s, in a way that causes frictions when ~I’m right and they’re
wrong~ we have differing intuitions about how to e.g. answer a
question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do honestly think that my way is better. I’m not blind to its
downsides, and it requires skill to do well&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn9"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn9" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And sometimes I even have that skill!&lt;/span&gt;,
but I think the downsides of the status quo are much worse, and choosing
them feels like a sort of collective cowardice to me.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-04-10:02.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-05-11:11.html</id>
    <title>"placeholder"</title>
    <updated>2024-01-05T11:19:55+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;"placeholder"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;header id="title-block-header"&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;


&lt;h1 id="reason-as-a-moral-mechanism"&gt;Reason as a moral mechanism&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another draft bankruptcy post. This ended up being another
overambitious philosophy piece of the sort I haven’t really figured a
time or place to write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve since learned that these go better in a google doc. Maybe they’d
go better yet if I expanded my notebook site to have an essays section
now that I’ve got sidenotes and full pandoc support for references and
such.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Attention conservation notice: This piece is quite inside baseball. I
think it’s of interest to a general audience in where it ends up, which
is why it’s on the newsletter rather than the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/"&gt;notebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Editor’s note: lol never mind.&lt;/span&gt;,
but it &lt;em&gt;starts&lt;/em&gt; by arguing about the logical underpinnings of
Kantian ethics. You should not however require much philosophy
background to read it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m currently doing a read through of Velleman’s “Self to Self”. You
can follow along with my increasingly frustrated noises I make as I try
to decode it on &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLxO1bY9tS9Kr1gkHMPa0kaJtIIIKxJgzH"&gt;my
YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; (Editor’s note: I also abandoned this series and
project), but be warned the production quality is approximately zero
these are very much notes I am taking in my reading.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m mostly still stuck on chapter 1, which is his introduction to
Kantian ethics. I find the content a frustrating mix of tantalisingly
close to pointing at something important I’m missing and just wildly
wrong. This post is an attempt to explain some of my frustrations with
it, try to make sense of what it might mean, and reconstruct something
that I think actually works and is pointing roughly in the same
direction, but definitely isn’t what Kant or Velleman mean.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="why-should-i-act-according-to-reasons"&gt;Why should I act
according to reasons?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the core premises of Velleman’s account of Kantian ethics is
that we have a basic obligation to “act according to reasons”. He
justifies this as such:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where we previously asked “Why should I act on my desire?” let us now
ask “Why should I act for reasons?” Shouldn’t this question open up a
route of escape from &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; requirements?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as we ask why we should act for reasons, however, we can hear
something odd in our question. To ask “Why should I?” is to demand a
reason; and so to ask “Why should I act for reasons?” is to demand a
reason for acting for reasons. This demand implicitly concedes the very
authority that it purports to question – namely, the authority of
reasons. Why would we demand a reason if we didn’t envision acting for
it? If we really didn’t feel required to act for reasons, then a reason
for doing so certainly wouldn’t help. So there is something
self-defeating about asking for a reason to act for reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you’re like me, your response to this is something along the lines
of “What? No.” or possibly “What on earth are you talking about?”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This argument is too clever by half and relies in a fundamental way
on an ambiguity in the term “reason” that, once you resolve, causes the
argument to dissolve into uselessness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The ambiguity is this: When you ask “Why should I do the thing?” the
answer to this is an &lt;em&gt;explanation&lt;/em&gt; of why you should do the
thing&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; which may or may not itself be present prior to your
doing the thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An answer to the question “Why should I act according to reasons?” is
not necessarily providing the sort of reason that compels action,
because the answer is intrinsically descriptive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The core problem in all of this is that it is attempting to weasel
out of the normative content of a “should” resting on you actually
caring about something by trying to figure something that you logically
must care about. But you can just not do that - I don’t need a logical
argument to care about not being hurt for example, I can do things to
avoid pain without needing a compelling logical justification for this.
“Because if you don’t the reason fairy will appear and hit you with a
big stick” is a &lt;em&gt;perfectly logically consistent&lt;/em&gt; answer to “Why
should I act according to reasons?” that does not have any
circularity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It grounds out the authority of reasons in the authority of pain, but
that’s fine if you’re willing to accept an ethics for human beings who
don’t like pain rather than an ethics for perfectly spherical ethicists
in a vacuum. It is only circular if you think “Why should I act to
minimise pain?” roots the authority of pain in the authority of reasons,
but that’s not what that question means - it is asking for an
explanation, not delegating authority, because the avoidance of pain
already has authority over you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rest of the chapter tacitly acknowledges all of this by basically
trying to work through a set of reasons for acting for reasons, it just
can’t say out loud because it’s built on this premise that reasons are
an inescapable&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In general the idea of escapability of authority in
Velleman’s account of Kantian ethics seems (Editor’s note: What does it
seem?? I apparently left this sentence hanging)&lt;/span&gt; source of authority.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a shame, because I think the actual source of the authority
of reasons is much more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="what-does-any-of-this-even-mean"&gt;What does any of this even
mean?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Velleman considers the meaning of “act according to reasons”
self-explanatory, but I think it’s not just not self-explanatory but
borders on meaningless given the ambiguity of the word “reasons”. If a
“reason” is a thing that causes something, then the obligation is
tautologically satisfied - all your actions are caused by something. If
a “reason” is a verbal explanation of why things happened as they did,
then it will generally come after the fact rather than prior to it -
almost everything we do well, we do without a significant amount of
verbal reasoning prior to it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;For an elaboration on this last point, I recommend “The
Enigma of Reason” by Dan Sperber and Hugo Mercier, and “Sources of
Power” by Gary Klein&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Throughout, I will use “&lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt;” to mean something
like “verbal causal explanation” - i.e. something you would say in
answer to a “Why?” question. I will use &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt; to
refer to something like… the state of the world that lead to a
particular outcome, a set of conditions which would lead to the same
outcome reliably. A &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; is a &lt;em&gt;necessarily
incomplete&lt;/em&gt; description of the &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’m using bold here to indicate that I intend these to
be precise terms which are compatible with but more specific than
colloquial meanings. When I use a bolded term without bolding I will
usually be referring to someone else using the colloquial word. Or I
forgot.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly, &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; are not normally present in our
mind at the point of action (they can be, but not necessarily). So when
you are acting “according” to a &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt;, in that the
reason accurately describes the &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt;, that
reason is not itself &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of the &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt;.
This is what I mean by the argument resting on an ambiguity: If you are
asking for a &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; to act in accordance with
&lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;, the fact that you can answer the question does
not create a circularity because your answer need not be part of the
&lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt; for acting for reasons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One easy way to see this is that often the &lt;strong&gt;actual
cause&lt;/strong&gt; exists prior to it being possible to give an explanation
for it. This is especially true for causes that are in some sense
physical. e.g. if you ask me why I’m not working my best today and I
have a low grade virus that is sapping my energy, that is part of the
&lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt; regardless of whether I know I have a
virus, or even have the concept of virus. Both “I have a virus” and “I
don’t know, I’m just not feeling it today” count as
&lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;. I could even answer “I’m lazy”, which would
arguably count as an incorrect &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, there is often far more &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; than
you are aware of in the moment, so you &lt;em&gt;could not&lt;/em&gt; have thought
of all the reasons in the time you had prior to action. Suppose you see
someone who has injured themself. You help them get to a safe place, and
then call the emergency services. Why did you do this? Because they were
hurt. Why is “because they were hurt” a sufficient
&lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt;? Because it’s morally the right thing to do. Why
must you do the morally right thing? Because I want to, and will feel
guilty if I don’t. Why would you feel guilty if you didn’t? Because I
was raised proper… etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a long chain of verbal &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; you can give
for this and &lt;em&gt;almost none of them went through your head when you
helped&lt;/em&gt;. You might have verbalised something like “Oh they’re
injured, I should help them”. Maybe you considered a couple arguments
and counter-arguments. But there was not a long chain of verbal
reasoning for why you should help them, the helping comes with an
immediacy of its own as the thing for you to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt; is thus not the reasons you give
for it, because those reasons were not present at the point of action.
The &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt; is necessarily something like “because
I am the kind of person who in these kinds of circumstances performs
these kinds of actions”, with the &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; attempting to
define some boundaries on all of those “kind of”s.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This should, I think, still be considered acting &lt;em&gt;according&lt;/em&gt;
to &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;, in that “I helped them because they were
hurt” is a &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; that accurately describes your
actions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, however, now a very weak requirement. All it demands is that
your actions be in some way comprehensible. “I helped him because his
shirt was yellow”, or “I helped him because I felt like it” are both
also potential &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;. This weakness is not a failing
of the Kantian account, which is in many ways all about deciding what
counts as a good &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; (although I think it is
incorrect in how it goes about doing this), it’s just important to point
out because we’re also going to need to strengthen it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two directions that I think are reasonable to strengthen it are as
follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You should be able to provide &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; for your
actions to peers (that it’s to peers will be significant later) who want
them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; should remain relatively stable,
in the sense that if they would apply in future then they should contain
to describe your actions, or you should be able to provide a
&lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; why they don’t.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What does “should” mean here? i.e. why should you act according to
&lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; in this sense? Kant and Velleman want this to
be through logical necessity, but I don’t think that’s valid, and I
think the weaker form that I am aiming at here is in many ways better.
It allows for more empirically accurate descriptions of how ethics
works, and in many cases by being weaker allows for stronger norms.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, my answer is that you should because life will go better for
you if you do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="norming-and-consequences"&gt;Norming and consequences&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things we do in our groups of peers is we create norms of
behaviour. What is, and isn’t, an acceptable to behave. We do this by
imposing consequences for that behaviour - we might chastise each other
for bad behaviour, withdraw future opportunities, etc. e.g. you might
not get a promotion if you behave badly at work, or you might just get
reprimanded the first time, in an extreme case you might get fired.
Similarly if you behave like a dick at a party I invited you to, you’re
not going to get invited back. Extreme cases might also include e.g.
physical violence, but most norming tends to be at least slightly more
subtle than this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Evaluating reasons is part of how we do this. When someone does
something, especially something we disapprove of, we will often ask why
they did it, and this factors in to our evaluation of their
behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;e.g. suppose we’re going to the movies together. I’m waiting for you
at the cinema and you never show, even by the time the movie was
supposed to have &lt;em&gt;ended&lt;/em&gt; let alone started. You’ve not sent me a
text, you’re not responding to mine. By default, I’m likely to be pretty
pissed off at you.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;There’s likely some cultural variation in this,
especially if you’re merely late - I’m a stickler for punctuality, but
know people from places where turning up an hour late is considered
completely normal. Regardless though, I’m not making a universal claim
that it is &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; to be pissed off about this, I’m saying that I
would be. Feel free to substitute your own example of someone letting
you down.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is likely that when we finally make contact, my first question is
going to be some variant on “What happened?” - I expect you to provide a
&lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; for the fact that you didn’t show when we’d
previously agreed to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Consider how I might respond differently to the following three
answers:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“I don’t know, no reason really, I just didn’t feel like it.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“I got the day wrong, was caught up in work, and didn’t hear the
notification and completely forgot.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“I was on my way here and there was someone in a terrible accident
and I had to stop and help and keep them conscious while waiting for the
ambulance.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These would change my response significantly. (1) would probably make
me &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; angry at you. (2) would probably reduce my anger a bit,
with how sorry you seemed about it and how many times you’d made this
sort of error error mattering more than the actual
&lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt;. (3) on the other hand my anger would probably
instantly evaporate, because I would agree that under these
circumstances that was completely the right thing to do. Indeed, if
instead you’d turned up and told me that there was such an accident but
you didn’t stop to help because it would make you late to the cinema,
I’d probably be angry at you for an entire different reason - of course
you shouldn’t prioritise going to the movies with me over helping
someone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this judgement is that we now have more context for the
action, and we can now ask not just how we feel about this particular
outcome, but how we feel about the process that lead to it. i.e. if
similar circumstances were to occur again, and you were to behave in the
same way in them, how would I feel about that?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a very lightened version of Kant’s categorical imperative.
Instead of asking whether you are acting according to
&lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; that constitute &lt;em&gt;universal&lt;/em&gt; law, we are
asking wether in our particular relational context your
&lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; are ones I would consider acceptable if they
consistently described your behaviour. Your behaviour is judged not
based on its consequences, but on what the &lt;em&gt;generalisation&lt;/em&gt; of it
(as described by your provided &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;) looks like. By
requesting &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;, we can judge you (positively as
well as negatively) not just by your one-off actions but by &lt;em&gt;how you
tend to behave -&lt;/em&gt; i.e. what sort of person you are.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="trusting-our-peers"&gt;Trusting our peers&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, I can only judge what sort of person you are based on your
reasons for action if the &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; you provide is one
that you are likely to act in accord with in future.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am a big fan of C. Thi Nguyen’s paper “Trust as an unquestioning
attitude”. My light generalisation of it is that you
&lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; that X to the degree that you do not really have
to entertain the possibility of not X. e.g. you &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt;
that the sun will come up tomorrow, because even if you think about
whether or not it will the possibility that it will not seems neither
plausible nor emotionally relevant. You &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; that your
partner is not secretly a serial killer because if you think about the
possibility it doesn’t seem remotely plausible. You also
&lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; to a lesser extent that your long-term business
partner isn’t going to betray you, your friends don’t secretly hate you,
etc. - it’s not that there is zero concern here, and you may worry about
it a bit, but it’s not a major part of your day to day experience.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly, you &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; that something will or won’t
happen. You might &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; totally that someone won’t
betray you, but that doesn’t necessarily mean that you
&lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; them to fly a plane.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can still &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; someone in a more generalised
sense, in that the better you know them the more you
&lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; about them. When I first meet someone I can’t
&lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; that they won’t be a dick to me, or that they’re
reliable, or that they are fun to be around, but as I get to know them
better I learn the ways in which I can &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; them (and
the ways I cannot).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="afterword"&gt;Afterword&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I actually still think that there’s something important here and I’d
like to try to revisit it at some point, but I think this kind of
dissecting of someone else’s arguments isn’t really for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular the role of trust and reason in constituting our moral
behaviour is something that I’ve been thinking about since and would
like to try to articulate more at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-05-11:11.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-06-07:04.html</id>
    <title>"placeholder"</title>
    <updated>2024-01-06T08:32:15+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;"placeholder"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;header id="title-block-header"&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;


&lt;h1 id="disingenuous-advice"&gt;Disingenuous Advice&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m a big fan of giving advice. You should give more advice. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-17-14:20.html"&gt;Appropriately&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-give-good-advice"&gt;effectively&lt;/a&gt;,
but helping people is good and advice, done well, is one of the easiest
ways to help people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But a thing I’ve been noticing for a while is that a lot of advice
isn’t really designed to help people. It’s designed to discharge your
responsibility, real or imagined, for helping them, in a way that makes
having the problem their problem rather than yours.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The characteristic features of this sort of disingenuous advice
are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s not exactly &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; advice. It’s important that it could,
in theory, solve the problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It tends to be quite one-size-fits-all. It shows very little
engagement with the actual problem - if you were going to put in enough
effort to tailor your advice, you’d probably make at least some effort
to give reasonable advice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It tends to be quite simple, so as to make it seem easy. It’s the
sort of thing that you could very naturally use the word “just” in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It seems to encourage closing off further conversation until you’ve
tried to follow the advice. Reasons why the advice won’t work sound like
excuses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is, in fact, very hard to follow this advice and even following
the advice isn’t guaranteed to work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The prompt for me to start noticing this pattern is how often “go to
therapy” is this. Therapy is a perfectly valuable tool that, if you can
afford it, can help with many categories of emotional problems. It also
tends to be suggested very blindly, for large categories of problems
that it’s not especially suited for, and to people who are probably not
well set up to benefit from it (e.g. because they can’t afford it, or
because the real problem is that their life sucks in very tangible ways
and their negative emotions mostly stem from that). But by suggesting
going to therapy you make it very clear that their problems aren’t
yours, you’ve suggested a solution now, they should go make it a
therapist’s problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“Learn to code” as a response to career problems is another common
one. It’s not necessarily bad advice - software is a pretty good career
option for some people. But it’s not a catch all solution to career
problems - not everyone is actually well suited to work in software,
retraining is hard, getting your first software job is hard, and there
may be many better lateral transfers for most people that actually get
to use their current experience.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Also not all jobs can be software jobs you do actually
have to move atoms as well as bits.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another example that came up on discord recently was students having
to ask permission to go to the bathroom in class, and how bad this is
(especially given that it can be refused). The advice “you should have
gone to the bathroom between classes” absolves your responsibility to
them by making it the student’s fault for their lack of forethought.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these very effectively discharge your responsibility without
being in any way helpful. They are, at best, &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/i/39151933/checklist-advice"&gt;checklist
advice&lt;/a&gt;, without any suggestion that you’re willing to do the rest of
the checklist or, heaven forbid, actually offer real advice once the
checklist is completed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, often it’s perfectly reasonable not to want their problem to be
yours. If it’s some stranger on the internet asking you to feel bad for
them and care about their problems then… I don’t know, I probably think
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-23-13:27.html"&gt;you
should feel bad for them&lt;/a&gt;. Certainly it’s not fard, but it might be
mustahabb.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I got the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fard"&gt;Islamic tiers of moral
obligation&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="/images/islamic-moral-tiers.webp"&gt;some
random Tumblr post that no longer seems to exist on the internet&lt;/a&gt; but
it’s very useful and somewhat better grain than most of the equivalent
English words. The point I’m making here is that this is a morally good
act that you are not required to do.&lt;/span&gt; But this is hard, and most people
don’t want to do it. What they do want, however, is to feel good about
themselves, so giving a plausible appearance of caring is helpful. Or,
even better, being able to credibly suggest that in fact the speaker is
bad for having this problem and it’s their fault for not having solved
it already, thus not only discharging your obligations but making it
clear that you didn’t have any obligations to discharge in the first
place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly bad behaviour when you’re not in the “strangers
on the internet” scenario and it’s someone who you do have some sort of
responsibility to - a personal relationship, one of your reports at
work, a student of yours, etc. There it is not just a disavowal of
responsibility that you don’t want to have, it’s a refusal to accept the
responsibility that you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even when you don’t have any responsibility to the person, I do think
it is your responsibility not to give this sort of disingenuous advice.
As well as being &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-04-10:02.html"&gt;dishonest&lt;/a&gt;,
the sheer ubiquity of this behaviour is a failure of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-14:34.html"&gt;collective
responsibility&lt;/a&gt;, and while you might have no individual
responsibility to the advice recipient, I do think you have an
individual responsibility not to make these collective problems
worse.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-06-07:04.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-07-08:50.html</id>
    <title>How to be better at everything</title>
    <updated>2024-01-08T05:49:09+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How to be better at everything&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m undergoing one of my periodic attempts to be better at Slay the
Spire, and setting myself a challenge of win streaking on Ironclad A1
(mimicking &lt;a href="https://www.twitch.tv/baalorlord"&gt;Baalorlord&lt;/a&gt;,
albeit at a much lower level). My best win streak so far is 8, which I
consider respectable but not as good as I’d like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things that is very obvious at my current level of play is
that the bottlenck on getting better isn’t actually skill. I’m plenty
skilled enough to play better than I currently play. The bottleneck is
that I don’t care quite enough.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me give you an example of what I mean: Slay the Spire has a bunch
of relics that retain state between fights. e.g. Ink Bottle, Nunchunku,
Incense Burner. Some of these are a modest boost when they go off, some
of them are a major boot - e.g. having Incense Burner on the right
number when you go into some fights can be win or lose a game all on its
own.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;If you’re going into the heart fight you really want to
be intangible on turn 2 or 3. If you’re going into Bronze Automaton you
really want to be intangible on the hyperbeam turn. Going through Act 2,
being intangible on turn 1 is really nice although less essential.&lt;/span&gt; Even the lesser relics are a big
deal and can make the difference between consistently great fights and
very unreliable ones. This makes it worth spending some time at the end
of each fight making sure your relics are on the right number.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I know how to do this. I’m not saying I’m great at it - it’s
definitely something I could practice&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Also arguably it’s something where I’m limited on other
skills. I could do this more easily if fights were easier for me.&lt;/span&gt; - but there’s nothing
fundamentally mysterious about it to me. I know how it works, I know why
it’s needed, and I know it well enough to do it and all the rest would
just improve by doing so. Also I just can’t be bothered. It seems so
fiddly and annoying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Almost certainly if I put in the work, it would become less fiddly
and annoying over time, and I think it would also improve my skills in
other areas to do it, but I don’t think it would ever become something I
was really excited about doing. Maybe I’m wrong and eventually it would
become natural, I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, the thing I need to do with Slay the Spire is &lt;em&gt;slow
down&lt;/em&gt;. Put in more effort. Actually bother to take the time over
things. But I don’t wanna, because that seems unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve also seen this from the other side. I am, allegedly, quite a
good software developer. I do in fact possess quite a high level of
skill, but often when I compare the things that I can do that other
people fail at, it’s not really because of skill, it’s because I did
legwork that they were perfectly capable of doing but didn’t do.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Sometimes this is because it didn’t occur to them to do
it of course. I’m put in mind about &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/acesounderglass/status/1743347591793033549"&gt;this
conversation with Elizabeth&lt;/a&gt; about my post about &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/learning-to-exercise-agency"&gt;learning
to exercise agency&lt;/a&gt;. But the things I have in mind here are something
that I think it’s worth doing basically 100% of the time when you’re
stuck or having a particular common class of problems, so I still feel
like it’s worth characterising this as a persistence problem more than a
skill problem, it’s just a persistence problem once you add one fact to
your existing level of skill.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, here’s how you track down an annoying bug: You basically
badger the code until it confesses. You insert prints everywhere, you
insert assertions everywhere. You delete code that you’re sure doesn’t
matter, and find out if it secretly did. You repeatedly run the code
that triggers the bug, narrowing it down into a tighter and tigher
location, until you know exactly where something you thought was
impossible occurs, and now you’ve found the bug. &lt;a href="https://blog.nelhage.com/post/computers-can-be-understood/"&gt;Computers
can be understood&lt;/a&gt;, you just have to do the work of understanding
them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This works, I promise. I once got on a call to help someone debug a
problem that they’d been stuck on for weeks and within about an hour
we’d narrowed down the issue this way. They were pleased with the
outcome and happily paid me for my time, but it was an extremely “Wait,
that’s it? Why didn’t I think to do that?” interaction on their end.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, most people can probably do better software development by
doing the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write more tests, ideally tracking coverage and aiming for 100%
coverage.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;By which I mean 100% coverage with the explicit get-out
clause that you’re allowed to mark some lines as not covered.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a linter and fix everything it complains about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write more comments.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’ve got some pushback on this one, and I think it’s
true that of the three of these, comments are by far the easiest to do
badly enough to be a net negative, but I think it’s probably on balance
still better to write comments than not when you’re operating at what
feels like the edge of your skill level.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But this seems annoying and fiddly and so you don’t do it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;To be clear, it is annoying and fiddly, and I also often
don’t do it. But whenever I actually &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; a project to be good,
I will do this, and a bunch of other things besides.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s not that there’s no skill in doing these things well. There
absolutely is. It’s that doing them badly is still better than not doing
them,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Most of the time. You can do them badly enough for it to
be a negative.&lt;/span&gt; and if you do them consistently then
you’ll eventually learn to do them well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s also not that these are always good ideas - sometimes there are
good reasons to do something badly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But they will always make your code better, and the thing stopping
you doing that is, rightly or wrongly, you&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Possibly collective-you rather than you-personally if
it’s a managerial/team thing.&lt;/span&gt;
don’t want to do the work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is probably a pretty general theme: Any time you want to
be better at something, it’s tempting to treat your performance as being
at the leading edge of your current skill level, but it’s actually not.
It’s at the leading edge of your current skill level &lt;em&gt;at the level of
effort you are currently putting in&lt;/em&gt;, and putting in more effort
will get you better results, and trying to develop more skill without
increasing your effort level won’t.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We want getting better to be a &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/difficult-problems-and-hard-weeks"&gt;difficult
problem&lt;/a&gt;, because that means we can solve it, but in fact getting
better is more effectively done with hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-07-08:50.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-08-05:49.html</id>
    <title>The skill element of (not) working harder</title>
    <updated>2024-01-08T07:46:17+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The skill element of (not) working harder&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-07-08:50.html"&gt;Yesterday
I wrote&lt;/a&gt; about how the key to getting better at things was to be
willing to diligently do things that seem annoyingly fiddly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I still think this is basically correct, but I subsequently performed
an experiment which made me realise that it was incomplete, in ways that
probably should have been obvious to me but apparently weren’t.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Fortunately, the notebook is not a place where I’m
compelled to be diligent, and off-the-cuff poorly thought through hot
takes are fine here. Where, you might reasonably ask, do I practice
diligently doing annoyingly fiddly writing work? Ah, excellent
question.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The experiment was this: I wanted to find out if I was actually right
that carefully babying relic counters in Slay the Spire would improve my
play as much as I think it does. So I decided to add a twist to my
current attempts at win streaking and use the console to give myself an
ink bottle at the start of the run&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I guess this is “cheating” but I don’t really care. It’s
not like I’m competing in any sort of official rankings here, and it’s
for learning purposes.&lt;/span&gt; and play with the goal
of getting the ink bottle on 9 or as close to 9 as possible at the end
of each fight, so that I started each fight with an extra card draw.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first one of these went pretty straightforwardly and was indeed
quite strong. The second one, the spire decided to hand me a happy
flower and a nunchuku&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This probably all sounds insane if you don’t know much
about Slay the Spire. These are other relics which have the same
property of preserving state between combats.&lt;/span&gt; to keep things interesting, and I
felt compelled to do my best to keep them on the right numbers at the
end of combat too, although I didn’t commit to it to quite the same
degree. This was exactly as annoying as I expected it to be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, from these two runs I’ve tentatively come to the following
conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was right that this would significantly improve my play. Some of
this is definitely that I’m starting with more of an advantage (a whole
extra relic!). Some of it is probably that it’s forcing me to play more
thoughtfully. But I do think a lot of it is that relic tracking is just
genuinely a very strong thing to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt; wrong about how much skill is involved in
doing this. I can definitely do this, it’s not beyond my skill level,
but there’s room to improve on it. The biggest thing is that it’s easy
to build decks which stop you from doing this because they kill the
enemy at a rate not under your control.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Two ways I’ve screwed this up: Combust, which deals
constant damage per turn, and Corruption, which eventually removes your
ability to play cards that don’t kill the enemy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’ve completely misunderstood the role of skill in making this sort
of diligence not annoying and fiddly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing about this run where I was keeping track of all the relics
is that it wasn’t just every bit as irritating as I expected, it was
&lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more irritating than I expected from having watched
streamers do it. Some of that is just that I could have been better at
it. There were definitely fights where I screwed up the counting and had
to start again,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And a few where I screwed up the counting and killed the
enemy at the wrong time and so couldn’t start again.&lt;/span&gt; and probably some more where I
adopted a suboptimal strategy for getting the relic on the right number,
but I probably couldn’t have done that in a way that was more than two
or three times less irritating even with the best skill in the world.
It’s just a lot to keep track of.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there’s actually a much bigger skill difference between me and
the streamers I’ve seen doing it, that significantly changes the
annoyingness level: Most of the time, they’re not doing it at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, expert players will make sure to get a relic on
the right number in basically two cases:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s easy, and they can opportunistically do it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They’ve got a big scary fight coming up that they are worried enough
about to optimise for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s not a case of consistently doing the maximal amount of effort,
it is a case of &lt;em&gt;knowing when it’s worth it to put in more
effort&lt;/em&gt;, and how much effort you’ll have to put in. You do the extra
work when it’s much easier than normal or much more worth it than
normal. You’re still putting more effort in in aggregate than people who
are not doing this&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although that depends how you count. You’re putting in
less effort per victory, but more effort per unit time.&lt;/span&gt;, but a lot less than doing it
constantly would take.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Unless you’re XecnaR I guess.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the same is true of programming. I talked about the slow
methodical way of debugging, but honestly 95% of the time my debugging
process is that I look at the stack trace and go “Oh yeah I know what’s
going on, it’s that bullshit I’ve seen before.”&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I recently had an experience where I did this twice in a
row with a very smart and capable colleague who was less experienced in
the ways of weird computer bullshit than I am, and I think it looked
like complete witchcraft to him.&lt;/span&gt;
Even in the remaining 5% I very rarely need to put in the effort of
extracting a full confession from my broken software, I take shortcuts
and do simpler things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I don’t always write fully commented, fully tested, lint
free code. A lot of my code is some bullshit I wrote in an IPython
terminal, or that I hacked on while running the program and seeing if it
works.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn9"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn9" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;More of &lt;a href="https://github.com/DRMacIver/shrinkray"&gt;Shrink Ray&lt;/a&gt; is like
this than ideal right now.&lt;/span&gt; But I’ve got enough experience that
even my some bullshit code is shaped by having written much better code
than that, and also to know when I can get away with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you learn these intuitions?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly, probably you learn them by doing it the hard way first.
Sorry. I still think the conclusion of the last post is basically
correct - if you want to do better, you need to work more
diligently.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I do think this offers a glimmer of hope that actually on the
other side of that you can probably go back to being less diligent
again, except when you really need to be.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-08-05:49.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-09-08:51.html</id>
    <title>Safety Advice and Judgment in Emergencies</title>
    <updated>2024-01-09T09:00:30+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Safety Advice and Judgment in Emergencies&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another draft bankruptcy post. I don’t know why I didn’t finish this
one. I barely remember writing it - it’s from a full year ago - and it
looks pretty close to complete to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Please note that improper application of what follows can literally
get you killed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not a joke. I’m about to explain how safety advice works, and
the reason it works the way it does is so that you don’t die. If you
read this article and go “Ah I see, safety advice is for dumb people,
but I am smart and know better so I can disregard it”, you will probably
die.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am emphasizing this because that is absolutely a risk factor
associated with this article. I would like you not to die and, equally
importantly to me, I would like not to get blamed if you do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact, my &lt;em&gt;official&lt;/em&gt; advice&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In my very official capacity as that guy wot writes on
the internet.&lt;/span&gt; is
that you should always follow safety advice to the letter. I’m now going
to explain to you why this isn’t always a good idea, and give some
examples where I have not done so. If, based on this, you sometimes
don’t follow safety advice, please don’t blame me. This newsletter is
for informational purposes only etc etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, let me be clear: Under normal circumstances, you should follow
safety advice. Under moderately abnormal circumstances, you should
follow safety advice. Under exceptional circumstances, after a careful
balancing of the trade offs and proper consideration, it might be
correct sometimes to not follow safety advice, but as far as my advice
is concerned, you should follow safety advice and if you don’t then
that’s on you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, with those caveats aside, let’s talk about how safety advice
works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in 2018, I went to A&amp;amp;E&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Accident and Emergency. British English for the ER /
Emergency Room.&lt;/span&gt; twice in one week.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, at night I was having a bit of trouble breathing. I wasn’t
gasping, I wasn’t really struggling for breath, but my chest felt a bit
tight and it felt like my breaths were never quite sufficiently
deep.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I called 111, the non-emergency medical advice helpline, and had
the following conversation:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me: (describes above symptoms)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operator: Yeah you need to go to A&amp;amp;E right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me: Are you sure? It doesn’t feel dangerous, just unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operator: We’re sending you an ambulance right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I went to A&amp;amp;E, waited a few hours in the middle of the night,
they duly did an ECG, found nothing wrong, and told me I was probably
fine. I got told to take some ibuprofen and an antihistamine and it’d
probably make the symptoms go away.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then it happened again a few days later, and basically the same story
repeated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The third time this happened I did the obvious sensible thing: I
didn’t tell a medical professional about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also at that point I figured out what was triggering it&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;A buckwheat pillow I’d got for correcting neck posture
at night apparently set off some sort of allergic reaction, though I am
not as far as anyone can tell allergic to buckwheat.&lt;/span&gt; and
removed it from my bedroom and after that I didn't have the symptoms
again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, if I had called 111 for advice that third time, I would have
found myself in an ambulance, because as far as 111 is concerned, if
you’re having trouble breathing, you go to A&amp;amp;E.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a completely reasonable thing for them to do, because they
are not in the position of doing a detailed medical diagnosis, they are
in the position of dispensing safety advice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Safety advice has three key properties:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is designed to help you avoid situations in which you die, or
other terrible things happen to you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is designed to be used with minimal information or skill, on
either the part of the person receiving it or the person giving
it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has a very limited set of concerns and treats everything
outside of those concerns as irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you call 111, you are not talking to someone who has a medical
degree. It’s a standard call center job with standard call center job
requirements. &lt;a href="https://www.londonambulance.nhs.uk/working-for-us/career-opportunities/111-health-advisor-faqs/"&gt;The
entry requirements are as follows&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Experience of dealing with members of the public over the
telephone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ability to remain calm when working under pressure&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ability to work to defined policies and procedures&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ability to work on own initiative&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Age 18 years or older (in line with legislation)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is presumably on the job training, but they are very much not
medical professionals, they are there to go through a decision tree as
to whether there is something simple you can/should do, or whether you
need to escalate to a medical professional - either “go to the GP”, “go
to A&amp;amp;E”, or things of that ilk.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this decision tree they are working through with you, some of the
branches involve you dying. They don’t want that to happen.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Most importantly, they don’t want to get blamed when
that happens.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can think of this part of the decision tree as the big that
decides “Do I send them to A&amp;amp;E or not?”. &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/02/theres-no-single-error-rate/"&gt;There
are two types of errors&lt;/a&gt; they can make here:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They can send you to A&amp;amp;E when they don’t need to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They can not send you to A&amp;amp;E when you do need to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the second one, you probably die, and they almost certainly get in
trouble (either personally or as an organisation).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first isn’t free. If it were free they’d send everyone to
A&amp;amp;E. But it’s a lot preferable to you dying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Basically, there are three costs here:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Risk to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burden on medical system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inconvenience to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From the point of view of the 111 operator, these are in decreasing
order of importance, and their importance decreases &lt;em&gt;sharply&lt;/em&gt;
with each item - they very much don’t want you to die, they don’t want
to create unnecessary work for doctors, and also they probably care a
little bit about not inconveniencing you but let’s be honest it’s barely
on their radar.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means that in any circumstances where the risk to you is high,
they will tell you to go to A&amp;amp;E, and they will right to do so. In
particular when there is a non-negligible chance that you might
literally die, they will tell you to go to A&amp;amp;E.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, here’s the wrinkle: “chance that you might die” is not purely an
objective property of the world. There’s “genuine” uncertainty - given
the true facts about your state, how at risk you are - but there’s also
epistemic uncertainty - given what we know about your state, how at risk
you might be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; in an ideal case is to make all the judgements
based on the genuine uncertainty. If you’re actually at risk, go to
A&amp;amp;E. If you’re not actively at risk, take care of yourself at home
and see your GP when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is that you don’t know the genuine uncertainty. You’ve
got some approximation of it cobbled together by your (unreliable) self
reports over the phone and someone who’s had a couple of weeks of
training and has access to an internal knowledge base which probably
isn’t much better than the NHS website.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What this means, is that they are very very strongly incentivised to
err on the side of caution. They have simple rules, and rather than try
to refine them, they offload them to people who are competent to do the
actual risk assessment. Thus most of the uncertainty in their assessment
is epistemic, not genuine, and they hand you over to a medical
professional to reduce it when it seems like it needs reducing because
it looks uncomfortable far from zero.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the case of difficulty breathing, this sounds sufficiently like I
might be having one of several rapidly fatal problems, that they very
much want to reduce that epistemic uncertainty down to zero and find out
if I’m actually going to die. Off to A&amp;amp;E with me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is good. It’s how the system is supposed to work. I want to be
clear on that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;BUT it does mean that you can make better decisions than the system
under two particular types of circumstance:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have significantly more applicable knowledge than they do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your preferences are significantly different than the ones they’re
optimised for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my case with the A&amp;amp;E visits, both applied.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I at this point had significantly more applicable knowledge than they
did - I’d talked to doctors about it and they’d examined me. Twice. I
literally had more relevant medical knowledge about my problem than the
operator at 111 could ever acquire, because I’d talked to medical
experts about this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My preferences were significantly different than theirs - being in
A&amp;amp;E for 3 hours starting at midnight &lt;em&gt;sucks&lt;/em&gt;. I didn’t want
to do it. They didn’t care about this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s tempting to say that they should be able to have a conversation
with me that takes these preferences into account. They shouldn’t!
That’s not what they’re for. They’re a human interface to the system. If
I want to have a proper conversation about the problem, I need to talk
to an expert&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;The experts also tend not to be very good at respecting
patient preferences and knowledge, but that’s a separate problem.&lt;/span&gt;, the phone operator, in trying to
act as such an expert, is likely to make significant errors, and those
errors are likely to kill people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The solution, unfortunately, is to not put them in a situation where
they are forced to give you bad advice. This is not always available,
and it requires you to have good judgement about when that is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I’m writing all this because I ran into another problem like
this recently, in which I flagrantly ignored safety advice, which is
that my house had a gas leak recently.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We’d had a smart meter fitted on Wednesday&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Editor’s note: This was written over a year ago, so the
Wednesday in question was in December 2022.&lt;/span&gt;.
The person who fitted it did a sufficiently bad job that the person who
fixed his work had a legal requirement to report him.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We noticed this problem on Friday when I noticed that operating our
gas stove caused a strong smell of gas in the living room. I turned off
the stove, checked the meter cupboard, and sure enough there was an even
stronger smell of gas coming from there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I turned off the gas, which solved the immediate problem, and called
the national gas emergency line, as one does when you have a gas
leak.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They informed me that a gas engineer would be with me as soon as
possible (“as soon as possible” turned out to be about 50 hours later.
We did not get gas restored until Sunday evening), and then very
insistently informed me that we must:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not operate any electrical appliances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep doors and windows open to ventilate the property.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stay out of any attics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I earnestly informed them that yes I would absolutely do this. Then I
opened the back door, waited a bit, verified that I could not smell gas
anywhere, and turned on a space heater.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;According to the official safety advice, I’d just behaved horribly
irresponsibly and was now going to blow up my house. This didn’t happen,
in case you’re worrying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why did I behave in such a seemingly flagrantly irresponsible
way?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was -6C outside (about 20F).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was no longer a gas leak, because the gas was off.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From their perspective when writing the safety advice:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gas leaks are very very bad, and you should not trust inexpert
judgement as to how bad a particular gas leak is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cost of gas leak mitigations is relatively low, because there
will be an engineer with there to deal with them rapidly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From my perspective:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was extremely confident in my ability to assess how bad this gas
leak was, because I knew exactly where it was occurring, I had turned
off the gas supply, ventilated the property, and sniffed around to
confirm a total absence of the smell of gas.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Technically of mercaptan, the additive they put in gas
to make sure you can smell it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When someone tells me “I can’t possibly comment” when I ask them
whether “As soon as possible” means “Some time today”, I know I’m in for
a long wait, and I was absolutely not going to have a long wait in sub
freezing temperatures with no heat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result was that the next 48 hours, while extremely unpleasant,
were not actively dangerous to my health. If I had followed their safety
advice, it would have been actively dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly, this is not good safety advice. It might be good safety
advice in the normal course of things where you really can count on a
two hour response time, but even then it’s not great.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is that this had two assumptions about the world encoded
into it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am incompetent to assess whether there is a gas leak.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They will respond fast enough that any inconveniences are
minor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first assumption is, honestly, probably fair enough. Gas is scary
and most people are indeed incompetent. I was happy to trust my own
judgement, but they probably do not have the information to determine
that my judgement is trustworthy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If their advice was “If you think it’s safe, treat it as safe”, this
would probably get more people killed, because most people probably
don’t have judgement you can trust.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;As this whole episode shows, you can’t even trust gas
safety certified engineers to reliably have good judgement.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, eh, regardless of whether they trust my judgement, I trust my
judgement! And I’m pretty sure I’m right to do so. The problem is, of
course, that many other people who also think this about their own
judgement do so incorrectly. This is part of why my official advice is
not “trust your judgement”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don’t really know what to tell you about how to tell whether you
should actually trust your judgement, but one partial test is that you
know when &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to trust your judgement. For example, I was at
the time basically 100% confident that I knew what the problem was and
that I could fix it. I was proven correct in retrospect too - the
problem was exactly what I thought it was, and doing what I thought
would fix it would have indeed fixed it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I sat on my hands for the full 48 hours and refused to touch it. This
was correct. Everything would have been fine if I’d tried to fix it, and
I knew that it would be fine if I tried to fix it, and I also knew that
I would still think it would probably be fine in many scenarios that end
with us being blown up or poisoned.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="afterword"&gt;Afterword&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think all that stopped me finishing writing this piece was I didn’t
have a very satisfying way to wrap it up other than to say “learn when
to trust your judgement, butplease don’t get yourself killed”. So uh,
learn when to trust your judgment, but please don’t get yourself
killed.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-09-08:51.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-10-07:48.html</id>
    <title>Showing people the door</title>
    <updated>2024-01-10T07:59:43+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Showing people the door&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another draft bankruptcy post. I think this was abandoned for a
fairly common reason for me to abandon posts: I tried to write it
because it was important, but it’s actually a fairly depressing subject
for me to write about and I didn’t particularly want to write it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I run a small&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Officially we’re about 400 people, with a regulars list
of about 100 people, of whom maybe half are regularly active.&lt;/span&gt; but fairly successful discord
server. &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/bY5XKnWMQj"&gt;You can join if you want
to&lt;/a&gt;. Nominally it’s about this newsletter, and occasionally we even
remember that, but mostly it’s just a bunch of nerds who hang out on the
internet, help each other navigate life better, and talk about stuff we
like. I think it’s pretty great.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I act as the sole authority figure for how the community works.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It’s not a cult, I promise.&lt;/span&gt;. This is a space on the internet I
manage to cultivate the sort of community and conversations I want to
exist. It’s what I’ve called &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-07-14-13:42.html"&gt;Living
Room Rules&lt;/a&gt; before - it’s the equivalent of people coming around to
my house to hang out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t mean the community do whatever I want. Truthfully, it’s
like herding cats sometimes. But it does mean that when the community
isn’t working, it’s my responsibility to fix it. Often in consultation
with others, but ultimately I’m the one who makes the call.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hardest part of this is that sometimes you have to show people
the door.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had to do this with someone yesterday&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Possibly he’s reading this. If so, sorry. Editor’s note:
Presumably not on the notebook. Also this “yesterday” was actually more
than a year ago.&lt;/span&gt;. He
wasn’t right for the community.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is only the second time I’ve had to ask someone to leave this
discord (I’ve &lt;em&gt;banned&lt;/em&gt; some people for outright terrible
behaviour, but that’s different), but I’ve seen it with other
communities in the past. Crucially, I’ve seen it with other communities
in the past because the community leadership &lt;em&gt;didn’t&lt;/em&gt; ask the
person to leave. This kills the community.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the key things you are there for in a community - what
&lt;em&gt;makes&lt;/em&gt; it a community - is the other people. A community is, at
its core, a group of people who do stuff together. Having someone who
fails to gel with the group and can’t easily be avoided around disrupts
that, because it adds friction to every interaction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What this means is that if some is disrupting the group’s ability to
interact, there is less of the thing that brings people there, and some
people who were already marginal stop showing up so much. This in turn
means that the people who were there partly to hang out with those
people stop showing up so much, which in turn…&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s not a complete death spiral even in the worst case. Usually some
subset of the community stays - those who don’t have any better options,
or who are still too attached to what the community used to be - but the
community turns into a shell of its former self.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More commonly, one person who doesn’t mesh with the others isn’t
enough to offset the rest of the benefits people are getting, but the
community contracts a bit and what’s left feels slightly less thriving.
If you add more such people, it may get worse, .&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Internet communities without a shared project are particularly
vulnerable to this, because there’s &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; bringing people
there except the other people, so if you ruin those interactions you’ve
got nothing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, communities built around something are a bit more
robust. e.g.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An open source project you have the motivation of the project itself
- you’re there because you want it for stuff. A sufficiently toxic
contributor can definitely drive you off, and someone you don’t get
along with can definitely sap your motivation to contribute&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Open source is pretty good at doing this on its own,
honestly.&lt;/span&gt;, but you’re at least there for some
specific purpose external to the people involved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volunteer-driven physical projects (e.g. charitable works,
maintenance of some space, etc) are the same but more so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communities built around access to some resource. e.g. you’re
probably not going to stop hanging out on the midjourney discord just
because you don’t like the people there, because that’s where you go to
use midjourney.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical communities with shared physical resources are even more
like this. The people at your local maker space or tennis club might be
super annoying, but if it’s the only place you can go to get access to a
laser cutter or a tennis court, you’re still going to keep going.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These places still can be harmed by people who don’t mesh well with
the group, and sometimes even outright ruined, but it’s much harder and
they’re more robust against it because of the additional draw to keep
coming back beyond just liking the people there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="who-needs-to-leave"&gt;Who needs to leave?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly, the person who I asked to leave wasn’t an asshole. He
was a bit hard to deal with, but he didn’t cross any lines where I could
feel good about just pressing the ban button. He just consistently
failed to mesh with the community in a way that made everyone else’s
experience worse when he was in the room.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Frankly, he was probably just of an age where relatively few people
would fit in with the rest of us - we’re mostly in our 30s, and he was
in his late teens or early 20s, and I think most people of that age
wouldn’t have fit. Certainly I can’t imagine a 19 year old version of me
doing well there. There’s just too large an experience gap.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of thing is, in general, the problem zone: People who have
not and probably never will do anything that lets you go “Right, you’ve
crossed a line” and kick them out, but you really wish they would.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you start feeling that way about someone, you probably need to
think seriously about asking them to leave. If you don’t, people you
want in the community much more will leave on their own instead.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="afterword"&gt;Afterword&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tapered out there partially because I don’t really have good advice
on how to navigate this. This is hard, and I’ve not got more than a
handful of personal examples of doing it, and I’m not confident that I
handled it especially well, or that I know what handling it well looks
like in full generality.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All I know is that I’ve seen communities die by not doing this, and
it’s a problem that needs solving&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-10-07:48.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-11-08:07.html</id>
    <title>"placeholder"</title>
    <updated>2024-01-11T08:07:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;"placeholder"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;header id="title-block-header"&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;


&lt;h1 id="thinking-in-memes"&gt;Thinking in memes&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another draft bankruptcy post, though I’m going to continue this on
for a bit as it’s really more of the prompt for a post than a full
abandoned draft.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;hr/&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of you get annoyed when I write very culturally bound things
that rely on a lot of shared context. Like Shaka, when the walls fell,
you will not enjoy this post. You may or may not wish to bear with me
anyway.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is a post about memes. Mostly of the internet sort, not
the Dawkins sort, although a little bit also of the Dawkins sort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="all-part-of-the-pattern"&gt;All part of the pattern&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was indeed a garden, like a lot of other gardens you got in areas
like Clay Lane. The gray soil was nothing more than old brick dust,
elderly cat mess, and generalized, semirotted dross. At the far end was
a three-hole privy. It was built handily by the gate to the back lane so
the night-soil men didn’t have far to go, but this one had a small stone
cylinder turning gently beside it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The garden didn’t get much proper light. Gardens like this never did.
You got secondhand light once the richer folk in the taller buildings
had finished with it. Some people kept pigeons or rabbits or pigs on
their plots, or planted, against all experience, a few vegetables. But
it’d take magic beans to reach the real sunlight in gardens like
this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, someone had made an effort. Most of the spare ground
had been covered with gravel of different sizes, and this had been
carefully raked into swirls and curves. Here and there, some individual
larger stones had been positioned, apparently with great thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vimes stared at the garden of rocks, desperate for anything to occupy
his attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He could see what the designer had in mind, he thought, but the
effect had been spoiled. This was the big city, after all. Garbage got
everywhere. The main disposal method was throwing it over a wall. Sooner
or later someone would sell it or, possibly, eat it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A young monk was carefully raking the gravel. He gave a respectful
bow as Sweeper approached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The old man sat down on a stone bench.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Push off and get us two cups of tea, lad, will you?” he said. “One
green with yak butter, and Mister Vimes will have it boiled orange in a
builder’s boot with two sugars and yesterday’s milk, right?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s how I like it,” said Vimes weakly, sitting down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sweeper took a deep, long breath. “And I like building gardens,” he
said. “Life should be a garden.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vimes stared blankly at what was in front of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Okay,” he said. “The gravel and rocks, yes, I can see that. Shame
about all the rubbish. It always turns up, doesn’t it…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes,” said Lu-Tze. “It’s part of the pattern.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What? The old cigarette packet?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Certainly. That invokes the element of air,” said Sweeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And the cat doings?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To remind us that disharmony, like a cat, gets everywhere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The cabbage stalks? The used [condom]?*”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At our peril we forget the role of the organic in the total harmony.
What arrives seemingly by chance in the pattern is part of a higher
organization that we can only dimly comprehend. This is a very important
fact, and has a bearing on your case.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And the beer bottle?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first time since Vimes had met him, the monk frowned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Y’know, some bugger always tosses one over the wall on his way back
from the pub on Friday nights. If it wasn’t forbidden to do that kind of
thing, he’d feel the flat to my hand and no mistake.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not part of the higher organization?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Possibly. Who cares? That sort of thing gets on my thungas, it
really does,” said Sweeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This passage is one of various things the world has chucked over the
wall into my mind. I like to imagine that the garden has been raked
around the rubbish in the same way as it would any large rock or
intrusion into it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/rock-garden.jpg"/&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Harima-ankokuji-sekitei01.jpg"&gt;Picture
of a Japanese rock garden by wikimedia user Jnn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is often how my mind feels to me. Things appear in it from the
world and stay there, patterns radiating outwards, interfering and
interacting and creating something unique and sometimes beautiful
patterns, but it often starts from garbage.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="trekkies-watching-darmok"&gt;Trekkies, watching Darmok&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The “Star Trek: The Next Generation” episode “Darmok” is about a race
of aliens whose communication style does not correctly translate,
because everything they say is in terms of analogy to previous
events.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Editor’s note: I think I stopped writing this post because this
section was boring. Please insert any one of various standard takes
about how the way we communicate on the internet is like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="the-associative-value-of-memes"&gt;The associative value of
memes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because what I actually wanted to talk about was the use of memes for
thinking rather than about how we talk with them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of this is just the usual straightforward way that any language
is a tool for thought: Having a concept for a thing allows you to think
about the thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But memes have an unusual sticking power, because of the richness of
the concept. They usually have an image with a quite specific vibe
associated with them. Sometimes they undergo enough evolution that they
leave the image behind, but even there there’s a whole web of
associations that helps make them feel really accessible and live.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve talked about a related phenomenon in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/reading-philosophy-for-the-examples"&gt;Reading
philosophy for the examples&lt;/a&gt;, where having a whole rich example for a
concept makes it much more relevant.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/duck-guy.png"/&gt; &lt;em&gt;Purple suited man riding a
rocket duck, as you do.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even in that post the images help. I’ve still got a concept for duck
guy that feels quite live,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I still don’t really know how to talk to him, though I
suspect I’m better at it than most.&lt;/span&gt; and Danny at the Grand
Canyon also sticks around, but I had to look up the rest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The particularly useful function of memes as a tool of thought though
is the way they spring unbidden to mind.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, a useful meme to acquire recently has been “Stop. Look.
Think. Are you eating yourself?”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ouroboros.png"/&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://topatoco.com/products/og-ouroboros"&gt;Buy the T-shirt
here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When stuck in unhelpful patterns, it’s helpful to remember this goofy
little guy and ask if I’m currently eating myself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another good related tool comes from catchy songs. Discord got a bit
obsessed with the song Diggy Diggy Hole for a while:&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I can’t imagine how this could possibly have happened
and definitely accept no culpability in it…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/ytWz0qVvBZ0?si=8JxlPuz0o1eb6dZw" title="YouTube video player" width="560"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It became a bit of an injoke for a while to come up with many
variations of this to the tune of verby verby noun&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I am on discord and I’m verbing a noun. verby verby
noun. verby verby noun.&lt;/span&gt;,
but the one that’s really usefully stuck is that when you’re caught in
that annoying state of endlessly browsing the internet, doomscrolling,
etc. you’re in a clicky clicky loop.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Clicky clicky loop. Clicky clicky loop…&lt;/span&gt; Having this concept
available is often enough to break you out of it when the music starts
playing in your head.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And of course, there’s the eagle that makes me go outside whenever I
think about it:&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This hasn’t actually worked very well recently, but in
my defence it’s been cold and dark and wet and I don’t like. Admittedly
this is also the eagle’s vibe so this isn’t much of a defence.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/stupid-little-walk.png"/&gt; &lt;em&gt;An eagle going on a
stupid little daily walk for it stupid physical and mental
health.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I partly think of these posts as my stupid little daily writing for
my stupid mental health.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="no-private-language"&gt;No private language&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think an important feature of memes is that they’re social. Very
few of these things would have stuck without a community of people
reinforcing them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Partly this is because talking about the meme makes it more salient,
part of this is because I think a group is much better at building memes
that are optimised to work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there are probably useful magical practices (sigil creation
etc) that do pull off this sort of trick privately, but personally I’ve
never got them to work. I think it’s important to me that eagle and
ouroboros are shared concepts for the things they represent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe this is something communities should do a bit more
intentionally though. Crafting and selecting memes for their common
problems. I’m not really sure what this would look like, but it’s worth
thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-11-08:07.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
