<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2025-04-23T14:03:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-12-16:30.html</id>
    <title>Anytime Projects</title>
    <updated>2025-04-12T17:57:44+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Anytime Projects&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-12&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something I’ve found over and over again is that there is a
particular way of structuring projects that, when you can manage it,
works very well. I call them Anytime Projects.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Named after &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anytime_algorithm"&gt;anytime
algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, which are algorithsm which you can interrupt at any
point prior to completion and they will tell you their current best
answer.&lt;/span&gt;
I’ve written about it &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/completing-completable-projects"&gt;a
bit before&lt;/a&gt; but never really fully articulated what Anytime Projects
are and why they work so well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The distinguishing feature of an Anytime Project is that can stop at
any point, and little of your time will have been wasted.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You make an anytime project as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You make a minimum viable version of the solution as quickly as
possible. This might just be the status quo, or it might be some initial
basic implementation of the thing you’re aiming at.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You proceed in a series of individually relatively small steps, each
of which leaves the project better off on completion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Optional features:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The project may not even be possible to finish. Many projects are
amenable to constant improvement over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be helpful to prioritise, so that you get a lot of the high
reward to effort tasks done first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, the way I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-23-21:48.html"&gt;clean
the kitchen&lt;/a&gt; structures it as an anytime project. There &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a
well-defined end state, but it’s done in a series of stages, where each
stage is fairly completable in its own right, and each stage being
completed is an improvement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, I recently converted my office in our house into a spare
bedroom&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;The office moved into the “box room” which is basically
a wide corridor joining the landing to the bedroom, and that I used as a
slightly awkard storage and study room before, so this is no great
hardship, except for the actual process of doing the rearrangement. I
actually like my new desk position better than my old one.&lt;/span&gt;, and the priority was getting the
new room usable in time for someone to use it, so my first step was
rapidly extracting everything from the office, much of which got dumped
in my bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an anytime project, because although I made
clear progress on getting the office ready to become a guest room, I did
not leave the system in a state where it was interruptible if I wanted
to be able to sleep that night.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, I think, one of the key feature sof an anytime project: At
any given point, you are a relatively small amount of work from just
being able to stop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why didn’t I do it that part as an anytime project? Too many moving
parts, too many dependency chains. I probably could have if I’d put in a
bit more forethought, but it would have been more work and taken longer
on the most important metric, which was getting the room ready.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is true in general I think: Unless something is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt;
naturally an anytime project, it’s usually going to be more work to do
it as one, and there will often be a faster route to any particular
point than doing it that way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So why do things as anytime projects?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One reason is just the definition: Whenever you end up abandoing the
project, you’ll still have ended up with something usable and worth
doing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But secondly, it’s actually been my experience that anytime projects
are &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more motivating, and the result is that you’re
&lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; likely to abandon the project! When there’s a huge amount
of work in front of you before you see any results, it can be quite
daunting. If in contrast you are presented with a constant stream of
easy ways to improve the situation, it’s easy to keep going until you’re
done - it always feels worth it to do one more thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s also possible to have many anytime projects on the go and pick
them up and put them down as and when you’re motivated to do a bit of
work on them. A blog is an anytime project, as is most software once
it’s in a releasable state - you can sit down, do something to it, and
make it better by publishing an article or adding a feature or fixing a
bug or something. This makes anytime projects &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-23-15:52.html"&gt;a more
natural part of your life&lt;/a&gt; than many larger more monolithic
options.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some things you end up wanting to structure them partially as anytime
projects. e.g. right now in the room move, dealing with the fallout of
it is an anytime project. After I tidied up the worst of the stuff I’d
moved into my bedroom, my bedroom and new office are usable, but there’s
still a lot to do, but I can just do it in small life-improving chunks
each day.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Sometimes I even do that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there’s often a very natural split of a project into two
phases: An initial prototyping or drafting phase where you do whatever
is needed to get some usable first version, and then an Anytime Project
of finishing it off. e.g. I’ve often used “writing a book” as an example
of something that isn’t an anytime project, but I think this is only
sortof true. &lt;em&gt;Writing a first draft&lt;/em&gt; is not, but after that draft
is written there’s a long process of editing and improvement which does
mostly naturally fit the anytime pattern of project design.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve thought of myself as bad at completing projects in the past, but
I think perhaps what I need to get better at is &lt;em&gt;completing
drafts&lt;/em&gt;. In &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/i/136296748/mode-shifts"&gt;Completing
Completable Projects&lt;/a&gt; I identified the idea of a &lt;em&gt;mode shift&lt;/em&gt;
in projects where the sort of activity you need to perform changes as
the projet nears completion. I think at the time I didn’t notice the
transition to anytime as a mode shift because the project I was talking
about didn’t have an editing phase, but I think this is notion of mode
shift is perhaps a good way of thinking about project planing: The first
stage of a project is to get it into anytime mode, as quickly and easily
as possible, and then after that you mode shift it into an anytime
project.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-12-16:30.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-13-14:46.html</id>
    <title>An improvised meal</title>
    <updated>2025-04-13T15:58:11+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;An improvised meal&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-13&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Due to a series of communication mixups where different people
thought it was someone else’s turn to cook, I got home the other day at
7:15 to discover that dinner had not even been started. We normally eat
dinner at 7:30, and the planned meal for the evening (bolognese) takes
several hours to cook. So I sprung into action and 45 minutes later we
had the following entirely improvised meal for five:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stir fried mixed greens with garlic and chilli&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thai omelettes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ground pork and tofu with fermented soy beans, garlic, and
chilli&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stir fried peppers with ginger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sausages&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I did think about doing something more interesting with
the sausages. e.g. turning them into tiny sausage meat balls and cooking
them in something that would flavour match them to the rest of the
dishes - they’d have worked pretty well with ginger and chilli and a bit
of honey added at the end for example. But that sounded like work and
the the child wouldn’t have eaten any.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sliced raw pepper&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Mostly for the child who wasn’t going to eat either the
cooked peppers or the stir fry green because they had too much flavour
and “the texture is weird”.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rate limiting factor was the rice really - our rice cooker takes
about 45 minutes to make enough rice, so the rest was just down to what
I could make while the rice cooked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this demonstrates a couple of interesting things about
improvised cooking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is that there’s a base meal there that I can just do on
autopilot: Rice, stir fried mixed greens, and thai omelettes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The stir fried mixed greens are &lt;a href="https://strongroots.com/en-gb/products/stir-fry-greens"&gt;actually
just from a packet&lt;/a&gt; but it’s a genuinely good product to have in the
freezer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thai omelette is something of a staple dish in our house because the
child loves them and everyone else likes them, and because they’re very
easy to make. You should probably use &lt;a href="https://www.seriouseats.com/thai-style-omelet-khai-jiao-recipe"&gt;the
serious eats recipe&lt;/a&gt; but ours is an extremely simple one: Take some
eggs, add a nonspecific amount of fish sauce, whisk with a fork, and
then fry in a hot pan with lots of oil.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m sure I’ve written about this before but I can’t come up with an
immediate reference,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Maybe &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-05-11:27.html"&gt;Seeking
out existence proofs in everyday life&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/span&gt; but a good general principle is that
you should first make sure you can solve the problem adequately, and
only then worry about improving on that. Having these sort of baseline
meals that you can throw together and then build around is, to me, key
to improvisational cooking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After the base meal, the next important question is “What do we have
that needs using up?”. e.g. you might notice that the sausages are a bit
out of place in this meal. I cooked them anyway, because they were
really on the last day they were still good, and we figured that they’d
keep for another day cooked if not eaten and also they would definitely
get eaten. They were.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The peppers were there partly because we had a large thing of sliced
raw peppers in the fridge from a previous meal where we’d sliced way
more peppers than we ended up eating. I dry fried them to get them nice
and charred, then added frozen diced ginger, sugar, salt, and oil, then
when they were cooked transferred them to a small bowl in the oven to
keep warm and moved on to cooking the pork.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty easy example of improvisational cooking I think:
Take a base ingredient, cook it in a normal way, and add some flavours
that would make it good. A lot of vegetables respond well to this
treatment, including many you wouldn’t necessarily expect. e.g. I’ve
stir fried leftover roast potatoes with ginger and soy sauce before and
that works great.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Not &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; vegetable will work this way of
course. Some vegetables don’t stir fry well, and some have such a
distinctive flavour that doesn’t fit this style of cooking. e.g. I would
not use leftover beetroot this way.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The pork and tofu was a bit more of a genuine creation. We had about
half a bag of tofu king deep fried tofu puffs left that were going off
that day, and about a quarter of a packet (so, I guess, roughly 75g) of
pork mince left over from a meal the other day that would have kept a
bit longer but didn’t have an obvious job associated with it. I’ve
enjoyed Mapo Tofu in the past, which is a completely different dish
combining pork and a different style of tofu, and decided that this was
worth an experiment, so I stir fried the pork with garlic and chilli
from the freezer and some salted fermented soy beans I had in the
fridge,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;A completely normal ingredient to have to hand, right?
No, honestly, I picked them up on a whim the other day when passing a
Chinese supermarket in Cambridge. But they’re really nice, I recommend
them. &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/ZHENG-FENG-Salted-Black-Soybean/dp/B0792GLN3S"&gt;These
are the ones we have&lt;/a&gt;. A nontrivial part of the motivation of this
dish was an excuse to experiment with them.&lt;/span&gt;. This is another appliation of the
“Take a thing and stir fry it with some flavours that would be good with
it”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While that was cooking, I cut the tofu in half (as I’d noticed it was
a bit chonky to cook well when I used the other half bag), and then
added it to the stir fry. Once that was all looking cooked, I also put
that in a bowl in the oven to keep warm, and cooked the greens (add a
bit more sesame oil to the wok, pour the packet in, done).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, all of this was of course only possible because I was in
my own kitchen, which has been stocked with a bunch of things that I
know I can improvise around. We almost always have rice, eggs,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;We’ve got &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; many eggs at the moment, because
we traded our fridge for some recently.&lt;/span&gt; and stir fry greens available, so
there was always a base meal to build around. Similarly, it’s a lot
easier to take a baseline and add some flavours to it if you know you’ve
got a ready supply of flavours to hand.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, preparation seems to be the key to improvisation: You
prepare a solid base of skills to improvise around, and a variety of
tools and resources that you know how to draw from, and the rest is just
elaboration on whatever you have to hand using that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-13-14:46.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-14-21:32.html</id>
    <title>Lessons from win streaking: Learning reliability skills</title>
    <updated>2025-04-14T21:55:14+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Lessons from win streaking: Learning reliability skills&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-31-18:47.html"&gt;still
working on win streaking&lt;/a&gt;. Recently, I got my win streak up from two
to nine.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I was about as annoyed not to make it to an even 10 as
you might imagine, but my actual goal was 5, so I’m still pretty pleased
with myself..&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, uh, I switched characters. I’m much better at Ironclad than
Defect&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;So is almost everyone else. Ironclad is just an easier
character.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This brings up my win streak for an obvious reason, which is that
it’s easier, but I think it also brings it up for a non-obvious one:
Because it’s easier, I can more readily tell what I’m doing wrong. It’s
very hard to learn from failure without good feedback loops, and in
easier games your feedback is clearer because there are fewer things for
you to do wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In doing so, I’ve noticed a couple of interesting things. They are
somewhat obvious in retrospect, but they were at least a little
non-obvious to me in foresight.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is: Once I try to win streak, my appetite for risk changes
significantly. That is, previously I would take risks that had a small
(say, 5-10%) chance of killing me, because they seemed fun or because I
thought I needed to. If you take a few of those chances per run, they
add up pretty rapidly and your win streaks are cut short.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why take risks at all? Because risks are how you get rewards. In Slay
the Spire the biggest instance of this is fighting elites - hard
monsters that drop a lot of treasure. If you don’t fight enough elites,
you don’t gain enough strength, and then you die to the boss fights
(which you can’t skip). So you want to take as many elites as you can,
but you also want to not die, and success is about balancing this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means that one of the most important skills for learning to win
streak in slay the spire is to be able to accurately assess the current
strength of your deck: To ask “Can I beat this elite?” and also “Can I
beat the upcoming boss?” and weigh your chances accordingly, and make
contingency plans.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, since starting to win streak, I’ve skipped a lot more
elite fights,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;On average probably 1-4 per game. In some cases because
I deliberately swerve before the elite, in others because I’m forced
onto a path with fewer elites.&lt;/span&gt; because I’ve looked at the upcoming
elite, gone “Can I take it?” and thought “Nah”. The streak I lost, I
actually knew I was likely to lose, because I’d correctly assessed that
I couldn’t take an elite fight and wasn’t offered a path that let me
skip elites for long enough.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of this process of assessment is just vibe play writ small -
I’ve got a good intuitive sense of what fights the deck can and can’t
take, and that has a better feedback loop than the game overall - but
some of it is being able to ask more specific and concrete questions
like “How much damage are Slavers going to do to me in the first two
turns and is that more than my hit points?” or “When Nemesis attacks me
for 45 damage, what exactly am I going to do other than block it with my
face?”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also informs the game more broadly, because when you realise
that the answer is “No, you can’t take it”, it tells you how your deck
needs to improve.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An interesting side effect is that it’s also improved my potion
use,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Potions are one-time use resources that grant you
specific effects when you use them. A &lt;em&gt;remarkable&lt;/em&gt; amount of Slay
the Spire skill seems to come down to knowing when to use a potion and
when to hold it.&lt;/span&gt; because sometimes the answer when I
ask this question is “Probably not, but you can spend potions to fix
this”. I’ve used potions more aggressively to win elite fights and
bought more potions in shops than I normally do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think, in general, improving reliability looks like this. It’s easy
to think of reliability as just a number, but it’s actually composed of
specific situations, and improving your reliability is about identifying
those situations. You improve reliability by &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-03-13:40.html"&gt;figuring
out what you should worry about&lt;/a&gt;, and come up with specific plans for
avoiding or handling those situations.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-14-21:32.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-15-22:18.html</id>
    <title>Real examples are messy</title>
    <updated>2025-04-15T22:53:15+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Real examples are messy&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading “On Caring” by Milton Mayeroff today. It’s a mostly
pretty good book, outlining a theory about what it means to care for
something, but it has an example quite early on which set me off.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obligations that derive from devotion are a constituent element in
caring, and I do not experience them as forced on me or as necessary
evils; there is a convergence between what I feel I am supposed to do
and what I want to do. The father who goes for the doctor in the middle
of the night for his sick child does not experience this as a burden; he
is simply caring for the child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think that this example is obviously made up, and I think that you
can partly tell that because of the straightforward lack of detail, but
I just think it’s also not true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If your child is currently in desperate need and on the way to ER
then sure, obviously, you’re not going to experience this as burdensome,
because your mind is focused on the immediate emergency, but that’s not
even particularly because it’s your child. In the middle of an emergency
I mostly find that I’m too focused on the actual crisis at hand to think
about how burdened I am by it, although I might have a moment of
thinking “Oh, what a pain” right at the beginning.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And, in real emergencies, have.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast if your child is up with, say, a stomach bug, and has
been vomiting, and you’ve just got off a long shift and you’re exhausted
and want nothing more than to go to sleep, then &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt;
you’re going to experienced this as burdensome. You’re exhausted, the
whole thing is a pain, and you want to go to bed. You (hopefully) do it
anyway, because its your child and you love them and you &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-29-10:40.html"&gt;do
things because you gotta&lt;/a&gt;. But that doesn’t mean you will never
experience it as burdensome, only that you bear that burden mostly
willingly, albeit sometimes begrudgingly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And I think that the idea that this devotion and caring in the
context of a child means that you don’t experience any burdens just
completely fails to capture the very normal experience of parenting. And
I think that if you were to look at many actual concrete examples of day
to day parenting you would find that parents experience those children
as burdens fairly often. And typically they will regard those burdens as
worth it, because they want what’s best for their child, but that
doesn’t mean that they never experienced these “oh gosh, my life would
be so much easier if I didn’t have to deal with this shit.” moments.
Most importantly, having these sorts of thoughts &lt;em&gt;doesn’t mean they
don’t care about their child&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And this is a big part of why I care quite a lot about this example
and its basic failure to capture the essential humanity of real
situations. If you’re in a parenting situation like this, where you’re
exhausted and have to deal with a minor medical crisis or other such
problem with your child, there is definitely going to be some part of
you that goes “oh god. Yet another fucking thing.” And, when it does,
there’s another part of you which looks at that part and goes “Gosh. You
must be a bad parent for feeling that way.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And this seems to me to be what happens when you start with these
tidy narratives, theories of how things should be rather than looking at
specific concrete examples of things as they actually are. You try to
understand your experiences through that lens, and you fall short
because you fail to be the perfectly spherical human in a vacuum that
the theory predicts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If, on the other hand, you talk to other parents about their
experiences, pretty inevitably what will happen is they’ll tell you that
yeah of course they feel like that sometimes too.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I can’t find a single biographical detail about
Mayeroff, so I don’t know if he had kids. If he did, maybe he had an
unusually saintly degree of equanimity. But I doubt it. I think he just
had a theory and made up an example to fit it without thinking about
whether it was true.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you instead listen to things as they actually are, as told by
people who actually been through the experiences, what you’ll find is
that there is a richness and a messiness to them that doesn’t conform to
sort of very tidy theories that say how things should work. And I think
this is key to personal growth, to self forgiveness, to navigating the
world in a humane manner, and being kind to both yourself and others.
You have to encounter humanity in all its messy complexity, rather than
humanity as you would like to idealise it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a smaller context, I’ve been sort of developing this theme
recently because I’ve been writing a bunch of really mundane blog posts.
These are things like &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-23-21:48.html"&gt;here’s
how I clean my kitchen&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-13-14:46.html"&gt;I had
to cook something on short notice in 45 minutes&lt;/a&gt;, or even just &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-14-21:32.html"&gt;here’s
some stuff I learned playing Slay the Spire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Each of these starts from a very concrete experience, talking about
how I navigated it and what I’ve learned in doing so. It’s not purely a
narrative about a specific thing - it sort of tries to point out where
I’ve used some idea that I think generalizes or some oddly useful
principle, but it is still fundamentally the story of that particular
event.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think these pieces are in many ways much more useful because they
are forced to grapple with the concrete reality of the task at hand. So
they contain a lot of details and how those details were dealt with that
would not have been present if I had started from some much more general
theory. I do then tend to write a little bit about generalisable lessons
from them of course, but I think starting from a real and detail-rich
experience and trying to figure out how to transfer it to other similar
situations gets you a lot further than trying to start from a tidy
theory and forcing your life into its procrustean view of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-15-22:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-16-18:31.html</id>
    <title>Recovering desire with care</title>
    <updated>2025-04-16T21:52:55+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Recovering desire with care&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-16&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently finished reading “The Reasons of Love” by Harry
Frankfurt.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;“By the author of the best-selling”On Bullshit”“. Harry
Frankfurt is a very respectable philosopher who writes really
interesting things about motivation and desire and how we live our
lives. He also wrote”On Bullshit”, which while genuinely excellent, ends
up being his Cherry Pie, and is the main thing people think of when he
comes up. I mentioned this book to a friend and her immediate response
was “Is that the bullshit guy?”. I imagine him grimacing every time
something like this happens, but I find it very funny.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s… one of those books that I don’t know whether or how to
recommend, because I got a huge amount out of reading it, but I don’t
know how much of that was actually in the book and how much of it was in
the context which I was reading it in. It’s short, well written, and
about as engaging as a moderately dry work of analytic philosophy can
be. I also cried multiple times while reading it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;But this is part of the context, and I’m easily brought
to tears at the moment. Don’t worry about it, I’m fine. Well, I’m not
fine, but things are trending in an upwards direction and the people who
need to know why I am sad do.&lt;/span&gt; So,
I guess I recommend it, and if you don’t like it then oh well it’s very
short.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things it discusses is what it means to care about some
outcome, and how this contrasts with desiring it. He says you can desire
some outcome without particularly caring about it. e.g. When bored, you
might watch a movie to alleviate that. You desire to watch the movie to
alleviate the boredom but that doesn’t mean you particularly care about
the movie. You can care about your work, but be so burned out that you
can’t manage any desire to do good work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Frankfurt suggests that caring consists, in part, of wanting or
thinking that it is important to desire the end. When you care about
something, and also desire it, that desire feels harmonious with your
intentions. When your desires - either their presence or their absence -
conflicts with what you care about, you desire (or perhaps just will) to
change your desires. When things are going well, your desires are the
same as (or at least compatible with) your cares, and when things are
going badly, the two diverge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this view, part of what enables the “&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-29-10:40.html"&gt;you
gotta&lt;/a&gt;” attitude is that you care about the thing that needs doing
(you think it’s important) even if you don’t want to do it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This isn’t entirely true of course, because sometimes
what enables it is that you care about something that acts as a standin
- what Agnes Callard calls a proleptic value. For example when H doesn’t
want to do something and I tell her to do it anyway, she may also not
care, but it’s still important and part of the role of a parent is to
help her understand that it’s important, and your good opinion as the
parent acts as the standin.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This distinction between desiring and caring is interesting
contrasted with some things I’ve thought and written about caring
before. Back in ancient days I wrote about &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;burnout as
acedia&lt;/a&gt;, in which I said:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acedia (pronounced a-seed-ee-a) is a state of feeling unable to care.
It’s not the mere absence of caring about things, but the feeling that
caring is difficult or impossible. As a sense of hopelessness is to
hoping, a sense of acedia is to caring.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Wiktionary gives the much simpler definition of
“spiritual or mental sloth; apathy.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think that when I wrote this, I was very much conflating desiring
and caring. I actually think the post works &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; with
Frankfurt’s notion of caring,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And its conclusions tie in very well with Frankfurt’s
later in the book.&lt;/span&gt; but at the time I think
I was very much implicitly conflating an inability to &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;
things and an inability to &lt;em&gt;care about things&lt;/em&gt;, and I think these
are actually pointing at very different experiences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have pretty longstanding issues with depression, and I’m not very
good at being happy. I’ve often found it’s hard for me to really desire
things in any stable way - I’m certainly not unable to have desires, but
they tend to be short lasting and not particularly intense, and tends to
be oriented much more around comfort and reducing distress than in
seeking joy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this difficulty in desiring things would previously have
seemed to me like acedia in the sense I outlined, but this clearly
conflicts with the idea that what I struggle with is &lt;em&gt;caring&lt;/em&gt;. If
you look at how I actually behave it’s really obvious that I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;
care about things. I care a lot, and I care quite stably about them. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-23-13:27.html"&gt;I care
so much it hurts&lt;/a&gt;. Whether I manage to act on that caring is highly
variable, but a lot of what I do is driven by a burning sense that &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/this-is-important"&gt;this is
important&lt;/a&gt;. Some of the things I care about are clearly in conflict,
but I don’t know that they have to be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Frankfurt says that when you find yourself caring about something but
not desiring it, you desire to desire it and will seek to rekindle your
desire for it. I think that’s true, but I’m left with a question…
how?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the answer is that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-22-21:54.html"&gt;there
is no sludge&lt;/a&gt;. There is no generalised failure to desire. What there
is is a collection of individual desires, all of which I have thorugh
one reason or another lost the ability to express.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I still care about them, and given that I should be able to
express them again. Starting from the care, and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;tracing
the pathways out from there&lt;/a&gt; and seeing where they are blocked, you
should be able to find the ability to want that thing again, or at least
acknowledge that you really do no longer care about it and also &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;don’t
believe you should&lt;/a&gt; and start to let that go.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-16-18:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-17-18:19.html</id>
    <title>Moving the consistency bubble around</title>
    <updated>2025-04-17T21:52:40+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Moving the consistency bubble around&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note: This is a post where I am thinking out loud about a problem I’m
trying to solve. I expect I will find out the solution I outline in here
doesn’t work or needs modification.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something I have found is that, much to my regret, my life is much
better when I am a morning person. It is also very hard for me to
reliably be a morning person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In theory, this is a simple matter. If I set my alarm to go off early
every day, I’ll get up early every day.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;lol. lmao.&lt;/span&gt;
This is what all of the good sleep hygiene advice suggests after
all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s just one problem: I don’t want to do this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, OK. Why not?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this is that I wake up feeling like death a lot of mornings.
This isn’t as common as it was when I was still dependent on caffeine (a
significant part of my problem with mornings when on caffeine is that I
wake up with massive caffeine withdrawal). This both makes me very
unwilling to get out of bed, but also means that I actually need the
extra sleep or I’ll be kinda useless all day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why do I wake up feeling like shit in the morning?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, one reason is that my sleep onset time isn’t consistent. If I
wake up at 7AM (which I usually do right now because of the dawn
chorus), I’ll be fine if I got to sleep before midnight and feel
exhausted if I got to sleep around 2AM.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, in order to wake up in the morning, I need to make my bed time
consistent.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;rofl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Obviously I’m not going to do that. I could try, but it’s the sort of
habit change where it’s too easy to disrupt,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;For example it might get to late and I might realise
I’ve not written a notebook post today…&lt;/span&gt; and
then disruptions compound. I &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; like to go to bed before 11
more consistently than I currently do, and that &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; be a good
thing to change, but I think if I make getting up in the morning reliant
on going to bed before 11 I’ll end up failing at both. This is
compounded because often the reason my bedtime is inconsistent is that
some mornings I wake up late. So in order to get to sleep on time I need
to wake up on time, and in order to wake up on time I have to get to
sleep on time…&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a common problem with anything with a feedback loop in it:
Moving any part of the system requires moving every part of the system.
This is hard, and as soon as one part fails it all comes tumbling down.
The only way out is to break the feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the question is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I get up reliably in the morning without having to go to bed
reliably in the evening?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I do that, how do I avoid feeling like shit during the day?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Previously, I’ve had a pretty good answer to that: Caffeine! I would
wake up, take a caffeine pill, and then go back to sleep until it kicked
in and I felt motivated to get out of bed. This worked pretty well. But…
I’m not using caffeine any more.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One option would be to just &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-29-10:40.html"&gt;well
you gotta&lt;/a&gt; and force myself out of bed knowing that I’ll feel shit on
doing so, but I don’t think that’s going to work. If there’s a genuine
thing that I gotta do in the morning, that’s one thing&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;When this was the case I have in fact managed to
consistently be a morning person.&lt;/span&gt;,
and force myself out of bed anyway. But morning David is not going to be
amenable to this plan, because among other reasons I don’t like feeling
like shit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think that the most reliable solution here is to try to address the
“feel like shit” part on days where I fail to get enough sleep, and I
think the solution to that is just… &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-rest"&gt;have a nap&lt;/a&gt; if I
need to. That way I’m not making a decision about whether or not to feel
like shit today, I’m just making a decision about whether to get out of
bed, and the nap is there as a safety net if I need it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If I build into the schedule of the day that I have a nap some time
late morning / early afternoon, but get up and shower consistently each
morning, this adds consistency into the system and removes the negative
feedback against it by creating an alternative safer place for
inconsistency to arrive. I can expand or contract the amount of napping
available, while trying to keep my normal wake up time consistent. I
don’t know if this is going to work, but I think it’s plausible. This
changes the sleep system into one where the parameter I want to control
(inconsistency of when I sleep) is moved into trying to minimise nap
time, and where destabilising will tend not to result in the whole thing
spiralling out of control, because the variance is kept in a separate
container that can be isolated from the rest of the sleep schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-17-18:19.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-18-23:33.html</id>
    <title>Sometimes things are actually important</title>
    <updated>2025-04-18T23:48:09+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Sometimes things are actually important&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-18&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buddha: happiness is obtained by embracing the four noble truths and
relinquishing desire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Satan: so what you’re saying is that if I were to relinquish the
desire to torture Richard Nixon, that would make me… happy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buddha: well, no… I think that might be a special case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(From “Old Harry’s Game”, paraphrased from memory because I couldn’t
be bothered to find the original)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Richard Nixon might also struggle to relinquish the desire to
not be tortured by Satan.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m thinking about this exchange because I’m reading “The option
method: the myth of unhappiness”, which is volume one of the collected
works of Bruce Di Marsico, and it’s making me want to punch the author
in the face and see whether he still believes that how you feel is
purely a choice about whether or not to be happy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In his defence, he does from time to time insist that he’s not
telling anyone that they shouldn’t be unhappy. It’s just that he does
this sprinkled occasionally throughout constant diatribes about how
unhappiness isn’t real and you’re only unhappy if you choose to be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s an attitude that I often wonder about that I generally
attribute to inadequate mathematical education, which is when people
make grand pronouncements and it’s clear they have not made any attempt
to find a counterexample.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This book, in particular, it feels like it suffers from a pervasive
problem in a lot of therapy culture: it doesn’t seem to understand that
some things actually for real matter, and the nature of them mattering
is not fully under your control, and while you do have some choice how
to respond to it, many of the responses you could in theory choose are
inaccessible to you and would in fact be bad if you could access
them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m imagining this method being applied to someone in an abusive
relationship and Bruce telling the abused partner that their unhappiness
is only in how they react to their partner’s violence, and I want to
punch him all over again and this time not in order to make a rhetorical
point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do not, I think, believe that he would in fact do this. Certainly I
hope he would not. But he is making grand pronouncements about how the
world works that would not hold up this example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the book talks a big talk about what it means to be crazy,
in a way that makes it very clear that he has never experienced anyone
having an actual psychotic episode.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a pervasive disclaimer that I maintain all advice, therapy,
and self help has that it fails to include in the literal test: “this
advice has a domain of applicability, and the author is not competent to
assess that domain”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But when you make grand universal claims about the nature of human
experience, it tends to get my back up even if there might be something
useful there. It does not feel like a genuine attempt to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-15-22:18.html"&gt;actually
engage iwth human experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lisa has a good test question when trying to understand a new domain:
“where wouldn’t you use this?”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this question is a little unfair in general because there are
areas where there are easy answers to this but people are bad at
answering because they’re not used to using their brains in minimally
competent ways. That is, it’s very easy to answer, but only if you
actually ever think in terms of looking for counterexamples.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to prime this, I often suggest a list of standard examples.
For example, when trying to understand a new concept, try asking “is a
cat an example of this concept?”. It often forces people to define the
outside better than they naturally would.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So far at least, the option method does not do a good job of
distinguishing why a cat is not happiness. More relevantly, it doesn’t
seem to acknowledge that if you were bitten by a cat you might
legitimately be unhappy about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, this book strikes me as an example of a pervasive problem
with a lot of therapy: it fails to recognise that the real world
actually exists and matters. It assumes that all problems come from
within, and all the changes that matter are in yourself. If you feel bad
about an event, the problem is in your response to the event. If you
want to change how you feel, change yourself not the world that you are
responding to. And often that’s true! I think particularly if you’re a
therapist seeing an endless see of &lt;sub&gt;mediocrities&lt;/sub&gt; perfectly
normal people who are miserable despite nothing terribly going wrong in
their lives, you’re extra prone to thinking it’s true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve had very frustrating conversations with even otherwise very good
therapists in the past where they really didn’t seem to grasp that yes
that I recognised that it wasn’t solely my responsibility to solve a
particular problem, but that the issue at hand was not my feelings of
responsibility but that there was an actual problem that needed to be
solved and nobody else who could take responsibility for it was, and
regardless of whether it was my fault or not I would still feel bad if
the bad thing happened because I cared about the outcome.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;There’s a wide range of things this could be referring
to and I’m not being specific because of privacy reasons, but the actual
example I have in mind was really boringly straightforward and obviously
a problem in which a real actual person suffered and which only one of a
handful of people could do anything about.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because the reality is that some things do actually matter, and while
you can in theory choose how you react to those things, in practice I
bet you can’t and also choosing to be happy about things that are
actually bad (according to whatever standards are important to you) will
go worse for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If what you are searching for is really a calm equanimity in the face
of all things… well, let me know how it goes for you, and I wish you all
the best, but it continues to be my position that what is needed is to
help people act better in the world, and gaslighting people into
thinking all their problems are in their beliefs about the situation
doesn’t achieve that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of why I’m reading about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-16-18:31.html"&gt;care&lt;/a&gt;
at the moment is that it seems to provide a better starting point.
Regardless of how you feel, some things are &lt;em&gt;actually important&lt;/em&gt;,
and you want to bring your feelings in line with that importance rather
than just seeking happiness whatever happens.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-18-23:33.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-21-20:49.html</id>
    <title>Resuming habits</title>
    <updated>2025-04-21T20:52:11+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Resuming habits&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-21&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I took a deliberate break from the daily posting habit over the
easter weekend. I think this was the right choice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But now, I’m faced with a perennial difficult problem: Once you’ve
paused a habit, you’ve lost inertia, and now you have to deal with the
difficult task of starting again from a cold start.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I’ve often found in the past is that this causes you to delay,
and then the habit develops an ugh field, and this makes it harder and
harder to start, and suddenly months have passed without you having
touched it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the solution to this is that whenever resuming a habit, even
after an incredibly short break but certainly after a long one, you
should deliberately do so in the lowest effort way possible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Like this.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-21-20:49.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-22-16:32.html</id>
    <title>Algebra and insight</title>
    <updated>2025-04-22T18:07:01+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Algebra and insight&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-22&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was reading up on Markov Chains today, as one does, partially
reminding myself about them and partly filling in some gaps in my
knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One bit I was reading about was reversible distributions. If you’ve
got some transition matrix &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(P_{ij}\)&lt;/span&gt;,
a reversible distribution for it is a probability distribution &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q\)&lt;/span&gt; over the states such that &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q_i P_{ij} = q_j P_{ji}\)&lt;/span&gt;. If you also lack
any intuition about what that means, me too at the point at which it’s
introduced. The broad intuition is that a Markov chain in a reversible
distribution can be “run backwards in time” and you can’t tell the
difference, but the main significance is that it’s an easy property to
verify that has strong consequences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specifically, it’s a theorem that every reversible distribution is
stationary. That is, if &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q\)&lt;/span&gt; is
reversible then &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q_i = \sum\limits_j P_{ji}
q_j\)&lt;/span&gt; for all &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; - the
distribution is not changed by running the Markov chain forwards.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The proof of this presented in the text I was reading is as
follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can write &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q_i = q_i \sum\limits_j
P_{ij}\)&lt;/span&gt; (because it’s a standard property of transition matrices
that this sum is 1), so &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q_i = \sum\limits_j
q_i P_{ij} = \sum\limits_j q_j P_{ji}\)&lt;/span&gt;, so &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q\)&lt;/span&gt; is stationary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can follow this proof of course. It’s very simple algebra. But
there’s something about it that feels like a magic trick. I don’t feel
like I’ve got any actual insight into the nature of reversible
distributions or have any sense of why they must be stationary from
this. I’m sure there are plenty of mathematicians who could, and I’m not
even sure that I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; that insight, but it bugged me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thinking about it a bit more lead me to come up with the following
alternative proof&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Which I suspect I have cribbed in some sort of
half-remembered manner from Geoffrey Grimmett’s “Probability on Graphs”,
but if so it was useful to recreate it from memory anyway.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One way to think about distributions on markov chains is that you’ve
got a certain amount of “stuff” (probability mass) floating around, and
at each step that you run the Markov chain, this probability mass flows
around the graph.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you’ve got a probability distribution &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q\)&lt;/span&gt;, all of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q_i\)&lt;/span&gt; flows out of node &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(\sum\limits_j q_j P_{ji}\)&lt;/span&gt; flows into it.
That is, for each node &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(j\)&lt;/span&gt;, the mass
in it flows out to every other node, and the fraction of it that goes to
&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; is &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(P_{ji}\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A distribution is stationary if for all &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q_i =
\sum\limits_j P_{ji} q_j\)&lt;/span&gt;, but equally we can write this as
&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q_i - \sum\limits_j P_{ji} q_j  =
0\)&lt;/span&gt;. The net flow of mass out of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; is 0.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can write this flow of mass out of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q_i\)&lt;/span&gt; as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(q_i =
\sum\limits_j q_i P_{ij}\)&lt;/span&gt; - the sum of the mass flowing to each
&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(j\)&lt;/span&gt;. So the net flow of mass out of
&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; is &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(\sum\limits_j P_{ij} q_i - P_{ji} q_j\)&lt;/span&gt;.
That is, there is a net flow along each edge, let’s say &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(f_{ij} = P_{ij} q_i - P_{ji} q_j\)&lt;/span&gt;. The
probability of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; remains unchanged
if &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(\sum\limits_j f_{ij} = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, the reversability condition is precisely that all of the
&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(f_{ij} = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;. That is, there is no
net flow of mass along each edge. As a result, a reversible distribution
is necessarily stationary, because a much stronger condition applies:
Not only is the total net flow across the edges from &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; equal to 0, it’s 0 along each edge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This proof is in some sense much worse. It’s longer and involves more
algebra rather than less. But after reading this proof I felt like I
understood why reversibility obviously implied a distribution was
stationary, and also why it was a much stronger condition than being
stationary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think mathematics - and many other things - benefits hugely from
this sort of chewing on a problem and seeing it from different angles
until it actually makes sense. If you just know that a result is true,
you often find yourself unable to really use it. If you understand at an
intuitive level why it’s true, it will stick with you and you can really
see how to apply it, including in cases where it doesn’t quite hold but
something similar does. Proof without developing insight alongside it is
certainly better than no proof, but it’s in some sense fundamentally
fragile and untrustworthy, and it’s often better to mull it over until
you find the right way to break up the problem to actually allow it to
make sense at an emotional level.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-22-16:32.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-23-14:03.html</id>
    <title>What is probabilistic programming?</title>
    <updated>2025-04-23T14:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;What is probabilistic programming?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Friends and family often ask me what probabilistic programming is.
This isn’t very surprising, as I currently work in probabilistic
programming. Unfortunately I haven’t had a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good answer for
them, as this is quite a recent development for me and I haven’t fully
understood the boundaries of the field.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think also it’s hard to answer because the field is a little
confused about what it is, and there’s a “What the field says it is”
answer and “What the field actually is” answer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I’m going to try to give my own answer of what I think the field
is. It will be a bit overbroad and claim some territory that could
equally be put in other fields, but I think the overbroad definition is
more informative than the overly narrow one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First, let me give you a narrow answer that I think people would
classically give:&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Probabilistic_programming"&gt;the
wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; gives.&lt;/span&gt; Probabilistic programming is the
field of developing probabilistic programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What’s a probabilistic programming language? Well it’s a particular
type of tool for doing the thing I’m about to describe in the general
answer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, this is what I think: Probabilistic programming is the field of
constructing random samplers with precise distributional properties,
centrally but not exclusively&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;That is, this is the origin of the field and the major
driver of progress in it, but the techniques are more broadly useful and
using them to do other things would still be considered probabilistic
programming.&lt;/span&gt; with the goal of
developing better Monte Carlo methods for doing statistics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I will now unpack all of those terms so that this definition actually
makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;random sampler&lt;/em&gt; is a program that, when run, generates some
value, typically at random. You could imagine e.g. a coin flip, which
randomly generates either “heads” or “tails” as your prototypical random
sampler. The work I did in Hypothesis is also an example of a random
sampler, where it generates test cases for checking your program with by
making a bunch of choices at random.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Random samplers have the virtue of being very easy to construct - you
can just write a simple program that makes a bunch of random choices and
bam you’ve got a random sampler.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, it’s often hard to reason about the behaviour of random
samplers, and in particular to construct random samplers that behave in
particular ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, suppose you were creating a random sampler to simulate
some physical process - say, the weather - it’s quite important that if
about 10% of your random samples say it’s going to rain tomorrow, then
you should expect that about 10% of the time tomorrow there will be
rain.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;What does that mean? Don’t worry about it too precisely.
If you want to worry about it more precisely, read &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-29-09:43.html"&gt;Probably
enough probability for you&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-05-10:29.html"&gt;World
counting as a tool for understanding probability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Having random samplers that have accurate distributional properties
like this - e.g. that our random model of the weather accurately
reflects what we should believe about the weather - is an essential
property for doing &lt;em&gt;monte carlo simulations&lt;/em&gt;, which just means
that you run a bunch of random simulations and use those as a
representative of the range for the true value you’re trying to
calculate. e.g. if you want to know if it’s going to rain on Tuesday,
run a few thousand weather simulations and see what fraction of them
rain on Tuesday. If you want to know the total rainfall you should
expect, average the total rainfall across all of your simulations,
etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are not the exact calculations that you might hope for in
classical statistics - what you get is a random number, and if you reran
the simulation you’d get a slightly different number, but it is a random
number that you can count on being very close to the true number you
want,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Figuring out how close is part of the general body of
theory needed and developed in doing probabilistic programming.&lt;/span&gt; and you can get it as close as you
like by running more simulations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, that’s all very well, but what this gives you is an accurate
estimator of these values &lt;em&gt;in your simulation&lt;/em&gt;. How do you get
your simulation right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is where probabilistic programming and its toolkit for trying to
control distributional properties of samplers comes in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular it often comes in via trying to do &lt;em&gt;Bayesian
inference&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bayesian inference works as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You start with some very general model of the world (a “prior
distribution”), and what data you would expect to see given specific
configurations of that world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You feed in a bunch of actual data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get an updated model of the world (a “posterior distribution”)
out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A great deal of probabilistic programming is concerned with how to do
this sort of Bayesian updating on random samplers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This allows for a very general approach to doing statistics:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You write a random sampler for a very broad world model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You feed in a bunch of data and do a Bayesian update on your sampler
to take into account the data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You run Monte Carlo simulations and use them to make predictions
about the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of the hard part is in Step 2. This is an almost impossibly
difficult problem to do in general. Many of the classic probabilistic
programming tools try to do this, and what you get is tools that
sometimes work very well and sometimes just run unusably slowly, with
very little ability to predict which situation you’ll be in or much
recourse for fixing it when it happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What the lab I’m in tries to do is to instead provide a toolkit that
makes it easy to write your own algorithms for your specific problem, by
providing an API for samples that you can perform a variety of
manipulations on - either standard algorithms or ones of your own
creation - that let you perform the update.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, in general, doing this bit well is where most of the active work
in probabilistic programming is, and why the tools have historically
been a bit underused. We’re hopeful that a mix of new improvements in
computing and new advances in probabilistic programming allow us to do a
lot better than we’ve previously seen, but this is still an active
research and development area, so we’ll see how that goes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-23-14:03.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
