<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2024-02-05T12:38:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-27-13:16.html</id>
    <title>Restrictions</title>
    <updated>2024-01-27T13:39:05-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Restrictions&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m staying on the 16th floor of a hotel at the moment. When I
arrived, this was a pleasing novelty. Buildings are rarely this tall at
home so I thought it was neat to have this casually be a thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then the fire alarm went off yesterday and I had to walk down 16
flights of stairs. I was less pleased by the novelty after that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(It turned out to be a false alarm, but I only found that out on the
ground floor)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It occurred to me belatedly that in actual fact I probably
&lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt; stay on the 16th floor of a hotel, because there’s no
guarantee of my ability to walk down 16 flights of stairs. As I
sometimes half-joke, it’s not that I’m disabled, I just sometimes can’t
walk. It doesn’t happen often, but maybe once every few months with no
warning my right knee goes and I can barely walk on it, and I would have
really struggled to make it down all those stairs if that had
happened.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that, today I am paying the cost of that with a significant
increase in the chronic pain in my right leg. My hip in particular
really doesn’t like me right now. Although I was able to walk, it comes
with genuine consequences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t thought about this before because tall hotels are largely
outside of my experience, so the thought never occurred. But not it has,
and I am aware of the risk. So, taking this new knowledge into account,
in future I should probably make a particular request when staying at
hotels to stay on a lower numbered floor. It’s the safe and responsible
thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to do that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this is just not wanting to overcorrect on rare events. I
think this is the first time I’ve had a fire alarm in a hotel I’ve
stayed in, and I’ve stayed in quite a few hotels. A rare event happened
and no terrible consequences occurred. This is a lousy prompt to create
a policy. Life doesn’t need more organisational scar tissue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Granted, asking to be on a lower floor isn’t a big deal (though it
would have required significantly more interaction with the hotel than I
did before arriving), but the aggregate effect of many things that are
individually not big deals adds up to quite a lot of effort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But more than that… adding many little restrictions and
accommodations results in a much smaller life. In the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-20-12:01.html"&gt;capacities&lt;/a&gt;
post I talked about how having a car lowers the activation energy of
many things, and so it’s not just that it’s easier to do the things you
were doing before, you do things that you wouldn’t previously done.
Adding restrictions makes many things that would previously have been
worth it not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Food is like this for me. I love eating out, and I love trying new
cuisines, but the difficulty of satisfying my dietary restrictions means
that I lose a lot of upside (many delicious things I can’t eat) and
experience a lot more downside (risk of digestive problems, awkward high
effort interactions with staff) and this means that many things are not
worth the effort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Individually, the losses are small. In aggregate though it makes
quite a meaningful impact to my life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve no great attachment to staying in tall hotels, but it’s quite
nice - it’s a pleasant novelty, and I enjoy the view. It would be no
great loss if I never did it again, but I do think the aggregate effect
of choosing to avoid these sorts of minor risks for an increase in
effort and a decrease in novelty would end up large, and would result in
a smaller and less lived life.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-27-13:16.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-28-16:21.html</id>
    <title>Visible parts of internal states</title>
    <updated>2024-01-28T17:37:20-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Visible parts of internal states&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I write a lot about feelings, emotions, etc. I’m well known for it,
and people say they find my writing on it helpful. So, let me tell you
something that I’m genuinely quite concerned about: What if everything
I’m saying is basically fake?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m very good at theorising and coming up with plausible explanations
for things, much better than I am at being reliably correct about them&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Not through any deep personal failings or idiosyncracies
you understand. Being correct is just hard.&lt;/span&gt;, so I’d probably be able to write
all this stuff even if actually it didn’t work at all and I was just
kidding myself about what had happened to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I don’t think this is the case. I’m &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt;
convinced that it’s not 100% the case. I’m… less convinced that it’s 0%
the case. A specific percentage is hard to pin down, but I do know that
I’m missing some important things, and I suspect some of them are in
areas that I’m pretty convinced I understand.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem with &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/describing-imaginary-experiences"&gt;describing
internal experiences&lt;/a&gt; is that there are no external reference points
that you can point to as a shared object. Part of why my &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/labelling-feelings"&gt;explanation
of labelling feelings&lt;/a&gt; focuses so heavily on externally visible
behaviour is that those are the bits that you can see. They constitute a
shared object you can talk about together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is a good partial measure of emotional progress. You
know that someone shouting and shaking their fist at you about how good
they are at anger management, how dare you say they’re not, is probably
fooling themselves.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;They could just be lying, but it’s such a bad lie that
fooling themselves seems more likely.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an extreme example, but I think you see a lot of this in the
self help space. e.g. I’ve seen plenty of people talk about how to
become less neurotic whose behaviour I’ve observed and, well, will not
be taking their advice too seriously.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Is it plausible that this is just because of their high
starting point and the thing they did is a genuine improvement?
Definitely! But it tends to be coupled with a lack of self awareness
about where they’ve ended up that makes me suspicious.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For my part, I think some of my claims to improvement are more
credible than others. I’ve definitely reduced my anxiety levels,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although experiences of attending dance classes have
definitely demonstrated that some claims I’ve made in the past to have
“fixed” my social anxiety are at best suspect. It does feel like a
different sort of thing - I find the experience stressful rather than
anxiety inducing - but I’m not sure the externally visible behaviour is
that different.&lt;/span&gt;, and I think a lot of my
presentation is more confident than it used to be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If, on the other hand, I claimed to have fixed my depression I think
you should look at a lot of my recent writing and put on your best
skeptical face.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’m working on it, OK?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think there’s a sort of general… knowing myself better, and
being better able to act on what I want, that I have improved at but am
still not good at. I can’t articulate this in a way that’s very
convincing though. It’s enough that I think it’s real, but maybe not
enough that you should too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The point is not, however, that you should only believe things are
real if you’ve got really clear visible evidence that they are. A lot of
purely internal things are real. It’s just hard to have full confidence
in them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means it’s &lt;em&gt;really nice&lt;/em&gt; when something nebulous and
internal that you’re trying to improve has some really clear externally
visible correlate. If nothing else, it makes it much easier to improve
the thing because you can just track whether the visible thing
improves.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Though beware &lt;a href="https://philarchive.org/rec/NGUVCH"&gt;value capture&lt;/a&gt;. No visible
improvement at all is suspicious, but once you start getting some
visible improvement more visible improvement will not continue to be
better indefinitely.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, one interesting handle I found on all of this recently is,
oddly, pilates.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried doing pilates and things like it in the past and I was bad
at it. Most of why I’m doing much better this time is not through any
deep personal progress or growth as a human being, I’m just paying a
really good teacher for one on one lessons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there is one specific thing that I’ve noticed that I can do now
that I don’t think I used to be able to do, which is that when I’m told
to do a movement and I can’t do the movement I can &lt;em&gt;figure out how to
do the movement&lt;/em&gt;. Most of the time anyway. There’s a specific sort
of introspection which feels a bit like… mentally rummaging around in
the relevant body part, wiggling it a bit and seeing what happens, until
I figure out how to use the right muscles to do the thing. I’m almost
certain I didn’t use to be able to do this, and now I can, and it feels
very much adjacent to the sort of introspection skills I’ve picked up
when doing Focusing or IFS or the like. This isn’t strong evidence for
any of that being useful of course, but it’s at least an interesting
link.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this observation of visible versions of internal goals
extends a lot into the exercise space more generally, although of course
most forms of exercise are visible to some degree. My overall exercise
goals are very internal in that they’re largely centred on being less in
pain. But subjective comparison of pain over time is hard. Sure I can
tell the difference between being in pain and not being in pain, but can
I tell the difference between being more in pain and less in pain? Not
reliably.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can, on the other hand, tell the difference between being able to
do an asian squat better or worse, or measure how long I can stand on
one leg for, and these are pretty good visible versions of the internal
experience of having better leg strength and mobility, so work well as
things to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-28-16:21.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-29-08:21.html</id>
    <title>Adaptive planning and grid systems</title>
    <updated>2024-01-29T08:32:32-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Adaptive planning and grid systems&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Consider, if you will, a perfectly flat city laid out in a perfectly
even grid, aligned with the compass directions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you are at grid reference (0, 0) and want to be at grid
reference (10, 10). You ask Google maps for a plan. What does it
say?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It will probably tell you something like “Go East 10 blocks, then go
North ten blocks”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is somewhat unintuitive but correct. You naturally think that
the shortest path between two points is a straight line and want to do a
sort of diagonal where you go East, then North, then East, then North,
then East, etc. or something like that, but on a grid system this
doesn’t buy you anything because each time you go North or East you
travel exactly one block, so every route you take must be exactly 20
blocks long. There is no route to your destination shorter than 20
blocks.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, a human ignoring Google maps will get there sooner than one
following it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is the correct fastest algorithm for getting to your
destination: Every time you are at an intersection, if there is a green
light for going either North or East, and that is a useful direction for
you to take (i.e. if you’re still South of destination and there’s a
North light, or if you’re still West of your destination and there’s an
East light), take it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Following this algorithm doesn’t reduce your travel distance. It
doesn’t even significantly reduce the amount of time you spend actually
driving. But it &lt;em&gt;significantly&lt;/em&gt; shortens your wait times along
the way.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;An interesting feature of this algorithm that I can’t
decide if it is a coincidence or not is that the resulting path will
look a lot closer to the straight line that you might have intuitively
drawn.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing about this algorithm is that it’s completely outside of
Google Maps’s ability to give you this plan. It’s not just that it’s not
a thing it considers, it’s not a thing that it &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; consider,
because there’s too much variability to predict exactly when the lights
are going to change on your journey, even if it had precise timing data.
This is however no problem for following the algorithm, because it is
&lt;em&gt;adaptive&lt;/em&gt; - it takes into account the information that you have
access to at the time of making the decision but do not have in
advance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Planning in advance is very useful, but it will always lack access to
this sort of on the ground information, and you can often improve on
purely up front plans by introducing an adaptive element to it like
this..&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The flipside of course is that we were able to do this here because
the decisions we confront in navigating a grid are &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-make-easy-decisions"&gt;easy&lt;/a&gt;.
Trying to make hard decisions adaptively introduces a significant cost
to executing the plan. One of the most important things to decide in
advance is how you are going to make decisions on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-29-08:21.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-30-07:03.html</id>
    <title>Computer ghost stories</title>
    <updated>2024-01-30T08:34:48-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Computer ghost stories&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-30&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was talking to a friend the other day and she related a story about
a friend of hers which she described as “Exactly the sort of story that
happens to him” and it occurred to me that I had recently had a story
that feels like exactly the sort of thing that happens to me. Given my
current interest in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-25-19:45.html"&gt;writing
stories about life&lt;/a&gt; it seems worth trying to develop a feel for that
sort of characteristic story.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is one of my characteristic sorts of stories: Ones in
which computers are haunted, and then Scooby Doo style you pull off the
mask and find it was old man unintended feature interactions all
along.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me set the scene: A week or so ago I was doing some work. All of
a sudden, focus was stolen out from under me,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is, of course, one of the worst crimes that a
computer can commit. Even worse than playing sound that I haven’t asked
for. Unfortunately we live in a high computer crime world.&lt;/span&gt; as
my browser insisted that I absolutely had to see the following
webcomic:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/353/"&gt;&lt;img alt="XKCD comic about flying using Python" src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/python.png"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want you to pause for a moment and think about why this might have
happened. I’ll explain shortly. Here’s a placeholder image to prevent
you from reading the spoilers too soon:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="A snake offering someone an apple" src="/images/applesnake.png"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;A snake offering someone an
apple&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the first thing you need to know is that this is what happens
when someone types “import antigravity” in Python. It’s a longstanding
and very tedious easter egg, of the sort that programmers think is
funny.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second thing you need to know is that I was in VS Code. Also my
Python virtualenv was lightly broken and as a result VS Code was failing
to find imports and I hadn’t gotten around to fixing this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This meant that when I was typing &lt;code&gt;import attrs&lt;/code&gt; it didn’t
find the &lt;code&gt;attrs&lt;/code&gt; library.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; means that VS Code went into its aggressively fuzzy
search mode, where it tries its hardest to find anything that might
match what you’re looking for.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, when I went back to VS Code to recreate what I’d just been doing
to trigger this, I tried retyping &lt;code&gt;import attrs&lt;/code&gt; and what
happened is that as I got to &lt;code&gt;import attr&lt;/code&gt; I saw that it was
displaying “import
&lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt;n&lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;ig&lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;avi&lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;y”.
The fact that all the characters in “attr” exist in “antigravity”
(albeit not in the same order) was enough to trigger that as a
suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And apparently, the fact that it was being suggested was enough to
trigger an import. Which runs arbitrary code. In this case, opening a
web browser.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/delight-in-the-imperfect"&gt;I
like this example because of how totally cursed it is&lt;/a&gt;, but it’s also
interesting in terms of how utterly inscrutable it is until you put
together two very easy pieces. Nobody I presented it to was able to
figure it out without me essentially giving the game away (I doubt I
would have been able to either). If you know about the easter egg it’s
at least clear what must have happened, but not how. But if you’re there
in front of the problem you can just retrace your steps and it’s almost
immediately clear what must have happened.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-30-07:03.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-31-07:40.html</id>
    <title>Learning from experts in having problems</title>
    <updated>2024-01-31T08:32:40-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Learning from experts in having problems&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-31&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was in a conversation with two other people, let’s call them Alex
and Pat,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Brought to you as the first two members of my standard
quartet of placeholder names: Alex, Pat, Kim, and Charlie. I wanted a
good set of gender neutral names to use when writing Voting by Example
and standardised on these.&lt;/span&gt; the other day where Alex and I had
clearly had rather more mental and physical health problems than Pat.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Or, possibly, had just hit the point of actually having
learn to deal with it when they hadn’t. I could very easily have been
Pat 10 years ago and it wasn’t because I lacked problems, I was just
ignoring them&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Alex and I were sharing tips about how to recognise different types
of low function days and what to do about them. I think we’d just been
talking about the significance of temperature in extremities - cold feet
in particular for me are a strong sign that my low function day will be
improved by something that raises my heart rate. A hot bath is an
excellent choice, jumping jacks are a solid second place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Pat said something to the tune of “Huh, I’ve never paid this much
attention to my body for debugging bad days”. Alex and I gently pointed
out that this was because they hadn’t had to, and that people with
sufficient problem in this space tended to learn these skills out of
necessity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, the thing is, these skills are actually useful to everyone, and
they’re not that hard to learn if someone is teaching you. But if you’ve
got relatively common and severe problems you both have a much stronger
signal to work with and many more opportunities to practice, making it
much easier to learn on your own. You’ve also got a much more urgent
need to learn them, so you tend to seek out literature on the subject,
have conversations like Alex and I were having, etc. and so naturally
become something of an expert on them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have that particular class of problem though,
you will still have cases where you urgently need the skills. Everyone
has bad days from time to time, everyone goes through bad experiences,
and knowing how to deal with strong emotions and low function and the
like is very useful for those times.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there’s a way of getting that without having to have to
have recurring mental and physical health problems: You can just talk to
and read people who do and pick up skills from them that they find
useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve adopted this strategy in the past by reading up on cPTSD. I’m
pretty confident I don’t have cPTSD, but the cPTSD literature is really
useful for understanding trigger management, and I certainly get
triggered. Knowing how to distinguish a Fawn from a Freeze from a Flight
is really useful,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It’s also useful but less difficult to distinguish these
from a Fight&lt;/span&gt; as is the more basic skill of being
able to notice the bare fact that I’m triggered at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another place where I’ve been actively using this strategy recently
is borrowing tactics from people with ADHD. I don’t have ADHD&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Though I have a significant number of friends and
strangers on the internet who randomly email me to tell me to go get my
ADHD diagnosed ASAP who disagree. I think they’re wrong. I have ADHD
tendencies but fall well short of actual ADHD.&lt;/span&gt;, but a lot of ADHD problems are
normal problems dialled up to 11, or experiencing normal things as if
they were the worst and most overwhelming version of them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But… sometimes you do actually get the worst and most overwhelming
version of them, or sometimes you’re exhausted and anxious and so it
also feels like everything you can normally handle is dialled up to 11,
and it sure is useful to have strategies for this case.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One general category of solution for when things get too overwhelming
is &lt;em&gt;externalisation of state&lt;/em&gt;. The easiest version oof this for
me is to just talk out loud about what I’m doing. “What am I doing this
morning? I need to finish writing my notebook post… I need to get
everything packed… I should look through all the drawers to make sure
I’ve not missed anything… I’ll do that now actually because it’s really
important and I mustn’t forget it”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A more extreme version of this which I’ve been deploying at work
recently is extremely detailed TODO lists in a shared slack channel
called drmaciver-todo.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Slack because I’m already always in Slack, so it stays
relevant, and shared because only shared digital objects have object
permance. I don’t know why this is, but for me and many others digital
objects are only real if they’re shared with other people. If only I
have access to them they fade from memory.&lt;/span&gt; This involves writing down
everything I have to do today, adding to it as things come up, modifying
it as I work on things, with big green checkmarks when tasks get
completed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This level of detailed TODO list is very much an ADHD strategy, or at
least a strategy I’ve learned from people with ADHD, but that’s because
right now I have very ADHD shaped problems: There is too much stuff to
fit in my head and it’s resulting in my being constantly distracted and
lost, and I need to externalise my working state. Essentially I’m
building a functioning &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-06-20-17:00.html"&gt;extended
brain&lt;/a&gt;, because my internal brain can’t cope with its task list right
now, and as a result borrowing strategies from people who regularly
can’t cope with their task list is very useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is another reason I like talking to people about their problems:
When I do, I learn about their solutions, and even if I don’t share
their exact problems there’s a very good chance that at some point in
the future I’ll have something similar enough that those solutions might
apply.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-31-07:40.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-02-01-15:09.html</id>
    <title>Anomaly report: The David that didn’t cough in the night-time</title>
    <updated>2024-02-01T17:24:14+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Anomaly report: The David that didn’t cough in the night-time&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-02-01&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve been travelling for the last 12 days and during this time
something really weird happened: I didn’t get ill during the entire
trip.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; happens. I get ill constantly at the best of
times, and I was in a new environment, surrounded by people,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Admittedly mostly in well ventilated spaces, and I
masked when in airports though not on airplanes.&lt;/span&gt; and extremely worn down.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I also got exposed to COVID on day 1, though I’ve had it
recently enough that I’m probably pretty immune, and we were outside so
it was probably safe.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I definitely felt like I &lt;em&gt;started&lt;/em&gt; getting ill a few times. I
got the telltale sore throat that is a common beginning of illness for
me, and there was one evening that I felt a little bit under the
weather… and each time this then just immediately went away.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is extremely surprising, but I have a theory. It’s not a good
enough theory that I have any confidence in it yet, but it’s got a
plausible mechanism of action for causing this, and seems enough worth
trying that I’m going to keep going for a bit and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The mechanism is this: While travelling, I was using &lt;a href="https://smartmouth.com/"&gt;Smartmouth zinc-activated mouthwash&lt;/a&gt;.
I ran into it because I was looking for zinc lozenges&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Which I do low key believe fend off colds, but
admittedly based on very weak evidence relative to their level of
inconvenience&lt;/span&gt; and
could only find homeopathic ones, but I also needed mouth wash, saw
this, and reckoned it was worth a go.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic idea as to why this, or zinc lozenges, might work is that
zinc is antiviral (as well as being antibacterial, which is its major
intended purpose in Smartmouth), so coating your mouth with zinc kills
off any virus living in your throat. This lines up with my experience of
starting to get sore throats and have them mysteriously go away.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is this a real effect? Unsure. Probably not. I think it’s worth
exploring further from a &lt;a href="https://acesounderglass.com/2022/10/13/my-resentful-story-of-becoming-a-medical-miracle/"&gt;luck-based
medicine&lt;/a&gt; point of view though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Other plausible theories include:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I really wasn’t exposed to that much virus with the quality of the
air filtration where I was.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was running on adrenaline, and now I’m about to get sick now that
this has calmed down a bit.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This isn’t consistent with when I normally get ill while
travelling though.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mostly I’m just preregistering the theory.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And wanted an easy post I could phone in having just
arrived home from a very long flight.&lt;/span&gt;
I’ll continue trying it for a while and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-02-01-15:09.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-02-02-12:17.html</id>
    <title>Learning to walk right</title>
    <updated>2024-02-02T15:39:36+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Learning to walk right&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-02-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of the back of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-24-22:09.html"&gt;my
realisation that I was standing on one leg wrong&lt;/a&gt; I had another
important insight of this type: I was walking wrong, and I could just
walk right instead..&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s a longstanding problem of mine that I have flat feet, and this
causes a lot of problems for my legs, especially my right leg. This
causes my knees to bow inwards and generally seems to underly a lot of
my general physical problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;During a walk the other day after I figured out the standing on one
leg thing, I had an important insight: I could just walk
differently.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I said on discord at the time:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a longstanding problem with flat feet. Major issue, arguably
my most basic one that creates all my other body issues&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried a bunch of things to fix this (albeit not very diligently)
and nothing seems to have helped&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’ve just figured out the solution and it’s so fucking
annoying&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is to pay attention to my feet while I’m walking and stop
walking with them flat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to be clear this is much harder. It feels difficult and
unnatural. But I think that’s actually a sign that it’s working for
building muscles I’ve neglected&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(In answer to a question about how) To a large degree arch is a thing
you do not a thing you have. But more specifically I guess: roll your
feet outwards so that more or the weight is on the outside of the
foot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of “flat feet” is really about letting what arch there is
collapse inwards&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also wear barefoot shoes and have been puzzled at how little they
helped, and I think the reason is that they’re a bottleneck on fixing
the habit of walking wrong but removing that bottleneck doesn’t cause
the habit to fix itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I’ve been working on a wrong implicit model where I’ve
treated physical problems as things that will fix themselves if you work
on the necessary muscles and stop doing the thing that creates the
problem, but the correct model is maybe more like “make sure you’re
using the right muscles and motions and that will strengthen the muscles
you need for doing it right directly”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway I’ve been practicing this exercise on and off for a few days
and… turns out this is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’d started to have suspicions this morning when I tried practicing
the position when standing in the shower, and noticed how much it
scrunched my toes up. That’s very much not the toe position of a healthy
walk.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I went to my one on one Pilates session and asked to go off
script and basically just focus on gait and leg exercises.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This isn’t really a pilates thing, I’m just relying on
my teacher’s broader expertise in body mechanics.&lt;/span&gt;. We
concluded that basically this was just walking differently wrong, wasn’t
actually exercising the right muscles, and probably was bad for my
hips.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think that the core insight that you can just walk differently
is good and I will be drawing on it, but I think probably (as various
people pointed out to me on discord) it’s never going to be quite this
easy. If you’re walking wrong you probably need to put in some active
effort into learning what walking right looks like, and yes developing
the muscles in question with some more basic movements, rather than just
lifting up your arches and expecting the problem to be solved.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-02-02-12:17.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-02-04-13:26.html</id>
    <title>Invitations and exclusions</title>
    <updated>2024-02-04T13:48:26+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Invitations and exclusions&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-02-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s a thing that I do in the design of my discord server that to
me seems just absolutely blindingly obviously the correct way to do it,
and is also directly the opposite of how everyone else does it, in a way
that very obviously causes problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s this: A channel is an &lt;em&gt;invitation to start a conversation
about a subject&lt;/em&gt;, not a place where &lt;em&gt;only that subject is
appropriate&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, we’ve got the #games channel. This is a place where you
are invited to talk about games. Sometimes it’s also a place where we
talk about philosophy, or programming, or parenting… but it’s mostly
about games. Looking at the #games channel I don’t really see much that
isn’t about games recently, and that’s fine too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is one very big consequence of this approach: We almost never
have to have talk about something being off-topic and request moving it
to a different channel.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;There are a few cases where we do that, but it’s always
because of more specific rules than a general “stay on topic” category.
During the height of the pandemic, we tried to uh quarantine pandemic
chat to #pandemic, and the owner of a &lt;a href="https://tasshin.com/blog/feeds-an-anthropological-report-on-a-powerful-online-social-technology/"&gt;feed&lt;/a&gt;
can always ask for conversations to be moved elsewhere.&lt;/span&gt; This removes a constant source of
background anxiety about staying on topic, and also it allows for many
conversations to occur that otherwise would be stifled.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason #games is a place to talk about anything isn’t because
people come to #games to talk about anything. It would be weird to just
randomly post a picture of your lunch in #games, because that’s not how
you start a conversation about #games. We don’t police that, it’s just
not a thing that people do because why would they? But if, for example,
you were talking about games you play with your kid, and it branched
into a more general conversation about parenting, that would be
absolutely fine, and the conversation could continue to be about
parenting for as long as you wanted it to, without any sense that you
were doing something wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of this approach is it changes when channels are
created. In the traditional approach, you create channels when volume on
a particular topic gets too high, and you want a place for it to go,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;We do occasionally do this of course. We created
#dubious-ontologies when sandwich discourse took over #chatter for the
third day running, and we branched off #slay-the-spire from #games
because Slay the Spire conversation was dominating too much and people
wanted a space where they could talk about games despite not being
interested in Slay the Spire.&lt;/span&gt; while on my discord I create
channels when there’s a particular topic I want to encourage more
conversation about (or when someone else suggests similar) and creating
a channel for it invites that conversation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that… This system obviously works better on a bunch of
specific practical factors, but to me the most important part of it is
that it removes a general background level of… cop behaviour from the
discord. In places where there’s a big focus on staying on topic, it
feels like everyone is constantly policing other people using a channel
wrong, and everyone is constantly worried that they might be using a
channel wrong, and this creates a pervasive background of low-grade
suspicion and anxiety that I don’t think is good for anyone, and in
general I really recommend designing systems that don’t make everyone
lightly miserable.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-02-04-13:26.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-02-04-14:50.html</id>
    <title>Help is easy to find these days</title>
    <updated>2024-02-04T15:38:04+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Help is easy to find these days&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-02-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve previously written &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:53.html"&gt;Getting
to know the right people&lt;/a&gt; about how it’s very hard to find quality
tradespeople and the best way to do it is through networking from
existing quality tradespeople, but there’s a bootstrapping problem of
how you find the original ones. I’ve now figured out the solution to
this problem and it’s sortof embarrassingly easy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s this: You find your local Facebook group&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;You almost certainly have a local Facebook group. I live
in a small town and there’s a 20k strong group for it and a few
neighbouring towns. Looking at the last two places I lived in London I
also find such groups&lt;/span&gt; and
ask there whether anyone can recommend someone to do this. This will
give you a mix of potential candidates responding to you directly and
recommendations from people who have had good experiences. The latter
aren’t &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; trustworthy, but they’re still a decent
positive signal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wrote about this a bit in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-20-12:01.html"&gt;the
post on developing capacities&lt;/a&gt;, but I’m taking advantage of it again
right now and it felt like it was worth its own post, where I used the
group to find a PA.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The PA in question unfortunately hasn’t really worked out, which is
representative of the problem in the original “getting to know the right
people” post. The title of this post is &lt;em&gt;help&lt;/em&gt; is easy to find
these days, but that doesn’t mean &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; help is. You still have
to find reliable people. But with the PA not having worked out, I’ll
just be going back to the original post and looking through the 5-10
other responses. There are plenty of candidates, some of whom are
vouched for, and it’s easy enough to try them out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ll have to find a different trial task though, because now that
I’ve got this approach just finding us a cleaner is a bit too easy of a
task. I’ve replied to a cleaner who got in touch regarding our initial
PA posting (I mentioned this as an example task there) and they’re
coming by on Thursday.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Or possibly they’ll come by on Thursday, be a disaster,
and we’ll have this task live again. Who knows?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But for me this is a much easier approach than previously where I was
using Google, because there I have to search, then I have to contact
them, and so on. Cold contacting is the worst, and also it tends to
result in a very rate of non or negative answers. e.g. when I last
looked for cleaners I did try contacting a couple and none of them had
availability. In contrast, asking for people on the Facebook group
heavily selects for people who have availability, and more importantly
they will come to you for you to respond to, which is much easier.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it particularly helps to start this with lots of easy
problems, because then you end up building up a network of people early
on before you really need it. e.g. A cleaner or a PA are much lower risk
things to try out than a plumber, because when they get things wrong it
doesn’t generally flood your house.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-02-04-14:50.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-02-05-12:38.html</id>
    <title>Yelling at the problem usually doesn’t work</title>
    <updated>2024-02-05T12:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Yelling at the problem usually doesn’t work&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-02-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you a little debugging story I’ve had, or rather mostly
failed to have, for a few months.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I got some airpods pro. This is a somewhat questionable life choice
because although I have a mac, I also have an android phone, and as such
Apple considers me a second class citizen of the airpods ecosystem. To
add to my crimes, I don’t even use iCloud (this will be relevant
later).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point, my airpods developed the most absolutely infuriating
bug: They would just randomly make chirping noises. Usually when I
opened or shut the case (it wasn’t charging noises - I’d turned those
off) but sometimes just for the hell of it with no particular prompting,
rhyme, or reason.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did some googling, asked around, and nobody seemed to have any
ideas as to what was up. It was generally concluded that probably the
solution to this was to connect them to my iphone and see what the info
there said.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’m actually not convinced it would have said any more
than connecting them to my mac would, but I don’t know for sure.&lt;/span&gt; This was, of course, unhelpful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, I adopted a reasonable and sensible debugging strategy in which I
systematically appraoched the problem and, err… OK that’s not what
happened. What actually happened is that I gave up on trying to fix it
and got angry at the fucking stupid unreasonable behavior of this shitty
device that Apple had inflicted on me, and cursed the name of every
Apple developer, and shouted at the airpods to shut the fuck up.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I have a reasonable and proportionate hatred of devices
that make noise when they shouldn’t, but this is a particularly
egregious example because &lt;em&gt;the entire point&lt;/em&gt; of headphones is
that you want to listen to something &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; making a noise
that bothers other people, and also because I’ll often want to have
headphones in my bedroom and, well, I do not appreciate random chirping
in the middle of the night&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It seems to be a recurring theme that I run into the most absolutely
cursed behaviour from Apple and every Apple user I talk to swears blind
that this &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; happens and I probably shouldn’t have spat on
the grave of Steve Jobs that one time or whatever dreadful sin it was I
must have committed to get some egregious behaviour from the
near-saintlike level of quality you get from products produced by Apple,
and this just felt part of that pattern, so I didn’t do anything about
it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this went on for a few months, because I do not always
practice what I preach.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then, yesterday, I tried to connect my airpods to my phone (I’ve done
this before, but for reasons I no longer remember had dissociated them
from it) and saw that the name of the bluetooth device was “Airpods -
Find My”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At that point I realised what had happened and swore a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point relatively early in my use of the airpods I was trying
to find where I’d left the case, so I turned on Find My mode on them on
my mac. Except, I didn’t, because as a non-iCloud user I got half way
through trying to do this and discovered that I’d have to log into
iCloud and I couldn’t be bothered to do that, so I started the process
and gave up. Apparently my airpods had been in Find My mode ever since
and the stupid chirping was a way of saying “Here I am! Here I am! I’m
not lost! Look over here!”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I spent about 30 seconds of thought at that point about trying to
figure out how to dissociate them from Find My and then realised what I
should have done all along: I factory reset the airpods, and the problem
went away.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I described the bug, the response I got was “Oh yeah, that makes
sense, that feature is super buggy”. This is also what happens every
time I figure out the cause of the allegedly uniquely cursed behaviour
that only I experience with Apple products.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The frustrating thing about this from a personal level is that I let
this problem go on for so long when the solution is so easy, but it’s
interesting to realise that it would have forever remained a mystery if
I hadn’t. Factory resetting the airpods would always have worked, but it
would also have destroyed the information that I only later acquired by
chance. This still would have been a huge net win, but it’s not obvious
to me how I could have accelerated the process of acquiring this
information &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; fixing the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-02-05-12:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
