<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-03-19T10:22:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-09-11:13.html</id>
    <title>The art of not having opinions</title>
    <updated>2020-03-09T12:52:35+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The art of not having opinions&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the same conversation with Dave that lead to us &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-28-06:33.html"&gt;talking about which way people veer to avoid collisions&lt;/a&gt; we ended up playing a sort of game.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For context: Dave works in transport. Transport is something we all encounter on a very regular basis, so we all tend to think about it a lot. However, transport is a complex system, so it's &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-04-11:18.html"&gt;more broken&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-11:43.html"&gt;less comprehensible&lt;/a&gt; than you might intuitively expect it to be. As a result, most people's opinions on transport are &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, the game: I had to keep coming up with transport opinions I held, and Dave would judge if they were bad opinions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually we ran out of time or got distracted or something (I forget) and I made it to that point without having any bad opinions. I was quite pleased by this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another place I was pleased with myself recently was my performance on the &lt;a href="https://programs.clearerthinking.org/common_misconceptions.html"&gt;common misconceptions&lt;/a&gt; test. The number of things I got right was only so so (I forget exactly, but I think about 85% right?), but I was almost perfectly calibrated: The ones where my confidence was high were right, the ones where my confidence was low were right in about the proportion they should be.
This was a bit surprising to me, as in the past I have definitely not been that well calibrated on similar things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think these both happened for fairly general reasons: Over the last decade, I've gotten much better at not having opinions on things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This might be surprising to you, as I have a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of opinions, but it makes sense: I've not gotten better at having fewer opinions, I've gotten better at not having opinions on any given thing unless it makes sense for me to do so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of social pressure against doing this.
We basically use having opinions at eachother as a social bonding activity to make sure that the person we're talking to has the "right" sort of politics, so there's a lot of social pressure against this, but I think it's worth doing if we want our opinions to be truth tracking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two useful prompts for recalibrating opinions:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; for me to have an opinion on this? If not, why do I have one?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If this opinion were wrong, would I be able to tell?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If the answer to either of these is no, why are you having an opinion on it? At the very least, you should be less confident in asserting it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-09-11:13.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-10-12:38.html</id>
    <title>Homophily and the tyranny of false positives</title>
    <updated>2020-03-10T13:37:44+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Homophily and the tyranny of false positives&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A while ago a friend of mine told me about what he called his Terribly Goth Theory of Friendship:
You can't trust people who don't have problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason is of course that &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; have problems, and that it's hard to trust people without them to know how to handle that well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it goes deeper than that: Actually many people with fewer or different problems than ours are in fact perfectly lovely human beings who we would get on fine with, but we can't tell that.
So we select for people who are like us because we can predict how they will react.
This is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homophily"&gt;homophily&lt;/a&gt;, the tendency to hang out with people like us. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, the question of who to be friends with is a classic example of the sort of thing I talked about in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/02/theres-no-single-error-rate/"&gt;there's no single error rate&lt;/a&gt;, where the only error rate that is visible to you is the false positive rate. As I argued in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-22-11:37.html"&gt;you should try bad things&lt;/a&gt; this will tend to cause you to narrow your selection over time:
If you only ever update to remove false positives, you will tend to increase the degree of homophily you exhibit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't necessarily a bad thing at the individual level, but bear in mind the way that bad rejections (false negatives) can contain &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/06/the-ethics-of-false-negatives-in-interviewing/"&gt;systemic biases&lt;/a&gt;.
My suspicion is that a lot of communities will tend to become more homogenous over time purely as a result of this effect: People who don't match the community expectations will tend to get filtered out, not necessarily because they're a bad fit, but because they don't act like the kind of people the community understands how to tell if they're a fit or not.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-10-12:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-11-07:15.html</id>
    <title>Suspension of annoyance</title>
    <updated>2020-03-11T09:35:51+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Suspension of annoyance&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been banging on a bit about "&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/38I7D5z"&gt;The Courage to be Disliked&lt;/a&gt;" since &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/m_ashcroft/"&gt;Michael Ashcroft&lt;/a&gt; recommended it.
My friend &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rixxtr"&gt;Tobi&lt;/a&gt; read it as a result, and the following is his review from &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/jm97tDN"&gt;bookchat discord&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished The Courage to be Disliked. It's a thoroughly annoying book, obnoxiously written, and I strongly disagree with a whole lot of what it says. At the same time it has been extremely useful to me, in an immediate and actionable way, and I'm very glad I've read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Useful, yet punchable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only found this thread on Twitter afterwards, and it contains pretty much all of the book without the obnoxiousness: &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1037715339314847747"&gt;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1037715339314847747&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I cannot disagree with this review. The book is objectively very annoying. However I was not particularly annoyed while reading it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this I've had practice. The particular foibles of this book were new to me, but I've read a lot of self-help and niche (especially trauma centric) therapy books recently, which has allowed me to get used to a particular style: That of a slightly self-obsessed author telling you their life story and the transformation they've been through, wrapped around what would probably be a fairly decent essay about a useful technique threaded through the entire thing in a way that makes it slightly hard to skip reading about the journey.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I said I wasn't annoyed while &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt; the books, not that I wasn't annoyed about the books)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When reading those books, I could look for things to argue with. It wouldn't be hard. The books are full of poorly supported pseudoscience, weak arguments, and irrelevant digressions. But I knew they would be going in, so why worry about it? I'm there to see if I can extract anything interesting from the book. I don't really care about whether the author is right or wrong, and I expect they're mostly wrong, but I can still try to derive some useful insights from their work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To go a bit Adlerian about this, what purpose is the annoyance with the book serving you?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it's mostly protective: Someone is saying wrong things, and you want to treat it as someone arguing with you, because if you were to take on the wrong things you would go on to believe wrong things, and that's bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But you could just do neither of those things. Don't read the book on the assumption that you'll believe anything the author has to say, but also don't be annoyed when you don't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead, take on the information that this is what the author believes. Acknowledge the possibility that some of it &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;might be worth trying&lt;/a&gt;, but don't read it with any greater expectation of truth than that.
Once you've done that, the protective mechanism of annoyance is not especially useful,
and you might as well just choose not to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-11-07:15.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-12-07:45.html</id>
    <title>Books should be taken seriously but not literally</title>
    <updated>2020-03-13T11:06:34+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Books should be taken seriously but not literally&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-12&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;fvathynevgl (I've got official sanction to pronounce this "Vathy" if that's helpful to you in reading this post without demonic incursions) has &lt;a href="https://www.fvathynevgl.com/cooperative-spherical-cows/"&gt;written about cooperative spherical cows&lt;/a&gt; as a model of various self-help ideologies:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cooperative spherical cow philosophies postulate a certain model of human behaviour and give advice on how to fix your relationships. Unfortunately, whether the advice works is conditional on all humans adhering to the ideal model, which they don't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All cooperative spherical cow philosophies have a hidden precondition which makes them applicable in the real world. If it is mentioned in a book at all, it will be as an off-hand remark or digression, accepted at face value and not explored in depth. You can tell it's a hidden precondition because it makes the philosophy no longer look like a silver bullet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is somewhat in response to The Courage to be Disliked which I wrote about in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-11-07:15.html"&gt;suspension of annoyance&lt;/a&gt;. Apparently &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/fvathynevgl/status/1237666299146272768"&gt;the timing is a coincidence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I agree with their post, I just think that it's only true under hidden preconditions that makes it look applicable in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;OK, that's unfair, but I couldn't resist the opportunity for the line. My more nuanced counterbalance to the post is this: Books like they are describing work best when you take them seriously but not literally, and the failure mode they are describing only occurs if you take them literally. If you read the books described and get religion over them and try to apply them verbatim to your life, it will likely go very badly for you, but the solution is just not to do that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a good thing to point out, because a lot of people do take books literally and get religion over them, and this reliably goes badly. I have likely been undercautious with my book recommendations as a result because I've assumed people have a better attitude to reading than they do, and will update accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That being said... I think this is, similarly, a post that should be taken seriously and not literally, because it will cause you to miss out on a lot of useful ideas.
There is enough &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-16-14:22.html"&gt;ghost knowledge&lt;/a&gt; out there without also ignoring that which is written down.
The books fvathynevgl recommends sound good, and I intend to read them, but only being able to extract knowledge from impeccable sources is a severe limitation that I cannot really recommend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a side note, I am also interested as to why exactly these books are not best sellers if they are so much better than the books that are best sellers.
This is not a disagreement with fvathynevgl, I'm just genuinely curious. Is there a need that the others are filling that these are not?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here is my base recommendation for how to engage with books:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The author is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; overly convinced of the truth and usefullness of their position. If they weren't, they wouldn't be writing the book. You cannot rely on them to provide the necessary preconditions, to the point where even if they do provide those preconditions you should &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; assume you need to figure them out on your own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The author is a nerd about the subject, in the sense outlined in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html"&gt;my post on nerding&lt;/a&gt;. They are much more interested in the subject than you are, and all of their advice has the precondition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The book is a book. As such, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-18-12:24.html"&gt;the books you create out of it in your head&lt;/a&gt; are more interesting than the book as an actual physical or digital object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The book is best treated not as a source of truth but as a textual artefact that you are examining.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The artefact is an &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-05-11:27.html"&gt;existence proof&lt;/a&gt; of a particular sort of mindset. You're not trying to adopt that mindset for daily use, but by being able to engage with it and figure out what it's like you are more prepared to adapt the tools from it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to treat books as artefacts of study rather than sources of truth you need to have reliable belief formation skills (so that you don't get lead in bad directions), and you need to have confidence that you do (so that reading things that are not true &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; safe as well as &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; safe).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recommended starting points for this: &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-09-11:13.html"&gt;Don't believe things unless you can act on them&lt;/a&gt;, and then &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;experiment with those beliefs and see how it pans out&lt;/a&gt;.
You will rapidly find the preconditions for applicability of anything you learn from books when you do this, and you will do so much more reliably than anything the authors tell you about those preconditions.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-12-07:45.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-13-09:49.html</id>
    <title>Communication: Collaboration and Conflict</title>
    <updated>2020-03-13T10:32:14+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Communication: Collaboration and Conflict&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-13&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is loosely a follow-on to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/fvathynevgl/status/1238082764609671170"&gt;discussions with Vathy&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-12-07:45.html"&gt;the previous post&lt;/a&gt; but this isn't about books, it's about communication.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The model scene for communication that I'll be thinking about in this post is two people talking to each other in person. A lot of what I'm going to be saying applies in general, but there are different constraints and considerations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every act of communication contains two things: collaboration and conflict.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are &lt;em&gt;collaborating&lt;/em&gt; in the sense that you are producing an artefact (the conversation) together, but you are in &lt;em&gt;conflict&lt;/em&gt; (in the Schelling sense) in that you are two presumably-human people whose values are imperfectly aligned.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How much of each is present varies, but no communication is free of either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've previously claimed &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1232716902352523264"&gt;you are underinvested in communication skills&lt;/a&gt;, but I think it's worth unpacking what communication skills &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lets think about teaching. Teaching is very much an act of communication. As I've previously argued, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-08-08:53.html"&gt;you can't teach anything to anyone&lt;/a&gt; (I've also &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/10/how-to-explain-anything-to-anyone/"&gt;previously claimed that you can&lt;/a&gt;. I'll admit I was being a bit hyperbolic there),
and the reason for that is that the other person &lt;em&gt;may not be willing to do the work&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've done a modest amount of one-on-one maths tutoring. Not a lot, and only with a handful of students, so I definitely wouldn't claim expertise in this, but I've taken a couple of students from "this makes no sense and I hate it" to "oh, this makes total sense and is kinda neat". I've also had one student who I &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; failed to teach.
Why? Because he didn't care, and would not engage. He would not do the work, and it was impossible for me to open his skull and insert mathematics directly into his brain, so no matter how well I taught him he would never learn.
It's possible, likely even, that I was missing some skill that would get him interested, but without fundamentally changing his values around willingness to learn mathematics (which I didn't know how to do), it didn't matter how clearly I communicated the subject to him, he wasn't going to learn it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In teaching, there are two categories of communication skills that are relevant (there are more than two, but I'm only going to point out two):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting someone interested in the subject.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communicating the subject in a way that they can understand it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm quite bad at (1) because I'm very bad at not being interested in things. Mea culpa. So in this post, I'm going to focus on (2).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One way to think of this aspect of communication skills is that it is about &lt;em&gt;workload management&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you had never been exposed to any mathematics, and you had to derive modern statistics from scratch.
Obviously you can't do this, but imagine that you could in principle do this, and think about how much work it would be.
That's the baseline for learning statistics.
Every aspect of teaching is designed to make it easier to learn statistics than that.
Ultimately you, the student, still need to do the work of learning and understanding statistics, but the purpose of the teacher is to save you a few thousand years of effort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, a lesson is primarily a collaboration between the teacher and the student, in which the goal of the teacher is to shoulder as much of the work as they reasonably can.
This is, I think, a key feature of all communication skills:
They are designed to manage the workload of the other party.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even a bad communicator can communicate to a sufficiently dedicated student, but a good one can lower the level of dedication required.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are what you might think of as the cooperative communication skills, ones that are designed to make the collaboration go as well as possible.
But as I said at the beginning: Communication has two parts, collaboration and conflict.
You can think of communication skills centered on the conflict as adversarial communication skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a useful workload management spin on adversarial communication skills too:
They are designed to &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; the workload of the other party where they are trying to achieve goals that you don't want.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.healthline.com/health/grey-rock#offer-nothing"&gt;grey rock&lt;/a&gt; method is a perfect example of this. When you are dealing with a toxic person, you distance and shut down your visible emotional responses.
Their goal (which you do not want) is to get a rise out of you, and gray rocking makes it harder for them to do that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From a collaboration point of view this looks like not communicating, but from a conflict point of view this is absolutely a communication skill, because it's managing the communication so that it goes in a way that you want rather than the other person wants.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-13-09:49.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html</id>
    <title>Alief/Belief Coherence</title>
    <updated>2020-03-14T15:19:03+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Alief/Belief Coherence&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me start with a word: Alief. An Alief is like a belief, but instead of it being something you &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; is true it's something you &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; is true (it's a pun you see - a-liefs come before b-liefs).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Alief is a very good word that I use a lot. If you don't have it yet, you're welcome, because you'll see it everywhere now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's particularly interesting to notice where your aliefs and beliefs diverge. Sometimes you believe things but you don't alieve them (e.g. you might know you are good at your job but experience impostor syndrome anyway), sometimes you alieve things but you don't believe them (you might think your friends secretly hate you).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you might have noticed from those examples, it is often my experience that our beliefs are more functional than our aliefs.
This isn't always the case. For example you might get a weird vibe off someone and go "No I'm just being unfair" and try to ignore it, only to later discover that they are indeed a massive creep who you are better off ignoring.
You alieved that they were dangerous but you didn't believe it, and the belief let you astray.
Hunches and intuition in general are often like this - you might have no objective reason to believe that a particular direction is promising, but you've got a strong hunch (an alief) that it would be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An alief is just a felt sense (in &lt;a href="https://rivalvoices.substack.com/p/what-even-is-focusing-and-why-eugene"&gt;the Gendlin sense&lt;/a&gt;) that something is true, but it's a felt sense that is usefully framed as being like a belief where you've just skipped over the surrounding propositional infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the advantages of beliefs is that we can use &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metacognition"&gt;metacognition&lt;/a&gt; to examine them. It's not actually true that we arrive at beliefs through simple propositional reasoning, but we're much more able to pretend that we are - we can put forth logical arguments for them, sometimes backfilling to construct ones where we realise we don't have them, etc.
Often once we attack a belief with metacognition we might find it degrades to an alief - we no longer think it's true, but we feel it's true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As this process suggests, there isn't actually a clear distinction between aliefs and beliefs: Beliefs are formed on aliefs, aliefs are informed by beliefs, and the whole thing is really a much more complicated network of interplay between felt sense, explicit verbal thought, and action.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is perhaps better to think of alief and belief as &lt;em&gt;directions&lt;/em&gt; - the more your relationship to a proposition is built on felt sense, the more like an alief it is, the more it is built on explicit reasoning, the more like a belief it is, but the reality is that there are no pure aliefs and no pure beliefs, only things that are more or less each (note that alief and belief are not opposite directions, but orthogonal ones).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Regardless of how pure they are though, we will still run into situations where we find that what we &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; is true is in conflict with what we &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; is true.
What do we do then?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A difficulty that people may have is that because they can explicitly work with beliefs through metacognition, they can update their beliefs relatively easily, but they have no such tools for updating their aliefs.
Thus in a conflict one of two things will happen: Their beliefs will change, or they will be stuck with unhelpful aliefs (which they believe to be false but cannot shake).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is where tools like Focusing come in, allowing us to work better with the felt sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this sense, things such as the tools I outlined in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;Emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt; can be thought of as the other half of the toolkit for ensuring coherence between your beliefs and your aliefs, bringing your aliefs into alignment with your beliefs when it is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html"&gt;the feeling that is wrong and that needs to change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-15-12:24.html</id>
    <title>Berkson's paradox is everywhere</title>
    <updated>2020-03-15T13:07:06+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Berkson's paradox is everywhere&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Everyone likes to tell you that correlation is not causation. They're right, but they're also boring. Also &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2014/05/spurious-correlations-and-causation/"&gt;all of their examples are wrong&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What they don't tell you about so often is the most common reason why correlation does not imply correlation is that most of the correlations you see in day to day life are, in some sense, fake: They are not present in the underlying reality, they're an artifact of how you're looking at it. This is &lt;em&gt;Berkson's paradox&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My go to example of this (I don't actually know if it's true, but it's a nice illustration) is that professional tennis players tend to be either tall or fast - tall tennis players tend to be slower, fast tennis players tend to be shorter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You could come up with some complicated biological explanation about why these two traits might be negatively correlated, but it would be wrong, because they're not negatively correlated in the general population, or at least not to the same degree. The reason is much simpler than that: Short, slow, people will rarely play tennis professionally.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, if height and speed are entirely independent of eachother (even if they're slightly positively correlated!) when you look at professional tennis players they will become negatively correlated, because it's more likely to be one or the other than it is to be both.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may seem like a weird niche edge case, but once you start noticing it it's &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, you know how popular things are often kinda bad and the really good things are niche? Is that true, or is it just that you don't notice things that are bad and unpopular?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You know how people who disagree with you seem kinda shouty? Do you notice people who disagree with you and are not shouty?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This repeats over and over again: The patterns we see in day to day life come as much from the process that causes us to observe the data as it does from any underlying causal mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does this matter? I think it does, for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As with "correlation does not imply causation" in general, we need to be careful about letting the inferences we draw suggest actions unless we understand what the actual causal mechanism is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because these correlations come from the process rather than reality, if the process changes then many of our old inferences become invalid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(2) is particularly important when we experience &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-28-06:33.html"&gt;culture shifts&lt;/a&gt;, because the entire generating process will have changed, so many things we thought were true become invalid.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-15-12:24.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-17-11:40.html</id>
    <title>Everybody is looking for permission</title>
    <updated>2020-03-17T13:36:48+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Everybody is looking for permission&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lens I started looking at the social world through a while back is &lt;em&gt;permission&lt;/em&gt;.
Specifically, that everybody is looking for it, and that many situations, relationships, and activities can be thought of in terms of what permission they give you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A common, practical, example of this is asking stupid questions in meetings: Often everybody is confused, but nobody feels they have permission to ask, so once somebody is prepared to break the silence everyone is more able to (although a friend has expressed concern that asking stupid questions has instead become high status as people have learned this).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another example that has been very relevant recently is giving people permission to freak out about COVID-19. I think at this point everyone has officially been given that permission, so it's no longer quite so useful (that may be more local / political. Certainly some people &lt;em&gt;aren't&lt;/em&gt; freaking out about it, and I suspect some of their friends still need permission), but there was a period of a few weeks where it was a bit more controversial to do so and people were fairly actively saying "Look, this is a thing I am worried about, it's OK to be worried about it".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/06/on-not-quite-fitting/"&gt;everyone is a bit worried about being weird&lt;/a&gt;, and despite these worries being widespread, a mix of everyone being weird in different ways and pluralistic ignorance (the majority privately reject a norm that the majority publicly enforce), and needs permission to break out of the norms that society has imposed on them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is that permission often needs to be a lot stronger than just providing an example, or telling someone it's OK. They don't necessarily believe you, or even if they do believe you they've &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/jiminy-cricket-must-die/"&gt;internalised societal norms too much&lt;/a&gt;.
Frequently mere verbal permission will be met with active opposition.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Again, pluralistic ignorance is a good example of this: Suppose most straight people are just not that fussed about heterosexuality (I think this is actually pretty likely, but if you disagree pretend it's a thought experiment). It's not that they're gay, or even that they're particularly bi, but they're open to the idea in principle and don't really see what all the fuss is about. However, if there are very strong norms enforcing it, these more-or-less-heterosexual straight people will probably enforce those norms &lt;em&gt;harder&lt;/em&gt; for fear of being caught on the wrong end of them. So you can't just straightforwardly give them permission, you need some way of committing to it. If they've sufficiently internalised the norms, it might not even be possible to give them permission, because the thing withholding permission is their own shame and the only person who can give them that permission is themself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think a lot of circumstances end up implicitly granting permission by making the action "playing the game". For example, people behave very differently when drunk, but a lot of this isn't actually because alcohol, it's because the fact that you're drunk gives you permission to behave like a drunk person. You see this with things like stag parties, hen does, etc. where people are given permission by the format to behave like complete asses in ways they normally wouldn't do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is also why a lot of "mandatory fun" fails: There is a certain sort of permission that you need to behave like a person in a fun situation, and often mandatory fun skips the "foreplay" element that is needed to provide that permission, so people end up in a situation where people are being expected to behave in a way that they do not feel they have permission to.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-17-11:40.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html</id>
    <title>Safety as an enabler of growth</title>
    <updated>2020-03-18T14:43:27+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Safety as an enabler of growth&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-18&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My friend Alex Chan &lt;a href="https://alexwlchan.net/2020/03/rich-enough-to-make-bad-choices/"&gt;recently wrote about how one of the big advantages of being rich is that the rich can afford to make risky investments&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being rich gives you a safety net to make bad investments, which helps you find more good ones. Over time, the rich don’t just spend less money, they find new ways to earn more money. In terms Samuel Vimes would understand: they don’t just invest in a pair of sturdy boots, they invest in experimental boot-making startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As Alex points out, this ties in to my argument that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-22-11:37.html"&gt;you should try bad things&lt;/a&gt;.
You can only try bad things if you have the resources to ensure that failure is no big deal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For some bad things, this isn't an issue, but for things which have a relatively high cost (financial, time, or otherwise), being poor (or even just not rich!) blocks them off from you.
This is particularly egregious in the examples that Alex points out, where the lack of financial security is the very thing that prevents you from gaining more financial security.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a general pattern that repeats in many other contexts.
In order to grow, it needs to be safe to try things, and lacking the thing that you want to grow is what makes it unsafe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is often connected with learning. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;The fastest way to learn something is to do something&lt;/a&gt;, but if doing something can go catastrophically wrong then you're not going to risk it, so whole avenues of learning are blocked off for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as financial, two common places this occurs are social and emotional safety (which can be tightly connected, but also can fail independently in their own way).
There's all the literature on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychological_safety"&gt;psychological safety&lt;/a&gt; about how feeling safe in your team is an enabler of success, because people are more able to propose ideas and learn from them.
This ties in to what I was saying yesterday about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-17-11:40.html"&gt;permission&lt;/a&gt;: One of the key features of psychological safety in a group environment is the way it gives you permission to experiment and try things that might not work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another type of safety is &lt;em&gt;emotional&lt;/em&gt; safety. For a lot of us the insides of our own heads are not safe. As I wrote about in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/01/a-crash-course-in-having-feelings/"&gt;a crash course in having feelings&lt;/a&gt;, one of the key steps to emotional growth is getting to a point where you can have feelings (especially negative ones) without being overwhelmed by them. As long as your feelings are dangerous to you, it's impossible to experiment with and learn about them, and this stops you from growing emotionally.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of insidious traps that one can fall into that can make an otherwise safe situation unsafe:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overidentification with success. You see this a lot with smart people and learning. If failure is an indication that you are not smart, because a smart person would have succeeded at this, and you strongly identify with being smart, you will often struggle to learn because anything that fails is a direct attack on your self-identity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Success as implying commitment. By doing something, you have demonstrated that you are able to do it, and now in future you can be coerced or pressured into doing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In both of these cases, the cost of trying things is raised considerably: In the first, the cost of failure is made much worse. In the second, success itself becomes the costly thing. Either way, you have found yourself in an environment where trying things cannot be safe, because success has become too high stakes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-19-10:22.html</id>
    <title>Good strategies often fail</title>
    <updated>2020-03-19T10:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Good strategies often fail&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/02/you-should-be-stockpiling-food-for-brexit/"&gt;stockpiled food for Brexit&lt;/a&gt;. A lot of people were skeptical of me for that, and many people have said that the way Brexit played out proved me wrong and that it was an overreaction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They are wrong and I was right. Stockpiling food for Brexit and not needing it was the expected outcome. It was never something that I thought I was likely to need, it was a capacity I was building in case of a low probability high cost event. The logic was that either food stockpiling wouldn't be useful, in which case I had a surplus to use up, or it would be kinda useful in which case it was a net positive, or it would be essential, in which case I would be incredibly glad I had it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3926VQH"&gt;Annie Duke&lt;/a&gt; calls this fallacy &lt;em&gt;resulting&lt;/em&gt;, and I think it's a rare instance of something escaping &lt;a href="https://maartenboudry.blogspot.com/2017/06/the-fallacy-fork-why-its-time-to-get.html"&gt;the fallacy fork&lt;/a&gt;.
Resulting is the fallacy of assuming that because you got a bad outcome you must have made a bad choice, when in fact you might just have got a bad outcome because you picked the option with a 60% chance of success instead of a 40% chance but it turns out that you're in the 40% chance world. Chance means that you can never perfectly control the outcome, and you should be careful not to let random chance inform your learning too much.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More complicated is that often good strategies you'll never even know if you succeeded or not. A lot of mitigations for COVID-19 are like this: You'll never know whether it really mattered that you were washing your hands, or socially isolating, because all you're doing is stacking the odds on a numbers game. You might get the virus anyway, or you might have never got the virus, there's no way to know. It's still a good strategy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Capacity building strategies in particular are often a good idea, because they can be useful in unexpected ways.
I didn't immediately dismantle my Brexit stockpile when it seemed unlikely that we'd need it, I've just been using it as a buffer, so now if we do end up on pandemic lockdown we'll be well placed for food supplies while self isolating.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-19-10:22.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
