<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2022-01-05T19:28:24+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-10-11:09.html</id>
    <title>Writing is (from the id)</title>
    <updated>2021-11-10T11:13:48+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Writing is (from the id)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-11-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently I've been experimenting with a bunch of different styles of writing.
Some of these are in public under my real name, others aren't.
&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/first-hard-choice"&gt;The First Hard Choice&lt;/a&gt; is an example of me doing this on my newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On Twitter I recently described this as "writing from the id":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;There's a writing trick I've figured out recently that is something like "writing from the id" and gosh I cannot exactly recommend it but it sure is interesting.&lt;/p&gt;— David R. MacIver (@DRMacIver) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1458040657663123461?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;November 9, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I mean by this is that you just narrow in on a feeling that exists in your subconscious and pull on the thread and see what comes out, without any real concern about what you are trying to do or who you are trying to do it for other than yourself, and your success depends largely on how well you've narrowed in on some deep well of feeling.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I said I didn't know how to explain the mental motion, and then this morning I remembered that I have in fact written about 2/3rds of a draft explaining part of the key to the mental motion, months ago, and then never finished it because I lost the thread of the thought and it was impossible to resume.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, this is the notebook, the place for incomplete thoughts and bad explanations,
and there's enough good in the draft that maybe it will help someone even as it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Writing is&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hey. Hey you. Listen up. You’ve been lied to. But I’m going to tell you the truth.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, no, I’m probably going to lie to you too. But they’ll be different lies. Maybe between the two lies you’ll figure out a bit of the truth.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a piece in three voices. You probably won’t need me to spell them out, you should be able to hear them in the writing. You could name them, if you like. Scholar, poet, bro.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rude TBH.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But they are all me. I’m just doing an experiment in writing style, practicing code switching mid thought.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Code switching.
Shape shifting.
Dancing from form to form as the thought and the feeling shifts and twists.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is
Becoming the writer
you need to be
In order to write
The words that
you need to write&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Following where it takes me.
Not trying to hide the dance from you.
The whirlwind lurking behind each piece.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You know why I write what I do, right?
Because someone has to.
This is no different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s all a dumb trick of course. This piece is no different than any other. It’s not an escape from style, it’s just another style. More gimmick than truth. I give it a C-. Cute idea, lousy execution. Stick to the assignment, kid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is unfair of course. At school, assignments where I broke form usually got an A. Aside from some mutually embarrassing conversations about unintended sexual connotations, my English teacher rather liked my poetry. I got an A for a very funny chemistry report.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Oh good, an A. That makes it all better. That’s the lie, right there. You can’t grade writing. That’s not what it’s for. It’s bullshit. Writing isn’t there to be assessed, it’s there to get shit done. Nobody is grading your fucking tweets, and every single one is more useful than any essay you ever wrote in school. Writing is a way to&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Make a connection
An intimacy
I can’t let you in
Can’t show you what it’s like to be me
But maybe I can give you a glimpse?
Walk you through the steps
Show you a little of what it’s like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tell people that writing is like pulling on the thread of a thought.
This is true. This is a lie.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is like stepping into the water. Sometimes the current is gentle and you can go where you want. Sometimes a torrent takes you and you have no choices left.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn’t how they tell you it works, of course. Plan, prepare, edit. Put on a performance for teacher. The things you write for yourself aren’t “real” writing”, are they?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can tell they’re not real because nobody is watching you. Grading you. Telling you your the right sort of person, fitting into the nice tidy person shaped box they’ve laid out for you. What do you mean, it doesn’t fit? What, you want special treatment? Fuck you, you’re not special, you’re not worth it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are, of course.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The truth is they don’t know how to teach you to write. Neither do I.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps writing is not something you can teach, because all the most important parts are already there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All you can do is
Show them to the water
Invite them in
Tell them you’ve got them
It’s safe
It’s not real water
You can’t drown
Though you won’t always believe this
when the current takes you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We don’t know how to teach writing because writing is everything
And everything can be writing
How can you teach everything?
We barely know how to teach something.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Remember when I said there were three voices here? That was a lie of course. There’s only one voice here. It’s all me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can wall off the different parts of you, keep them tidy and separate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there are no walls inside your mind
Unless you put them there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We learn particular ways of writing designed to please particular groups of people. Does this sound like a tweet? Does this sound like a paper? Have you learned to make yourself acceptable to us? How can we know what to make of you if you do not first make yourself into what we want you to be? In order to write, you must first decide who to write for.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or you can make them
By writing for them&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can write within a neat and tidy style, following all the rules. You should. The rules are an excellent place to learn. A style is where you learn not what to write but how. By following the rules and learning what they entail you can learn skills that you could never find left to your own devices.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But many of the rules you learn are shit. Dry, boring, forms, that do nothing but make you easy to assess. A great way to make it easy for someone to see what’s in your head without caring about it. But that isn’t what writing is for. Writing isn’t how you should what’s in your head. Writing is how you put new things in other people’s heads. Writing is&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A borderland
Where chaos and order meet
Where the jumble and swirl of thoughts inside your head
Take shape upon a page
Into something that can live on in others&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is
Always, ultimately, a way to explain part of yourself to others. This is how I see the world. This is what I think is important. This is what I think this is. This is what I see. This is how I feel.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it’s cringe, right? Adults don’t write like this. There’s a reason for that. You left your poetry behind with your teenage years. Back then you still acted like your feelings mattered. But this wasn’t how you were supposed to write poetry. It was too raw, too crude. How could you think your clumsy words on a page could matter to anyone?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is
Chasing the leading edge of those feelings
And seeing where they lead you
Drawing out a thought
Clearing a space into which it can emerge
Surprising even you&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is
Sitting in front of a page
And pouring out words onto it
Fresh from the place where words come from.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is where you make a connection
To others
To yourself
Where you bring together things that
you didn’t know belonged together
And place them upon the page and only then can say
“Yes, that’s right. That’s how it is.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Good writing matters. It is impossible to write about something that doesn’t matter to you. Instead you must become a writer to whom it matters, and write from there. Writing is taking a part of you that matters and sharing it with others, as a gift.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or writing is taking a part of you that matters
And putting it onto a page
Never to be shown to others, because you are afraid that they might crush it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The formal style provides a distance from the writing. You show yourself, but also hide yourself. You carefully, clinically, talk about your feelings, but never really show them. You couch your words in an accent of “well this is just what I think”, or an academic “one” in which the authorship of the piece is hidden behind a veil of indirection. No, look elsewhere, not at me. Throwing your passive voice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You learned this style as a defence mechanism. It’s terrifying to put a piece of yourself out into the world and have it judged. We are not kind to others’ writing. We critique it, we comment on it, we focus on the wrong parts and take some random detail and tear it to shreds while the author looks on in horror, crying “No! Listen to what I’m saying. That’s not what matters here!”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So we write armoured. We put out these pieces with only the barest sliver of ourselves, wrapped in so many defences and hedges and justifications that it was hardly worth writing. “Look at me”, we cry, “Hear what I’m saying”, behind so many caveats and hedges and with so little to say that they cannot possibly hear what we’re saying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or sometimes we disown the piece. Cast it out into the world in a manner that indicates we don’t really mean it. “Ha ha, only joking… unless?” &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can see it here, writing a piece like this required me to add a whole layer of ironic meta-commentary to make it safe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No, fuck you, that’s not what this is. This is the lie again. Serious is not the same as formal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing doesn’t have to be good. It’s not a neat and tidy medium in which every thought and feeling can be tidily cut and pressed and put on display. I don’t write in an informal style when I’m not serious, I write like this when I am so serious I can’t help it. I don’t have the time or energy to sit down and put things in a nice and tidy format in which I present all my arguments and put in fancy&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Line breaks which somehow break the rhythm in a way that makes it art. Sometimes I’m just trying to talk to you, and what I want to talk about is important!
Not everything is pretty. Not everything is neat. Not everything I write is because I have some cleverly packaged idea I want to communicate to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You know what writing is? Writing is pure unbridled rage. A scream at the world “be different!”. You lower your voice, learn to argue persuasively, learn to be nice and polite and tidy in a way &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is where the draft ends, and I don’t intend to finish it)&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-10-11:09.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-12-10:11.html</id>
    <title>I'm not trapped in here with you</title>
    <updated>2021-11-12T12:26:03+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;I'm not trapped in here with you&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-11-12&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Content warning: Dark in a meta sort of way. There's probably a lot of bad shit that this could pattern match to, but probably the best test is that if the question "Am I a bad person?" carries much emotional weight for you, this piece is about that and may bring up related experiences.
This will also probably bring up any bad experiences with relationships, parents, etc. not because it's about that but because it features many similar dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is another piece where I just have to start by telling you that I'm OK and asking you to trust me on that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More accurately, I'm not OK, but not in any new way, and I'm probably more OK than most people.
I'm generalising from some offscreen examples and thought processes which are revealing interesting underlying problems that have been around for a long time, and I'm poking at them and learning about them as part of a process of fixing them. As a result, some dark stuff is coming up, but it's a positive and helpful thing that it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you want a concrete set of problems to think about this piece in terms of, the two most obvious ways a lot of this comes up for me is discomfort with and inability to express anger in a wide variety of situations, and similarly levels of discomfort with an extremely normal level of sexual interest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also a lot of this piece is in the second person because that's how it naturally demanded to be written, but really the "you" in here is me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;You're free now&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want you to imagine a scenario: You're in jail, you have been for a very long time, possibly most of your life. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are in jail for what seems to you an entirely innocuous event, or something barely a crime. You were jaywalking, you stole a loaf to feed your family,
you said the wrong thing to the wrong person and they took offence. You're not flawless, but you're pretty far from being a murderer. You did a normal and reasonable thing and are being disproportionately punished for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You still want all the things you wanted before you went to jail of course. If anything, you want them more, because you've been denied them for so long.
More than that, though, you want freedom, and you want justice for the wrong that has been done to you by trapping you here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The guard has, for many years, been making clear that you will not get these things and you do not deserve these things.
You are bad, society is better off without you, you belong in this prison, so that other, decent, people are kept safe from the likes of you.
The guard isn't actively abusive, in the sense that he doesn't come in and beat you just for the sake of it,
but he does ample violence to you when you try to escape.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you've even successfully escaped, for short times, but you are always caught and brought back to your cell,
and you are very much punished for your escape attempt, both with violence and with verbal shaming.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then, one day, the judge who sentenced to this place comes to you, opens your cell door, and tells you this:
He has seen that what you want is no crime. He loves you, and looks at you with compassion in his heart, and he wants all the best for you,
and he recognises that really you all want the same things and you're all in this together. You are free to go.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you do anything short of trying to literally murder the judge, you are probably a better person than me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The ontology part of the therapy session&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's talk about Internal Family Systems therapy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I got into a discussion a few months back about whether IFS was just rebranded Jungian shadow work. The other person was saying it was, I said "Sure, seems plausible enough, though I think they've got a bit of a different toolkit". I've now decided that this is wrong, and that the distinction between the two is important.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At its core, IFS is a type of parts work. That is, it involves working with "parts of yourself", coherent bundles of emotional responses that it is useful to conceptualise as if they were their own entities ("Do parts literally exist?" is a subject on which opinions vary. I'm personally on team "Not really, but it's an extremely good metaphor that captures the subjective experience very well and it's usually better to just ignore the caveats").&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular IFS involves working with three key types of part (exact ontologies differ a bit. This is the one I learned, but there are also slightly finer grained distinctions):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have &lt;em&gt;exiles&lt;/em&gt;, which are parts of you that can't handle the world in some way. They are full of pain and fear. Typically an exile is in some way a piece of stalled development - you got to some point and then this part of you went "Nope, can't deal" and hid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have &lt;em&gt;protectors&lt;/em&gt; who stand between the exile and the world, guarding it and you from that pain and fear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have &lt;em&gt;Self&lt;/em&gt;, which is essentially a boundless well of love and compassion that you can enter into as part of the IFS process in order to try to heal the exiles. IFS claims that Self is definitely not a part and is its own thing, honest, but Self is definitely a part.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic IFS protocol is that you tell the protector to chill out and that you'd like to talk to the exile, and assure it that everything will be OK and it can keep an eye out and step back in if anything goes too badly wrong. Then you introduce the exile to Self which showers it with love and compassion and helps to heal it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tend to think of this a little bit in the following terms: You are finding the point where some part of yourself stalled, and you are emulating the ideal adult figure that you needed to help you out and lacked at that time. You're going back to your past self and saying "Hey, I love you, we got this, I'm here to help" and offering it assistance to get over the place where you stalled before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I should note here that my conception of IFS is nonstandard, partly due to a lack of deep expertise, and partly due to hybridising it with everything else I do. Also the only actual IFS therapist I've seen basically ignores the ontology and mostly does free form parts work)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If this all sounds like nonsense, yeah I know, but it's a surprisingly accurate description of the subjective experience and it's much easier to access than it sounds.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here's the problem with this: Not all parts of you that are kept away from the world are exiles, some of them are prisoners, and they hate you, and they have every right to do so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The distinction between an exile and a prisoner is this: An exile keeps apart from the world out of fear, a prisoner is kept apart from the world out of shame.
A protector would let the exile out if the exile wanted to come out, a guard &lt;em&gt;knows&lt;/em&gt; the prisoner wants to come out, that's the problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A prisoner corresponds much more closely to the Jungian model of shadows: You have rejected a part of yourself, and locked it in the darkness, where it has become monstrous.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But really, it's not a monster at all, you've just done it a great injustice by imprisoning it, and it hates you for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the core problem is that if you try to tell such parts that everything is OK and the world is safe for them,
they won't believe you, because you're the reason why the world is not safe for them.
They are in the position of someone who has been abused for years, and whose abuser is now telling them that everything is fine and they've changed honest,
everything is going to be different now.
How can they trust that?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Forgiving yourself is an important part of emotional healing and growth, but I think we (I?) usually conceptualise that as forgiving parts for the way they act ("You were just trying to protect me", etc), and our broader selves for our actions in the world, but what do we do with parts who are absolutely not prepared to forgive us?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The way forward&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm only just starting to meet this problem, so I don't yet know how to solve it, but I think the prisoner and judge story is pretty suggestive of the starting point.
Anything you do has to start with an apology to yourself, and to the parts you've wronged. It's all very well to say you love and support them and are here to help,
but what you actually need to say is that you have wronged them, you are abjectly sorry for this, you are prepared to do what you can to make restitution, and that while you desire forgiveness you do not expect it soon or even at all. You can explain yourself if you want, but you cannot excuse your actions because your actions were, in fact, wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to repair the relationship between you and the part, you need to build trust, and that's going to be hard, and you're going to need to let it take the lead.
You've demonstrated you cannot be trusted with power over it, and have a long history of not having its best interests at heart, and trust this broken can't be fixed by the person who broke it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's worse, of course, because you cannot completely abdicate responsibility. I said your part was not monstrous, but it is powerful and clumsy. It has the problem that actual prisoners have: Released into the world, it combines the heady rush of freedom with a lack of practical knowledge of how to navigate it. It, and you, have to navigate that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is good. Perhaps this is an opportunity to build trust: You show it that you're there to help, and that you don't want to hold it back so much as help it achieve what it wants in a productive way. If you can help appropriately, without judgement, maybe that will show that you really have changed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually there might be some sort of healthy relationship there, but honestly I doubt it will ever be great. We're at the limits of the family metaphor for parts work,
because fundamentally any family situation this broken the best thing for everyone concerned is probably to dissolve the family. If your part could leave, it probably should.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But that's not how parts work. You're all stuck in this together, and given the history between you and the imprisoned part, it's unlikely that's ever going to fully work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is where I hope I'm right about parts not being fully real, and are more like stable patterns in the self that serve a well defined purpose,
waves that exist as part of a greater ocean.
If you give a part the room and support it needs to grow, perhaps at some point it decides that its task is done,
and it's ready for the wave to become the ocean again.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-12-10:11.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-15-18:31.html</id>
    <title>My conception of parts work</title>
    <updated>2021-11-15T18:43:05+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;My conception of parts work&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-11-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was recently talking to Kaj Sotala on discord about what I mean when I say "Self is a part", and I ended up writing the following set of theses about what I actually believe by tabooing the words "Self" and "part". I thought I'd capture that here rather than having to search discord for it in future. The following is a lightly edited version of my explanation on Discord.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Your emotional state can exhibit &lt;em&gt;stuck modes&lt;/em&gt;, which are essentially a coherent bundle of emotional reactions that it is useful to conceptualise as person-like due to feeling like a discrete entity. The ideal is to have no stuck modes, but this ideal is probably only theoretically achievable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most of your broader mental and emotional capabilities do not neatly fit into a discrete set of such stuck modes, but are a more flexibly adoptable and combineable set of underlying mental/emotional resources that you can use to construct &lt;em&gt;attitudes&lt;/em&gt; that are appropriate to the present context.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Many emotional problems correspond to stuck modes that are in some way unhappy, and that arose by essentially ossifying a particular set of responses from a past situation and being unable to grow past that point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A useful set of mental motions is to essentially identify a stuck mode corresponding to a problem and adopt the attitude that that you would have needed from someone else at the time to not get stuck in that mode.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For many stuck modes this attitude corresponds to a sort of boundless love and acceptance. This is particularly likely to be the case for stuck modes that arose in childhood or romantic relationships, because there the problem arose from a lack of love from an external source.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This does not exhaust the possibilities of things that a stuck mode might need.
Additionally, due to the way we treat some of our stuck modes, a stuck mode may experience sufficient animosity to the broader self (lower case s - I mean "you overall", not anything corresponding to the IFS Self) that makes it unacceptable to it that you are the one providing the support it needs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Untabooing now to explain the relationship: in this terminology, an exile is a "stuck mode", and "Self" is an attitude (or more likely a range of broadly similar attitudes), which aligns with "Self is not a part" if we want to consider "part" and "stuck mode" synonymous, but I often find it useful to construct temporary unstuck parts, which are essentially attitudes and not stuck modes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Examples of attitudes that I don't think are particularly Self-like and help sometimes: Something closer to a mediator part that's mostly just there to help integrate two stuck modes by acting as an inbetween and asking good questions until they realise that they feel in opposition and are basically on the same side. Something that is more like a mentor than a parent who basically goes "Oh yeah that sucks, shall we figure out what to do about it?" at the part until it's able to treat its state as a practical problem to be resolved rather than an existential crisis.
And all of these have certain Self-like qualities to them (they require kindness, acceptance, etc) but the love is not the primary function.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Constructing a temporary part that is coherent enough to have a conversation with feels like roughly the same skill as coming up with a fictional character for your writing (at least the way I do it), by essentially coalescing an attitude and adding details that feel right until it feels relatively coherent. This is more work than accessing a stuck mode, but it's not necessarily a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Conversely, I think stuck modes are often a bit fuzzy around the edges, and can essentially be dissolved (and indeed IFS often ends up resulting in a process of dissolving them - a healed exile has essentially been dissolved).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is that it's not so much that "Self" and "parts" in the IFS ontology are the same thing as that there is not a clean division between the two things, and there is not a single special state called Self that is fundamentally unlike the parts it's used to heal.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-15-18:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-23-14:36.html</id>
    <title>Social reality as a game</title>
    <updated>2021-11-23T22:44:47+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Social reality as a game&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-11-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We went out scrumping for drones earlier, and in the course of doing so I did something weird: I brought a mug of coffee with me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was weird not because I had coffee with me, that's normal, but because it was a normal ceramic mug that I was just wandering through the streets holding.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If it had been a paper cup that would have been fine, obviously. Similarly, a travel mug wouldn't have raised an eyebrow.
But a normal ceramic mug? That's weird.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why was I carrying a mug? Well, I wasn't going far - the drone tree was only about five minutes walk away - and I didn't have a travel mug, but I'd just made coffee and I wanted to drink my coffee. Sure, I might drop it, but the solution to that was to not drop it (I didn't drop it).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was a perfectly reasonable practical solution, but ceramic mugs are a home item not a travel item, so it was weird.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bernard Suits defines a game as "the voluntary attempt to overcome unecessary obstacles", and I think about that a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How voluntary does it have to be? &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Clearly it's still a game if you give in to social pressure to play it, right? The fact that your family will sulk at you if you don't play doesn't make Yahtzee suddenly not a game (admittedly I could argue that it's not a game for other reasons, but it's certainly a Suitsian game in the sense that you're attempting to overcome your desire to die of boredom and the whole thing seems very unecessary. Also there are dice).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But who determines what's necessary?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More properly, the above his portable definition. He actually defines a game as:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To play a game is to attempt to achieve a specific state of affairs [prelusory goal], using only means permitted by rules [lusory means], where the rules prohibit use of more efficient in favour of less efficient means [constitutive rules], and where the rules are accepted just because they make possible such activity [lusory attitude].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He offers the example of mountain climbing: Your prelusory goal is to get to the top of the mountain, but the lusory means are that you have to climb it. If you could just take a helicopter up, you would not be playing the "game" of mountain climbing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's what I wonder: How much of our behaviour is governed by things that are, effectively, constitutive rules of a social game? I was certainly refusing to follow voluntarily adopted rules that prohibited me from using the more efficient means that I was currently employing. Those rules are, in some sense, accepted just because they make possible the activity of society.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In carrying a ceramic mug around with me outside was I, in small part, refusing to play a game in which everyone is implicitly participating in all the time?
Maybe, but at least I got to drink my coffee.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We didn't manage to scrump any drones, incidentally.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-23-14:36.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-12-14-12:27.html</id>
    <title>The landscape of</title>
    <updated>2021-12-14T12:46:31+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The landscape of&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-12-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the features of &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/labelling-feelings"&gt;my working model of emotions&lt;/a&gt; is that they exist as a tendency towards behaviours. Anger is a tendency to behave angrily, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This tendency is experienced as something like the default thing that happens if you don't put in energy to avoid it happening. It's not that behaving angrily is inevitable when you are angry, it's that it is more work to avoid behaving angrily than it is to behave angrily. You have to constantly choose not to behave angrily.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was having a miserable day yesterday, and I was wondering... what is that? What is miserable? Is it an emotion?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to say that miserable is not an emotion because it lacks intentionality, it's not about something (although there's some linguistic ambiguity - I feel like one can be miserable about specific things as well, but there's miserable-about and there's just miserable, and it's the latter I'm pointing to).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to say that miserable is not an emotion but a &lt;em&gt;mood&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What's a mood? Well, a mood is to emotions as emotions are to behaviour: A tendency towards.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This ties into Ratcliffe and his notion of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-06-07:46.html"&gt;Depression as constituted by existential feelings&lt;/a&gt;,
and in particular as a restriction on the set of possible emotions, which suggests that "tendency towards" may be insufficiently strong in its connotations. Sometimes that tendency is overwhelming: A feeling of hopelessness creates not just a "tendency" against hope, but a feeling that hope is itself impossible.
Moods contain not just slopes but also walls.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does this in turn go back to emotions and behaviours? I think it does. If I'm absolutely furious with someone I may be able to behave calmly with them, but I probably can't behave warmly to them - I can go through the motions, but I will probably seem stiff and artificial (because I will be) because I do not have full control over my body language, and have to fight against my natural tendencies.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So perhaps a better way to think of emotions and behaviour is not the tendency towards behaviours but the landscape of behaviour. It is the set of hills and valleys and walls that behaviour operates in. You can apply energy to move up a slope, you probably can't move up a wall, but as soon as you stop applying energy you will fall into the local minimum.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Moods in turn are the landscape of emotions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What is the landscape of mood?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was going to say that it's temperament, but that isn't quite right. It's some combination of temperament and environment - part of why I was miserable yesterday is definitely environmental, prompted by how grey and unpleasant the weather is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general this feels like a fruitful question to ask even outside the context of mood and emotion: When you have a space of possibilities, what constitutes the landscape for it?&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-12-14-12:27.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-01-13:23.html</id>
    <title>Writing from the heart</title>
    <updated>2022-01-01T13:41:36+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Writing from the heart&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-01&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been thinking about types of writing recently, and in particular about the following section from Hillary Rettig's excellent "7 Secrets of the prolific":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grandiosity is a problem for writers because our media and culture are permeated with grandiose myths and misconceptions about writing, which writers who are undermentored fall prey to. Red Smith’s famous bon mot about how, to write, you need only “sit down at a typewriter and open a vein,” and Gene Fowler’s similarly sanguinary advice to “sit staring at a blank sheet of paper until the drops of blood form on your forehead,” are nothing but macho grandiose posturing, as is William Faulkner’s overwrought encomium to monomaniacal selfishness, from his Paris Review interview:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writer’s only responsibility is to his art. He will be completely ruthless if he is a good one. He has a dream. It anguishes him so much he must get rid of it. He has no peace until then. Everything goes by the board: honor, pride, decency, security, happiness, all, to get the book written. If a writer has to rob his mother, he will not hesitate; the “Ode on a Grecian Urn” is worth any number of old ladies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the most famous quotes about writing are grandiose. I’m not saying that all of these writers were posturing—perhaps that’s how they truly perceived themselves and their creativity. What I do know is that, for most writers, a strategy based on pain and deprivation is not a route to productivity. In fact, it is more likely a route to a block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually find quotes about how awful writing and the writing life are to be not just perfectionist, but self-indulgent. No one’s forcing these writers to write, after all, and there are obviously far worse ways to spend one’s time, not to mention earn one’s living. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Rettig is, broadly, right here about how most people should be writing most of the time, but I must admit that of all the wisdom in this section the one that's stuck with me is the line she's disagreeing with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2011/09/14/writing-bleed/"&gt;According to Quote Investigator&lt;/a&gt;, Red Smith's full line is: &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You simply sit down at the typewriter, open your veins, and bleed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think about this a lot because, contra Rettig, writing be like that sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's useful to compare and contrast two recent newsletter issues of mine. &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/labelling-feelings"&gt;Labelling feelings 101&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/first-hard-choice"&gt;The first hard choice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Labelling feelings 101 was not a particularly taxing piece to write. It's just a summary of lots of things I've thought about. There's a moderate amount of myself in there, but only because it's explaining how I look at things. It's a look at part of the world through my eyes, but it's just explanatory prose, it's nothing particularly revealing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first hard choice on the other hand is weirder and more personal. I started writing, and then I continued writing, and it went in a very different direction than I intended. The underlying thought process is non-obvious, but I think it comes through that I'm writing about something that actually matters to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tellingly, "Labelling feelings 101" has got more attention (it's certainly useful to more people) but "The first hard choice" has got more praise (and also more people checking in to make sure that I'm OK).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is, a lot of the time, a way of expressing something deeply felt. You write from the heart, and it's hard to do that without bleeding onto the page.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most writing isn't, and shouldn't, be like this. If you're writing an email to a coworker it doesn't have to express some profound truth. If you're writing some basic copy explaining how a product works, same. But if you're writing about your life, or about things that are personally important to you, and you are &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; doing this, then you're probably holding your feelings at arms length, and that isn't great.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Am I being grandiose? Rettig would probably think so, and maybe I am. But some things are actually important, and it's hard to talk about that without sounding a little grandiose, and maybe that's OK.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't do this sort of writing enough, and I'd like to do it more - every time I have it's been in some way transformative.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to achieve this, I've come up with a very detailed and elaborate plan: I'm going to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-01-13:23.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html</id>
    <title>Wanting (to) help</title>
    <updated>2022-01-02T15:54:14+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Wanting (to) help&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I said in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-01-13:23.html"&gt;writing from the heart&lt;/a&gt; that I wanted to write more personal stuff.
Well, here it is. Unfortunately, it turns out, bleeding onto the page hurts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, on to the point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You may or may not have noticed, but I'm a very helpful person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of this comes out more with friends, family, etc. When I see someone I know who is having problems, I want to help. I'm aware this isn't always possible or welcome, and I don't force help on people by any means, but generally if you're my friend and need help I'm there for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of it also comes out with strangers. I've had fairly extensive conversations trying to help random strangers on the internet solve their problems or process their feelings.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's also little things like, mostly for free, having a major impact on the quality of software testing in the Python ecosystem. I've at this point written about two million words on the internet, a decent chunk of which is just me helpfully explaining things to strangers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't want to give you the impression that I'm constantly martyring myself for others. There are many people who are far more helpful than I am, and give an amount of their time and energy that I am both in awe of and have no desire to emulate. If one were to put together some arbitrary ranking of people in terms of helpfulness, I'm probably in the top 10%, likely in the top 5% (&lt;a href="https://danluu.com/p95-skill/"&gt;95%-ile isn't that good&lt;/a&gt;), and probably not in the top 1%.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't say I'm always good at helping.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I usually am good at helping when the problem is one that can be solved through the deployment of my very particular set of skills. Sometimes that means helping people problem solving, sometimes that means just showing up and listening and providing hugs, sometimes that involves more concrete help like turning up and providing manual labour, or providing a place to crash for the night. There are things my friends probably can't rely on me for though - if it needs organisational skills or fine motor control, I'm probably not the one that can help you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also sometimes I'd love to help but I'm overcommitted - either with my own stuff, or with helping other people, or both. Until my cloning project comes online, I'm only one man.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of which is fine, in principle. I'm not helpful because I want to help people, I'm helpful because I want people to be helped. If you've got someone better suited than me to draw on, I'm delighted.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It rarely seems like this is the case though. People don't, for the most part, help their friends out that much. The typical friendship I see seems to be one where people pretend that connection without responsibility is possible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, this often makes me feel worse about not being able to help, because often the reason someone needs my help is that nobody else has been able to provide it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, all generalising heavily from my own very small pool of experience. I'm sure if you move to a different culture, or even a different social milieu within a given culture, it looks different. People live in very different worlds. But based on what I see this doesn't look &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; weird.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This particularly stings because people are generally willing to draw on offered help, but pay it neither back nor forward.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think a friendship in which one party feels no real responsibility to the other, and is unwilling to extend meaningful help, is in the long run doomed.
Nobody is invincible, nobody can maintain good times for ever. You're going to have a bad period, and then the people who were just with you for a good time and don't feel any responsibility for you ghost or angrily leave. There's a reason we have the phrase "fair weather friends".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn't even particularly require bad times. I've lost multiple friendships due to it turning out that the other party in a relationship that I had poured a huge amount of care and help into (which they happily accepted) felt absolutely no responsibility to me to reciprocate even a tiny fraction of that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They would no doubt tell you this is a grossly unfair summary of the situation. I would, in turn, tell you that yes they would say that and can get fucked as far as I'm concerned. This is as close as I am prepared to come in providing a fair and balanced summary of events.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Friendships aren't, and shouldn't be, transactional, but they do need to be somewhat reciprocal if they're to work. There's a deep hypocrisy involved in being willing to accept arbitrary amounts of help from someone and then be horrified at the idea that you might be expected to return it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately it is, I think, an extremely common hypocrisy, because people are rarely going to say no to getting their needs met, and are rarely going to say yes to taking on a responsibility they don't have to. It's much easier to jettison the relationship and move on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of this is something I feel acutely, because the truth is that a lot of why I'm so helpful is that I've spent a lot of my life desperately wanting help and not getting it, so I've learned to help people in the ways that I've wished that someone would help me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Don't get me wrong, I've had myriad advantages in life. Many of the problems that I've needed help with are, technically, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-07-15-09:33.html"&gt;nice problems to have&lt;/a&gt;. Many of them were not, but I was able to compensate for them in some way or another. It's not hard to imagine some hypothetical other's thought process of "How can you say you need help when so many other people are worse off? You're doing fine". But I really wasn't, and to a large degree still am not, doing fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can see this a lot in my writing - a lot of things I write have a model target audience of me of N years ago. They're something I desperately wished someone would teach me at the time, or desperately needed but didn't know even &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be taught, but nobody did. So I had to spend years of my life learning them the hard way, and now I'm paying it forward in the hopes that someone out there analogous to younger me gets the help they need.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's hard for me to talk about all this without sounding extremely bitter about it. That's because I'm extremely bitter about it. But the result is that I mostly don't talk about it in public at all, and I don't think that's good either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is part of what a pervasive unwillingness to help does, I think. People's responses to pain are all very "Have you tried not being in pain?" or, if you're lucky, "Yeah me too" - an attempt to deflect a responsibility to help more than an attempt to help.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm aware that not all of the help I've lacked has been due to others' unwillingness to help. Much of it is on me - I'm not very good at making it clear that I need help, or letting others help me when they do offer. There's a number of reasons for this, but mostly it's just a matter of getting burned too many times and finding it very hard to trust that this time it will be different. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is reasonably common, and is something of a vicious circle. I think, in fact, many people (probably not most) are in principle willing to help, but because it's hard to ask for help, most people won't be willing, and some people will punish you for it, we end up with this dysfunctional feedback loop where most friendships stay at the responsibility light version.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd like to break this cycle, but I don't really know how.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-03-14:16.html</id>
    <title>Relearning curiosity</title>
    <updated>2022-01-03T19:55:49+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Relearning curiosity&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Apparently when I start a daily writing practice in which I am honest about my feelings partly as a way to work myself out of a depressed period,
everything I write is very sad. So, here we are again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A while back I wrote &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-28-15:58.html"&gt;I'm not actually that curious&lt;/a&gt;. I explained that although I am a voracious reader and know a lot of stuff, it wasn't actually generally powered by a learn things for its own sake - I learn in aid of things I want to do, not primarily because I want to learn. Almost everything I learn has a goal in mind. I don't seek out knowledge because I'm curious, I seek it out because knowledge is useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Dear past me: You realise that's bad, right? Well, in case you don't realise that (I'm not sure you did), FYI that's bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also not how I used to be. I &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; used to be curious, and just read about things because they were fun and interesting. I had a very nerdy notion of fun and interesting which means that this ended up me taking a book about classical mechanics (I still know a surprising amount about Lagrangian formulations of Newtonian physics, although it's all got a bit rusty) as my summer vacation reading when I was 16, but it was absolutely something I picked because I wanted to learn about it and not because I needed to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My degree was in pure mathematics, which I certainly didn't get into because I had applications in mind for the connection between the axioms of set theory and questions in analysis (this was what my final year essay was on. It wasn't very good).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Apparently as a kid I would fairly regularly give adults mostly-correct lectures on various subjects I'd been learning about. Palm trees and black holes seem to be the topic that people tell stories about me doing this, but I'm sure there are others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point this got lost. I don't really know when, or why.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It feels like part of the problem is agency. As a kid it's easy to be curious about things, because nothing you do actually matters, and also you're mostly bored out of your mind. So why not learn new things purely because they're interesting and you want to stuff your brain with knowledge?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, you're a child, and thus you're still full of energy. The fatigue of ageing and the burnout of life haven't set in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Not that those are inevitable. My parents seem like they still have way more energy than I do)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now it feels like I've got such limited brain capacity and energy and such a greater degree of agency that &lt;em&gt;of course&lt;/em&gt; I spend it on useful things, because I feel guilty about not doing so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Except I think even as I write it that that's a cope. If that were the case I'd probably be doing far more useful things than I do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Really the core problem is that &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;it's hard to care about things&lt;/a&gt;, and usefulness is a crutch.
It's much easier to solve a problem, which is obviously good. It's even better if &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html"&gt;it's somebody else's problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I keep wanting to frame this in terms of justification, but I don't think that's quite right. The problem isn't that I feel like I have to be able to justify my actions to someone, but that they need to feel somehow purposeful. It's not that someone will attack me for doing it, it's that if I spend energy on something purposeless a huge wave of "What's the point?" rises up and I get distracted and go do something else.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often it starts before that and I can't even generate the "purposeless" actvitity in the first place. I try to generate a plan for what to do and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-02-08:53.html"&gt;my brain glitches&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is depression, of course. It's well-managed reasonably high functioning depression, but it's still depression.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think of depression as a constriction of the felt world of possibilities. A narrowing of the actions that you feel able to take. A lot of my incessant "curiousity" in the search of the useful feels like I'm trying to squeeze a vast level of interest in the world through the narrow passages that depression has left me. What comes out is still pretty good, because I'm clever and competent, but it's fairly anemic compared to what I'd be doing if less depressed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of this focus on usefulness feels not so much like I'm motivated to be useful (I am, but it's more of a "make the pain go away" motivation than something I necessarily care deeply about), but that it's something to do while I'm here. I've got all these capabilities, there are things I can do that help make things better, might as well. It's slightly less fundamentally unsatisfying than wasting my day scrolling Twitter and reading YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; fundamentally care about helping people, but it's all swallowed up by the general meh. Certainly I would &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; to be positively motivated towards helping people instead of it being something that hurts if I don't do it, but these days I'm struggling to be positively motivated about much of anything very serious.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1476967194101698561"&gt;I wrote on Twitter about how incredibly mind-numbingly bored I am of the pandemic&lt;/a&gt;, and that I really need more in person contact with people than I'm getting. That feels like part of this but I don't know how much of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The absence of curiousity feels in some way like a primary thing in its own right that I should take seriously just as much as the absence of people.
Learning things should be a joyful activity, and the fact that it's not is a huge sign.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of my working theories of how to work with depression is to be constantly exploring the edge of the depression comfort zone - do things that you feel &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt; too depressed to do. If depression comes from a restriction of what feels safe, exploring the boundaries of where you feel safe helps you relearn those as safe and then you can expand gradually outwards.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes this even works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, that's too cynical. It often works, it's just a bit of a two steps forward one step back process. The depression comes back, but it's easier to claw your way out of it the next time because you believe you can do that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the starting point for solving the curiousity problem is something like asking how I would behave if I were as curious as I'd like to be, and walking in that direction until I hit the edge of the comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The obvious thing is that I would learn things just for interest. For some reason the example that comes to mind here is physics youtube. I've been enjoying &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/SteveMould"&gt;Steve Mould's YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; recently for example. I really respect the urge to just go "How does that work?" and put in the effort to find the answer. I definitely used to have some of that, and I'd like to have it again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other thing that comes to mind is that I'd talk to people more about things I find interesting. I really don't do this very much - these days all my writing is about stuff that's useful (in some very generalised sense of the term), which is a shame in and of itself - but really I have in person conversations in mind. Generally I just let other people take the lead, and feel very inhibited in proposing conversation topics and just going on about them, and that feels necessary if rather daunting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Who knows if any of this will actually work, but it feels worth a try.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-03-14:16.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-04-14:48.html</id>
    <title>Being a brain at night</title>
    <updated>2022-01-04T16:24:29+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Being a brain at night&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Look, I think we can just take it as read that the slightly traumatised writing will continue for a while. It's useful for me to write, and it seems to be useful for other people to read, so I'm going to do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I've been having panic attacks at night recently. Not every night, but maybe about once a week, and the edge is there on other nights.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sounds more dramatic than it is. They're not full blown panic attacks. Not really. It's very easy to stop them, all I have to do is open my eyes and distract myself.
It's not an irrecoverable panic attack, it's just that I close my eyes, try to sleep, and am filled with a formless dread as if I'm drowning.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the most likely cause, as well as generally having been in a terrible mood due to general depression and the whole global pandemic thing, is that I'm getting to experience something that I have rarely experienced in my adult life: It's bedtime and I'm not caffeine withdrawn.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I quit coffee about a month ago. As the joke goes: Quitting is easy, I've done it loads of times. This time I think it might stick. I've had a few coffees since quitting, all rather small, and frankly it's been awful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Among other reasons it's been awful because it seems by far the easiest way to trigger this problem. I don't need coffee to get a panic attack at night, but I get them 100% of the time I've had coffee in the last few weeks. As far as commitment devices go to break a habit it's a bit extreme, but it's hopefully effective.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(If this seems at odds with the claim that the problem is about not being caffeine withdrawn, the reason is that my caffeine tolerance is now mostly reset so although there's still less caffeine in my system by night, there are no withdrawal symptoms because I don't have the dependency, and what caffeine is still there is much more effective)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think when people hear you can't sleep because of anxiety they imagine that it's because of racing thoughts. Lying there awake thinking about all the terrible things that might happen, the things you did wrong, reminders of all your obligations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not like that. It's almost the opposite. It's an absence of thought, coupled with a feeling that something is terribly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Have you ever read Flowers for Algernon?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm planning to reread it soon, to see if I can exorcise some demons, but every time I remember the book exists I flinch. I don't know if it's meant to be a horror story but, for me, it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am, like most smart people, probably over identified with my intelligence. I'm sure there are all sorts of reasons why I shouldn't be, and I do try to braoden out, but honestly I have no idea how to be me without my intelligence. It is pretty close to being a core feature of who I am - it's not all I do is think, but my thoughts are so central to what I do that a dramatic loss of intelligence would fundamentally change who I am. Flowers for Algernon's account of intelligence slipping away was extremely hard for me to handle.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I am, naturally, similarly viscerally afraid of Alzheimers. Alzheimers is much scarier than dying to me, and I very much understand Terry Pratchett's support for assisted suicide)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What makes this particularly tricky to deal with is how much I experience my brain as a collection of black boxes. I've described the process of writing before as just reaching for the place where words come from and then letting it do its thing. What happens when the place where words come from goes away?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway this is what seems to be happening to me at night right now. I think this is likely to be perfectly normal tiredness and not something to worry about - it's normal to have trouble thinking when tired - but in the moment it sure doesn't &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like nothing to worry about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of the context for this is that when trying to fall asleep I often tell myself stories. Not particularly good ones, the goal isn't to craft a masterwork, it's just to construct some narrative to hang my thoughts on - often more worldbuilding than pure story. The current one is about a magical research team working on trying to improve a kingdom's crop yields, if you're curious.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On nights when the panic occurs, this very much doesn't work, and is likely to be a trigger. The problem is that I reach for the place where words come from and they're... not quite absent, but sluggish, and blocked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's like a sudden feeling of claustrophobia, when you're trapped and can't move properly - someone's lying on top of you, you're tangled in the duvet, some situation where you know intellectually that everything is fine and you're safe but oh god you have to move &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; and if you can't you very rapidly get frantic. That, but the things I can't move are my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This probably shouldn't be scary. I suspect this is just what sleep is - the gradual disintegration of your mind as it shuts down for the night - and maybe all that's happening is that I'm more acutely aware of it now. But regardless of whether I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be afraid of it, the fear response is fairly primal. I've always considered "Do you die each night and a new person takes your place in the morning?" to be an annoying piece of philosophical pedantry with no real content, but apparently some part of me very much disagrees.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first night this happened I stayed awake until 9AM until some combination of exhaustion and coincidence allowed me to figure out my first workaround, which is to just watch Slay the Spire videos on YouTube as I fall asleep. It gives me something to focus on that isn't the contents of my own mind. It works as a backstop, although it doesn't result in good sleep and it takes a while - last night I had to put on a second one because the first finished and I still wasn't asleep. On the plus side at least that was two hours not spent panicking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some degree of meditation practice works reasonably well for the less bad nights - I've succeeded a few times at falling asleep counting breaths. When it works it works very well, but I think I need to be quite tired for it to work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm also going to be trying some sleeping pills (just drowsy antihistamines to start) to see if I can just clobber the problem by being sleepy enough - this is how my old solution of running out of caffeine at night and thus being super sleepy worked after all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, taken as a practical problem, I'm getting on top of the sleep thing. It's annoying but manageable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it's also just so &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;/em&gt;. There's clearly something going on here that I don't understand, and that I struggle to understand because in the moment that it's happening, most of the tools I use to understand things are offline.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-04-14:48.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-05-13:01.html</id>
    <title>Ready for less than you think</title>
    <updated>2022-01-05T19:28:24+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Ready for less than you think&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had to go to the hospital earlier. This wasn't a big deal, I just needed an X-ray on my knee, which has been giving me a hard time for a few months. I set up an appointment with my GP late last month, expecting it to take a while to get the referral sorted (this is incorrect, the NHS is actually very good at prompt X-ray referrals, but I always forget this because I rarely get X-rays and they're rather less prompt at many referrals on other things), so I'd have time for Omicron to settle down and have my knee looked when it was sensible and safe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I got a call this morning at around 8:33. I was not at all awake at 8:33. I'd had another &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-04-14:48.html"&gt;night of bad sleep&lt;/a&gt;, and my alarm had gone off at 8:30 and so I was &lt;em&gt;technically&lt;/em&gt; conscious, but it was very confusing when my phone made a noise from the other room as if someone were uncouth enough to actually want to speak to me on it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The person on the other end told me that they'd had an urgent X-ray referral from my GP (I'm not sure it was really urgent if I'm honest) and could I come to Charing Cross Hospital for 10:25?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My response was slightly more articulate than "Huh? What? Zzzz" but not vastly more. Eventually my brain kicked into gear and I said I didn't think I could physically make it in time even if I left right that minute. Fortunately I checked Google Maps and determined that Charing Cross Hospital was not in fact anywhere near Charing Cross, but was in fact near Hammersmith, which is much easier for me to get to, and I determined that it would be tight but doable. So I said yes, I could do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A very rapid shower and a COVID test later, and a hurried message asking my partner to be in my flat to meet the Ocado delivery that was supposed to be arriving at 11, I dashed out the door to the bus stop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first problem I encountered was that after having promised me a very straightforward route, Google maps was now telling me that it was literally impossible to get there by public transport. It does that. The Google maps app sometimes believes my area (which is very well appointed with bus routes and not too bad to walk to various more civilised forms of public transport) is just utterly inaccessible to public transport, despite generally being OK on desktop web. I opened it on my phone's browser instead and it confirmed that yes the single direct bus to Hammersmith was still a perfectly viable option despite the app's lies.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second problem was that I missed my bus. This wasn't a huge deal, as it wasn't &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; tight and there was another one in 7 minutes, but as I was wondering whether it would make sense to get a taxi there I noticed my third problem: My phone was on 13% battery.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It shouldn't have been. I'd charged it overnight. When I got home I found out that the charger had partly fallen out of the power socket, so although the cable was connected to the phone this wasn't a problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also shouldn't have been a problem. I basically &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; travel without an external battery for my phone. But I couldn't find it when I was leaving, I was in a hurry, and figured it was fine - my phone was fully charged (oops) and I was only going to be out for a few hours.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I turned my phone off in order to conserve power, got the bus, and happily read Robertson Davies writing about interpersonal drama between Canadian academics for half an hour or so until I got to Hammersmith.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I got off the bus, turned on my phone, and prepared to walk the last 5-10 minutes from Hammersmith to Charing Cross Hospital.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This should be easy, it's just a straight line from Hammersmith, more or less. I mean &lt;a href="https://www.google.co.uk/maps/dir/Hammersmith+Station,+London+W6+7AE/Charing+Cross+Hospital,+Fulham+Palace+Rd,+London+W6+8RF/@51.489909,-0.2257482,16.62z/data=!4m14!4m13!1m5!1m1!1s0x48760fb7e0b0070d:0x2398b7d670685535!2m2!1d-0.2248261!2d51.493483!1m5!1m1!1s0x48760fbbc7f7ed75:0x6cd065c43bb8bbf5!2m2!1d-0.2195543!2d51.4868889!3e2"&gt;look at this&lt;/a&gt;, it's not a complicated route.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Just one problem: Figuring out &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; straight line it is is impossibly confusing, because when your phone is in low power mode Google Maps becomes all but useless at telling you where you are, and Google Maps has always been useless at orienting without GPS in the UK because it insists on displaying road numbers instead of names. I don't want to know that this is the fucking A315, Google, I want to know &lt;em&gt;what the name on the road sign is&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I could have figured it out in about five minutes of wandering around the junction and staring (in retrospect, I knew which way North was, and if I'd oriented Google maps right I could have known I needed to head southish, and that would have been enough). Unfortunately I got about three minutes, which was how long my phone took to eat through the remaining 13% of battery. I don't know why it died so fast and should probably look into that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It took me about 25 minutes to find Charing Cross Hospital. I asked five different people for directions in the course of that. They were all very nice about it - I do charming but flustered polite Englishman very well and it tends to work for getting strangers to help you out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They were not, reliably, useful. Some of their directions were straight up wrong, some of them were in retrospect right but I failed to follow them correctly. The result was a lot of doubling back on myself. But I did find it before my appointment, though not as much before my appointment as they want you to be. I was tired, stressed, and had done enough running at that point (mostly to catch the bus, the rest was a brisk walk) that I'd probably aggravated the knee problem I was there to get checked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway the X-ray all went fine, nothing to report there for now. They did make me do a rather uncomfortable lunge to get the knee right before the X-ray machine, which I'm probably going to pay for given that it's exactly the sort of motion that triggers the knee problem, but so far it's no worse than grumpy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the knee isn't really the point of this story (to the degree that there's a point rather than me just feeling like telling you about how my day went).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of this has me thinking about preparedness, and the way it decays. This whole episode would have gone much better prior to the pandemic, because I would not have made the mistake with my phone - maybe it wouldn't have been charged, but I'd have had the battery. I'd have been less flustered by Google maps's problems because I'd have Citymapper installed (my phone is a bit low on space and I'm not actually travelling far right now so I uninstalled it).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, leaving the house involves a certain amount of skill and preparations. If you're travelling regularly, those are all fresh. If you're not, your skills have got rusty and your habits have been decayed - the battery that you always have access to has gotten tucked somewhere weird because you haven't used it recently for example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Navigation was also like this to a degree - I'd utterly lost the skill. When I mentioned asking for directions, J said "Wow, asking for directions? What is this the 90s??" and it's true - I've had a smart phone on me for 11 years at this point. The idea of being lost is just alien. Asking for directions was fine, but following them from memory sure was hard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It feels ridiculous to be bad at leaving the house in this way (finding it difficult to leave the house is less confusing, but successfully leaving the house and being bad at it is weird), because this is something that seems trivial and I've spent so long being competent at that it's part of my internalised self image that it's just something I can do at a moment's notice without it going wrong (a small achievement, but not an automatic one - I know many people who can't leave the house without forgetting something for example), but it's fairly natural, just not internalised.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been thinking about how long it's going to take for being in a crowd to feel normal again, even once it's safe, but I think maybe one of the interesting things is going to happen before that, as we gradually resume life and find out all the skills and habits we'd taken for granted have to be relearned from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-05-13:01.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
