<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2022-05-29T05:59:24+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-31-14:38.html</id>
    <title>Soul death</title>
    <updated>2022-03-29T20:14:03+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Soul death&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-31&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Slight content warning: If internal family systems and other parts work is load bearing for you, and if I am right, there is a small possibility that this post contains information that will make your life actively worse, especially in the short term while you integrate it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's probably fine, and I'm currently hoping that this thought process is helpful (as I certainly can't unthink it), this is just a heads up. Proceed with caution.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/the_wilderless/status/1456619189171638276"&gt;let me show you a hilarious tweet from the_wilderless&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IFS people: how do I hunt this part down, slaughter it, and leave its carcass as an example to the others?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The tweet itself is funny, but what's really funny about the tweet is the number of people in the replies clearly failing to recognise that it's a joke, and sounding really quite distressed about the very suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Yes I'm laughing at distressed people, several of whom are my friends. I shall nevertheless regard the part of me that is a dick with unconditional love and compassion)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of this reaction is much more funny-interesting than funny-ha-ha. This tweet is &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt; a joke, right? And yet people don't get this. It's not that they're responding to it as if it was a bad joke, they're responding to it as if it was not a joke at all. That's interesting, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I like Johnathan Morreall's theories of humour, from his book Comic Relief, in which he describes the characteristic features of humour as:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic pattern [of humour] is that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We experience a cognitive shift – a rapid change in our perceptions or thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are in a play mode rather than a serious mode, disengaged from conceptual and practical concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of responding to the cognitive shift with shock, confusion, puzzlement, fear, anger, or other negative emotions, we enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our pleasure at the cognitive shift is expressed in laughter, which signals to others that they can relax and play too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the book he discusses False Alarm laughter:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see what might have been involved in this disengaged mental processing, and how it might have benefited early humans, imagine the following scenario. A band of early humans is walking across the savanna, when they spot a lion in the clearing ahead. They freeze in their tracks for a moment, but then they see that the lion is feasting on a zebra and doesn’t even look up at them. With the sudden realization that the lion is not a threat, they laugh, signaling to each other “We’re safe. We can enjoy this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Humour requires something like this realisation: "We're safe. We can enjoy this."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So perhaps something about the wilderless's joke makes these respondents feel unsafe. That's interesting, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Consider another fictitious scenario. Suppose someone who you distrust and know could really genuinely hurt you makes a "joke" about hurting you. Do you think you would be able to interpret it as anything other than a threat?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I propose one possible explanation for why people reacted so badly to this tweet: They contain two parts, one of which would absolutely hunt down the other, slaughter it, and leave its carcass as an example to the others, and the other part very much knows this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A core principle of IFS and other parts work is that you can't actually murder parts. You can treat them badly, you can suppress them, you can ignore them, but you don't actually have the ability to cut off a part of yourself and kill it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is even true, but I can't help but notice that it's a very convenient belief to hold. Without it, doing IFS is like doing group therapy for a bunch of people all of whom are openly carrying firearms, and several of them are looking mighty twitchy. With it, the therapy environment isn't exactly &lt;em&gt;safe&lt;/em&gt;, but it's boundedly dangerous. You can hurt each other with angry words and feelings, but you're ultimately all in this together and stuck with each other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As soon as the possibility of soul murder, where one part of you kills another, is on the table, it becomes very hard to create an environment in which healing is possible. You have to be able to tell parts that they are safe, and it is much easier to tell a part that it is &lt;em&gt;intrinsically&lt;/em&gt; safe because you &lt;em&gt;can't&lt;/em&gt; kill it, than it is to convince it that you could absolutely kill it if you wanted to and also some part of you wants to and also you won't because you love it honest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly true with &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-12-10:11.html"&gt;the sort of part I've previously described as a prisoner&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here's the problem with this: Not all parts of you that are kept away from the world are exiles, some of them are prisoners, and they hate you, and they have every right to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction between an exile and a prisoner is this: An exile keeps apart from the world out of fear, a prisoner is kept apart from the world out of shame. A protector would let the exile out if the exile wanted to come out, a guard knows the prisoner wants to come out, that's the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A prisoner corresponds much more closely to the Jungian model of shadows: You have rejected a part of yourself, and locked it in the darkness, where it has become monstrous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But really, it's not a monster at all, you've just done it a great injustice by imprisoning it, and it hates you for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Can you possibly trust someone who is armed, dangerous, and has previously harmed you that they're not going to use their power and murder you?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note that all of this is true &lt;em&gt;even if&lt;/em&gt; soul murder is impossible. What we're seeing here is not necessarily that people have a false belief, but that they have a belief that they are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; motivated to need it to be true. Even asking the question of whether soul murder is possible is very dangerous, because your entire practice rests on the parts you work with believing that it is not in order to feel safe enough to engage.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The additional problem is that I don't believe that soul murder is impossible. I think it is likely that it's entirely possible, it's just that people are doing it wrong. You don't murder a part through violence, you murder it by persuading it to kill itself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the themes I've been trying to work with recently is  that of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-22-17:13.html"&gt;holding myself too tightly&lt;/a&gt;. What is that part of me that does it best to maintain a calm reserve, refusing to let me engage with the world freely and joyously? It seems remarkably unwilling to budge on this. Why?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One key aspect of it is that it feels like budging is irreversible. Like if I release, I won't be able to pull myself back together. If I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-23-13:27.html"&gt;acknowledge the pain of the world&lt;/a&gt; I will no longer be able to shut it out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But when I try to access what that feels like from the part's point of view, the core feeling is something closer to this: "AAAAAAH I WILL DIE".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To which another part of me has only this to say: "Good".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On more sophisticated reflection, I do not endorse that this would be wholly good. This reserve has served me well in many regards, it has a genuine protective function. It is there to help me, and I appreciate it. I do not want it to go away and die. I wish to ritually sacrifice it, consume its flesh, and take its power for my own.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, this metaphor is not wholly helpful for getting the part on side with this plan.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my prisoners post I said:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I hope I'm right about parts not being fully real, and are more like stable patterns in the self that serve a well defined purpose, waves that exist as part of a greater ocean. If you give a part the room and support it needs to grow, perhaps at some point it decides that its task is done, and it's ready for the wave to become the ocean again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've explained "parts not being fully real" thing in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-15-18:31.html"&gt;My conception of parts work&lt;/a&gt;. A part is a stuck mode of being, and the goal of parts work is to be able to get them unstuck, to allow them to stop holding themselves too tightly and fluidly reintegrate into your broader whole. The boundary of the part dissolves, and the wave becomes the ocean again. The part has died.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the part of me responsible for this reserve knows what it needs to do. The "I will die" feeling isn't &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; that of a refusal to die. It's not spitting defiance in the face of death and shouting "Not Today", it's more... it knows that it is time to let go, but it is afraid. I know how it feels, naturally, but I mean that on many levels.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Resident Contrarian &lt;a href="https://www.residentcontrarian.com/p/unsolicited-advice-on-the-institute"&gt;has a great piece on marriage&lt;/a&gt; that's mostly unrelated to this post, but in it there is a metaphor that has really stuck with me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A man was walking through the woods and in time came upon a ravine. Near the ravine was a man who, after a few moments, ran full-tilt at the ravine and leapt into the void over it as if to clear the entire gulf in one mighty jump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as the man observed the jumper, he also noticed that he was dragging a parachute; this slowed the jumper’s running as he approached the ravine. As the Jumper leapt, the parachute filled with air, stopping his forward motion completely. He then fell into the ravine; the parachute slowed his fall enough to make sure he wasn’t seriously injured, but he still scraped and banged against the sides on his way down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man watched as the jumper climbed back out and attempted the jump again with the same results. He approached him and asked “Why are you doing that?”. “Because I want to jump the ravine”, the Jumper replied. “No, I mean - why are you using the parachute when it keeps you from being successful?”. The Jumper looked at him like he was insane, and replied “That’s to minimize the damage from the fall.”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And, well, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Much of my approach to life, growth, healing, etc. is to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;make things safe&lt;/a&gt; and then act freely within that safety. I work with careful, incremental, steps where I gradually clear out problems, make new things possible, and cautiously explore and enlarge the boundaries of my comfort zone. It's worked very well for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But with something like this, where I hold tightly to the belief that any change is irreversible, maybe there is no safe way forward? Maybe I have to accept that at a certain point, change becomes unsafe, and that you have to do it anyway, or choose cowardice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe at some point the only way forward is to take off the parachute and jump.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-31-14:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-02-14-08:52.html</id>
    <title>Fewer than 100 thoughts on "Jokes"</title>
    <updated>2022-02-14T14:05:11+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Fewer than 100 thoughts on "Jokes"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-02-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This month is supposed to be reading month, and I'm not doing a very good job on reading new books, so I've been revisiting some old books instead. Unfortunately in order to get what I want out of this, I find myself in the position of having to do something that is anathema to my very nature: Taking notes on the books I read.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm rubbish at private writing, so I'm going to experiment with formats for doing that on here. How useful they'll be to anyone else, I don't know. Feel free to skip these.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today's format experiment is that I'm going to try to write down 100 thoughts on Ted Cohen's book "Jokes: Philosophical thoughts on joking matters". I'll first do a linear scan through the book jotting down anything that I think of as I write it or exerpting any particularly insightful quotes, then I'll start sampling at random, and once that stops working I'll try to synthesize thoughts from further up the list.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;100 may be ambitious (it's more than one thought per page in the book) but let's see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page x (in the acknowledgements before the formal numbering). "James Lorie reminds us of the ster standard according to which no joke without obscenity is really a joke, and that a really fine joke is fit for any company". What is the actual relationship between obscenity and humour? Very few of the jokes in this book are actually obscene - a few are tasteless, but very few contain actual obscenities (even the jokes about sex are mostly PG!). There is clearly something distinctive about obscene humour, but obscenity seems inessential. It's possible I'm reading this line too literally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also page x. "Nicholas Rudall is [...] one of those rare companions with whom one can work on a joke". This seems like an interesting experience that I mostly lack. I was wondering about the art of joke making, but maybe I should be focusing on the art of collaboration on a joke.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 1. "The fact of jokes - the fact that there are such tings - is something of note, something worth thinking about."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 3 "Many jokes are usefully thought of as solutions to problems that have been set" - notably though, they're problems with absurd solutions. A joke that will come up later is "What do Winnie the Pooh and Alexander the Great have in common?". This is a central example of such a problem-based joke, but the reason it is a joke is that it is designed to break you out of the normal logic that you would use to address such a question. A joke that is a problem is a joke that is designed to remind you that your normal tools do not exhaust the set of tools you may need. (They have the same middle name)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Paraphrased from page 4). It is an essential feature of jokes that they rely on your prior knowledge - a joke that has to explain the background knowledge in order to get the joke will fail to land.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the background pieces of knowledge you can assume when telling jokes is that the listener is familiar with jokes. As such, you can tell jokes that are funny partly because of their relationship to the nature of telling jokes. For example "How many surrealists does it take to change a lightbulb? Fish." is not a funny joke unless you are familiar with the category of problem-solving jokes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 10. "there will be no comprehensive theory of jokes or their purpose, not only because I have no such theory but also because I believe there could be no such theory." - this is the core of what makes "Jokes" an interesting but somewhat limited book I think. It's mostly Cohen giving a tour of some things he finds interesting in the space of jokes, but it could use a bit more theory to tie it all together. I often struggle to remember what I get out of this book because of the lack of unification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also think he's wrong about the impossibility of such a theory. His argument seems to be that joking is too contextual to admit a unifying theory, but I'm not sure this follows - eating is also very contextual, but there are unifying principles underlying our appetites and what makes a dish work. One shouldn't confuse the highly contextual nature of expertise for a lack of unity in the underlying problems being solved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 11. You can tell this is a book about philosoph of humour because it contains the following joke: "According to Freud, what comes between fear and sex? fünf". All books about philosophy of humour have to contain this joke, it's the rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cohen claims that this joke doesn't really work written, but I don't have a problem reading it. I wonder if this varies based on how people read and whether they hear the words in their head as they read?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back to page 10. Cohen talks about joking as a two-stage art, consisting of both composition and telling. I have &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-14-12:00.html"&gt;a whole prior post&lt;/a&gt; disagreeing with this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 12). There is no such thing as a pure joke. All jokes are conditional on what the audience understands - at the bare minimum you have to share a language (though this is perhaps only true in Cohen's specific conception of "joke" - it seems to me that some physical humour could be universal. Although even there you have to share a body language, which isn't as cross cultural as all that), but really a joke can only land if it fits in with and askew to the audience's understanding of the world. See &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-04-12:52.html"&gt;The humour test for expertise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cohen uses the term "hermetic" for a joke that requires extensive background knowledge or beliefs (e.g. a mathematician joke)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 17. "It is not required that the audience (or the teller) actually &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; that [the stereotype on which a joke was predicated], but he must be acquainted with this idea. When jokes play upon commonplaces - which may or may not be believed - they oten do it by exaggeration."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 20. "It is difficult to say just when such jokes [about particular regional or ethnic stereotypes] become offensive." - one thing that often comes through in this book is that Cohen seems to have a very high tolerance for jokes that would definitely get you cancelled these days. It seems partly a very 20th century attitude, but also partly particular to Cohen. This isn't just that he's fine with them for other groups either - he talks about antisemitic jokes in the same way that he talks about Polish or black jokes (though, it does seem to me that his examples of antisemitic jokes are milder than his examples of racist jokes against black people. Though also in his defence, he mostly uses the latter as examples of jokes that go too far)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 21). "Conditional jokes that depend upon feelings in the audience, likes and dislikes, and preferences, I call affective. Typically, these jokes are understood by many people, but the success of the jokes—their capacity to amuse—depends upon the affective disposition of the audience."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 22). Jokes can have many layers of response. A joke can be funny to most people, but also have affective or hermetic conditions which render it funnier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 24). An example of this that he mentions and that I hadn't realised before is that when Hamlet says "Get thee to a nunnery", this line lands very differently if you know that "nunnery" is slang for "brothel".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 25). Cohen talks about the futility of trying to explain a joke, but I'm not so sure. There's definitely an art to explaining a joke so that it's funny, it's just funny for very different reasons than the joke would otherwise be funny. It's more like a sort of Stewart Lee "domming the audience into laughing". It's also very annoying, but it does work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 25). "a deep satisfactionin successful joke transactions is the sense held mutually by teller and hearer that they are joined in feeling". This is a recurring theme in the book - that jokes are a form of shared intimacy, based on the fact that you both find the same things funny. Cohen doesn't explicitly link this to any theory of humour, but I think part of the significance here is that a shared joke indicates that you and I find the same things incongruous, and thus that we must look at the world in a broadly similar way. Sharing a laugh is revelling in some way that we are the same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 28). Cohen talks about communities of amusement, and I don't think he's right. He's committing a classic mistake that likeness and relationships are enough to constitute a community. People who share an amusement with you are like you, and like each other, but lack a sufficient unity as a group to constitute a community. It's more like a type than a community, and types can serve as the starting poitn for a community but are not one themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 31). "Why do we recommend these things to one another, anyway? [...] Because we wish one another well? Well, maybe, but at its core I do not think this is entirely a matter of altruism. [...] I discover something of what it is to be a human being by finding this thing in me, and then having it echoed in you, another human being. [...] I want you to like it beause I like you and I want you to have something you like, and I want you to be grateful to me for supplying it. But I also need you to like it, because in your liking I receive a confirmation of my own liking."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I did not make it to 100. This got me about a third of the way through the book, and took me about an hour, and I think that's enough for now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't find these useless to write, but I also don't think this is the right format. I'll probably try something more essay-like next time.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-02-14-08:52.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-02-17-10:36.html</id>
    <title>You are not expected to understand this</title>
    <updated>2022-02-17T11:19:27+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You are not expected to understand this&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-02-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People have been reviewing Edward Teach's book "Sadly, Porn" recently, and I love this. The reviews are hilarious. The book is probably hilarious too, but I prefer to enjoy it from afar. There's something beautifully horribly wonderfully awful about the dense rambling misanthropy-laden prose that Teach uses to reach out from the page and shape your brain, bypassing any attempt at understanding and going straight for the feeling. True art, in that it takes the world and makes it strange to you, the truth that bypasses the need for argument. You read it, you do not understand it, and you go away rejecting it and nevertheless changed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I notice that Teach has this and is high status, and therefore in keeping with Teach's teachings, I want it and desire to take it away from him. And so I shall.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an experiment and you are not expected to understand it. I encourage you to roll with that, because I certainly will not be explaining it to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The difference between me and Teach is that Teach hates you and thinks you are contemptible, while I love you and think that you are hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are, perhaps, the same thing, because everything is the same thing. You cannot understand something well enough to love it without also knowing how to hate it. You cannot give something the attention required to hate it without also giving it the attention required to love it. The line between love and hate is razor thin and comes down solely to a choice. Perhaps the hardest choice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You will, of course, deny this, because you do not want to believe that you could hate that which you love, or love that which you hate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More importantly you want permission to maintain your hate. How could you love that? It must be impossible, and therefore it cannot be a choice, and therefore you are absolved.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Don't worry, I absolve you. You are allowed to hate. All that is forbidden you is to deny the choice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a part of you that craves being understood. There is a part of you that feels burdened by the need to be understood. These are the same part because every part of you is the same. Parts are an illusion created to deal with others. Others are an illusion created to give you parts. Everything is the same, and everyone is the same, and when you choose between love and hate you are also choosing how to love and hate yourself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Everything is the same as everything else, but also everything is different from everything else. Fortunately, "Everything is the same as everything else" is the same as "Everything is different from everything else".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"But wait", you say. "Surely "Everything is the same as everything else" is obviously different from "Everything is different from everything else"?". Yes exactly, now you're getting it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Like love and hate, same and different are choices you make about the world, not the world itself. Everything is the same, if you choose it to be the same, everything is different, if you choose it to be different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To your counterexample, I say this: I never said it was an &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt; choice. Shush now, listen.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way you look at the world, at the other, and yourself, is the way you have chosen to look at it in order to make it safe to look at. You are bound in by walls of fear, desperately denying your attention to that which you cannot safely look at.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You cannot hate what you fear, not truly, because you cannot look at it at all, so you cannot love it, so you cannot hate it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You choose sameness, and difference, in line with what you can handle. That which you love must be different from that which you hate, because you fear them being the same.
A careful dance of merging and differentiating until the universe achieves a configuration that you believe you can live with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This works, for a time, but life is a continual confrontation with the universe as it is, and you are forced to face over and over again that that which you chose the same is diferent, and that which you chose diferent is the same.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Remember: You are hilarious and I love you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are hilarious because you are an absurd mass of contradictions, maintaining this ridiculous pretense of sameness and differentiation in the face of a universe that cares not at all about your illusions, but also cares deeply about them because it is you and you are it because everything is the same.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Remember though, contradictions do not exist. That which is, is, and everything that is true of it is consistent. You create contradictions because you are small, too small to handle the vastness of everything, so you spread your web of understanding gossamer-thin across a universe that is too large to contain, and then cry at its inevitable breaking, and then to try again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are small, but you strive to contain the world.
I think this is beautiful and I love you for it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-02-17-10:36.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-04-05-21:53.html</id>
    <title>Beef and lentil stew "recipe"</title>
    <updated>2022-04-05T21:56:10+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Beef and lentil stew "recipe"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-04-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was going through some dead drafts and found the following recipe that I'd forgotten about that I was regularly making in the instant pot during this past winter and had completely forgotten about, so I thought I would save it here before I deleted the draft:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chopped white onions (I use frozen, which is honestly great), enough to cover the base of the instant pot so I guess a couple cups?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A couple cloves worth of chopped garlic (frozen again)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pack of bacon (often frozen too, but that’s irrelevant here it’s just where I keep my bacon)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minced beef, about 750g&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A cup and a half of green lentils&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chilli, rosemary, and thyme, to taste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salt, also to taste&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two cans of chopped tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three or four large carrots, sliced into coins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A couple of potatoes, chopped into cubes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two beef stock cubes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About half a bottle of red wine (I used what is probably a perfectly adequate Malbec last time but honestly I know nothing about wine)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To make it, pretty much do the obvious things. Put the instant pot on sauté, fry the onion and garlic with the spices, chop the bacon and add that at some point, then once that’s cooked add in the beef until it’s browned, then add in everything else, stir thoroughly, and add wine until the whole thing is covered in liquid. Put on a low pressure cook for half an hour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve written about this style of recipe before, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-07-10:05.html"&gt;in the context of an apple and cashew dessert dish I like&lt;/a&gt; (which reminds me, I should make it again), and I got the response from someone that it “wasn’t a recipe”. They’re probably just as angry about the above recipe, and in some sense they’re right. Certainly you won’t recreate the dish exactly based on the above explanation, but nor do I recreate the dish exactly each time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But independently of whether or not it’s consistently the same dish each time, the result is delicious, and very satisfying as a winter meal, and I end up eating far too much of it every time I make it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's interesting how easy it is to forget and lose the habit of recipes. I was making this extremely regularly, but utterly forgot about it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-04-05-21:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-04-30-11:56.html</id>
    <title>Notes towards a name</title>
    <updated>2022-04-30T11:56:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes towards a name&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-04-30&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/connerdelights/status/1519705466854539265"&gt;Andrew Conner&lt;/a&gt; asked on Twitter "What would you call this?" where "this" means "the thing that is like philosophy but not", and this lead to a discussion between me, him, and David Chapman in which we all expressed our frustration as to what it is we actually &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;.  More specifically, what do we call it?
None of us know.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hubristically, I replied, "This seems like a dumb problem for us to have. Maybe I'll fix it". So here I am, trying to fix it. These are some rough notes that I am writing because it is useful to write out my thoughts on the subject, and sharing because they may be interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What is it I actually do?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the best way I can explain what I do is this: You know how some days you find yourself thinking "Holy shit why does being human not come with a user manual?". I'm trying to write that user manual.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, a completely impossible task. Such a user manual would be unusably vast, and I am not qualified to write more than a tiny fraction of it. That's OK. I'm not trying to write more than a tiny fraction of it, and most people don't need more than a tiny fraction of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's perhaps more accurate to say that what I am trying to do is develop the general skill of writing the thing that you would get if you were to look up the section of the humanity user manual that you need right now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My basic question is "What is it like to be human and how can we be better at it?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;David Chapman has as a tagline "Better ways of thinking, feeling, and acting" and that definitely feels like part of what I do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"How to live" is maybe closer. It's a bit too close to the Aristotelean "How to have a good life" (which is not a frame I like).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps "How to think about living" is closer?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My tagline for my newsletter is "Overthinking everything", which is a bit tongue in cheek, but I do think captures something important.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps "Tools of thought for living"? Or "Tools for living".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"How to think about living in a way that helps you flourish"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have always liked "Human flourishing" as a turn of phrase. It's a little connected up to virtue ethics and the like, and I do tend to reject the eudaimonic frame of "happiness" as the end goal of life, partly because I don't think framing life as having a goal is helpful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is something fundamentally ethical about my project though. "How to live" is very much the classical point of ethics, although not of modern ethics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is in general a theme of what I do. It's &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; a lot of things, but as they were meant to be and good though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think that what distinguishes me from philosophy in general is that I'm more interested in the practical side of it. If you consider the think/feel/act split, I'm interested in all three but my goals are in decreasing order of priority:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Act&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is funny because I'm primarily working on the think layer, but that's because it's a very high leverage layer (especially for me). How you think has a huge amount of impact on what you do and how you feel about it, and I'm trying to use thinking to improve your experience of the world. It is a focus on right action rather than right thought, and in getting these all to line up in a way that you feel good about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is part of why I'm not sure I'm a fan of applying the "philosophy" label to what I do. I don't love wisdom, I just say that to get it into bed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It does tie back into the virtue ethics thing again, but I do like "phronesis" as a word - practical wisdom. And to a large degree this &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; what I work on. Practical wisdom for living.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What does David Chapman do?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly, beats me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1519788775337074695"&gt;I said on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; that part of my problem with coming up with a common name is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sometimes I feel like you and I are working on basically the same problem and sometimes I feel like you and I are working on completely unrelated projects, and I'm not sure I could come up with a coherent justification for either feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I like David and I value our conversations, but I really don't know that I know what his project is about, and I suspect he feels the same way about me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So let's start with how David and I differ (aside from in our last names).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think his &lt;a href="https://metarationality.com/"&gt;metarationality&lt;/a&gt; project is probably heavily overlapping with mine, in that we're both concerned with the problem of how people think in practical contexts and how to do that better, but I think of his main work (certainly it's his Twitter handle!) is Meaningness, and this is the one I can't really tell if it's at all similar to what I'm doing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you look at &lt;a href="https://meaningness.com/"&gt;meaningness.com&lt;/a&gt; his tagline is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Better ways of thinking, feeling, and acting—around problems of meaning and meaninglessness; self and society; ethics, purpose, and value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And we're kinda overlapping on all of this except... I don't feel like I'm particularly invested in the questions of meaning and purpose, which I think is rather his whole thing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is about meaningness. “Meaningness” is a word I invented, referring to the quality of being meaningful and/or meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word “meaning” has two quite different meanings in English. It can refer to the meaning of symbols, such as words and road signs. This book is not about that kind of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People also speak of “the meaning of life.” That is the sort of meaningness this book is about. So I apply “meaningness” only to the sorts of things one could describe as “deeply meaningful” or “pretty meaningless.” The book is about matters such as purpose, ethics, and selfhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meaningness is a quality, not a thing. I don’t think there is a definite meaning of life. Meaningness is always nebulous: indefinite, uncertain, ambiguous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And I must admit I don't find this very personally interesting. It's not &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; connected to my project, but I think if someone came to me talking about this as their core issue I would probably start by checking if they were depressed, or if their life sucked in concrete manners.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do basically buy &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/eggprophet/status/1470425201615773702"&gt;eggprophet's model&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what if ur complicated, high status problems like "meaning crisis" "culture war" "societies fall in epicureanism" are actually simple, low-status problems like "bored" "want community" "need blanket"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Bored" definitely feels closer to any problem I want to address than "lack of meaning" does.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear, I don't mean this as a dismissal of David's project. I love it when other people get deeply invested in things that I don't find very interesting, because then I can come in afterwards and extract the bits that I care about and wouldn't have figured out on my own. But this does suggest that David's meaningness project and my project are not necessarily that closely tied.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-04-30-11:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-25-09:47.html</id>
    <title>How to be lucky</title>
    <updated>2022-05-25T10:01:29+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How to be lucky&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-05-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to be doing some draft bankruptcy over the coming week or two,
where I delete things from my newsletter drafts and post salvageable bits
here on the notebook.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's some extracts from a piece called "How to be lucky" that I may or may
not eventually write, but certainly will want to start from scratch with 
a little bit of reused material rather than trying to ressurect this draft.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Luck, happenstance, and circumstance&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd like to distinguish three different things that are often called
luck, and I will only use "luck" to refer to one of them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first thing is what I'd like to call &lt;em&gt;happenstance&lt;/em&gt;. An event that
happens as a result of chance. You might win the lottery, you might be
late for a meeting, you might go a different route than usual and
discover something interesting... These are all chance events, they
might be good they might be bad, they might be neutral.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People will often refer to individual happenstance events as lucky or
unlucky, which is perfectly reasonable in normal usage but not how I
will be using the term. Winning the lottery is not, in the sense I will
be using it, the result of luck, it's just random chance. Could have
happened to anyone who played the lottery. If you exhibited a consistent
tendency to win the lottery I would call &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; luck, but not a single
win no matter how large, it's just a highly positive happenstance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Circumstance on the other hand is the conditions in which you find
yourself. This too is often referred to as luck. e.g. you're lucky to be
born into a rich family, you're lucky to have good friends, you're lucky
to be in a secure job, etc. I again think this is perfectly reasonable
usage, but it's not what I mean when I say "luck" here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I say luck, what I specifically mean is the aggregate effect of
happenstance in your life. Good luck is the tendency of chance events
to, on average, improve your life. Bad luck is the tendency of chance
events to, again on average, make your life worse.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Four types of circumstance&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's talk about circumstances and how they impact luck. Many of these
things will be out of your control (or only weakly under your control),
and I'll talk about things that are more under your control in a bit,
but I think it's important to be up front about the different fortune
landscapes people find themselves in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the easiest ways to be lucky is to have circumstances that enable
it. Here are some such circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first way is that you can be rich, either in money or other
resources. Luck is, ultimately, about being able to benefit from random
chance, and this involves playing a lot of numbers games. By far the
easiest way to be able to play numbers games is to have a lot of buffer
against risk. If a great opportunity comes your way and it costs £1000
but will probably earn you much more than that (in money or other
value), then there are roughly three options: You might not be able to
pay £1000 at all, in which case sucks to be you. £1000 might be
affordable but not an amount you can comfortably risk, in which case you
may or may not take the opportunity but you certainly can't take the
next such opportunity that comes along if this one falls through. Or you
can be well enough off that £1000 isn't a big deal to risk given the
high upside. Rich people are luckier than poor people because they have
the opportunity to take advantage of many sources of happenstances that
improve their life that are too risky if you're poor.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second way is that you can be extroverted, sociable, etc. Social
connections are one of the biggest and most accessible source of luck in
day to day life - you meet people who will transform your life, your
social circumstances, give you access to opportunities you'd otherwise
lack, etc. There's &lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0190272518812010"&gt;a whole paper about how the best way to be lucky is
to go to more
parties&lt;/a&gt;.
It's much easier to take advantage of this if you naturally want to
spend lots of time socialising, are good at it, and find it emotionally
rewarding rather than a source of anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The third way is that you can be
pretty (I tend to use "pretty" in a gender neutral sense. There are some very
pretty men out there. That being said, the way this manifests is definitely different with different genders).
This tends to raise the chances of success in a lot of circumstances - people will
seek you out more, give you more opportunities, you'll benefit from halo
effects, etc. Being pretty tends to both increase the number of
opportunities (because they seek you out) and increase the chances of
any of those opportunities that depend on the judgement of others from
working.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these are somewhat changeable but are at best hard to change,
and aren't necessarily where your bottleneck &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Luck as a skill&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, this doesn't mean you can learn to be supernaturally lucky. There's
no way you can, for example, improve your ability to play the lottery.
You will probably, on average, be luckier if you &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; play the
lottery.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It also doesn't mean that everyone's luck is purely determined by their
skill. There are roughly three components to luck, in decreasing order
of importance for most people:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privilege&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yes, chance is the &lt;em&gt;least&lt;/em&gt; important component of luck, I promise. It's
not that chance doesn't matter, it's that if chance matters too much you
are not actually being lucky.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason, in short, is that luck mostly occurs as the sum of many
chance events, and statistically the chance effects average out over
time. If you toss a coin 100 times, you've no ability to predict which
way any given coin toss will go, but you'll get heads about 50 times,
and you'll with overwhelming likelihood get heads between about 30 and
70 times.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Privilege on the other hand can matter a great deal. For example, people
who are unusually attractive or unusually intelligent will have a much
easier time being lucky (more on why later). It's also &lt;em&gt;vastly&lt;/em&gt; easier
to be lucky if you're wealthy or have other resources you can draw on.
If that's you, you can capitalise on it, and it's worth paying attention
to, but ultimately what matters more is how these affect your ability to
develop the skill of luck than the privilege itself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to the most important part: Skill. This is the most
important part both because it's the bit that matters the most, and also
because it's the bit that's most under your control.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;An informal mathematical glossary&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here I've deleted a lot of material that I covered better in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-29-09:43.html"&gt;Probably enough probability for you&lt;/a&gt; so go read that bit instead.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Luck 101&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Luck is a numbers game. Luck is the aggregate result of many small
events, each of which is unlikely to have any upside, but which on
average have a much greater upside than their cost. Let's call these
events &lt;em&gt;opportunities&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Getting luckier is a process involving two things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing the number of opportunities you take.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving the average effectiveness of opportunities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Privilege affects these differently. e.g. Being resource-rich tends to
make the first easy, being attractive tends to maximise the second, but
both are under your control to a large degree.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, note that this is somewhat non-uniform, in that the &lt;em&gt;types&lt;/em&gt; of
opportunities available to you matter a great deal. It's possible to
e.g. be very lucky in business but have no luck in dating (or vice
versa), due to being good at these in one context and bad in another.
This is particularly true for people who have never spent much time
strategizing about luck in general and have just, well, lucked into some
good habits in some specific contexts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Lottery luck&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Imagine a simple lottery, you pay £1, you have a one in 10 million
chance of winning £1 million. You play the lottery, and unsurprisingly
you don't win. Someone else plays the lottery, and they do. Are they
luckier than you?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this specific instance, they have certainly been luckier than you,
but in a generalisable sense they are not. What actually happened is
that millions of people played the lottery, so even though every
individual one was a sucker, one or two people got lucky. Those people
have what you might call lottery luck - it's a one off unrepeatable event,
and any strategy for improving your luck that relies on lottery luck is
a losing game.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can think of the basic practice of luck as being about trying
repeatedly, and seeking lottery luck is &lt;em&gt;actively harmful&lt;/em&gt; for this
because the more times you try the worse off you will be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What would have come next&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is the point at which the draft trails off, which is unfortunate as what comes next is all the interesting bits.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I was planning on covering next ties together:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The work of Richard Wiseman in his book "The Luck Factor" which I think is
  a very good book for getting better at an important but kinda boring type of
  luck.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brian Lui's notion of &lt;a href="https://brianlui.dog/2020/10/06/upside-decay/"&gt;Upside decay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lewis Hyde's book "Trickster Makes This World", which is about trickster myths and what they teach us about luck and creativity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The core idea being that the most interesting skill of luck is treating your engagement with the world as a creative process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a mild post mortem note, I think one thing this points to is that when writing a newsletter post I should &lt;em&gt;start by writing the interesting bits&lt;/em&gt;. Then I can backfill to give people an onramp to it if I think that's actually necessary. Write the newsletter more like the notebook, so that when I hit the point where I'm done and don't want to write any more I can just click send. Writing as &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-23-15:52.html"&gt;an anytime algorithm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-25-09:47.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-26-07:09.html</id>
    <title>Promethean work</title>
    <updated>2022-05-26T07:12:18+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Promethean work&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-05-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is another draft bankruptcy post. The following is the only
bit I had written from a post entitled "Stealing lifehacks from the gods":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do you ever think about how weird it would be to be in the myth of
Prometheus?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prometheus stumbles into camp, looking haggard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Prometheus, you have returned from Mount Olympus! What have you
brought back from your time among the gods?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Uh, well, I've brought back the secret of fire. Pretty sure that'll
be helpful. Very useful stuff, fire."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Tell us, oh great Prometheus! What powers must we invoke to summon
fire? What rituals must we perform?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Um, yes. Rituals. OK, so, you take some dry grass, and two sticks."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Grass... and sticks? Do we fashion these into an offering? Do we
carve runes into them?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"No, you see, what you do is, you rub the sticks together. After a
while they'll get real hot. Then you put the hot sticks on the grass
and it'll catch fire because dry things catch fire when they get hot."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"What the actual fuck, Prometheus."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Yeah, kicking myself for not thinking of it on my own TBH. Still,
it's a simple enough trick that at least the gods won't be super mad
at me for borrowing it, huh?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Please note that this both entirely misrepresents &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prometheus"&gt;the myth of
Prometheus&lt;/a&gt; and also &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l8C8qPoMZdo"&gt;how to
start a fire with sticks&lt;/a&gt;.
But in my defence it's funnier that way)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This actually &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1521187395319836676"&gt;got turned into a tweet&lt;/a&gt; way earlier,
and was probably more like a tweet worth of idea.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The core to this is that a lot of what I do is go into complicated specialised disciplines and try to take their most accessible ideas and make them broadly useful. This is Promethean work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1520007832556474368"&gt;related tweet&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I have seen far, it is because I have repeatedly wandered up to giants and asked "Gosh! How did you get so tall?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-26-07:09.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-27-14:08.html</id>
    <title>Leaving shiny things behind</title>
    <updated>2022-05-27T14:18:27+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Leaving shiny things behind&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-05-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something I've been thinking about recently is how useful it is to have names to describe crucial aspects of your problems.
Not that this is a new thought, but it's been on my mind.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result of this thought process, I realised I needed a name for a particular phenomenon: The way it is very hard for me to focus in the presence of my phone, which tends to grab my attention and lead to me checking Twitter without really meaning to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I propose the following name: The phone is a &lt;em&gt;shiny thing&lt;/em&gt;. Shiny things catch your eye with their glint, in a way that makes it hard to avoid looking at them. As long as they are in your field of awareness somehow, you have to put in active effort to not pay attention to them, because they have a natural gravity to them that distracts and captures your attention.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Shiny things aren't necessarily interesting or desirable.
Another example of a shiny thing is when the TV is on in a room, even with the sound off - even if you literally couldn't care less about what's on the TV, the fact that it is there with its attractive moving pictures tends to naturally draw your attention. Observe how much less engaged a conversation happening in a room with the TV on in the background is, even when you could in theory easily ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Shiny things aren't intrinsically bad - I like my phone, I like Twitter, I like watching TV - but they are bad to have around &lt;em&gt;when your purpose is not to engage with the shiny thing&lt;/em&gt;, because they entice and draw your attention. Even if you successfully avoid them, you expend energy on doing so that could be more productively used. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's possible that a sufficiently advanced set of mental skills could allow one to be immune to shiny things. It's not unlike &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/first-hard-choice"&gt;The first hard choice&lt;/a&gt;, where you would like to be able to listen to the sirens' song without being drawn onto the rocks.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But unlike the sirens, there is no virtue to being in the presence of a shiny thing that you don't currently want to use. It's just a pure cost. They can be there when you actively choose to use them, but they should be put away when you do not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lately I've been going on my stupid little walks for my stupid mental and physical health without my phone, and it has greatly improved the experience. Sometimes I bring a book, sometimes I bring a dictaphone, but neither of these are shiny in the way that my phone is, and so they do not distract me from doing whatever it is I choose to do in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-27-14:08.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-28-08:54.html</id>
    <title>The costs of being understood</title>
    <updated>2022-05-28T09:57:48+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The costs of being understood&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-05-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's another abandoned draft, which is about the costs that being illegible
impose on your interactions with the world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Many to one interactions&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me start with some experiences of mine that you may or may not share
that I think are usefully illustrative of a broader problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had a tweet, or blog post, or something similar become
unexpectedly popular? The &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/people-dont-work-as-much-as-you-think"&gt;People don\'t work as much as you
think&lt;/a&gt;
piece was this for me recently. To a much lesser degree, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1493181712427274241"&gt;this recent
tweet about many versions of a thing being evidence that none of them
are good&lt;/a&gt; is
another one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What happens is this: You get a lot of people responding in obvious
ways. Maybe they've misunderstood you. Maybe they're picking up on
something you missed, or didn't think was worth mentioning. Maybe they
disagree with you on ideological grounds. There are plenty of reasons to
make an obvious response.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At first, you can respond reasonably enough to these - pointing out
their misunderstandings, acknowledging that yes thank you for pointing
out that edge case but you were already aware of it and don't think it's
a problem, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the fifth time someone has made the same point at you, it's much
harder to stay polite, and by the hundredth message it doesn't really
matter if the observation is novel you just want these people to shut up
and leave you alone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can try getting cranky at them, and indeed it will probably be
incredibly hard work not to get cranky at them, but fundamentally it
doesn't work because the only reason crankiness can be a useful strategy
is when other people notice it &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; you have to get cranky at them
and modify their behaviour accordingly, and if the people doing this
were actually paying attention to others' behaviour they wouldn't be
repeating the same points you've already heard a dozen time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an example of an &lt;em&gt;asymmetric cost&lt;/em&gt; - although the cost of the
interaction is about the same for you and the other party, when you are
interacting with many people, the cost of their behaviour on you is
effectively much larger than any cost you can impose on them, because
they only have to pay it once, while you have to pay it once for each of
them. The cost of the interaction is effectively multiplied by the
number of people you have to have it with, which for you is large and
for them is you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not just a Twitter thing. Another (comparatively trivial)
example of this is that I have to explain my name to people over and
over again, and it gets tiresome. Yes that's a capital I, not a lower
case l. No, it's pronounced Mack-ee-ver, not Mack-ay-ver. Yes, it's
Scottish, but I'm not. No, it's not spelled or pronounced like the guy
with the paperclips. Yes that joke you've just made about it is
extremely witty and I definitely haven't heard if five hundred times
before. Ha ha.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not a big deal, and I generally remain polite throughout these
conversations, but there is definitely an internal sigh of resignation
as I think "Oh, we're having this conversation again are we?" each time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem with these sorts of asymmetric costs is that, like the
Twitter thing, they're almost by definition invisible to those who
impose them on you, because if they were there during That Conversation,
even if it was initiated with someone else, they wouldn't have to have
it again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Many to few interactions&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This comes up in more serious conversations too. Vegetarians are often
tired of having a conversation justifying their vegetarianism, people
are often tired of having a conversation justifying their religion or
lack thereof. Coming out as queer, poly, trans, etc. is something you
end up doing over and over again, and for most people it's tiring and
scary every time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The difference with these conversations however is that you're not the
only one having them and, as a result, chances may be pretty good that
someone you encounter outside of your group has already encountered one
of you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you're in a population with a 50/50 split between two groups (e.g.
gender), there is no asymmetry in the obvious conversations you have -
there is one man for every woman, more or less, so the number of obvious
day to day conversations you have is about equal. This falls apart in a
whole number of cases - e.g. in environments with large gender skews (In
either direction! There are large asymmetric costs in being e.g. a dad
in parental spaces dominated by mums, as well as e.g. being a woman in
software), and in situations in which the size of your demographic is in
some sense "artificially lowered" because of visibility (e.g. you'll get
to have all sorts of obvious conversations with men if you're a woman
whose tweet goes unexpectedly popular). But, by default, regardless of
how bad communication tends to be between the two groups there tends not
to be asymmetry of the sort that I'm talking about because the numbers
are broadly equal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, as the groups get smaller the asymmetry grows sharply. If
your group is x% of the conversation, then there are (100 - x) / x
people not in your group for every member who is. For example if you're
20% of the population, there are four of them for every one of you, if
you're 1% of the population there are 99 of them for every one of you,
etc. This means that, all else being equal, the smaller your group is,
the higher the asymmetric costs you experience as a member of it
interacting with people outside it are.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, all else is rarely equal. I am, for example, a member of the
group of people with weird names. We're a relatively small group, but
also the cost per interaction is relatively
low, (Once you reach adulthood anyway. Children are &lt;em&gt;brutal&lt;/em&gt; about this),
so even though the costs imposed are highly asymmetric, the total costs are still not that bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Necessary conversations&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of the time this problem can be solved by just ignoring it. I
don't have to correct people on my name, you don't have to tell people
about your vegetarianism, or your religion, or any other thing that
makes you unusual, unless it's directly relevant to the interaction.
This often brings down the rate enough to be manageable even if the cost
per interaction is relatively high.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This works great right up until the point where you need to do it. For
example, if you're vegetarian, you will often need to explain this to
people in order to be able to make sure you can eat something at a
location. If you have disabilities (visible or otherwise) you may need
to explain them in order to get accommodations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you need to be understood not for your sake, but because it's
the only way to get other people off your back. For example I think
about &lt;a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/why-is-it-hard-to-acknowledge-preferences?r=514ov"&gt;this Astral Codex Ten post about respecting
preferences&lt;/a&gt;
a lot:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently stayed at a B&amp;amp;B owned by a nice elderly couple. Very, very
nice. The moment I stepped in the door, they asked how my flight was,
where I was from, what I did, how I\'d enjoyed my three minutes of
visiting their city so far, what kind of food I liked, what my
favorite color was, et cetera. I played along - no point in offending
people - but I warned that my friend, who would be arriving a little
later, was much more introverted, and would appreciate being
efficiently directed to her room without the welcome committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little later, my friend arrived. From my room, I could hear them
start welcoming her, ask her how her flight had been, start trying to
get to know her - until I ran out and rescued her, for which she
reports gratitude. For the rest of our stay, they continued to talk
both of our ears off, with my friend growing increasingly annoyed and
uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent the trip back dissecting what had gone wrong. Neither of us
believed the proprietors didn\'t care about her feelings: they were so
very, very nice. They couldn\'t have forgotten my warning; my friend
arrived less than an hour after I did. We concluded that they were
just inexplicably bad at some sort of mental gear-shifting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The worst part was, I knew this would happen. When I told them to
please respect my friend\'s introversion, there was a voice in my head
quietly adding \"...even though you obviously won\'t and I have no
idea why I am even making this request\".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think all that's going on here is a failure of understanding,
but I do think it starts with a failure of understanding. People hear
preferences and round them out to someone just making a fuss, because
they can't internalise what an extremely big deal that preference is for
the other person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think, to some degree, this is reasonable - people are constantly
imposing their preferences on us, and it's impossible to respect all of
them, so people tend to disregard a lot of things as unimportant, or as
something they're not obliged to respect. Just because you have a
preference to be referred to as Your Majesty and tithed 10% of my wealth
annually, doesn't mean that I have to do that. In order for me to
respect that preference you must either force or convince me to do so.
Generally we frown upon the "force" option unless you're &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; an
imperial power, so you should try to convince me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This happens with more reasonable preferences too - to continue the
vegetarianism example, there's a lot of work that goes in to persuading
people to respect your dietary preferences. Virtually everyone who has
such preferences have stories of them being argued with or ignored
(often covertly! Many people think it's perfectly reasonable to e.g.
sneak butter into something that they serve to someone who has said they
can't eat dairy. This is a really bad idea, but distressingly common).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can argue that people shouldn't need to understand your preferences
in order to respect them and you'd be, more or less, right, but the fact
of the matter is regardless of whether they should do that people mostly
do, and I'd argue that some degree of this is pretty much inevitable.
It's really hard to respect preferences you don't understand - it goes
against how memory works, you reliably fuck details up, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Certainly people should be a lot better at this than they currently are,
but expecting people to be maximally good at meeting preferences without
understanding them very much goes against how humans work, and besides
which can only possibly work at a very shallow level (though the shallow
level is still important for interactions with strangers).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;When you are hard to understand&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So you want to respect people's dietary constraints and preferences?
Thanks, that's great. I don't eat dairy, wheat (really most cereals in
its family are bad. "gluten free" isn't quite right but to a first
approximation is probably fine), brassicas, or lamb. Some onions are
fine if they're cooked but too many is likely to be a problem. Lentil
heavy dishes are probably a bad idea, but things that use lentil flour
seem to be mostly fine. Also I prefer not to eat fish for ethical
reasons, but don't worry about that as a one off.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You've probably almost immediately forgotten the details of that
paragraph. As well you should. Why would you memorise the details of my
food preferences if you're not cooking extremely regularly for me?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My experience is that almost nobody can keep track of my dietary
preferences, even before you get to the complicated ones. I normally
don't even mention anything past "No wheat, no dairy, no brassicas, and
you're probably fine but maybe check in with me if you're unsure?", and
this is usually still at least one too many details to keep track of
(people never remember the brassicas one, but unfortunately it's very
important).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is actually completely reasonable, because there are two different
asymmetric costs that are going on here: The first is the one to me, the
annoying conversation around dietary preferences that I have to have
with everyone who cooks for me. The second is the one that people have
when they cook for others, trying to keep track of everyone's food
preferences. Sometimes one cost dominates, sometimes the other, but
either way it's really quite a lot of work to keep track of everything
that everyone can and can't eat (I think I'm unusually good at this, and it's a lot of work to be good at
it and also I still get things wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem with my particular set of food constraints is that there is
no sensible organising principle to them. It's just a list of
empirically derived things that trigger my digestive system to freak
out. If there were a simple term that allowed people to check whether
something was suitable for me (e.g. gluten-free and dairy-free are both
examples of that, and people can usually stretch themselves to
remembering two terms) and that they could remember as being normal
problems for people to have, they would probably mostly
remember.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Though people absolutely can and do get these wrong. If you're not used
to doing it it's really hard to remember to check the ingredients list
and see if some asshole has snuck wheat into somewhere where wheat
really doesn't need to go.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even with more reasonable food constraints, you end up with a problem
that asymmetric costs are not always additive. It's much harder to cook
for someone who is both dairy-free and gluten-free than it is to cook
for someone who is one but not both. (It's also much harder to cook for
two people where one is dairy-free and one is gluten-free at the same
time, for much the same reason). It's not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; as hard to cook for
them if you don't have to do it at the same time (e.g. one guest one
night, one guest another), but it is easier to cook for two separate
gluten-free or two separate dairy-free guests than it is to cook for one
gluten-free and one dairy-free guest, because you learn skills and
habits with each - it's not just a matter of not doing the thing after
all, it's a matter of learning how to achieve your goal (producing a
delicious meal) while not achieving the thing, and that takes actual
effort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's easy to discount this effort, because you have curse of knowledge
around your own experience - it's hard to remember how hard it is to
understand something once you already understand it - but it is a real
effort that people have to expend to understand you. And it's not just
about diet, it's about everything else - things that annoy you, your
preferences for social interaction, triggers, pronouns, etc. All things
that it's completely reasonable to want other people to keep track of,
but also all things that contribute to the cognitive load of what others
have to keep track about us.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The web of legibility&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this point the post basically turns into an attempt to integrate the
following two previous posts of mine here on the notebook:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-02-09:31.html"&gt;Legibility as a relationship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-23-09:37.html"&gt;Legibility privileges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is another one where I did all the framing work and ran out of energy by the point I got to the meat of the post.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-28-08:54.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-29-05:50.html</id>
    <title>What every programming tutorial gets wrong</title>
    <updated>2022-05-29T05:59:24+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;What every programming tutorial gets wrong&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-05-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another piece of draft bankruptcy. This is my attempt to explain a common
failure mode of programming tutorials. I got quite far, but eventually
abandoned it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Scene setting&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A while ago I was helping teach a coding workshop to a bunch of people
who had never coded before, and we were working through the written
materials which were very "Do this, then do that". Copy this code and
you should see this happen, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point a student asked me "OK, but what is actually going on
here? What does any of this mean? I can follow the steps, but I have no
idea what is going on."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was an incredibly reasonable question and I\'m glad she asked it of
me, and that I could answer it, because I can\'t imagine that she would
have come away with any knowledge of programming without it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't remember the specific thing we were talking about, but I think
the example was something like:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"login"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"Bob"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"login"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;"Bob"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"some other key"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gt"&gt;Traceback (most recent call last):&lt;/span&gt;
  File &lt;span class="nb"&gt;"&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;"&lt;/span&gt;, line &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;, in &lt;span class="n"&gt;&amp;lt;module&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gr"&gt;KeyError&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class="n"&gt;'some other key'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is entirely clear if you're a programmer (especially if you're a
Python programmer, but it's sufficiently universal that probably most
programmers will have a pretty good idea of what's going on), but if
you've never programmed before it's just so much noise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In response to this question I would have said something as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The program you're using here is called the REPL(Read-Evaluate-Print-Loop,
but don't worry about that. It's pronounced
repple, like ripple with an eh). You're entering commands into it by writing statements in a
programming language called Python.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The interpreter keeps track of a number of "objects", which are a chunk
of data along with a particular set of commands that can you can use to
change that data, ask questions about it, etc. There are also commands
that let you interact with the computer more broadly (e.g. reading and
writing files) but we won't worry about them just yet in this tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here what we're doing is creating an object, giving it the name &lt;em&gt;user&lt;/em&gt;
that we can refer to it by, and issuing some commands and seeing what
happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specifically, we are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating an object of a specific type called a &lt;em&gt;dictionary&lt;/em&gt; and
    referring to it by the name &lt;em&gt;user&lt;/em&gt;. The curly brackets &lt;code&gt;{}&lt;/code&gt; create a
    new dictionary, and "&lt;code&gt;user =&lt;/code&gt;" is where we declare that we will
    refer to it as &lt;em&gt;user&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dictionary is an object whose job is to keep track of a table of
    information. It maps &lt;em&gt;keys&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;values&lt;/em&gt;, which are just arbitrary
    things you can put into it, so that if you tell it to associate a
    value with particular key, and then later ask for the value
    associated with that key, you get the same thing back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telling the dictionary we have just created (referred to by its
    name, &lt;em&gt;user&lt;/em&gt;) that it should associate the value "Bob" with the key
    "login". "Bob" and "login" are objects of a type called &lt;em&gt;string&lt;/em&gt;,
    which represents a piece of text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking up the key "login" and getting the expected value "Bob"
    back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking up the key "some other key" and getting an error that tells
    us that the dictionary has not yet been told to associate any values
    with that key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't a perfect answer, because I just made it up on the spot and
haven't tested it against students to see what questions they ask, but
it's probably pretty good. It certainly gives them more of a hook to
play around with dictionaries in the interpreter and see what happens,
and it gives them better questions to ask than "Help I don't understand
anything about what's going on".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Theory, examples, and ability&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to be using "theory", "examples", and "ability", in slightly
specific ways (which are possibly slightly idiosyncratic to me, although
I think compatible with normal use) in this issue, so I'll try to
explain what I mean by them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An example is just any concrete version of the thing being taught. For
example, "do these steps in the REPL" above is an example. Showing
someone a program is an example. Showing someone a mathematical proof is
an example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Theory" is the knowledge that you need to answer questions like "What's
going on here?" and explain the behaviour of a particular example. For
example, in the above, you need some sort of theory to answer the
question "Why did typing &lt;code&gt;user["login"]&lt;/code&gt; show &lt;code&gt;"Bob"&lt;/code&gt; but typing
&lt;code&gt;user["some other key"]&lt;/code&gt; showed an error message?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Ability" is the set of things the student can now do themselves. The
goal of teaching is to help the student expand their abilities. People
don't generally expand their abilities directly as the result of
teaching - you can only learn to do things by doing things - but
teaching points them in the right direction by giving them better ideas
of things to try. They still learn by trial and error, but teaching can
give them better things to try and help them understand their errors.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The goal of the above tutorial was to help them develop the ability to
write simple Python programs involving dictionaries, and to some degree
it succeeded. After going through this tutorial the student knows how to
launch the Python REPL, and has at least one example of something
reasonable to experiment with. Given a little bit of time to sit and
play with the REPL they might come up with a pretty reasonable theory
for explaining its behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why do they need to develop that theory? Because theory gives them the
ability to &lt;em&gt;generalise&lt;/em&gt;. If you have a theory that can explain why a
given action succeeded or failed, you now believe that any action that
matches that same explanation will also work or fail. This lets you try
out other things and see whether they confirm or deny your theory, which
is typically a much more productive model of trial and error than one
can manage without a theory of what's going on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Examples are vitally important&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I should be clear: It is very good that the tutorial we were doing was
dumping people in the REPL and getting them to play around with it. This
is not my complaint, it's the correct thing to do. My complaint is that
the tutorial did not then contain anything like my answer above.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of my pet peeves that has been coming out in places on the notebook
blog recently is that I hate people who introduce theory without
supporting examples in which to understand it. See e.g. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-02-09:29.html"&gt;People are bad
at defining
things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular it's often worth having examples &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; (this isn't
always possible), because then you can refer to concrete features of
them while introducing the theory. You saw a bit of that in how I
explained what was going on in the programming tutorial: I started with
an example, and then I highlighted specific features of it to ground the
theory (We're creating a thing called an objec&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The examples are particularly important. In order to understand a
theory, you need to be able to see how it applies to real concrete
things. Abstracting from concrete instances is literally the point of
theory, so without seeing how it relates to the things it abstracts
theory is just so many words.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that, examples are often key to developing abilities. People
do not, generally speaking, reason from first principles from a theory.
If you read the literature on naturalised decision
making, what people
tend to do is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recognition_primed_decision"&gt;recognition-primed decision
making&lt;/a&gt;. They
look at what's in front of them, they reason by analogy, thinking "Oh,
this looks like that thing I saw before, let me see what happens if I do
the same thing that I did there...". Having a rich and varied library of
examples is vitally important for this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I'd recommend Cedric Chin's &lt;a href="https://commoncog.com/blog/a-framework-for-putting-mental-models-to-practice/"&gt;A Framework for Putting Mental Models into
Practice&lt;/a&gt;,
but it's also worth reading Gary Klein's "Sources of Power" and maybe
some of his other work.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Theory helps you remember examples&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's look at our example again:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; user = {}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; user["login"] = "Bob"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; user["login"]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;"Bob"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; user["some other key"]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;Traceback (most recent call last):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;   File "&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;", line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c"&gt;KeyError: 'some other key'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do you think you could recreate this example from memory? I certainly
could, and I think most programmers could with only a little bit of
thought. It possibly wouldn't be character by character perfect, but you
could certainly get the right general idea.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now consider the following highly readable example. Do you think you
could recreate &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; from memory?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"T{ o Bm&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"T{sn)gK[ena o n:g}n&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"T{sn)gK[ena&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;g&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"T{sn"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;gyT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;g&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;](&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tTuna&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ilT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ilt&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;kyg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"] {TlTe] li)) )i"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class="p"&gt;,[)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;T&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;nE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"]h[e&amp;lt;n= )[eT b= [e Eyghd)T&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;FTuc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;g&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"gyT g](T{ tTur&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you haven't figured out the trick, this is the same example as above,
I've just jumbled all the letters through a mapping that replaces them
(e.g. &amp;gt; gets replaced with \&amp;lt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do you think you could recreate this example from memory? I sure
couldn't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In some sense this contains exactly the same information as the
original, but because you're unable to easily turn it into a sensible
representation, it's much harder to remember and thus much harder to
understand. As well as the Python specific bits you also rely on e.g.
brackets matching, quotes matching, familiar understanding of the
meaning of the = symbol, the ability to clearly distinguish which bits
are identifiers because they're contained in quotes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When we know what's going on, we can describe the example as the
following sequence of steps:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a dictionary called user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insert the value "Bob" into "user" with the key "login"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look up the key "login" in "user" and get the result&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look up the key "some other key" in "user" and see an error from
    looking up a missing key&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;em&gt;high level representation&lt;/em&gt; of what's going on. It describes
the steps we are taking, not the specific details that we know. This is
easy to remember, because it's a set of comprehensible steps.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, we're not expecting students to actually memorise specific
examples, but ability to memorise is a pretty good proxy for how well
the example fits in their head - if you can't easily remember what
should be a fairly simple example, that's a sign that there's too much
going for you to really figure it out and you're trying to learn too
much at once.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of translation into a high level representation is what theory
does for you, and lets you organise your mental library of examples.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Theory helps you generalise&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as helping you remember examples you've seen before, theory lets
you &lt;em&gt;adapt&lt;/em&gt; those previous examples to your needs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This high level representation does a number of important things for us:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It allows us to understand the meaning of the thing we are writing
    in terms of what we are trying to do rather than the literal
    characters on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes it easier to remember because we can remember "Create a
    dictionary called user" separately from the literal syntax for
    creating a dictionary. We still have to remember both, but the
    latter is a fact we can more easily look up and will use often
    enough to remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It lets us make predictions for what we would see if we changed the
    example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Doing (the right) things is the most important&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This particularly shows up in the trial and error process of learning.
While you are still floundering around trying to figure things out, good
specific examples are especially important because you will lean hard
on emulating examples, so having good examples to emulate is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is where I stalled. I'm not quite sure why. I think partly the
post was getting too long, and I didn't know how to continue, or
I ran out of energy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's a known problem that I'm very bad at revisiting things once
I've stopped writing them, and as a result I tend to fail to
finish longer pieces. I would like to work on that but have not
yet managed.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-29-05:50.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
