<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-02-26T16:07:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-17-09:56.html</id>
    <title>Coevolution and the bad take machine</title>
    <updated>2020-02-17T10:23:48+00:00</updated>
    <content>

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Coevolution and the bad take machine&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may come as a surprise to you, but there are some people on Twitter whose tweets are &lt;em&gt;really bad&lt;/em&gt;.
I don't just mean that they're not very good, I mean that their tweets are so bad that it feels like they sat down and twirled a metaphorical moustache and went "I wonder how I can make the most people mad today?".
I have three particular examples in mind, but I'm sure you can come up with hundreds more.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why are they like this?
Two reasons, basically:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They want to be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We've trained them to be good at it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first I feel should be obvious: If this level of negative response doesn't deter them,
it's clear that they must be getting something out of it. Either they enjoy the negative reaction (annoying people is funny), they feel like they're "sparking important debate", or some other reason.
At the very least if they found the reactions unpleasant they would have learned to stop doing this.
It's mostly smart people doing it after all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For the second... lets talk about evolution.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Life makes more sense when you view a lot of the world as systems of replicating patterns:
Patterns mutate, successful patterns get copied, unsuccessful patterns die off,
and the shape of the world is patterned after what worked,
for a value of worked that means nothing more than "was able to replicate itself".
We tend to talk about these patterns as "replicators", as if they were concrete things that reproduced themselves,
and I will use that terminology, but I find thinking of them in terms of patterns is more helpful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Genes are the classic replicator, but there are many others.
Memes in the Dawkins sense (Dawkins-memes) are another, as are memes in the modern sense (cat-memes).
Cat-memes are both driven by and drive Dawkins-memes, which is an important example of coevolution:
We can look at cat-memes as replicators in their own right (cat-memes are copied and modified and selected for),
but their replication will make much more sense when we consider the Dawkins-memes.
The replication has a significant loop where Cat-memes replicate partly by generating Dawkins-memes which replicate and generate more cat-memes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an oversimplified view of the process that ignores many important details and other loops,
but I think it is still an illuminating one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These coevolutionary processes are common. Culture and genes are another one:
e.g. consider lactose tolerance. Lactose tolerance is widespread in the west,
because of the coevolution of dairy farming techniques (culture) and genetics (the ability to consume milk as an adult without getting very ill).
Each replicator drives the other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another replicator is &lt;em&gt;behaviour&lt;/em&gt;.
We typically model our behaviour on past behaviours of ours (new behaviours can of course be introduced, but most behaviour is derived from past behaviour).
When a behaviour goes well, we do it more, when it goes badly, we do it less. This is classic &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operant_conditioning"&gt;operant conditioning&lt;/a&gt;, the thing with the salivating dogs, viewed as an evolutionary process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another thing that counts as a replicator is "things people are talking about on Twitter".
People talk about stuff, so others engage with it, or find out what's going on and talk about it too, etc.
So tweets are a replicator.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So when you have a bad take machine, you get the following processes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They make a bad take.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People are outraged and talk about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bad take machine likes it and does more of that behaviour in future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If, on the other hand, they make a take and nobody cares, they do not get reward and the behaviour is selected against.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The behaviours drove the spread of the outrage replicator, and the outrage replicator provides the selection mechanism for the behaviours.
Thus, via the spread of our outrage on Twitter, we have operant conditioned the bad take machine into producing worse takes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which is to say, it's bad on purpose to make you replicate it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-17-09:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-18-12:24.html</id>
    <title>Extracts from "How to talk about books you haven't read"</title>
    <updated>2020-02-18T13:07:20+00:00</updated>
    <content>

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Extracts from "How to talk about books you haven't read"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-18&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm a big fan of Pierre Bayard's "How to talk about books you haven't read".
I've even read it twice (insert witty joke about title here).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it is written exactly like you would expect nonfiction written by someone who specialises in literature to be written:
Badly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't entirely fair. The quality of the writing is excellent. The problem with it is written to tell a story,
but in fact it is a book that is trying to teach you something.
This makes it a pleasure to read, but a pain to actually use because every time you go back to it you need to hunt through it to find the bits you want because there is no goddamn index and the crucial terms are introduced embedded halfway through a story.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I've hunted down these terms enough times that I thought I'd just write them down.
So I thought I'd write a note about the three types of representations of a book that Bayard talks about.
Page numbers all refer to my copy, so yours might not be the same, sorry.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Three types of library&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Collective Library (p. 12)&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most statements about a book are not about the book itself, despite appearances, but about the larger set of books on which our culture depends at that moment. It is that set, which I shall henceforth refer to as the collective library, that truly matters, since it is our mastery of this collective library that is at stake in all discussions about books. But this mastery is a command of relations, not of any book in isolation, and it easily accommodates ignorance of a large part of the whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Inner Library (p. 73)&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might use the term inner library to characterize that set of books—a subset of the collective library—around which every personality is constructed, and which then shapes each person’s individual relationship to books and to other people. Specific titles figure in these private libraries, but, like Montaigne’s, they are primarily composed of fragments of forgotten and imaginary books through which we apprehend the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Virtual Library (p. 125)&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third type of library that I am introducing here, the virtual library, is the realm in which books are discussed, in either written or oral form, with other people. It is a mobile sector of every culture’s collective library and is located at the point of intersection of the various inner libraries of each participant in the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Three types of book&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Screen books (p. 44)&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freud uses the term screen memory to designate false or insignificant childhood memories whose function is to conceal others less acceptable to the conscious mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...the books we talk about are only glancingly related to "real" books - indeed what else would we expect? - and are often no more than screen books. Or, if you prefer, what we talk about is not the books themselves, but substitute objects we create for the occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Inner books (p. 83)&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I propose the term &lt;em&gt;inner book&lt;/em&gt; to designate the set of mythic representations, be they collective or individual, that come between the reader and any new piece of writing, shaping his reading without realizing it. Largely unconscious, this imaginary book acts as a filter and determines the reception of new texts by selecting which of its elements will be retained and how they will be interpreted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second of three "books" studied in this essay, the &lt;em&gt;inner&lt;/em&gt; book influences all the transformations to which we subject books, turning htem into &lt;em&gt;screen books&lt;/em&gt;. The term &lt;em&gt;inner book&lt;/em&gt; appears in Proust with a meaning close to the one I am giving it: "As for the inner book of unknown symbols (symbols carved in relief they might have been, which my attention, as it explored my unconscious, groped for and stumbled against and followed the contorus of, like a diver exploring the ocean-bed), if I tried to read them, no one could help me with any rules, for to read them was an act of creation in which no one can do our work for us or even collaborate with us [...] This book, more laborious to decipher than any other, is also the only one which has been dictated to us by reality, the only one of which the 'impression' has been printed in us by reality itself"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Phantom books (p. 160)&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third type of book I am introducing here, the &lt;em&gt;phantom book&lt;/em&gt;, is that mobile and ungraspable object that we will call into being, in writing or in speech, when we talk about a book. It is located at the point where readers' various &lt;em&gt;screen books&lt;/em&gt; meet - screen books that reads have constructed based on their &lt;em&gt;inner books&lt;/em&gt;. The phantom book belongs to the virtual library of our exchanges, as the screen book belongs to the collective library and the inner book belongs to the inner library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Thoughts on the book overall&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I really like this book but am also very frustrated by it.
I might have to read it a third time to get it out of my head,
at which point I will attempt to turn it into some essays.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The source of my frustration is that it is a very good book,
and it achieves its purpose in a way that a more technical essay of its nature would not have I feel,
but I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; wish that technical essay also existed, and I don't want to have to be the one to write it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-18-12:24.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-19-10:37.html</id>
    <title>Books by writers are the worst</title>
    <updated>2020-02-19T11:46:02+00:00</updated>
    <content>

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Books by writers are the worst&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the big problems with being good at writing is that it makes you think that your writing is good,
but this is unfortunately not the case.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a problem I run into particularly with people who have "writer" as part of their identity.
Often they are very good at writing, so are entirely justified in this identity claim, which is why they write really badly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic problem is that &lt;em&gt;writing is communication&lt;/em&gt;, and at some point what you're bottlenecked on in the quality of your writing is not actually the quality of your writing, but the quality of your communication, and because people think "I'm a writer so all I need to do is write well and the writing is good" they overfocus on things that are no longer the rate limiting factor.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular, the two skills that I often see writers &lt;em&gt;utterly&lt;/em&gt; failing at are clarity of explanation and organisation of information.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some sins I regularly see nonfiction books by writers fall into:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being very sloppy about how they introduce terms. The terms are casually introduced in the middle of a paragraph, as if the reader should obviously understand what they mean, without examples or any real clear delineation of how they are supposed to be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not organising their book for nonlinear reading. In particular, not organising their book for rereading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A particularly egregious sin in (2) is bad indexing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You saw some of this whinging in the post about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-18-12:24.html"&gt;How to talk about books you haven't read&lt;/a&gt;.
I think in general this is a common problem: Writers experienced in fiction really don't have the skillset for writing nonfiction by default (and vice versa!). Frequently they are great essayists anyway, because the essay is a format much more forgiving of these sins, but they've concluded that all book writing is the same and not bothered to confront how it's different.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-19-10:37.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html</id>
    <title>Emotional reactions as legacy code</title>
    <updated>2020-02-20T09:54:00+00:00</updated>
    <content>

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1214492384089792513"&gt;One of my most popular tweets ever&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Minds are basically computers" is wrong if you think of computers as abstract turing machines but spot on if you think of computers as a horrible assemblage of kludges bridging incompatible legacy code which only work because critical bugs are masking other critical bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think a lot of our emotional reactions are like this:
They are a lifetime of legacy that we have learned and implemented,
and they mostly fit together well enough to work,
but they are kludgy and unwieldy and often in need of some serious refactoring.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Individual_psychology"&gt;Adlerian psychology&lt;/a&gt; maintains a distinction between &lt;em&gt;aetiology&lt;/em&gt; (the study of the causes of things) and &lt;em&gt;teleology&lt;/em&gt; (the study of the purposes of things),
and maintains that in order to change you should ask not "where does this behaviour come from?" (to which the classic psychotherapy answer is "trauma") but instead "what purpose does this behaviour serve?".
e.g. someone might experience social anxiety in order to prevent them from talking to people, which serves as a protective mechanism against being hurt by those people.
The aetiology might be that they learned they would be hurt by people as a child, but the teleology is the protective mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Adlerian psychology seems to go as far as to say that trauma does not exist, which I think is a bit much,
but a useful synthesis of the two ideas of aetiology and teleology is this:
An emotional reaction serves a purpose, but that purpose is not necessarily still relevant.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you have an emotional reaction in a situation, you can ask what purpose it serves,
but the real question is &lt;em&gt;where did I learn this and what purpose did it serve there&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, many reactions were learned in childhood, where you were surrounded by very different people and had a very different power dynamic. You might have had abusive parents, you might have been bullied at school,
and in both of those circumstances you were trapped unable to leave.
The protective emotional reactions that you learned there are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different from the ones that you need as an adult with more control over your own life and who you associate with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looking at this prior context allows you to examine the emotional reaction critically and decide whether and how to change it.
If &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/i9xyZBS3qzA8nFXNQ/book-summary-unlocking-the-emotional-brain"&gt;coherence therapy&lt;/a&gt; is to be believed,
this can best be done when the emotion is active.
When it is active, you can relearn a new and better version of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A principle I've been trying to adopt recently is to notice emotional reactions as they occur and, rather than dismissing them or leaning into them,
instead ask "Where does this come from?" and try to understand it and think about whether it's needed in this scenario.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Learning &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/39TBwRv"&gt;Focusing&lt;/a&gt; was a big help for this,
and understanding how to recognise triggers was a good next step for knowing when to deploy it (essentially: If you have a physical reaction to an emotional event, that's a trigger. They don't have to be big scary flashbacky things, those are just the extreme end).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A thing my friend Alex suggested which I've been partly implementing off the back of this is to apply &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/37HpZ6h"&gt;Marie Kondo&lt;/a&gt; style decluttering to these reactions:
Thank them for their service, tell them they have done their job in protecting you but that they are no longer needed,
and let them go.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-21-10:04.html</id>
    <title>Constraints on skill growth</title>
    <updated>2020-02-21T10:53:19+00:00</updated>
    <content>

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Constraints on skill growth&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-21&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Previously:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/05/how-to-do-hard-things/"&gt;How to do hard things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2014/07/programming-and-mathematics/"&gt;Why mathematics makes you better at programming (and so does everything else)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Have you noticed how when you first start learning a skill, you rapidly get better at it?
Then, after a while of that rapid growth, you start to plateau. You've seemingly picked all the low hanging fruit and are no longer improving.
Why is that?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well there probably isn't any one reason, and some of it is legitimately the low hanging fruit problem - some ways of getting better at a skill are easier than others, and once you've done all of those things you're left with the hard ones - but I'd like to suggest one reason that I think is underappreciated.
It's because you've hit a &lt;em&gt;constraint&lt;/em&gt;, and the skill you are practicing does not give you a good feedback loop for improving on that constraint.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The theory of constraints is a management philosophy thing.
It is the very obvious common sense idea (which is to say that it's an idea that in the moment people find completely nonobvious and never think of): If something isn't where the bottleneck is, it doesn't matter how much better you make it.
e.g.~it doesn't matter if you improve your widget production if the distribution system can't keep up with the new number of widgets.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is true for skills too and ties in to a problem I talked about in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-19-10:37.html"&gt;Books by writers are the worst&lt;/a&gt;.
If the quality of your written works is bottlenecked on communication skills, it doesn't matter how much you improve your writing skills your books are just not going to get much better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Skills are generally improved by tight feedback loops, and often simply using the skill to achieve your goals is not a very tight feedback loop for the particular aspect of it you are constrained on,
because there's so much else going on that it makes the feedback loop very slow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To continue the writing example, say you want to improve your communication skills.
You &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; write more books in order to practice that, but writing a book takes a very long time.
You don't necessarily have that many books in you.
You could instead practice these skills by writing essays,
or even by having conversations with people on Twitter or in person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is the point I made in "why mathematics makes you better at programming": Different subjects and tasks give different feedback loops on different aspects of skill,
so often the best way to get good at a skill is to practice a different but related skill.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, sometimes constraints are hidden from you.
Often the constraint on a skill is anxiety management, or discomfort tolerance,
or one of various other things that you don't even really think of as skills you can get better at.
Sometimes the best way to unconstrain yourself are to go and do something &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; different which force you to confront that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-21-10:04.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-22-11:37.html</id>
    <title>You should try bad things</title>
    <updated>2020-02-22T11:45:55+00:00</updated>
    <content>

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You should try bad things&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-22&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Earlier &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/avyfain/status/1231148942756237312"&gt;Avy asked me the following question&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why would you read something if you expect to be terrible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My answer started with a few specific reasons, but finished with the following general observation:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also fundamentally... If you never to anything you think is going to fail, you'll repeatedly fall victim to confirmation bias and never leave your comfort zone. Sometimes it's worth branching out just to see what happens when you do&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a problem I talked about in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/02/theres-no-single-error-rate/"&gt;There's no single error rate&lt;/a&gt;:
If you only only observe the consequences of one part of your selection process (what happens when you try things you expect to be good) you've given the other part (what happens when you try things you expect to be bad) free reign to be basically arbitrarily wrong. This means you're missing out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular it means you're missing out &lt;em&gt;systematically&lt;/em&gt;, because you will never correct on traits that you think of as signalling something terrible because you will always avoid them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do a lot of reading outside of my comfort zone, because that's where things I don't know about live. Sometimes this requires gritting my teeth and reading something bad because it contains information I will get nowhere else (I find a lot of therapy reading like this - it's written in a style I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; dislike), and sometimes this requires reading something I expect to be bad and finding out that it's actually very good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you only try things that you expect to be good, your interests will narrow over time, because you will learn that more things that you thought were good are actually bad, but you will never learn that things you thought were bad are actually good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you're &lt;em&gt;certain&lt;/em&gt; something's going to be bad because you've tried it enough times to know, skip it sure. If something is very high effort, or very high risk, you similarly shouldn't push yourself into doing it. But if you can find or create relatively cheap and safe opportunities to try out something that might be bad, try it out. You might learn something important.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-22-11:37.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-23-09:37.html</id>
    <title>Legibility Privileges</title>
    <updated>2020-02-23T10:01:13+00:00</updated>
    <content>

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Legibility Privileges&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is the notion of passing privileges: The privileges you get when your marginalisation is one where you can pass as a member of a non-marginalised group. e.g. bisexual people have the ability to pass for straight, some people of colour have light enough skin that they can pass for white, some trans people are not read as such and can pass as cis, autistic people who can mask well enough can pass as neurotypical.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Passing is not a universally desirable thing (if you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; pass then you can be coerced into passing), but nevertheless passing privileges are a real and important thing that it is useful to be aware of.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd like to suggest that there is another form of privileges related to marginalisation, and that this form is underappreciated.
For example, I have the following experiences:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have complicated dietary requirements where some foods will make me ill, but there's not a simple summary of what these foods are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standing for protracted periods of time will make me very uncomfortable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crowded rooms with poor acoustics will make it hard for me to function and cause me to be very anxious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;None of these are easily summarisable, and don't necessarily correspond to any particularly clean identity lines.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Are they a big deal? Well... sometimes? The food one is a particularly big deal - I've more or less stopped eating out,
because there's a high chance I will end up eating something that I shouldn't because I don't fit in to any of the neat boxes that people understand food intolerances to fit into, and even if I don't it's high effort to avoid that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not suggesting that these make me unusually marginalised in degree. I'm clearly not. I doubt these even make me uniquely marginalised in kind - all of the things I've described are fairly common - what I'm suggesting is that there is a specific character to these issues that is underappreciated:
These marginalisations are &lt;em&gt;illegible&lt;/em&gt; to society.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because they do not fit into a clean categorisation scheme which allows me to readily communicate them,
they come with their own specific set of disadvantages that are not shared by more legible marginalisations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact I think &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; marginalisations are illegible to some greater or larger degree - e.g. everyone with even very legible food needs is used to having to explain in great detail that yes actually cheese &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a dairy product or similar - but some marginalisations are significantly less legible than others, and my suspicion is that most people experience some illegible marginalisations,
things that exclude them from some aspect of life that they cannot readily communicate without being seen as difficult,
of varying degrees of severity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I think a lot of the ways that we do feminism and social justice, e.g. with focuses on diversity, end up reinforcing that:
e.g. It's very easy to look at a conference and say "Have we made accommodations for wheelchair accessibility? What percentage of attendees are women? Do we have a gluten free food option?" because these are legible categories you can focus your diversity efforts on.
It is, in contrast, much harder to think about and optimise for illegible marginalisations because they are,
by definition,
too difficult for you to easily quantify.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-23-09:37.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-24-10:37.html</id>
    <title>All knowledge is connected</title>
    <updated>2020-02-24T11:04:21+00:00</updated>
    <content>

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;All knowledge is connected&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-24&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I read a lot. You might have noticed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I read a lot about a really broad range of subjects.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It gives me a lot of really weird spikes in my skill set,
and one of my favourite things is getting about half an hour into a conversation with some specialist and having them suddenly go "wait, hang on, aren't you a computer science? I forgot you weren't actually in my field" when I ask some really dumb question despite having been able to talk about the subject at expert level up until then.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things that you notice when you read this widely is that (extremely Dirk Gently voice) everything is connected.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You may not think that understanding nuclear war has much to do with understanding gender (ICBM dick jokes and recent controversial stories about the militarization of gender technology aside),
but Thomas Schelling's "The Strategy of Conflict" was one of the most informative things I've read about gender until I read "The Origins of Unfairness" which is more directly about the game theory of gender.
These both tie in well to "Conflict is not Abuse" (a book about speech norms in LGBT and social justice communities),
and to "Queer Phenomenology", about how we use gender to orient our way through society,
or to "Models: Attract Women through Honesty" (a surprisingly good book of dating advice for men),
or to Raewyn Connol's "Masculinities", or to...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I say "All knowledge is connected" I don't mean that "Every piece of knowledge is directly connected to every other piece of knowledge". The link between "The Strategy of Conflict" and "Models" would not have been at all obvious without some of those other books as intermediaries.
I call such books &lt;em&gt;bridging books&lt;/em&gt; - ones which unify two previously unconnected things in a way that enriches your understanding of all of them - but increasingly I think that limiting it to books is too confining and I should just call them bridges.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One prompt for this was the paper I read recently on &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-16-14:22.html"&gt;ghost knowledge&lt;/a&gt;. This ruined the idea of bridging as a book specific thing both by pointing out how much of the world's knowledge isn't written down &lt;em&gt;anywhere&lt;/em&gt;, let alone in books, and also by itself being a bridge between &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-18-12:24.html"&gt;How to talk about books you haven't read&lt;/a&gt;'s ideas about communal libraries and the notions of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2019-06-04-09:58.html"&gt;hermeneutic and contributory injustice&lt;/a&gt; from the epistemic justice school of thought.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A useful metaphor for understanding how this works is Susan Haack's &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF02683186"&gt;Puzzling out science&lt;/a&gt;, and obscure-ish piece of philosophy of science.
In it, she argues that a great metaphor for the process of science and reasoning about the world is the crossword puzzle.
In a crossword puzzle you have both the clues, and the grid. The clues are things you observe about the world, and the grid is the thing that forces them to be consistent with eachother.
You might fill in parts of the puzzle independently of eachother,
and then try to join them up and discover to your annoyance that this square that you thought was a "c" cannot possibly be one and still fit with this other clue.
The process of solving a crossword puzzle is thus a constant tension between solving it locally based on evidence and using the constraints to force updates to other part of the puzzle when you discover inconsistencies.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This propagation is why the connectedness of knowledge matters:
Although there's no real direct connection between nuclear war and gender,
there's this long chain of connections, and updates in one place might inform updates in others by propagating through that chain.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-24-10:37.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html</id>
    <title>How to make decisions</title>
    <updated>2020-02-25T11:18:14+00:00</updated>
    <content>

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How to make decisions&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The base model for decision making is a coin flip.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not saying that you should flip a coin for all your decisions, I'm saying that any decision making strategy you adopt &lt;em&gt;needs to be demonstrable better than flipping a coin&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or, when is more normal, you are making decisions between a number of options, your decision making strategy needs to be better than choosing among them uniformly at random (drawing lots, etc).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People think that the best decision making approach given n items is to choose the best item.
This is foolish and wrong, which is why the entirety of economics is based on this theory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is a mean dig and is not true, but it's also not unfair. Economists don't @ me)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason it is foolish and wrong is that the effort of determining which is the best may exceed the benefit of choosing the best over one of many other options. Consider &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buridan%27s_ass"&gt;Buridan's ass&lt;/a&gt; (but don't ogle it, that would be uncouth):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buridan's ass is an illustration of a paradox in philosophy in the conception of free will. It refers to a hypothetical situation wherein a donkey that is equally hungry and thirsty is placed precisely midway between a stack of hay and a pail of water. Since the paradox assumes the ass will always go to whichever is closer, it dies of both hunger and thirst since it cannot make any rational decision between the hay and water. A common variant of the paradox substitutes two identical piles of hay for the hay and water; the ass, unable to choose between the two, dies of hunger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Dying of hunger is an obviously worse strategy than flipping a coin. I do not recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But consider... what happens if one of the piles of hay has an extra mouthful on it. That's obviously the better pile of hay, right? You should pick that one and then eat from it, right?
But how long will it take you to find out which one has more hay on it? You'll get quite hungry and waste a lot of time doing it, you ass.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this is the first thing we should learn from the coin flip:
If the decision doesn't matter much, just pick something, more or less at random.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What do we do if the decision &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; matter that much?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The following is a pretty good heuristic solution:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eliminate any options that are &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt; worse than another. Like, if you're being offered £200 or £300 you don't need to think hard to pick the £300.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify pairs of options that are obviously more or less equivalent to eachother and randomly discard one of them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have more than one option left, maybe gather some more information to improve your knowledge of the situation if there's still a wide range of potential outcomes. Only do this if the cost of gathering information isn't too high or the benefit of gaining it is much higher. Repeat (1) and (2) if this changes anything there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you still have more than one option do something like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Probability_matching"&gt;probability matching&lt;/a&gt; on what's left, picking an item with probability equal to the (subjective) probability of it being the best outcome. If this seems hard, just pick uniformly at random. Or pick a pair uniformly at random and invest in a bit more effort in deciding between the two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You almost never need to do anything this formal, but the general idea is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't spend too much effort on eliminating options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend only as much effort on improving your knowledge of the situation as the situation warrants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If after you've done that it's still not obvious what to do from the remaining options, deploy whimsy and gut feel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Related:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/10/vocabulary-building-satisficing/"&gt;Vocabulary Building: Satisficing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-22-11:37.html"&gt;You should try bad things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/02/theres-no-single-error-rate/"&gt;There's no single error rate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html</id>
    <title>The fastest way to learn something is to do something</title>
    <updated>2020-02-26T16:07:00+00:00</updated>
    <content>

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The fastest way to learn something is to do something&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you have a problem to solve. What do you do?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, you sit down and think real hard,
and after extensive and careful planning you try the well thought out and rigorous solution that you have thought up.
Right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No, wrong! Bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The correct thing to do when you have a problem is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think for a &lt;em&gt;short&lt;/em&gt; amount of time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure it is safe to try things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try something you think will work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Observe the result.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you succeeded, yay you solved the problem!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it didn't work, think about what that means for the nature of the problem and try again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every attempt to solve the problem is an opportunity to learn about the nature of the problem,
and the nature of the tools you can use for solving problems in general.
It will often teach you &lt;em&gt;significantly&lt;/em&gt; more than either sitting and thinking about the problem or trying a less directed experiment will.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Caveats&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Obviously there is a place for learning about things that is less connected to a specific problem (given the number of books I read for general interest I would be a hypocrite to claim otherwise). Additionally, some problems are not well suited to this because e.g. They are high risk or they are long cycle time, but even then there will usually be subproblems like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason this is quite as strident as it is is as a necessary corrective to a tendency that most people have to overplan and get too hung up on finding the "right" solution. The lessons on &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;cost of decision making&lt;/a&gt; apply in spades to solving problems.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
