<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-04-10T10:53:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-29-21:16.html</id>
    <title>Everything is a teachable moment</title>
    <updated>2020-03-29T22:24:23+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Everything is a teachable moment&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Previously I have written blog posts about:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2017/02/thinking-through-the-implications/"&gt;A cat who can open doors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-26-09:48.html"&gt;Fixing a shower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2013/08/how-did-you-get-started-so-quickly/"&gt;How to get started in a new code base&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Except that's not what any of these are about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They're actually about:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolkitized thinking&lt;/em&gt; - how to apply things that you've learned in other contexts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pragmatic problem solving&lt;/em&gt; - how to let go of the desire to solve the problem properly and just solve the problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Efficient learning&lt;/em&gt; - how not to get distracted by &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-22-18:01.html"&gt;the impossibly large number of things to learn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Each of them are of course about both these things: Something happened, and by looking at what happened you can learn something generalisable about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Typically of course, you don't actually see a single thing and get the general insight, you acquire the general insight after seeing many different things, but often a specific example is exactly what you need to &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/10/how-to-explain-anything-to-anyone/"&gt;explain the point&lt;/a&gt;, possibly to someone else, possibly to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The important feature of these generalisations is that by doing this you learn beyond the specific circumstances you encounter and &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1758026/"&gt;experience the world richly&lt;/a&gt;, letting you draw on your past experience more effectively in novel situations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One way of looking at mathematics is that it's about taking a look at an argument and paring it down to its bare essentials and generalising it. Trying to take something hyper specific and turn it into a simple reusable principle that can be applied, by asking what about the problem actually matters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our interactions with the world are like this too. Everything is a teachable moment, all you have to do is look at it through the right lens and use it to teach something.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-29-21:16.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html</id>
    <title>Desire as a driver of growth</title>
    <updated>2020-03-30T23:37:46+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Desire as a driver of growth&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-30&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wrote before about how &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety is the enabler of growth&lt;/a&gt;: The thing that allows you to grow is to be safe to experiment, so you can learn new ways of being.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is true as far as it goes, but it has a big problem: If you're safe, it's very easy to just stay where you are.
The possibility to grow exists, but you have no particular reason to take it, so you don't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can see this in the stereotype of the spoiled rich kid (although often they're not exactly in safe environments either, so this is weak evidence. Consider it an illustrative example).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic problem is that growth is hard work. You have to want to do it. You have to actually &lt;em&gt;desire&lt;/em&gt; to grow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One key to doing this is what I wrote about in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-23-15:52.html"&gt;life as an anytime algorithm&lt;/a&gt;: Designing goals so that you gain partial benefits as you go. This ensures that you're getting feedback on growth as you proceed, and it doesn't feel like &lt;a href="https://www.fvathynevgl.com/momentum/"&gt;a long hard slog with hopefully a reward at the end&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't enough, because it depends on what type of progress you're making. In particular, I reliably find that progress that just makes things less bad doesn't have the right shape. 
The nagging urge is always there to backslide and just fall back to the old ways. The old ways weren't good, but they sure were easier, and stable, and stability is comforting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to create a desire for growth you need the changes you see to be an actively positive thing.
It makes you hungry for more, and the work feels less like work and more like achievement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two examples where I have encountered this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In my various work on &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;emotions&lt;/a&gt; one of my specific goals has been around the experience of positive emotions. I don't just want to be less miserable, I want to be happier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've been working on my diet. This means I no longer have a permanently upset stomach. That's great and all, but it sure is tempting to backslide because pizza is delicious. But... I must admit, I'm really enjoying the weight loss. I know, I know, body positivity, but I feel &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-27-08:18.html"&gt;a lot better about my body&lt;/a&gt; than I have in some time, and that's really nice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You need to clear out the negative stuff too (more of my emotion work is on anxiety than joy, but the two feed into each other). It's important not to overfocus on the positive, but without the positive to drive growth you will often give up, and that means you end up doing less work on the negatives in total.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-31-09:52.html</id>
    <title>Vampire bats as a model for flirting</title>
    <updated>2020-03-31T11:02:31+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Vampire bats as a model for flirting&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-31&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-29-21:16.html"&gt;everything is a teachable moment&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-24-10:37.html"&gt;all knowledge is connected&lt;/a&gt;, I'm now going to explain why the social behaviour of vampire bats tells us important things about flirting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I am bad at flirting. I've got a lot better at it recently, but I am definitely not good at it. This is a post based on the process of my becoming less bad at it. Fortunately that's &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/sarahdoingthing/status/877018612447313920/photo/1"&gt;apparently the perfect time to write about such things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, before we talk about flirting, lets talk about vampire bats. &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/19/science/vampire-bats-blood.html"&gt;Vampire bats know sharing blood with friends is good manners&lt;/a&gt;, and this is how flirting works too. Well, flirting rarely involves the sharing of blood except for at very specific sorts of parties that I do not get invited to, but the general principle is sound.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way vampire bats share blood between non-kin is that they start by grooming. If that's reciprocated, they maybe share a little bit of blood. If that too is reciprocated, they share more, and so on. They &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-24-09:46.html"&gt;build trust&lt;/a&gt; by repeatedly offering slightly more than was previously offered, and waiting to see if it's reciprocated. This is called a raising-the-stakes game. The general strategy is described in &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/28160"&gt;Development of cooperative relationships through increasing investment&lt;/a&gt;, although I confess to not actually having read it yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is also how flirting works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I previously wrote &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-27-08:18.html"&gt;about sexiness and the process of attraction&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experiencing someone as sexy is about fascination. You see something about them, and it draws you in, and makes you want to learn more about them and to explore it. It makes you want more of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Skillfull flirting is about mutually cooperating to escalate this fascination. You exhibit interest, to see if it is reciprocated, and you progressively dance your way through this back and forth, each of you expressing some interest and seeing how the other responds to it. If they don't, you back off (or at least stop escalating and stay at the currently comfortable level). If they do, you escalate further.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually, if you both want it to, you've each drawn the other in enough that it becomes time to make the fascination more explicit, either by action (e.g. kissing) or talking about it, but this doesn't have to happen. Flirtation is about escalating fascination, but you don't have to keep escalating, you can just have fun with it at whatever level you like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This can go wrong in three major ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is that you can just mess it up. Unskillful performance of flirting is incompetent, and thus unsexy, so may turn the other party off and lose the fascination. (If you're lucky and they're into you it may be adorable rather than unsexy, which has some chance of success. If I'm honest this is historically the most successful flirting strategy I have adopted).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second, is that you may lack the skills of picking up on interest. This is particularly true if you struggle to conceive of yourself as attractive (you miss interest that is there). It can also be true if you read interest that is not there (men are often bad at this - I've heard it said that men tend to overinterpret friendliness as flirting and women tend to overinterpret flirting as friendliness), but that tends to lead to unskillful performance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The third, and is the way I have personally failed at this until recently, is that you can be bad at showing interest you actually feel.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If attraction is fascination, then flirting is a process by which you create attraction. Usually it starts from some initial seed, but it can go down as well as up - if your attraction is very obviously not reciprocated, it will tend to diminish (this isn't always true, and there are some ways the opposite can play out, but they tend to be predicated on both a high level of initial attraction and the possibility in principle of it being reciprocated).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A consequence of that is this is that unless you are in some way extraordinarily attractive, unless you can demonstrate the attraction you feel towards others, they will probably not exhibit much attraction to you. If you find yourself in a situation where people just don't seem to find you attractive, consider whether that might be what's going on.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-31-09:52.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-01-09:41.html</id>
    <title>The problem of deduction</title>
    <updated>2020-04-01T10:22:13+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The problem of deduction&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-01&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1245261142966050822"&gt;I mentioned on Twitter earlier&lt;/a&gt; I am trying to reread books I've already read a bit more, because I'm failing to read new material. Not reading them cover to cover, just dipping in and refreshing my mind about interesting bits, seeing how it fits in with new information, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The book I picked up to do this with this morning is Harman and Kulkarni's book &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2R2dL2z"&gt;Reliable Reasoning&lt;/a&gt;. Great book. Strong recommend if you've got the prerequisites (mild mathematical and philosophical sophistication) and are interested in the subject (inductive reasoning and what we can learn about it from statistics).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I opened it in the middle, decided I needed some refreshing on the first chapter, so went back to that and read it for a bit. On doing so I encountered a bit which caused me to go "Hmm. This is a good and powerful insight. I must remember it."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is, however, a problem, which is that having that insight makes me realise that this is the &lt;em&gt;third time that's happened&lt;/em&gt;. So now I'm going to explain it to you so that hopefully I'll remember it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The official story: Deductive reasoning is when you go "All A are B. This is an A. Therefore it is a B". Inductive reasoning is when you go "All A I've seen so far are B. This is an A. Therefore it is a B". The former is obviously valid. The latter is obviously invalid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:59.html"&gt;mentioned my favourite joke before&lt;/a&gt; but here it is again:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a joke about a planet full of people who believe in antiinduction: if the sun has risen every day in the past, then today, we should expect that it won’t. As a result, these people are all starving and living in poverty. Someone visits the planet and tells them, “Hey, why are you still using this anti-induction philosophy? You’re living in horrible poverty!” “Well, it never worked before...”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem of induction is basically "Why is induction so weird compared to deduction?". Deduction is based on seemingly universally applicable principles, it's reliable and trustworthy. It really is true that if all A are B and this is an A it must be a B. That's just how logic works. In contrast, the inductive version &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; true - we're in the middle of a major &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_swan_theory"&gt;black swan event&lt;/a&gt; right now, so we know damn well that sometimes the world surprises you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This book offers a surprisingly good answer: This question is a category error.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Deductive reasoning isn't a thing, because deduction is not a reasoning process. It is a logic of what follows from what. You can build reasoning on top of that, but you cannot do reasoning with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you believe all swans are white, and that this bird is a swan, and that this bird is black. This is, deductively speaking, an inconsistent set of beliefs. As it is inconsistent, anything follows from it. From a black swan it follows that eating cabbage grants you immortality. However, we would look quite suspiciously on this as a line of reasoning I hope.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way the book puts this is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From inconsistent beliefs, everything follows. But it is not the case that from inconsistent beliefs one can infer everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is true that if we believe all three of 1) All swans are white, 2) This bird is a swan, and 3) This bird is black,
then anything follows, but our inference procedure from here is not that we infer whatever we like, it's that we stop believing one of these things (or choose to remain inconsistent and are very cautious about what we infer from them).
Deductive logic doesn't give us any insight as to which of these things we should drop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is still the case that a deductive argument from premises to conclusions is universally valid.
It is &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; that if all three of these things hold then cabbage makes you immortal. This is a valid deductive argument. But a deductive argument is not a reasoning process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The category error is thus that deduction is a process of argumentation about what follows from what, and induction is a process of reasoning of how we infer beliefs from information. These are not the same thing, and when you properly integrate deduction into the reasoning process what you find is that actually most of the things that were straightforward about it don't help you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, if you want to know why induction is so weird, the reason is that induction is the bit that lets you actually reason and infer things about reality, and the problem of deduction is that it can't actually do that for you.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-01-09:41.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-02-09:44.html</id>
    <title>Teleology is fake</title>
    <updated>2020-04-02T11:28:32+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Teleology is fake&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tobi has written about &lt;a href="https://ramble.rixx.de/2020/03/30/on-origin-stories.html"&gt;origin stories&lt;/a&gt; and the importance of asking "What is this for?" instead of "Where does this come from?". He doesn't use the word teleology (the study of the purpose of things) but in the Adlerian psychology the post is based on that is what he's talking about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've previously talked about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;the usefulness of teleology in understanding our emotional reactions&lt;/a&gt; and how understanding the purpose of an emotional reaction (its teleology) is important to adjusting it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Both Tobi and my posts have the same aetiology (origin story), which is that we read The Courage to be Disliked (a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-11-07:15.html"&gt;useful yet punchable book&lt;/a&gt;), which is in large part about using an understanding of teleology to change your social behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do not want to minimize the importance of this approach, which is very powerful and important, but it does have a critical problem with it: Teleology is fake. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-11-07:15.html"&gt;Things don't happen for reasons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Questions to ponder:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why is this fence here?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why do giraffes have long necks?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why am I taking singing classes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The answer to all of these questions is: There isn't a good reason, but they're still important. Teleology is fake.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G._K._Chesterton#Chesterton's_fence"&gt;Chesterton's fence&lt;/a&gt; is the idea that if there is a fence in a field, you should not take it down unless you know the reason why it is there:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the matter of reforming things, as distinct from deforming them, there is one plain and simple principle; a principle which will probably be called a paradox. There exists in such a case a certain institution or law; let us say, for the sake of simplicity, a fence or gate erected across a road. The more modern type of reformer goes gaily up to it and says, 'I don't see the use of this; let us clear it away.' To which the more intelligent type of reformer will do well to answer: 'If you don't see the use of it, I certainly won't let you clear it away. Go away and think. Then, when you can come back and tell me that you do see the use of it, I may allow you to destroy it.'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But "Why is this fence here?" is a slippery question. Do we mean it as a question of aetiology or teleology? "What is the use of this fence?" is a very different question from "Who put this fence here and why?". You might answer the latter, find out that it is for reasons that no longer apply, and tear the fence down, and discover that the local ecology collapses because now grazing sheep can get somewhere they previously couldn't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a quote that is &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/7659686-tradition-is-a-set-of-solutions-for-which-we-have"&gt;apparently from a sci-fi novel I've never read&lt;/a&gt;, by Donald Kingsbury:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Tradition is a set of solutions for which we have forgotten the problems. Throw away the solution and you get the problem back. Sometimes the problem has mutated or disappeared. Often it is still there as strong as it ever was.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This, like Chesterton's fence, is an extremely conservative principle against reform that is also wildly optimistic about how easy reform is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is that tradition is not just a solution to problems we've forgotten, it's also a foundational layer on which we have built subsequent things. In the fence example, maybe the sheep came long after the fence, and were just never a problem before now. Changing the tradition invalidates foundational assumptions for many other things you were doing, possibly without even knowing they were there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now lets talk about giraffes. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-31-09:52.html"&gt;Animals are a good model for social behaviour after all&lt;/a&gt;.
Why do giraffes have long necks?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well there are &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giraffe#Neck"&gt;a couple possible reasons&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to high up leaves which lets them outcompete other grazers by having more food supply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sexual selection (male giraffes fight by beating each other using their necks. It's terrifying).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being able to see predators from further away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these seem to be good hypotheses. Which one is the true reason?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well... probably all of them. Evolution doesn't actually do things for reasons. Evolution just tries random nonsense, and sometimes the random nonsense proves useful in ways that gives a net advantage. If something is useful for multiple weak reasons, that's just as good as it being useful for a single strong reason (potentially even better! More robust, more directions to develop in). So the "reason" giraffes have long necks might just be "All of the above, plus some things we didn't think of, plus these add up to being worth the cost".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Evolution doesn't design things how a human designer sits down and design things (although in practice things created by humans are also designed in an evolutionary way, but the "mutation" process is a bit more directed) - it doesn't need simple legible reasons for what it does, it just &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;tries stuff&lt;/a&gt; and sees how it pans out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Even this is of course too much of an anthropomorphisation of evolution, but it's a useful one)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Moving away from complex messy evolved systems that make no sense to instead discussing the human mind and its decision making, which obviously makes complete sense, I'm going to be taking singing lessons once the pandemic has lifted and I can find a teacher.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why? Well...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm not very good at breathing and want to get better at it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm slightly embarrassed about how bad I am at singing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I do a lot of public speaking and I'd like to be better at projecting as a result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better voice control seems an interesting skill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's a great embodiment practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It ties in well with Alexander Technique, which I'm learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It seems fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It would be a good self-confidence boost to be able to be good at singing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Those are the big ones, but there are more. But no single one of these is remotely close to enough to convince me to learn to sing. Any two or three wouldn't be. What's convinced me to learn to sing is that an accumulation of enough good, individually insufficient, reasons, has tipped it over to the point where the cost-benefit analysis is a clear net win.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is how everything works. Teleology is a useful lens to look at problems through, and should not be discarded, but ultimately if we think things are happening for a simple, clear, and comprehensible purpose, and that if we change them then nothing will change except insofar as it is related to that purpose, we're going to be in for an unpleasant surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-02-09:44.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-03-13:40.html</id>
    <title>Anxiety vs Worry</title>
    <updated>2020-04-03T17:46:23+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Anxiety vs Worry&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is a distinction I've found useful recently: You are &lt;em&gt;anxious&lt;/em&gt; about something if the emotion attaches to the uncertainty in the situation, you are &lt;em&gt;worried&lt;/em&gt; about something if the emotion attaches to the possible outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;NB that this doesn't &lt;em&gt;perfectly&lt;/em&gt; track colloquial usage, but I think it works pretty well with it.
Also if you're not sure how to tell what the emotion attaches to, may I recommend &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2UWXQDL"&gt;Focusing&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's certainly possible to worry about things without being particularly anxious about them. Sensible precautions often work like this: e.g. I lock my door because I'm worried that if I don't people might otherwise come in and steal stuff, but there's no anxiety attached to that worry because it's just something I can act on to limit the chances.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can be anxious without worry in situations when all of the potential outcomes are positive (it's also possible &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Misattribution_of_arousal"&gt;to mistake excitement for anxiety&lt;/a&gt; in these scenarios, but the anxiety can be real too). If one possible outcome &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anxiety and worry are far from mutually exclusive, and indeed tend to go hand in hand, but it is worth &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:35.html"&gt;untangling&lt;/a&gt; the two conceptually,
and even where both are present they are still different emotions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, with COVID-19, I  am &lt;em&gt;worried&lt;/em&gt; about specific outcomes - harm to people in general, harm to people I love, overall negative societal effects, but am also also COVID-19 has more or less destroyed my ability to reason about the future, and that makes me &lt;em&gt;anxious&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the COVID-19 case the anxiety feels almost more like an &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-06-07:46.html"&gt;existential feeling&lt;/a&gt; - there's not a specific thing I'm anxious about so much as a general sense that the unknown unknowns are dwarfing the known unknowns, let alone the known knowns (the unknown knowns remain huge given how ideological responses are being). The thing that is making me anxious is the uncertainty itself, not the bad outcomes possible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reducing worry is often more tractable than reducing anxiety, because you can reduce worry by planning. If you have a scenario you're worried about, you can ensure that you're prepared for it (e.g. COVID-19 precautions, or talking through your concerns about a situation with the people involved before you get into it). I like Chris Hadfield's advice for dealing with worry, which is "Figure out the next thing that's going to kill you" - plan for the worst, and convince yourself you can handle it. Also often what you're worrying about is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html"&gt;outdated scenarios that no longer apply&lt;/a&gt;, so &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;learning to debug that can help with this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anxiety can be resolved by reducing uncertainty by making the situation more deterministic, but often that's not a good idea! &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;A certain amount of nondeterminism is often very useful&lt;/a&gt;, and many of the ways to reduce uncertainty do this by increasing the chances of failure (e.g. procrastination until it's too late to do a good job).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of things you can do:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on any worries first, because often a lack of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety&lt;/a&gt; is the thing that makes uncertainty uncomfortable. Uncertainty isn't intrinsically bad, because if you're always certain you'll never learn anything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See if you can reframe any of the anxiety. For example, you can be uncertain about the outcome but certain of your ability to handle it. Can you focus on that? Are there good things about the uncertainty too? Can you appreciate those as excitement? (This one rarely to never works for me)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you've managed to get your anxiety down to a low enough level, it can be worth practicing a certain amount of discomfort tolerance. Anxiety isn't intrinsically bad, it may be telling you useful information about the world, so the correct amount of anxiety may be non-zero, and it's important to acknowledge that and be prepared to sit with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you've not managed to get your anxiety down to a low enough level, often me neither I'm afraid (I've got a lot better since I've acquired the "legacy code" tools). Consult someone with better advice than me and let me know what they said.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-03-13:40.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-06-15:20.html</id>
    <title>Being safe for others</title>
    <updated>2020-04-06T15:52:38+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Being safe for others&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It will come as no surprise to the regular reader of this blog that personal growth is a bit of a thing for me right now.
It is unlikely to come as a surprise (given that I'm writing about growth and run a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-25-16:02.html"&gt;support group&lt;/a&gt;) that I'm also keen to help others with theirs.
I've had a lot of good experiences on this front recently, many of which I owe to other people, and want to help pay it forward, both to my friends and also to random people on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the skills that seems most helpful in doing this is &lt;em&gt;being safe to tell things to&lt;/em&gt;.
People are mostly OK at the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; part, and where they're not you can't really help them with that outside of a very close relationship, but everyone is lacking in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety&lt;/a&gt;, and if you're to be able to provide people with a platform for growth you need to be able to extend that safety to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is only one thing you really must do for this: Don't react badly, especially don't react judgementally, when people tell you things that they've been hiding about themself.
You need to be someone people can &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-24-09:46.html"&gt;extend trust to&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, extremely difficult in general. If someone confesses to some truly terrible crime, of course you're going to react badly to it, no matter how highly you think of them. It doesn't matter how much good faith you're extending, some things are just too much.
Fortunately, usually it isn't this bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not yet sure what to advise on developing this skill, but some things that seem to help:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning good boundaries - being able to say "Actually, I'm sorry, I don't think I can help you with this" rather than trying and failing to help, or reacting defensively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;Learning to manage your own reactions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Appreciating just how weird and diverse humanity is, and how many seemingly "unhealthy" things are actually very normal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asking whether it's &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-09-11:13.html"&gt;useful to have an opinion&lt;/a&gt; as to whether the thing being described is good or bad (if you're judgemental, will they stop doing it, or will they just go find someone who will encourage them to do it more?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look for the underlying pain, rather than focusing on how they're conceptualising a solution to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply the communication skills from &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2RehhHl"&gt;the customer service survival kit&lt;/a&gt; to empathically defuse highly emotional communication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of these are, of course, the skills that one learns to apply as a therapist, but I'm hopeful that more people can develop them without retraining as therapists.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-06-15:20.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-07-10:05.html</id>
    <title>What's cooking?</title>
    <updated>2020-04-07T11:17:06+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;What's cooking?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;A Recipe&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's start with a recipe, because everybody hates it when food blogs start with a long preamble before you finally get to the recipe:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raw cashew pieces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three apples (one granny smith, two... IDK something red?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raisins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allspice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Honey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Quantities left to your own judgement, but roughly I had about a 3 : 3 : 1 ratio of apples, cashews, raisins.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Making this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coat the cashews in just enough oil to lubricate them (don't use too much! They'll get super oily if you do), add salt to taste, mix thoroughly, and bake at 180C for 15 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, chop the apples as finely as you can be bothered. Toss them with "an amount" of allspice (honestly I would have used cinammon but I could &lt;em&gt;find&lt;/em&gt; the allspice)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take the cashews out of the oven, add the raisins and apple to them, mix thoroughly with a suitable amount of honey.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raise the oven to 210C and bake for another half hour (then turn the oven off and leave it while you finish making the rest of dinner, in my case a chicken, vegetable, and lentil, soup)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You may notice a couple of key features of this recipe:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's a little weird&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The instructions are completely half-arsed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is, fortunately, delicious, but it will probably be tinkered with endlessly if I make it again, and I doubt I'll ever formalise it with anything so gauche as &lt;em&gt;quantities&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;A Story&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As this is apparently now a food blog, it's time for a deeply personal anecdote about my relationship with this food.
It's a story in two tragedies, first &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2xXqsF2"&gt;one sort of plague&lt;/a&gt; and then another (and after all, &lt;a href="http://clarkesworldmagazine.com/kritzer_11_15/"&gt;food blogging during a plague is a fine tradition&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why did I make this recipe? Well, because I had far too many of the ingredients. This is something I tend to call "forced abundance": When you have too much of a good thing and have to reorient your plans around making use of that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First, we had Brexit. We still have Brexit, and we're probably going to massively self-own at a crucial pandemic-handling moment as a result of it, but last year I argued (And I still believe my argument was correct) that &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/02/you-should-be-stockpiling-food-for-brexit/"&gt;you should be stockpiling food for the event of a no deal Brexit&lt;/a&gt;. Either the food would be neutral to mildly positive to have or the food would be essential to have, and the probabilities of the latter were low but far enough from zero to be worth planning around.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, I underestimated how positive this could be, because now that we're trapped in lockdown due to COVID-19 it's really useful to have a giant larder of food supplies. As I put it, annoyingly presciently, in that post:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another scenario is to consider is that if things get unpleasant, we’ll have a situation reminscient of the London riots – it’s not that you can’t leave the house, you’d just maybe... rather not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately my prepping supplies were less sensible than my argument, and one of the things I didn't realise is how short the shelf life on some items were. In particular the cashew nuts and the raisins mentioned above are about 6 months out of date. They're mostly fine still - the cashews are a little stale, but fine as long as they're cooked. The raisins are very dry but perfectly edible. No sense at all in throwing them away, but better to use them up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, it turns out that 2.5kg of cashews and 5kg of raisins are really quite a lot of cashews and raisins.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of this I placed an order for a fruit and veg box from &lt;a href="https://allgreens.co.uk/"&gt;allgreens&lt;/a&gt;. Allgreens allow no customisation of their boxes, and as a result I had a great deal of apples.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do I like them apples? Cooked. For some reason I'm just really not very into raw apples. Not sure why.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, long story short, I had a great many apples, cashews, and raisins to use up, and I was pretty sure that was a flavour combination that would work well, and after some cursory googling confirmed that I probably wasn't completely off base, and the above is what I came up with. It is indeed a flavour combination that works well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;An Observation&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting things about forced abundance is how rarely it happens in modern life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My parents have a garden, so I'm used to it. During the appropriate seasons you discover that there is, for example, such a thing as too many delicious, fresh, raspberries, and that it is perfectly feasible to fill yourself up on artichokes.
The degree and specifics of this vary from year to year, but the feeling of sometimes having too much is a thing that everyone with a garden is used to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Supermarkets don't do that to you. The only time I've ever had anything resembling forced abundance from a supermarket was the year where a Sainsbury's misjudged how many blueberries people wanted for Christmas and so on the 27th we discovered that there were a very large number of blueberries a day or two before their use by date available for about 20p per punnet. We bought a lot of them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another relatively common experience of forced abundance is leftovers - when you've made a really large quantity of something and then end up having to eat it up for a week. Especially common after Christmas or Thanksgiving if you've roasted an entire turkey for fewer people than an entire turkey is needed for (Solution: Have a better bird for your holiday meals. Turkey is fine I guess but mostly very boring).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I discovered this week, vegetable boxes are another one. I used to have an Abel and Cole subscription and the "Oh gods what do I do with all these vegetables?" struggle was significant. Even with the allgreens boxes being purchased on demand I expect I'll still have this, because the thing about boxes is that they bundle everything together. Being out of bananas and fixing that suddenly mean that you've got a lot of tomatoes to use up too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Generically, two main things that can create forced abundance:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things coming in at a greater rate than you can use or store them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things that you already have stored that are about to go off.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The apples are an example of (1), the cashews and raisins of (2).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason these things don't happen with supermarkets is basically supply and demand. If a supermarket needs to get rid of something, they lower the price on it (either on individual items through reductions or sales, or more globally for in season produce and the like) until it clears. If &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; will move a product then they throw it away, which is essentially a limited version of &lt;a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2020/04/01/business/oil-prices-crash-storage-space/index.html"&gt;the price going negative&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Supply and demand and market pricing is very good at distributing abundance (it's not necessarily good at distributing it &lt;em&gt;fairly&lt;/em&gt; mind you, that may require other mechanisms), and through supermarkets we are all the beneficiaries of that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, as an individual who is not set up to sell things, we can't do this. Theoretically my parents could sell the output of their garden (and they now have an informal deal where they dump excess on a local cafe in exchange for favours in kind), but because they are not set up for selling things already it's vastly more effort than it's worth. Some years my mother tries to sell her pumpkins and even that is just not worth the trouble.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For most people, in normal times, our food supply comes from supermarkets on a fairly as needed basis this limitation doesn't really come up, because we're operating on a pull-based rather than push-based model: We decide what we need to make, informed by availability and price certainly, and acquire what we need to make it. Any surplus on the supply end is not our problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This creates what is, historically, a somewhat anomalous relationship to food: We treat ingredients as something we have free choice over rather than the starting point. Cooking is a process of creating meals, not a process of turning raw ingredients into meals.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a subtle but important difference that you can see even during normalcy. There are, roughly, two types of cook:Those who decide what they're going to make before they go to the supermarket, and those who use the supermarket to find out what they're going to make (this is, of course, actually a spectrum rather than a binary). I'm very much in the latter camp, and I feel like we're having a much better time of cooking in quarantine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's nothing wrong with recipes of course, and in many ways pull-based cooking is excellent. I'd be hard pressed to argue that forced abundance is a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; thing - it's quite annoying in some ways, and it's tellingly not something that people opt into unless created by circumstances - but it's certainly an interesting thing, serving as the culinary equivalent of a writing prompt, and it forces you in creative directions that you otherwise wouldn't have taken.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-07-10:05.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-08-16:12.html</id>
    <title>The rule of three twos</title>
    <updated>2020-04-08T16:25:23+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The rule of three twos&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-07-10:05.html"&gt;In the last post I wrote about improvised cooking&lt;/a&gt;.
Some people find this much easier than others.
Here I thought I'd share a quick tip that usually makes it quite easy:
the rule of three twos.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rule is very simple: If you have three flavours, each pair of which works together, then the combination of the three can probably be made to work well and be interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This works well for both food and drinks, and is often the basis for a good cocktail.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was the basis of the recipe I made the other day, because cashews/apples/raisins was reasonably certain to work (I wasn't sure about cashews and apples, but cashews are such an innocuous flavour it seemed unlikely they wouldn't).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is essentially the practical implication of the &lt;a href="https://www.georgehart.com/triad.html"&gt;incompatible food triad problem&lt;/a&gt;: Even if such a triad exists, it's really hard to find it, so most things will work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, you can't just mix the three things together any which way and expect it to be great, but the rule gives you a good foundation because it lets you start from something that you can be pretty sure will work.
This restricts the problem of making it great to:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figuring out the right proportions, especially which flavour you want to dominate (e.g. the fact that that recipe had much fewer raisins than the other ingredients, or figuring out the right quantity of spirit in a cocktail)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figuring out supporting flavours that you can use to accent or bridge the base three (e.g. salt and allspice in the above, bitters to add to a cocktail)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not every good meal can be produced this way of course, but that's not the point. The rule lets you produce something reliably good without worrying too much about it, which is often a useful &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-05-11:27.html"&gt;existence proof&lt;/a&gt; to have when doing improvised cooking, and gives you safe fallbacks if you don't feel like doing anything fancy.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-08-16:12.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-10-10:53.html</id>
    <title>Maybe everyone was right all along</title>
    <updated>2020-04-10T10:53:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Maybe everyone was right all along&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-04-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A common subject of mockery right now is that a lot of people are treating COVID-19 as evidence that their ideologies were right all along.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do share a certain amount of amusement over this, but would like to suggest the following counterpoint: Actually, most of these people probably &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; right all along, at least in some ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The easy example is that people calling for greater social safety nets, medical care, etc. who are now going "Hey, you know, maybe those things would have been useful in a pandemic??" are obviously right. Those things &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; have been useful in a pandemic. The pandemic genuinely is providing good evidence for why people need &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-04-05/spanish-government-aims-to-roll-out-basic-income-soon"&gt;universal basic income&lt;/a&gt;, and it really is a damning criticism of a lot of countries' healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specifically what's happening here is that the pandemic is highlighting two major problems that were present all along:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many people's lives are extremely financially precarious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Healthcare, especially emergency care and infectious disease control, is a collective problem that we cannot ethically or practically rely on individuals being able to afford.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People who have built significant aspects of their ideology around these problems are in fact entirely justified in saying that the pandemic is proving them right all along, because these problems are real and major and the pandemic really is highlighting them, and there's nothing remotely surprising or controversial about pointing that out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I'd like to suggest though is that most other examples of people saying they've been right all along are like this too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's tempting to think of ideologies in terms of what proposals they make for radically restructing society,
but I think it's more useful to start with what their &lt;em&gt;critiques&lt;/em&gt; of society are. An ideology is, first and foremost, a set of problems that you care about. The proposals made by the ideology are, largely, grounded in those critiques and designed to solve those problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Generally critiques start from a real source of pain, and a more or less accurate understanding of the world.
Sometimes that pain is one we want to consider "invalid" (e.g. it's selfish), sometimes that more or less accurate understanding of the world is less more and more less, but on the whole society is messed up in too many different ways for people to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html"&gt;nerd&lt;/a&gt; about all of them, so you end up with a lot of specialist bodies of knowledge each focused on a specific critique, so it's not surprising that this results in a lot of different ideologies.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People's intuition is that all of these ideologies can't be right at the same time, and in some sense that's true,
but I think it misunderstands the nature of ideological conflict.
Ideologies come into conflict in (at least) two different ways:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have incompatible critiques.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have incompatible solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first absolutely happens of course - e.g. white supremacist ideologies and intersectional feminist ideologies are genuinely in conflict - but I think more often than not it's the second, and it would be perfectly plausible to synthesise the two ideologies into something workable,
because what's actually happening is that they have perfectly compatible complementary critiques of society, but the solutions they proposed don't take into account the other's critiques.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It may not be obvious from the inside that this is happening, because people overidentify problems and solutions (this happens literally all the time, not just in ideological contexts), and even once you realise it's happening it may be genuinely very hard to form that synthesis, but I think until you've done the work to diagnose a conflict it can be worth assuming that this is what's happening - it makes it easier to extend empathy across ideological differences and to learn from other people's critiques of society.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Backtracking to COVID-19 this is, I think, why most people are treating it as evidence that they were right all along:
Their critiques of society were, within their own values, actually pretty accurate, in ways that COVID-19 is showcasing.
Society is constantly &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-04-11:18.html"&gt;skirting the edge of disaster&lt;/a&gt; and COVID-19 came in and threw a spanner in the works, so a lot of the things we did to paper over issues are now fraying, and all of the problems that they were previously noticing are suddenly brought into stark relief.
As a result nobody is going to go "Actually I was wrong, this thing I thought was a problem isn't a problem after all", because the thing they were critiquing is now if anything &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, the only way COVID-19 can really change your ideological stance is by convincing you that things you had previously dismissed as non-problems are actually problems they do need to care about. We see this happening with e.g. libertarians and anarchists who are going "Actually, most of my critiques are still valid, but you know this does seem something where massive central coordinated response is helpful. BTW have you noticed that the institutions for doing so are exactly as broken as we said they were?" (We're also seeing this with some privacy advocates who are about facing and going "Wait no surveillance is good actually" but I'm less impressed with those people).
This is largely what I was suggesting was the good sort of ideological incompatibility: The underlying critiques are perfectly compatible, we just need to figure out how to put those together in a more productive way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, in short, my ideological stance has always been that we can learn a lot from people with different problems and areas of knowledge than us, and that although it's not true that the "truth lies somewhere in the middle", we probably do need to synthesise things from a wide variety of ideologies and viewpoints if we want to come to a useful conclusion that works for everyone. Fortunately, COVID-19 has proven that I've been right about this all along.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-10-10:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
