<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-05-21T09:32:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-15-09:54.html</id>
    <title>Teach me of your human notions of love</title>
    <updated>2020-05-15T10:49:03+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Teach me of your human notions of love&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2y3eU3x"&gt;Finding Our Sea-Legs&lt;/a&gt;, p 41:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is not the oldest philosophical question in the book, but is one of the most recurrent, at least once puberty has kicked in: "What is this thing called love?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, lets see what the book has to say about it. From Tiffany Watt Smith's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Lu4EEF"&gt;The Book of Human Emotions&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there anything left to say about love? Reams of poetry and songs, libraries' worth of philosophy, are dedicated to trying to express it, to understand and define it. The very volume of words tells us not only how much there is to say on the subject, but also how little can be said with any certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thanks Tiffany, that's very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Buckingham, on page 42, suggests that unlike philosophy (which asks questions like "What is love?"), storytelling tends to ask "What is love &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt;?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He is quick to point out the flaw in this question (on page 43):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, however, we need to be philosophically cautious. The way that this second question is phrased, "What is love like?" risks seducing us into thinking that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; in fact, a single thing, love, towards which this new question will lead us. But the more we ask this kind of question, the more it becomes apparent that love is no more a single thing than is death. What emerges from our storytelling is not Love, but a multiplicity of loves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This multiplicity of loves is, I think, part of the core of the practical problems of love. In reality, we are not so much interested in the question "What is love like?" any more than we are interested in the question "What is love?". What we want to know tends to be questions more like:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they love me?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I love them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I find someone who will love me?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I love myself?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think we will find that when we ask these questions they will not always mean the the same notion of love.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Love, like most things, doesn't really have a formal definition - you can look it up in a dictionary, but dictionaries describe use rather than providing authoritative definitions, and the dictionary's selection of meanings for love are particularly useless.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most words used in practice are defined &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ostensive_definition"&gt;ostensively&lt;/a&gt;, meaning that we point to a bunch of examples and hope that you can figure out the general pattern because we sure as hell don't know how explain it to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly tricky for things which are primarily phenomenological - purely or predominantly aspects of our subjective experience. We barely have a coherent vocabulary for talking about &lt;em&gt;pain&lt;/em&gt;, and pain is at least relatively easy to reproduce on demand. How is this supposed to work for things like love, which are vastly more complicated, and which you cannot easily point to an example?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Buckingham's answer is to let go of the question and embrace this plurality. I think this concedes too much, because it runs into a substantial problem: We can &lt;em&gt;disagree&lt;/em&gt; what love is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've talked about Bell Hooks's notion of love as "The will to extend one's self for the purpose of one's own or another's spiritual growth". I think this is a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; definition. It's not true, in that I don't think one can meaningfully assign a truth value to the question of whether that is what love &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, but I think that it provides a good starting point for reasoning about many of the positive aspects of love.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it's certainly not a definition that everyone can agree on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;David Chapman talks about &lt;a href="https://meaningness.com/nebulosity"&gt;nebulosity&lt;/a&gt;, the cloudlike nature of things - clouds are ill defined at the boundary. If you ask "What is the weight of a cloud?" you will end up with uncertainty that is in some sense fundamentally ontological (concerned with categories - which bits of matter do you consider "part of the cloud"?) rather than epistemic (concerned with knowledge - trying to pin down facts of empirical reality). Some parts of reality are clearly part of the cloud, some parts of reality are clearly not part of the cloud, but at the boundary there is a region where it's... kinda part of the cloud but it's not really clear, and the answer to your question about the mass of the cloud will depend on how we decide that question of categorisation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you ask "Do I love them?" you will experience this nebulosity of love: Some people the answer is obviously no, hopefully some people the answer is obviously yes, but if you are asking the question you are probably in that boundary zone where the answer is the rather frustating "It depends what you mean by love?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But when you ask "Do they love me?" the question is more complicated yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not everyone has the same notion of love. Some notions of love are different, and some notions of love are better than others (there's no total ordering here - it's &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-17-10:16.html"&gt;very unlikely that there's a single best notion of love&lt;/a&gt;). Many notions of love that we see in common use are coercive, abusive, or proprietary. "I would love you more if you changed to be what I want", "I hurt you because I love you", or "I love you, so you are mine".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In those cases the difficulty is still one of ontology. There are still questions about where the boundary of love is, but that boundary is now not merely fuzzy but contested. This is no longer a collaboration where you are trying to pin down an area of uncertainty, but a fight over the correct positioning of that boundary.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-15-09:54.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-07:43.html</id>
    <title>Truth and the Ghost Library</title>
    <updated>2020-05-16T10:22:04+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Truth and the Ghost Library&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-16&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ritual and its Consequences, p. 162:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Fundamentalism] equates truth, which is nonindividual and supraindividual, with its interpretation, which is invariably personal and conditional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this claim is interesting and mostly true, but also mostly false. That might be because of my interpretation of it, which is invariably personal and conditional.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm reading James C. Scott's "Domination and the Arts of Resistance" at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The book, as with most of Scott's work, looks at an aspect of how people behave in response to power imbalances.
In societies when one group dominates another, such as caste societies, or historical slavery in North America,
the way those groups talk among themselves is very different from the way they talk in public.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This leads to the idea of &lt;em&gt;hidden transcripts&lt;/em&gt;.
The idea is that there is a public transcript, which is the record (usually implicit) of what goes on in public,
and the hidden transcripts, which record how the groups talk among themselves.
Both the oppressed and the oppressor have hidden transcripts that are very different from the public transcript,
which can be thought of an elaborate ritual to maintain order, in which the oppressors perform strength and the oppressed perform deference.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hidden transcripts are a key part of the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-16-14:22.html"&gt;ghost knowledge&lt;/a&gt; that pervades society - knowledge that is built and widely shared inside a community of discourse, but is never written down and is not widely known outside of that community. Unlike much ghost knowledge, which is merely &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; shared, the hidden transcripts are actively kept from those outside of the community as a protective measure.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can think of knowledge about the world as being a kind of infinite ghost library, with different groups occupying (with varying degrees of jealousy) their territories within the library.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a key part my objection to the quoted passage I opened with: Interpretation is not just personal, it's very much driven by what you know, and who you talk to. People interpret in groups, and those interpretations become hidden transcripts within the ghost library.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Scott is careful to point out that these hidden transcripts &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; don't necessarily represent any sort of "true selves" of the oppressed, but are instead another social order, which may have its own barriers to authenticity, but I do think though that there is a gradient where the more hidden a transcript it is, the more sincere it is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Scott, on page 26, lists the following under "Hypothetical Discursive Sites, Arranged by Audience, under Slavery":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harsh master/overseer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indulgent master or overseer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whites having no direct authority&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slaves and free blacks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slaves of same master&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Closest slave friends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immediate family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;With the first three being part of the public transcripts, the last three being part of the hidden ones, and the 4th straddling the two. In the public transcripts you are very much participating in the ritual order of society, but in the private ones you can break character into sincerity and talk about what's &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; going on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From this point of view, fundamentalist social orders can be thought of as access control in the ghost library: The idea that this secret body of knowledge is in some sense &lt;em&gt;immoral&lt;/em&gt;, and that that which cannot be discussed in public should not be discussed at all.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-07:43.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-12:06.html</id>
    <title>Notes on Acedia</title>
    <updated>2020-05-20T17:58:35+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes on Acedia&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-16&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2X2QOP2"&gt;Leisure: The Basis of Culture&lt;/a&gt; which is a strange book, which I'll be exploring a different angle on in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/"&gt;my newsletter&lt;/a&gt; on Monday, but one thought from it that I thought was interesting and worth exploring further was the idea of &lt;em&gt;acedia&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This post is just some gathering of notes from different sources related to the subject, plus some vague thoughts..&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acedia"&gt;Wikipedia entry on acedia&lt;/a&gt; has the following to say:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acedia (/əˈsiːdiə/; also accidie or accedie /ˈæksɪdi/, from Latin acedĭa, and this from Greek ἀκηδία, "negligence", ἀ- "lack of" -κηδία "care") has been variously defined as a state of listlessness or torpor, of not caring or not being concerned with one's position or condition in the world. In ancient Greece akidía literally meant an inert state without pain or care. Early Christian monks used the term to define a spiritual state of listlessness and from there the term developed a markedly Christian moral tone. In modern times it has been taken up by literary figures and connected to depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The wikipedia article &lt;a href="http://www.hermitary.com/solitude/acedia.html"&gt;cites what is apparently a blog for hermits&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acedia (or accedie) has a narrow religious definition but is a far larger and wider psychological and spiritual term relevant to the history of eremiticism and solitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrow sense is that of sloth, indolence, laziness, as in the Western world's list of seven capital sins. Eastern Christianity is a little more comprehensive in referring to seven "temptations." Acedia is a psychological rather than moral condition, with implications for modern attitudes toward culture, conformity, and contentment. Acedia was a historical bane to monks, hermits, solitaries, and -- by extension -- to any one spiritually or intellectually inclined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of acedia begins with the ever-observant desert fathers and mothers who first perceived and diagnosed the condition. Their first impulse was to shoo it away like a pesky insect by keeping occupied, as in the narrative of Anthony beset "by many sinful thoughts" and cured by angelic advice to stay busy  plaiting rope. Poemen avers that "acedia is there every time one begins something, and there is no worse passion, but if one recognizes it for what it is, one will gain peace." And John Cassian adds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also good to recall what Abba Moses, one of the most experienced of the fathers, told me. I had not been living long in the desert when I was troubled by listlessness [i.e., acedia]. So I went to him and said: Yesterday I was greatly troubled and weakened by listlessness, and I was not able to free myself from it until I went to see Abba Paul. Abba Moses replied to me by saying: So far from freeing yourself from it, you have surrendered to it completely and become its slave. You must realize that it will attack all the more severely because you have deserted your post, unless from now on you strive to subdue it through patience, prayer and manual labor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly acedia is not willful sloth or indolence, less so "sin," but a spiritual lethargy or indifference, a turpitude that affects the well-intentioned. Amma Theodora says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should realize that as soon as you intend to live in peace, at once evil comes and weighs down your soul through acedia, faint-heartedness, and evil thoughts. It also attacks your body through sickness, debility, weakening of the knees, and all the members. It dissipates the strength of soul and body. ... But if we are vigilant, all the temptations fall away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A practical experience of acedia is described by the desert hermit Heraclides, who received a brother troubled by restlessness in his new cell. Heraclides advised him not to follow an extreme regimen of self-discipline but to eat, drink, and sleep as needed. He only asked that the brother not leave his cell. But, the narrator tells us, the brother fell "prey to acedia" and doubted the old man's advice. The brother followed his regimen but when he went to bed he found a demon lying on it, gnashing its teeth at him. The brother fled his cell to the old man's dwelling, imploring his help. Heraclides, seeing that the younger man had not followed his counsel to stay in his cell, refused to open, but the next morning, finding him still at the doorstep, Heraclides took pity on him. "Then, according to his capacity, he taught him the discipline of the solitary life, and in a short time he became a good monk."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Cassian went further than his conversation with Abba Moses to describe the physical symptoms so literally, even to the hour of the day when they peak, that acedia became known as the "noonday devil." He provides an excellent description of the psychology of acedia as well, indicating that acedia is a "tedium or perturbation of heart ... akin to dejection and especially felt by wandering monks and solitaries, a persistent and obnoxious enemy to such as dwell in the desert." He goes on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this [acedia] besieges the unhappy mind, it begets aversion from the place, boredom with one's cell, and scorn and contempt for one's brethren, whether they be dwelling with one or some way off, as careless and unspiritual-minded persons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The listlessness of acedia is akin to a feeling of inertness, John Cassian notes, producing no spiritual fruit, a sense of any practice being "empty of spiritual profit." John's remedy, following desert tradition, is a level of sustained activity approximating rigorous physical labor and what were to be called works of mercy, which fend off cynicisms. Physical labor as a solution is seen in the example of the first Christian desert hermit Paul, who regularly wove baskets of palm leaves. But being too far from a market to sell them Paul would burn his handiwork once a year and start over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In The Book of Human Emotions, page 16, Tiffany Watt Smith describes it as:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acedia (pronounced a-seed-ee-a) or sometimes called accidie, is an emotion that has no real equivalent today. It was a short-lived but disastrous emotional crisis, usually striking between 11AM and 4PM. Its first signs were listeness and irritability, but it didn't take long to turn into desolation and despair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the sixth century =, acedia was dropped from the list of mortal sins. Some of its symptoms were absorbed into the illness melancholia, a forerunner to our own states of depression and anxiety (see: MELANCHOLY). The rest became the moral vice sloth. Though people still spoke of feeling acedia, it came to mean something more like inertia - an equivalent, perhaps, to that listless feeling which descends on a rainy Sunday morning (see: APATHY).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In "Leisure: The Basis of Culture" acedia is introduced as follows (p27):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did the old code of conduct mean by idleness, by &lt;em&gt;acedia&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, it meant something other than we usually mean when we speak of the "root of all evils."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Idleness, for the older code of behavior, meant especially this: that the human being had given up on the very responsibility that comes with his dignity: that he does not want to be what God wants him to be, and that means that he does not want to be what he really, and in the ultimate sense, &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Acedia&lt;/em&gt; is the "despair of weakness," of which Kierkegaard said that it consists in someone "despairingly" not wanting "to be oneself". The metaphysical-theological concept of idleness means, then, that man finally does not agree with his own existence; that behind all his energetic activitity, he is not at one with himself; that, as the Middle Ages expressed it, sadness has seized him in the face of the divine Goodness that lives within him - and this sadness is that "sadness of the world" spoken of in the bible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In Voices: The Educational Formation of Conscience, Thomas Green has a slightly different take (p. 40):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[When one behaves correctly but does not care to be correct] the internal speech of the self would be: "It doesn't really matter, but this is the way they like it. I know what they want, so I'll go along with this senseless charade even though nothing vital is at stake." Such a posture of detachment is the perspective of the uninvolved, the apathetic. It is the condition of anomie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key to this interior speech is found in that indefinite, obscure, omnipresent, and distant 'they'. How remote, how disguised, 'they' always are! How senseless; yet, at the same time, how pervasive are the norms of everyday life when viewed simply as the edicts that 'they' deliver, and how thoroughly, under like circumstances, do those edicts lack even the most minute measure of moral authority! This condition, as nearly as I can describe it, is closely related to a kindred state that the medievals describe as &lt;em&gt;acedia&lt;/em&gt;. i.e., a kind of spiritual torpor or sickness that nowadays is often expressed as &lt;em&gt;ennui&lt;/em&gt; or boredom. The ancient idea extended, however, to something more fundamental even than mere boredom. It included the notion of a certain rebellion, a condition of being asleep to life, a resolute rejection of any possible contentment with being what one is, namely, a human being and thus essentially a creature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Both Green and Pieper seem to be framing acedia as a form of disconnection from sources of meaning. For Pieper this source of meaning is spiritual, for Green it is full participation as a member in a normative community.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's interesting that the hermitage site suggests working with your hands as an antidote to acedia.
I'm put in mind of Matthew Crawford's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3bzPSqt"&gt;Shop Class as Soulcraft&lt;/a&gt; where he argues that professions that are very hands on are in fact much more nourishing sources of meaning than office work (I do not especially recommend this book, although there are things I like about it).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm also put in mind of James C. Scott's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2X0qAN3"&gt;Two Cheers For Anarchism&lt;/a&gt;, where he argues that we should think about work not solely in terms of its productivity, but in terms of its effect on workers:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we were to ask a different question of institutions and activities than the narrow neoclassical question of how efficient they are in terms of costs (e.g. resources, labor, capital) per unit of a given, specified product? What if we were to ask what kind of people a given activity or institution fostered? Any activity we can imagine, any institution, no matters what its manifest purpose, is also, willy-nilly, transforming people:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[the assembly line] was deliberately designed to eliminate the artisanal-craft knowledge, and the power this knowledge conferred on workers, that characterized the carriage-making era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Lx4yMm"&gt;Talking About Machines&lt;/a&gt; Julian Orr describes such a community of artisanal-craft knowledge, in the form of photocopier technicians at Xerox PARC. These technicians clearly have both Scott's artisanal-craft knowledge and Green's normation to a community of practice. Reading Orr's descriptions of it, the technicians certainly &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; satisfied with their jobs, but it's also very clear that management would really rather not have to deal with the complex messy realities of depending on an actual community of experts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm additionally put in mind of Rebecca Solnit's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Ar3MOL"&gt;A Paradise Built in Hell&lt;/a&gt; where she talks about the communities that arise in disasters, where she shows how people band together towards a common cause, and find it a powerful source of meaning - in many ways the aftermath of a disaster is a positive experience for people in these communities.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Pieper argues that Total Work is the source of this acedia, or perhaps that acedia is the source of total work, but it seems to me that communities of people working together towards a common cause, in ways that allow each of us to grow as a person, are in fact the &lt;em&gt;cure&lt;/em&gt; for acedia, and the problem is perhaps not work per se but the way that power has reshaped work into something that treats workers as a resource to extract value from instead of people to develop alongside.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-12:06.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-17-11:45.html</id>
    <title>Requiem for a pair of trousers</title>
    <updated>2020-05-17T14:14:26+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Requiem for a pair of trousers&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Based on random prompting this morning think today's post is supposed to be about using stories to communicate philosophical ideas, but I don't wanna, so instead I'm going to tell you a story to communicate philosophical ideas.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've spent about the last 45 minutes sitting out in the sun destroying a pair of trousers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't a euphemism, or a side effect, or anything else. I was literally sitting there in my garden taking a seam ripper to a pair of trousers, taking it apart for spare material.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The trousers were dying - there was a hole in the crotch, and the surrounding material was thin enough that if I'd patched it it'd probably have just ripped again. I didn't have any material to make a patch, and also the trousers weren't very good (and were a little tight) in the first place so I probably wouldn't have worn them even once patched. I have vague intentions of using some of the material to make home made face masks, but I'm not sure how suitable it will actually be for that, and most of it won't be used that way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't get very far. So far I've removed the back pockets and the zip and some of the other parts have been partially separated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is no sense in which this is a reasonable use of my time. I'm not especially good at sewing, or in this case unsewing. I could buy a cloth facemask for not that much money. If you look at the day rate I could charge a software company for my consulting services I could probably have bought two new pairs of trousers for the price.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These trousers came from somewhere. There's no spontaneous generation of trousers - someone sewed these together somewhere. Probably, I must admit, in a sweatshop. They're from Gap, who I doubt have the most ethical of production practices (there's a high cost in human suffering for the prevalence of cheap clothing. I'd be lying if I said I was very good at taking that into account in my purchasing habits).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've probably already spent more disassembling these trousers than that unknown factory worker spent assembling them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It may interest you to know that I'm alternating writing this post with continuing my trouser disassembly project. I just removed a belt loop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It probably doesn't interest you to know this. That's OK. There is probably no sense in which reading this post is a reasonable use of your time either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I said there was no sense in which disassembling these trousers was a reasonable use of my time, but actually that's not true. There are two important senses:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to do it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I feel better for having done so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It certainly wasn't &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; reasonable spending time doing this than it would have been, say, watching TV, or playing a game. I'm not going to claim it was more reasonable, but it's still something that could be considered a leisure activity for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wrote yesterday about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-12:06.html"&gt;acedia&lt;/a&gt;, the sense of being disconnected from sources of meaning, and how working with your hands is one possible antidote to that. I'm not going to claim trouser disassembly is the great cure for modern ills, but there's definitely something nice about sitting in the garden with your hands occupied, thinking as you work on semi autopilot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't know how to use a seam ripper before this. I was vaguely aware seam rippers were a thing, but I had to look them up in order to figure out that I already owned one in my sewing kit. So one nice side effect of this is that I now know how to use a seam ripper.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was going to say that this was completely useless knowledge, but then I realised that actually I could use the seam ripper to remove the label from the inside T-shirt I was wearing, which has a really weirdly annoyingly large label.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I forgot that the seams on labels are usually structural - they're not added on top of the seam they're attached to, but are sewn directly into it, so now I have a hole in my T-shirt that I need to sew up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is probably a metaphor for something, but I don't know what.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-17-11:45.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-18-09:41.html</id>
    <title>Bug Fixes and Performance Improvements</title>
    <updated>2020-05-18T12:46:52+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Bug Fixes and Performance Improvements&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-18&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today we release Version 37.0 of the DRMacIver software system. We've been working on it for a whole year, and are pretty excited to share the results with you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In reality we of course practice continuous deployment and so have been rolling out releases through the entirety of the last year, and all of our changes are breaking changes so there's no hint of semantic versioning in our release process, but nevertheless bumping the major version number is a good chance to talk about some of the exciting new developments over the last year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The major improvements we've seen since the Version 36.0 release are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We've refactored an awful lot of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;legacy code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Significantly improved write performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modest improvements to read performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We've fixed the bug where the brain randomly crashed in social situations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The system has finally &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/"&gt;evolved to the point where it can send email&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In case you don't get the joke (you probably get the joke) it's my 37th birthday today. Today is, legally speaking, the year where I have to start saying I'm in my mid to late 30s rather than in my mid 30s.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in ancient times, when I were a wee lad in my late 20s, I used to say that I didn't really mind the idea of hitting 30 (back then 30 seemed very old) because the people I knew in their 30s were mostly like the people I knew in their 20s only they had their shit a bit more together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I then spent the first half of my thirties with my shit &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; not together - life went a bit sideways in the dying months of 29 and it took me about five years before I hit rock bottom enough to start doing something about it.
The result was me rather disconnecting from people emotionally, and it didn't have a great impact on my career either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People don't really notice that I'm not a software developer any more, partly because I only became famous as a software developer after I stopped being one. Officially &lt;a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/lp/python-developers-survey-2019/"&gt;4% of Python developers are running my code&lt;/a&gt;. I wrote that code &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/i/status/1194550244496814081"&gt;entirely after burning out&lt;/a&gt;. I haven't actually been employed as a software developer since early 2015, outside of the occasional short term contract for Hypothesis work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something about the software development industry that burns people out. I don't know what it is, but it does it to most people. Maybe every industry is like this and I just mostly see it in the one I know? Maybe it's just &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-12:06.html"&gt;acedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I started to pull myself out of the hole around 2017 I guess - I moved back to London, started a PhD, kinda started seeing people. In late 2018 I started a new relationship, which has been going very well.
It prompted some reflection, and I've spent a lot of the intervening period attempting to sort my shit out in the way that a decade ago I, apparently, naively assumed would come with age.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is it working? I guess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of why I wrote &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-07-07:57.html"&gt;Easy Changes and Uncomfortable Reflections&lt;/a&gt; was that it was what I needed to hear (that's why I write a lot of these posts). It's quite hard to escape the feeling that I could have done all this work seven years ago, or seventeen years ago, or even twenty seven years ago, and life would have gone a lot better for it. I think this is partly true, but mostly false, but it still feels like a wasted opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today's Tarot draw (I've been doing daily draws even when they've not made it into the notebook) is the &lt;a href="http://www.learntarot.com/ca.htm"&gt;Ace of Cups&lt;/a&gt;, which signifies among other things getting in touch with your feelings. Well I've done that. It's got its good points, and there's yet more to do on that front, but also it kinda sucks in that one of the major downsides of becoming more in touch with your own feelings is that you're more aware of your feelings, and sometimes those feelings are bad. I think I've in many ways been less depressed over the last year than I've been... ever, possibly, but it doesn't necessarily &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like that because I'm more aware of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Especially given, as you might have noticed, there's a global pandemic on at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This post was meant to be reasonably optimistic - I do think that the next few years will be quite good for me - but entering my late thirties in the middle of a global pandemic feels weird. I can barely predict what next week is going to look like, let alone the next three years.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All told, I'm doing what I can to lay a solid foundation for whatever comes next. It might even work.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-18-09:41.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-19-09:35.html</id>
    <title>Working with the audience</title>
    <updated>2020-05-19T10:52:04+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Working with the audience&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From Lois McMaster Bujold's "A Civil Campaign", page 137:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Madame Vorsoisson", Mark said with dignity, "is a very sensible woman. When presented with compelling facts, &lt;em&gt;she&lt;/em&gt; doesn't let a thoughtless emotional response overcome her clear reason."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"A Civil Campaign" is probably my favourite book in the Vorkosigan series. The Vorkosigan series is largely an "Adventures! In! Space!" series, but as it goes on there's increasingly fewer adventures in favour of exploring the lives of the characters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Adventures in A Civil Campaign primarily center on a number of things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Planning for the imperial wedding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Miles (the protagonist of the series) attempting to woo the aforementioned Madame Vorsoisson, with a thoroughly inappropriately military approach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark (Miles's clone/brother) attempting an early stage biotech startup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many exciting politics as a hereditary patriarchal nobility adjusts to things like gene tests and gender changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probably some other things I'm forgetting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This exchange is about the third. Mark has just fed Ekaterin (Madame Vorsoisson) some of his startup's food product. It is a vaguely pleasing but mostly a bit bland product that I imagine as being a bit like cream cheese.
The product is nutritious, flexible, cheap to produce, and has significant environmental benefits.
It should be a miracle product that will make Mark extremely successful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also it comes from bugs. The bugs are particularly disgusting looking. They call it bug butter. The bugs are called butter bugs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, they're trying to sell their product made from genetically engineered bugs on a planet that regards mutations with visceral horror.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ekaterin has, kindly, reacted primarily to the quality of the bug butter as a food product rather than its origins. Miles and everyone else have reacted with horror to the name, the branding, and the general visceral association of the food product with its origins (it's vomited up by horrifying bug creatures).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mark believes that Ekaterin is in the right and that Miles and the others are in the wrong. Mark is wrong. Mark is bad at startups.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Oh, Ekaterin is of course behaving very well. It's &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; to be able to suspend emotional reactions and look at the potential in a situation. However, Mark is conflating how he feels people &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; react to his product with how people are actually going to react to his product. Miles and everyone else are providing him with valuable insight.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mark does eventually turn this around, mostly because of Ekaterin's help on branding, but without her he would have been insisting that people are reacting to his actions &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; and complaining about the unfairness of it all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an easy trap to fall in to, both in startups and in general: If people react badly to your actions that &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be unfair, and it's legitimate to feel aggrieved about it, but ultimately at some point you need to ask whether you want to have an impact or not, and if you want to have an impact it's usually better to ask how you can effectively work with people's reactions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's all very well to demand that people react to your actions differently, but it doesn't usually work. If you want to change the world, if you want people to use your product, you need to start from where you are and work with the audience you have. Even if you do, ultimately, want to change their behaviour, you're not generally going to get there by demanding that they comply - you need to instead work with rather than against their existing reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-19-09:35.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-19-17:31.html</id>
    <title>Parts of you are missing</title>
    <updated>2020-05-19T18:34:29+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Parts of you are missing&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's an article that was going around earlier in The Current Situation: &lt;a href="https://hbr.org/2020/03/that-discomfort-youre-feeling-is-grief"&gt;That Discomfort You’re Feeling Is Grief&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't find the article itself very useful or interesting, but the title stuck with me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's an idea called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transactive_memory"&gt;Transactive Memory&lt;/a&gt; - often we don't remember things, we remember who to ask about them. In a team, or in a relationship, there are many things where we are offloading our memories to the people around us. The group as a whole remembers things, and we are able to rely on that. The group as a whole functions as an extended part of the minds of each person within it - I don't need to know the details of that aspect of the project, because I know who does and I can talk to them about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Couples in particular form complex webs of transactive memory, where they each remember details about their shared lives and responsibilities, and each delegate parts of that memory to the other. Some of these are very practical: One of you knows about the accounts, one of you knows what to do when the boiler breaks. Some of these are more emotional - one of you has a better memory for the places you've been, and when you share stories they fill in the rich details.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And then one of you dies, or leaves, and all of a sudden there are holes in your memory. Every time you reach for the parts of your memory that live outside your body, you find an uncomfortable absence. That discomfort you're feeling is grief.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It goes beyond memory. We are social creatures, and we integrate other people into our lives. Into our selves. We talk to each other, we help each other process our feelings.
When we interact &lt;a href="https://www.brainpickings.org/2015/10/21/telling-is-listening-ursula-k-le-guin-communication/"&gt;we join together&lt;/a&gt;, becoming more than the sum of our parts, and each of us brings part of that whole into ourselves.
Being with others is an opportunity to be different versions of our selves,
letting the whole create an environment that brings out a different aspect of who we are.
Many of our &lt;a href="https://www.rewriting-the-rules.com/self/new-year-new-zine-plural-selves/"&gt;plural selves&lt;/a&gt; only come out in environments that give them the support they need to be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Oh, those other people who bring them out aren't necessarily &lt;em&gt;gone&lt;/em&gt;. Certainly many people have died of COVID-19 or its social fallout, but that is a less complicated and more intense sort of grief. For most of us the people are there, and we're even talking to them, but it's not the same.
We're talking to them over text, or phone, or Zoom, and that's good and it is good that we are doing it, but it isn't the same.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-13-09:56.html"&gt;talked about books&lt;/a&gt; before, and how wrong our ideas of reading are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading is not an act conducted by a pure mind engaging with an idealised platonic flow of information. Reading is an active engagement between a physical body and a physical object. The purpose of reading is to engage with the content, but reading itself is a physical act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If this is true for books, how much more so for people?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Have you ever tried to have a conversation where one of you is typing and the other speaking? It's almost impossibly frustrating for the typist. You're so limited in what you can say - it's slower and less expressive. It's like speaking in a language you understand but are not fluent in. Only a fraction of what you want comes through.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The minds we create together over the internet are interesting and powerful and they have many positive characteristics that it is hard to create in person, but they have many weaknesses over in person communication too. They lack some of the strengths that we need to support ways we could be in person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Can you touch someone over Zoom? Can you dance with them? "Body language" is not just a metaphor - the presence of the other in your world is a key part of how we relate to each other.
Long distance relationships are, of course, possible, but the longer we have been apart, the more our memory of each other's physicality fades, the harder it is to become the person that we allow each other to be. We try to hold on to it as best we can, but memory can only take us so far. The ghosts of our absent selves are a comfort, to be sure, but they are also a reminder of absence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not even just people. A thing that is especially visible as a mathematician, but is true for most people, is how much of the work of thought lives outside your head. A mathematician without pencil and paper (or a blackboard, or an equivalent) is not a mathematician, they are merely the potential to be one. A swimmer without water cannot swim, cannot become the version of themself that swims.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When we shop, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1248560936102887424"&gt;we become the supermarket&lt;/a&gt;. That part of you is missing too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When we are cut from our environment, we lose the parts of ourself that the environment allowed us to be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of the parts that are missing we will meet again, and it will be a joyous reunion. Some we are glad to be rid of. But they are still missing, and we can feel their absence, and the memory of what it was like to be them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We are all, desperately, trying to find replacements for the parts of us that are missing - new versions of our self that we can be in the environment that we have access to. Some of those versions will be delightful new discoveries that we are happy to meet. Some of them will be mere shadows of the versions we would rather be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But either way, they are parts that we had grown used to, familiar parts that we were able to embody at need, and every time we would want to slip into that way of being, and can't, we are reminded of that absence. Parts of us are missing, and that feeling of discomfort we experience from it is grief.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-19-17:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-09:54.html</id>
    <title>Morality and Emotion</title>
    <updated>2020-05-20T10:45:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Morality and Emotion&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3g53ayI"&gt;Voices: The Educational Formation of Conscience&lt;/a&gt;, page 18:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"What is my duty?" is made, by many accounts, the entry question into philosophical ethics. For a philosophy of moral education, however, entry is gained more fully through the Socratic question, "How ought one to live?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The distinction that Green is drawing in this book is between philosophy of ethics, which develops ethical theories of what it is like to behave ethically, and philosophy of moral education, which asks how people learn to behave ethically.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is intimately tied to my point in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-10-08:54.html"&gt;How to become a better person&lt;/a&gt; that as well as a &lt;em&gt;theory&lt;/em&gt; of ethics we need a &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; of ethics.
A philosophy of moral education is not necessarily that practice, but it is at least less far removed from it:
If you ask "What is my duty?", an answer can assume that part of your duty is that you are responsible for figuring out how to uphold your other duties. If you ask "How should I live?", you might quite reasonably object if the answer is a little light on practical details about how, exactly, you are supposed to be able to live in the manner described.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something about the question "How ought one to live?" that feels hopelessly naive and/or oppressive these days. Who are you to tell me what to do?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; in particular feels dangerous. It feels like a question that can only be asked in the presence of a certain amount of coercive power - as if whatever answer you give to the question, that's the answer you're going to impose on others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that, there can be no single &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt;, because are all different people with different desires and constraints. The idea of a one sized fits all "best life" seems both impossible and undesirable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And yet, I still think there's something there. Perhaps not "How ought one to live?" but "How can one figure out how to live?" or "What tools are there to figure out how to live?" or "How can we help people live their best lives?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think we underestimate the interplay between morality and emotional health. Many of our strongest emotions and feelings have a moral component. Guilt and shame, certainly, but also love and empathy. Emotions and morality interplay strongly as we act in the world, especially with regards to other people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suggested in "How to be a better person" that improving your emotional skills would probably automatically make you a better person, but I think the converse might be true too: Becoming a better person will improve your emotional health (as long as it's paired with good skills for working with emotions - I still think those are the foundations).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-12:06.html"&gt;acedia&lt;/a&gt;. I think one of the causes of acedia is living out of line with our values - sometimes because our values are bad, sometimes because we are forced to, and sometimes because it is easier to ignore that dissonance than deal with them. We learn not to care as a defence mechanism, and bringing ourselves more in line with our values allows us to repair some of that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another part is the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety&lt;/a&gt; model. Emotional skills are what provide you with safety to become better, but others are often the spur for that. Certainly much of my current growth came from having people who I wanted to be better for.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my first read of Green &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/jiminy-cricket-must-die/"&gt;I was pretty negative about some of this themes&lt;/a&gt;. I still think that's right - a great deal of his work is about how we adopt a community's norms, and my experience is that most communities' norms are very unsafe to internalise. My current read is more sympathetic: I still think moral norms are dangerous tools that are often misused, but I think they also might be a key part of finding our way to better lives as long as we can find the right people to develop them with.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-09:54.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-17:58.html</id>
    <title>How I fix anxiety triggers</title>
    <updated>2020-05-20T19:57:16+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How I fix anxiety triggers&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a sketch of the skillset I use to deal with anxiety. It works well when:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anxiety is at a level that I can deal with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is anxiety &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I currently feel vaguely anxious. Not sure what about. It's not especially hard to deal with, I'm just noticing a certain tension in my shoulders and that I feel slightly on edge. This is undirected anxiety, and I don't currently have a good skillset for dealing with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm currently putting off a whole bunch of accounting stuff because accounting stuff makes me super anxious and I don't &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to deal with it. I should do this, but I haven't, and forcing myself into doing it is probably not helpful for dealing with my anxiety on the subject.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might not be me, and have different sets of problems as a result. I'm reasonably confident that something in this space works for fairly general reasons, but I can't promise that doing exactly what I do will work for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Basic Procedure&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The procedure is very simple:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice that a thing is triggering anxiety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figure out &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it's triggering anxiety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask if the current situation is actually one I need to be anxious about.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If yes, keep being anxious, taking appropriate steps to increase your safety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If no, stop being anxious, and also be less anxious in similar situations in future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All three of these are very simple but they are not easy and require developing some foundational skills that I'll talk about at the end.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does it work? In my experience, pretty reliably, as long as you can actually work through the procedure (which can be both intellectually and emotionally difficult).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Why does this work?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic philosophical premises of this are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anxiety is not in and of itself bad. Anxiety is your reaction to being in a dangerous situation, making you aware of it so that you can be prepared. It is good to be aware of when you are in a dangerous situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your brain does not do a perfectly rational threat assessment of the situation, it learns simple pattern matching rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When a rule is active you can change it by better understanding the situation and gently guiding yourself towards understanding why it doesn't apply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(3) is the basic idea behind &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/i9xyZBS3qzA8nFXNQ/book-summary-unlocking-the-emotional-brain"&gt;coherence therapy&lt;/a&gt;: You can retrain emotions when they are triggered.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've previously explained the idea that your bundle of emotional reactions are a messy complex system that you can debug and refactor in the previous three posts:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;Emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html"&gt;Your emotions are valid but probably wrong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;Alief/Belief Coherence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What doesn't work&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The main thing that people try to do with anxiety is suppress it. This doesn't work, and probably makes your anxiety worse, for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It causes you to ignore anxiety in unsafe situations where it's actually worth being anxious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you can only fix reactions when they're active, if you succeed at suppressing a reaction it'll just come back later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotions tend to rise to the level that is required to get us to do something about them, so this will tend to make anxiety worse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately because we've got into the habit of treating anxiety itself as the problem, this is the natural thing to do. My instinct is that you are better off palliating to deal with the anxious situation or avoiding it entirely rather than trying to suppress it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Foundational Skills&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although the procedure is simple, it requires some relatively difficult foundational skills:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-compassion, the ability to talk compassionately and without judgement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focusing, the ability to use felt sense and verbalisation to understand your own feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discomfort tolerance, the ability to remain uncomfortable without treating it as an emergency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noticing triggers, the ability to explicitly notice and identify triggered states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I talked about some of these in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/01/a-crash-course-in-having-feelings/"&gt;A Crash Course in Having Feelings&lt;/a&gt;. I don't necessarily have good advice beyond that post on how to develop these skills, but some books that I found helpful in learning about each of these are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-compassion: &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3g52wRL"&gt;Rewriting the Rules&lt;/a&gt; by Meg-John Barker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focusing: &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3cPJEnN"&gt;Focusing&lt;/a&gt; by Eugene Gendlin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discomfort Tolerance: &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2ZlZ2EB"&gt;Conflict is not Abuse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noticing triggers: &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/36ghhg9"&gt;Complex PTSD: From Surviving to Thriving&lt;/a&gt; (I'd probably recommend starting with &lt;a href="https://www.rewriting-the-rules.com/self/trauma-and-cptsd-101/"&gt;Meg-John Barker's Post on this&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But to be honest I think with all of these the real way to get good at them is just to practice. Of these I'd most strongly recommend "A Crash Course in Having Feelings", "Focusing", and MJB's post on trauma. The others were important to my development, but I read a lot of books so that's relatively cheap for me, and was only really a way to get started. The best thing for actually developing these skills was to use them in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-17:58.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-21-09:32.html</id>
    <title>Against the Classification of Books</title>
    <updated>2020-05-21T09:32:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Against the Classification of Books&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-21&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2ylGMjz"&gt;How to Read a Book&lt;/a&gt;, p 64:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have already discussed a rough classification of books. The main distinction, we said, was between works of fiction, on the one hand, and works conveying knowledge, or expository works, on the other hand. Among expository works, we can further distinguish history from philosophy, and both from science and mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is part of a general section about how analytical reading should start with the question "What sort of book is this?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On page 60, they list this as the first rule of analytical reading:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must know what kind of book you are reading, and you should know this as early in the process as possible, preferably before you begin to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The authors do not, frankly, justify this very well. At the end of this chapter their argument is this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, just as there is a difference in the art of teaching in different fields, so there is a reciprocal difference in the art of being taught. The activity of the student must somehow be responsive to the activity of the instructor. The relation between books and their readers is the same as that between teachers and their students. Hence, as books differ in the kinds of knowledge they have to communicate, they proceed to instruct us differently; and, if we are to follow them, we must learn to read each kind in an appropriate manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To which I offer the following responses:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A book is not a person, and our relationship is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different to that of a person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The argument is nonsense for people too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can engage with a book however you like. There's no moral obligation to engage with a book as the authors want you to - if you want to read a book of science through a literary criticism lens, or a book of literary criticism through a scientific lens, you can.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even the practical vs theoretical distinction is dubious: I read a lot of philosophy. This philosophy is, for the most part, eminently theoretical, but I am reading it for practical reasons, to help me make sense of things. This requires me to do a lot of translation by doing the active work of framing practical situations using the tools provided.
This is not a style of engagement that a philosopher would generally be receptive to (it depends on the philosopher of course) and they would probably find it quite frustrating. A book can't be frustrated with me, so I'm free to use it however I like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's certainly true that treating a science book as a science book and a piece of literature as a piece of literature will result in results that are more... in line with the intent of the author I guess, and you should probably do that more often than not - it's useful to learn the norms before you violate them - but they don't necessarily produce more &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; outcomes, and different reads will tend to help you
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-24-10:37.html"&gt;bridge the gaps between different areas of knowledge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second problem is that the idea that coarse grained classifications are anything like enough. People have very individual styles and, yes, those are rooted in their communities of practice, but those communities of practice are only loosely defined by disciplines - they're often very different between subdisciplines, departments, individual teacher / student lineages, etc. You need to do at least as much work to identify those individual differences in engagement as you do to identify the genre.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead of asking "What sort of book is this?" I think the questions you should be asking are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can I engage with this book in a way that I want to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If not, where can I learn the skills for doing so?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Knowing what sort of book it is &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be helpful for answering the question, but often it is going to be much more about your relationship to the subject matter than it is about the type of book per se.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-21-09:32.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
