<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-03-06T09:49:38+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html</id>
    <title>The fastest way to learn something is to do something</title>
    <updated>2020-02-26T16:22:35+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The fastest way to learn something is to do something&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you have a problem to solve. What do you do?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, you sit down and think real hard,
and after extensive and careful planning you try the well thought out and rigorous solution that you have thought up.
Right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No, wrong! Bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The correct thing to do when you have a problem is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think for a &lt;em&gt;short&lt;/em&gt; amount of time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure it is safe to try things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try something you think will work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Observe the result.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you succeeded, yay you solved the problem!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it didn't work, think about what that means for the nature of the problem and try again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every attempt to solve the problem is an opportunity to learn about the nature of the problem,
and the nature of the tools you can use for solving problems in general.
It will often teach you &lt;em&gt;significantly&lt;/em&gt; more than either sitting and thinking about the problem or trying a less directed experiment will.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Caveats&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Obviously there is a place for learning about things that is less connected to a specific problem (given the number of books I read for general interest I would be a hypocrite to claim otherwise). Additionally, some problems are not well suited to this because e.g. They are high risk or they are long cycle time, but even then there will usually be subproblems like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason this is quite as strident as it is is as a necessary corrective to a tendency that most people have to overplan and get too hung up on finding the "right" solution. The lessons on &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;cost of decision making&lt;/a&gt; apply in spades to solving problems.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-27-17:48.html</id>
    <title>Supersaturation of knowledge</title>
    <updated>2020-02-27T18:56:35+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Supersaturation of knowledge&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something interesting that happens when you read at the rate that I do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You might expect that the amount of knowledge you get out of reading scales linearly with the rate you read,
and in some sense this is true, but there is a major qualitative change that happens to me once I start reading fast enough (multiple books a week, ideally related), and the metaphor I use for this is &lt;em&gt;supersaturation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Supersaturation is when you have more solute dissolved in a solution than is strictly supposed to be there at the current temperature.
It's a very unstable state - if you add a bit more of the dissolved substance, give it a sharp tap, or sometimes just look at it funny, suddenly you get a huge crystal formation. It's pretty cool, and yet for some reason all the youtube videos about it are &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; bad, so I can't link you to a demo. Take my word for it though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the thing about reading at a high rate is that it feels like it creates supersaturation in my brain.
Knowledge is coming in faster than it is getting banked into longer term memory and I'm still thinking about them, so I have all of these ideas that are still floating around in easy reach of eachother, until my brain feels "full" and there are too many related concepts that I'm thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And what happens then sometimes is that the right event or piece of information triggers a thought and suddenly everything connects up together and my brain fills up with new and exciting thoughts as I realise that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-24-10:37.html"&gt;everything is connected&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Things like the model described in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt; are the type of thing that come out of this, as are a number of recent helpful therapeutic realisations reading about discomfort tolerance and similar that I may write about in a future notebook post.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-27-17:48.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-28-06:33.html</id>
    <title>Culture is deeply contingent</title>
    <updated>2020-02-28T07:10:27+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Culture is deeply contingent&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an example I got from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DavidRickmann/"&gt;Dave&lt;/a&gt; recently which I thought perfectly illustrated something I've been thinking about on and off for a while, and was most recently prompted to think about in depth by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1228233781317734401"&gt;The Origins of Unfairness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you are walking down the street and someone is coming towards you, do you step left or right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, obviously you step right.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;...of course, I would say that. I'm a Londoner. If you're from a different city and you are visiting London (or, theoretically, if I were visiting your city, but as I said I'm a Londoner, we don't actually leave London).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out that which direction you step is a strong cultural norm that varies from city to city. Different cities pick different directions to step in, and it doesn't really matter which you pick as long as you all pick the same one, and because most interactions are within-city there's no strong pressure to conform between cities.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A decent lens to look at this through is evolutionary game theory. Everyone is adopting a mixed strategy where they step right with some probability \(p\).
When two people interact, if they both step the same way they reinforce the decision to step that way (increase \(p\) if they both step right, decrease it if they both step left), otherwise they move towards stepping the other way (the opposite). This is of course a toy model, but it captures the idea pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you look at the population average of \(p\), the chance that a randomly selected person will step right, what you find is that under these dynamics there are three points of equilibrium, that is points where this average remains constant over time: \(p = 0\), \(p = 1\), \(p = \frac{1}{2}\).
However, these three are not created equal:
The \(p = \frac{1}{2}\) point has two crucial features that the others lack: 1) It's much worse. People are miscuing about half the time, and everyone gets annoyed. 2) It's unstable. Although it's an equilibrium point, if you perturb it even slightly (e.g. \(p = 0.5000001\)) the value will tend to shift away over time, eventually ending up at whichever of \(p = 0\) or \(p = 1\) is on that side (this isn't quite true - if you're close enough to \(\frac{1}{2}\) randomness can cause you to switch which side you're on and oscillate for a bit, but eventually you get far enough away and from then on it's essentially a done deal).
As a result, what happens is that essentially arbitrary starting conditions get amplified into one of two simple deterministic states, where everyone adopts the same convention.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An important feature of this model is that this is &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; true in interacting populations, which is why we see different effects in different cities. There's no reason to expect people to pick the same left/right convention if they don't interact, because the convention is entirely arbitrary and has no significance except to be the same as everyone else's. Where people don't interact, they likely create different norms, because the norm is the result of a mix of evolutionary pressure on the strategies and the entirely arbitrary starting point they happened to be in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of culture is like this. It exists not because of any particularly good reason, but because you needed to do &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; and this is where you happened to end up. If culture is the way we do things around here, culture is by necessity deeply contingent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two consequences of this that matter:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you join a new culture, expect a lot of things to be different than you expect for no particularly good reason except that's how they happened to pan out here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to change a culture, think in terms of the evolutionary aspects of it. You might be able to do it by just shaking things up and letting it slide into a new equilibrium, but this only works if there's an equilibrium where you want to be. Fighting the adaptation pressure is a losing game.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-28-06:33.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html</id>
    <title>The social obligation to be bad at things</title>
    <updated>2020-02-29T10:50:52+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The social obligation to be bad at things&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-02-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A thing I got pissed off at a while ago was reactions to someone talking about having weekly one-on-ones with his wife.
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1141648249255686144"&gt;My thread about it&lt;/a&gt; went as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I honestly think this sounds like a pretty good idea - structured communication is great, and better communication with partners is also great. Even if it turns out not to work, it's something that seems at least reasonable to try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of whether it's good or not, I'm actually pretty pissed off at everyone who has been making fun of it. I am very much not here for your mocking someone's attempts to improve their communication in their relationships because you think the way they're doing it is weird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes it's framed in a very business speak language. So what? Person in taking valuable communication skills learned in one context and seeing if they can use them to make other communication in their life better shocker!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know the OP and I don't know if the way they are handling their romantic relationship(s) is healthy and productive, but what you're doing is making fun of people for being a different sort of weird than the one you approve of and it's not a good look&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was at a &lt;a href="http://www.liberatingstructures.com/"&gt;liberating structures&lt;/a&gt; event recently,
and one of the people I was working with related an anecdote in which he tried a party game as an ice breaker.
Many of those are cringe, but this one sounded fun and inoffensive (it was a sentence continuation game where each person said a word following on from a previous one, in an attempt to construct something that sounded like an aphorism).
Most people were reluctant initially but got into the swing of things, but a few people just dug their heels in and would not engage properly with it because of concern over looking weird.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But trying something new, or in a different context, is always going to look weird.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When someone tries to do something good and we don't think it's the right thing, we punish them.
When someone tries to do something and fails, we laugh at them.
This means that if you want to avoid punishment the only way is to not try until you are certain that you are doing the right thing and will succeed at it, but &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;the fastest way to learn something is to try something&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you say you are good at something, that's arrogant. When you say you're bad at something, people tell you that you're not, or treat it as weakness. This makes it very hard to talk honestly about how good you are about things,
and people are very bad at judging how good they are at things so it's very hard to know how good you are without talking about it.
Unfortunately, self-knowledge of your own abilities is also essential for getting good at it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If, despite all of this, you succeed, we put you on a pedestal, and worship you, and then as soon as you inevitably turn out to be a flawed human being like everyone else,
we tear you down and destroy you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So to recap:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be punished for trying new things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be punished for trying things that don't work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be punished for trying to understand how good you are at something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will be punished for succeeding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If I sat down and tried to design a set of social norms for discouraging people from being their best selves,
I honestly don't think I could have done a better job than this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why don't we want people to be good at things?&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-01-08:04.html</id>
    <title>There are no deterministic voting systems</title>
    <updated>2020-03-01T09:15:01+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;There are no deterministic voting systems&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-01&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As many of you are aware, one of my weird niche fandoms is random ballot, which I initially proposed &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2013/09/towards-a-more-perfect-democracy/"&gt;using for parliamentary democracy&lt;/a&gt; but am also keen on for &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2016/11/democracy-for-lunch/"&gt;deciding where to eat&lt;/a&gt; and many other decisions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the objections that I often hear to it is that people don't like nondeterminism in their voting systems.
Well, I have bad news for you: There are no deterministic voting systems.
The question is not whether you have nondeterminism, the question is how sharp the transitions between regions where the probability of an outcome is nearly deterministic are.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lets take an easy example: Suppose you have a vote between two options, and the population of voters is largeish, say a thousand people for convenience. You want to choose between these two with a simple majority.
Suppose, despite that large population, you somehow manage to get an &lt;em&gt;exact&lt;/em&gt; tie.
\(500\) people vote for the bikeshed to be blue, \(500\) for it to be orange.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What you do in this circumstance is flip a coin, right? This is a time honoured tradition for resolving ties.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, even our simple, deterministic, majority system has at least one case where it's nondeterministic. However that seems fine: In practice that doesn't really happen, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now suppose that the vote goes slightly differently and \(501\) people vote for orange and the other \(499\) vote for blue. This is a "clear" win for orange.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does it seem vastly more fair than coin flipping though? It doesn't to me, but it's OK if it does to you, and it's indeed deterministic in these regions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a problem though: The determinacy is an illusion. It's a deterministic function of &lt;em&gt;votes cast&lt;/em&gt;, it's not a deterministic function of &lt;em&gt;voters' actual beliefs&lt;/em&gt;,
it just moves the nondeterminacy from the voting system and into the voters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose voters fail to vote with a dropout rate of \(1\%\). e.g. through getting lost on the way to the ballot box, misreading the instructions, spoiling their ballot, etc.
What are the chances of orange winning now?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's some Python code for calculating these probabilities:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;numpy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;scipy.stats&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;st&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;win_probability&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dropout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.01&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="sd"&gt;"""If there are ``a`` votes for orange and ``b`` votes&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    for blue, and people drop out with a dropout rate of&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    ``dropout```, what is the probability of orange winning?&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    """&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;p_voted&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dropout&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;a_votes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;st&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;binom&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;p_voted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;b_votes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;st&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;binom&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;p_voted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;tie_possibilities&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;arange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;min&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Probability of winning from a tie is the probability&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# of the two having the same number of votes exactly&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# times half for the coin flip.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;tie_wins&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;a_votes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;pmf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;tie_possibilities&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b_votes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;pmf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;tie_possibilities&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# A clear win happens when a has strictly more votes&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# than b.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;all_possibilities&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;arange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;b_chances&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b_votes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;pmf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;all_possibilities&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;a_exceeding&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a_votes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cdf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;all_possibilities&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;clear_wins&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a_exceeding&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b_chances&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tie_wins&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;clear_wins&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can play with this a bit to get a feel for it, but the short version is that the result is nondeterministic but quite sharp. With the numbers above orange has a \(74\%\) chance of winning. If the dropout rate goes up to \(5\%\) orange has a \(61%\) chance of winnning.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast if we raise the majority to \(510\) vs \(490\) the dropout rate has to go really very high before it becomes nondeterministic. A dropout rate of \(10\%\) gives orange a \(97\%\) chance of winning, a dropout rate of \(50\%\) gives it a \(74\%\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Under this model simple majority voting is a nondeterministic system, but it's one where the curve between regions that are "morally" deterministic is very sharp. Exactly how sharp depends on the dropout rate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How high is the dropout rate in practice? Hard to say, but given that voter turnout rates in the UK seem to hover in the \(60\% - 80\%\) region, \(5\%\) seems if anything optimistically low.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;None of this is intended to suggest that because voting is intrinsically nondeterministic any nondeterminism is valid.
What I want to do by pointing this out is to shift the argument from "Is nondeterministic voting acceptable?" to "How do we want to manage nondeterminism in voting?"&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-01-08:04.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-02-09:31.html</id>
    <title>Legibility as a relationship</title>
    <updated>2020-03-02T10:36:07+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Legibility as a relationship&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An idea that has been fairly foundational to my thinking is &lt;em&gt;legibility&lt;/em&gt;, an idea introduced in James Scott's "Seeing Like a State". &lt;a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2010/07/26/a-big-little-idea-called-legibility/"&gt;Venkatesh Rao's introduction&lt;/a&gt; is probably where you need to go if you're not familiar with it. I've also &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2017/11/shaping-the-world/"&gt;previously given a talk about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've written a bit (&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2019-06-04-09:58.html"&gt;notes on the legibility war&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-23-09:37.html"&gt;legibility privileges&lt;/a&gt;) about how legibility interacts with identity, privilege, etc. What you might not have noticed in these posts is that I was using the concept "wrong".
I think my usage is better than the original, so I'd like to expand on it a bit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my usage, illegibility is the amount of work required for the entity to understand the system - a highly legible system is one that is low effort to understand.
Legibility is that which streamlines things and makes the system low effort to understand.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing about how the concept is originally used is that it treats legibility as a property of the system,
but it's not. Legibility is a property of the &lt;em&gt;relationship between the system and some entity&lt;/em&gt;.
A thing is not legible or illegible in and of itself,
it's legible or illegible to someone (or something - a government, a company, etc).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A useful analogy might be attractiveness.
Attractiveness is at a fairly fundamental level attractiveness to someone in particular,
but it still makes sense to talk about someone being more or less attractive.
People can be more or less attractive in some "objective" sense, but all that really means is that there are as many different notions of attractiveness as there are people, but there are a number of strong correlations between those different notions.
These correlations will depend strongly on local norms, and less but still strongly on a few universals,
but there will also be a huge amount of individual variation and you cannot really understand attractiveness without paying attention to that variation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Scott's work is a piece of anarchist theory, so he's particularly interested in the legibility of the relationship between a single large and powerful entity (perhaps a large company, but more ordinarily a state) and many comparatively powerless individuals, but equally important (especially to marginalised people) is the power individuals exert over each other, and focusing on legibility as a relationship.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The important point in Scott's work on legibility is that when we couple understanding to power,
we force the world to become more legible to us through our attempts to control it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A good example of this is the standardisation of weights and measures.
Prior to standardisation, there were a large number of local weights and measures with each village (and often each individual merchant!) using their own, but the government imposed a single unified standard so that, among other reasons, they could tax things properly (this is often the reason for government's imposing legibility).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly, no individual choice of weights or measures was more or less legible than any other.
The thing that created the illegibility was that people using different standards were not mutually intelligible to eachother without additional work. You can translate, but you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to translate if you want to become mutually understood.
Because the government was interacting with many more of these local standards, the cost of translation was &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; higher (to the point of being almost impossible), and their ability to impose their own standards was also much higher,
so standardisation happened.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But standardisation happens locally too. Although individual merchants may have their own weights and measures,
if two merchants interact regularly enough they're going to come up with some common standards.
They might not adopt them for everything, but at some point it becomes easier for them to just share a standard.
If, in contrast, they hardly ever interact, there is no such incentive.
This is akin to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-28-06:33.html"&gt;the way people learn which way to veer in a collision&lt;/a&gt; - conformity is driven by interactions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The role of power in this is that of determining which side has a stronger incentive to conform to the other.
A merchant interacting with a government has a very strong incentive to conform (the government has much more power) while the government has a comparatively weak incentive (as well as the merchant having less power, there are many other merchants with equal and competing demands).
Thus the merchant becomes legible to the government rather than the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, marginalised people are forced to become legible to the mainstream rather than the other way around,
because by definition there are fewer of them and they have less power, so they have less ability to impose their standards of legibility on others.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-02-09:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html</id>
    <title>Your emotions are valid but probably wrong</title>
    <updated>2020-03-03T16:48:53+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Your emotions are valid but probably wrong&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a follow on from &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;Emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Premises:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All emotional reactions serve a purpose. They are designed to get you into a particular mode of thinking and acting in response to some stimulus that makes that seem like a good idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learned emotional reactions do not go away on their own, and most people do not have the skillset for making them go away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ignoring or arguing with your emotions as "bad" will typically not help and may intensify them, because they will still feel relevant and will respond to the fact that you're ignoring them when they're needed by rising to a level which you can't ignore. (Going very dissociative seems partially protective against this but has its own set of problems, guess how I know).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, we can conclude:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your emotions are valid, in the sense that invalidating them is the worst thing you can do if you want to respond to situations more healthily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your emotions are usually wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is simple: Childhood is very different from adulthood, and you learned many of your emotional reactions in childhood. Those early learned emotional reactions will have had a long time to bed in - either you've been embracing them, and learned that that works, or you've tried to ignore them, and they've intensified to stop you from doing that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Those emotional reactions you're having from childhood? They were adaptive when you learned them. They weren't necessarily &lt;em&gt;good ideas&lt;/em&gt; when you learned them (e.g. you might have learned that getting angry and screaming would get you attention. It probably wasn't ever a good way to get attention), but they filled a functional role.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is that your adult environment is very different from your childhood one:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are surrounded by different (and often much better) people than you were in childhood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have significantly more agency and power than you did in childhood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have significantly more skills and competence than you did in childhood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In most circumstances where things are bad &lt;em&gt;you can leave&lt;/em&gt; (this isn't always true, but it's true more often than people treat it as being).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This environment is so different from most people's experiences of childhood that it's &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; unlikely that the strategies that were adaptive as a kid are still adaptive as an adult, but unless you relearn the emotional reactions you've inherited from your child self, you will behave in very maladaptive ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a personal example, for me school was a living hell. I was the weird kid, I found everyone else completely unrelatable, I had no communication or emotional skills. It was awful and I was stuck there and there was nothing I could do about that because every attempt to improve my situation made it worse, so I was utterly powerless. I really cannot recommend anything about the experience.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, as an adult, I have wonderful friends who I find &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; relatable. I'm still weird, but in ways that are very compatible with those around me. I have a fair bit of social status (again, in my wonderfully weird niche communities), I'm almost certainly in the top 10% of the population as far as emotional and communication skills go (in some respects I'm much higher, in some respects I've still got a lot of learning to do, so this is a complicated claim to make, but I think top 10% is true by any reasonable metric), and if someone or something is causing me trouble I can usually exit the situation, or modify it to work better for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is a degree of agency that I am totally emotionally unprepared for by my childhood experiences, and I constantly have to retrain my emotional reactions to remind myself of that. Fortunately this is invigorating rather than exhausting.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-04-11:18.html</id>
    <title>Skirting the edge of disaster</title>
    <updated>2020-03-04T11:34:37+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Skirting the edge of disaster&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Have you ever looked at a system and marvelled at the fact that it works at all?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course you have, you are one. You also work at one, live in one, if you're in London you certainly commute on one.
Complex systems are a mess and the only reason we can believe that they work is that they, somehow, do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why does this happen?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's a boundary defined between two competing forces:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If an important system is broken, we fix it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a system has spare capacity, we place more demands on it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Any system subject to these forces will skirt the edge of disaster: It will constantly be on the verge of being broken, and yet somehow work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason is very simple: If the system is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; on the edge of disaster, it will either be currently broken, and move towards the edge by getting better, or it will currently be under capacity and more demands will be put on it, and move towards the edge by getting worse. The edge is the only point of equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The best way to fix this that seems in widespread use is not to try and remove this dynamic, but instead to &lt;em&gt;move the edge&lt;/em&gt;, by changing what counts as a problem that needs fixing.
You still skirt the edge of "disaster" but your definition of disaster is now that the system is working suboptimally instead of just broken.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One way in particular to do that is to treat situations in which disaster was plausible rather than actual (near misses) as things that need fixing in their own right. &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1758026/pdf/v012p00465.pdf"&gt;Learning from samples of one or fewer&lt;/a&gt; is a good paper about this, describing how organisations can learn to avoid low probability high cost events which they, thankfully, not yet actually experienced.
Experiencing &lt;em&gt;near misses&lt;/em&gt; as things to learn from and feed back into the system is a key part of this.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-04-11:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-05-11:27.html</id>
    <title>Seeking out existence proofs in everyday life</title>
    <updated>2020-03-05T11:44:07+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Seeking out existence proofs in everyday life&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When trying to solve a problem, it is worth separating out two things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can I solve this problem to a level that is useful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it even possible to solve this problem at all?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An example that I think of a lot is Hypothesis and the way it integrates test-case reduction into generation.
The idea isn't novel to me, although some of the details and most of the engineering are,
but unlike previous attempts at achieving this sort of integrated test-case reduction it actually worked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing that allowed me to do it was that I knew something like it could work, because I had already demonstrated that the thing that it was doing was possible with a previous, much worse, version.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am slightly embarrassed at having shipped that version to production. It was awful. It was buggy, overcomplicated, and offence against good taste. But it &lt;em&gt;worked&lt;/em&gt;, and that gave me both the knowledge that what I was trying to do could be done, and helped me get a rough sense of that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another example: Skill development. I was talking to a friend who does climbing, and she was relating an experience she had at practicing jumps during climbs. This was one of the big &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-21-10:04.html"&gt;constraints on her skill growth&lt;/a&gt;, because she's quite short so needed to be able to jump to traverse some routes, and she wasn't making progress on it.
Eventually she realised that part of the problem was that actually she had literally just never jumped and caught something and supported her whole weight on it, and she was worried about it hurting or even dislocating her arms (not a rational fear, which she knew, but an understandable one).
So she practiced jumping and grabbing on to a pullup bar. Turns out, arms are pretty robust, and now she knew the thing she was trying to do was possible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yet another example: Emotional range is a thing that I'm working on. Mine is quite restricted, and I don't like it. Turns out "restricted emotional range" is a long way of saying "depression". So I'm working on the skill of having emotions (yes it's a skill, shut up). But this is hard if you don't know what emotions are supposed to feel like,
so it's worth doing a bit of experimenting in order to try to induce specific emotional states.
Cuddle a cat and really narrow in on what that's like to experience contentment, play untitled goose game to experience malicious glee, get really high to experience joy (disclaimer: First travel to somewhere where weed is legal. May I recommend Amsterdam if you're in Europe? But don't be a dick about it. They're bored of high tourists).
These are not sustainable ways to experience those emotions all the time, but they're great for demonstrating to you that it is possible to feel those emotions,
which is great for being able to find your way back to them the hard way (and can be refreshed every now and then if you forget what it's like).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think of these things as &lt;em&gt;existence proofs&lt;/em&gt;, because I'm a maths nerd.
They don't help you construct a specific example, but they let you know that such an example must exist,
and that you're not wasting your time chasing something that is logically impossible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also think of it as looking for feasible solutions in an optimisation problem (or &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/10/vocabulary-building-satisficing/"&gt;a satisficing problem&lt;/a&gt;). First, solve the problem any which way, then worry about improving that solution into one you'd actually be happy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-05-11:27.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-06-07:46.html</id>
    <title>Depression as felt restriction on emotional range</title>
    <updated>2020-03-06T09:49:38+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Depression as felt restriction on emotional range&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2IpgbDS"&gt;Experiences of Depression&lt;/a&gt; Matthew Ratcliffe does a great analysis of what it's &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; to be depressed. Key to his analysis is a distinction between &lt;em&gt;intentional&lt;/em&gt; feelings ("intentional" meaning "about something" rather than "deliberate". It's a philosopher thing. I often use "about" instead of "intentional") and &lt;em&gt;existential&lt;/em&gt; feelings, which are more pervasive feelings that colour your existence rather than being about one specific thing.
You could think of these as feelings-about (intentional feelings) and feelings-of (existential feelings) if that helps.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Many of the feelings of depression are existential rather than intentional, which is why it is so frustrating when people ask you what you are depressed &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt;. You're not depressed about anything, because the feelings that make up your depression are existential ones, which lack aboutness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the types of existential feelings that seems most central to depression are ones concerning &lt;em&gt;restricted emotional range&lt;/em&gt;.
A central example of this is hopelessness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Hope" is an intentional feeling. You hope &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; something. Hope has an intrinsic aboutness to it.
Hopelessness on the other hand, is an existential one: It is more than merely a lack of hope, it is a feeling that hope is impossible.
You can lack any particular hope without feeling hopeless.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It may be helpful to think of it as like being stuck. Feeling stuck is more than just the absence of movement. You can be non-moving without feeling stuck. Stuckness is the idea that movement is impossible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In Minksy's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/39wOsg8"&gt;The Emotion Machine&lt;/a&gt; he talks about emotions as ways of thinking, and how one of the various systems that regulates our emotional experience are &lt;em&gt;critics&lt;/em&gt; which are designed to protectively limit our thoughts and actions based on past experience. He suggests (p. 82) that there are at least three types of critic:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Corrector declares that you are doing something dangerous.
  "You must stop right now, because you're moving your hand toward aflame."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Suppressor interrupts before you begin the action you're planning to take.
  "Don't start to move your hand toward that flame, lest it get burned."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Censor acts yet earlier, to prevent that idea from occurring to you -
  so you never even consider the option of moving your hand in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I don't necessarily buy Minsky's models in this book as 100% true, but I find them useful metaphors)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd suggest that it is useful to think of hopelessness and similar as the felt sense of a censor (a felt censor, so to speak).
A censor is active that is preventing certain emotions from activating,
and you can &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; that that censor is there,
and that feeling is an integral feature of the depressive experience.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-06-07:46.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
