<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2022-01-27T19:02:55+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-17-09:08.html</id>
    <title>Fulfilling work</title>
    <updated>2022-01-17T10:31:45+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Fulfilling work&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's &lt;a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2013/04/23/good-idea/"&gt;almost certainly apocryphal&lt;/a&gt;, but there's a supposed quote by Gandhi that goes as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journalist: What do you think of Western civilization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gandhi: I think it would be a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is what I feel about the enobling power of work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a thing I've noticed on and off which is that people who have never worked, in some generalisable sense, are &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;/em&gt;, in a way that I do not intend to be as complimentary as I often do when I describe someone as weird.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't necessarily mean "had a proper job", and there's all sorts of other things that count as "work" in my book here. My central example of someone like this is not someone on unemployment benefits, but a trust fund kid. People who are rich enough that their life hasn't ever really required them to work for things. They may still have had a hard life in other ways, and I'm sure they have myriad &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-07-15-09:33.html"&gt;nice problems to have&lt;/a&gt;, but there's something that feels very dysfunctional about them - a sort of purposelessness and failure to engage with the actual reality of the world, or their relations with other people, because they have never really had to test themselves against the former and have always had the resources to avoid relying on the latter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a problem that, to some degree, I can relate to, and feel like I'm struggling with a bit myself. To the degree that I have not fallen into this trap, my history of actually working seems to be a large chunk of the character I rely on to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've not really had a "proper" job for the last 6 years - I've had projects, and I tried doing a PhD, and I've picked up freelance work on and off (which I'm properly taking seriously now so will be more on than it has been), so it's not like I've been idle or had no money coming in, but it's definitely felt more like being a NEET than like being in employment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And there are aspects of employemnt I miss a great deal, even if there are other aspects that I do not miss at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To me it feels like there's some sort of central human experience which has all of the following components:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A group of people, working together on a problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problem has an actual (even if small) impact on the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problem is difficult and without working hard on it they will fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All (or most) of the people in the group actually care about the problem and want to succeed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No member of the group could succeed at the problem on their own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each member of the group is an active participant in the process, and the end result depends on how well they fulfill their role.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Possibly this list isn't sufficient, but it all seems necessary to be an example of the thing I'm pointing to, which one might as well call something like "fulfilling work".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For me the optimal examples of such things are research and development, but they don't have to be. Renovating a house or working in a garden, for example. Hosting an event to some degree counts (it depends a lot on the event - certainly running something like a conference does. Throwing a party seems to be lacking something, probably the impact aspect).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think many people have roughly zero experiences like this in their life, but their job is the thing that comes closest. Some people even have this in their jobs, although I think it's not the norm.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Certainly, jobs being fulfilling work is not my experience - my jobs have all failed on (4), in that I think roughly nothing I have ever been paid to work on as a software developer has felt like something I cared about for its own sake. Some have reached the heady heights of "Oh yes I guess that might be good to exist", some of them have been intellectually neat problems to work on (which I then reluctantly went and worked on the boring engineering they obviously actually needed rather than the neat problems they hired me for), but none of them have been things I would have considered worth my effort if, well, they weren't paying me a lot of money for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was also a bit lacking in (6) - generally the end result wasn't bottlenecked on how well I fulfilled my role because the nature of working at startups is that the thing that will kill you is whether or not the people with power are competent to run a company and choose a product direction. Spoiler: They usually aren't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It does, however, have all of the other characteristics, to a much larger degree than really anything else in my life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Hypothesis is a close second, but I sortof failed at working on it around the point it was starting to become truly collaborative, for unrelated reasons)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-16-08:40.html"&gt;Yesterday's post&lt;/a&gt; was partly me coming to terms with the fact that hobbies and personal interests &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; don't fill this role, and the other people are a necessary part of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of discourse that one could handwavily frame as "work vs leisure". Obviously you need both and the strawman versions of both of these positions are idiots, but I feel like the thing that is missing from both the pro and anti work discourse is that the sort of work you need is not just any work but &lt;em&gt;fulfilling&lt;/em&gt; work, and that much of what people experience at work is a cruel caricature of that experience.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And I do think that we need something of this nature, not just leisure. People create themselves in concern with other people, and test themselves against reality, and this sort of shared project that actually matters is our best tool for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-17-09:08.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-18-13:15.html</id>
    <title>Difficulty finishing things</title>
    <updated>2022-01-18T14:11:39+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Difficulty finishing things&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-18&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a psychological quirk of mine that I've never really got to the bottom of. I've occasionally noticed it in others, and I wonder how common it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's this: Some part of me clearly rebels at finishing things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't slacking. I do also slack on some things, granted, but that's not what I mean. I mean I do something like 90-99% of the work and then just... stop. I don't want to take the final step and complete it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This shows up across a variety of areas. I'm not quite sure what the common thread is - there needs to be some sense in which it's a "task", but it happens for both enjoyable ones and unenjoyable ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A trivial example of this is that often I'll fail to wash up everything. I'll do almost all of it but I'll leave one or two items on the side because I can't be bothered to do those right now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It also shows up on large writing projects - I'm the worst at large writing projects. I know I write a lot, but virtually all my successful writing happens in one sitting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Games, too. There are a number of games I've played something like 90% of the game and then "got bored of". Sometimes this is because the game got too hard towards the end, but I don't think that's all of it. I definitely stopped playing before I plateaued.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've also noticed this in what projects I'm attracted to. I really like problems where it's impossible to solve them optimally and there is always room for improvement. I still stop before the end, of course, but that's now because there is no end. My recent adventures in Wordle solving are an example of this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some things the source of the aversion to finishing is pretty clear: If I finish the project, I have to act on it. If I finish writing a paper, I have to go through the publication process. If I finish a blog post or newsletter issue I've spent ages on, I have to deal with the fact that it might not succeed, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But this doesn't actually feel like a central example of the problem. As I've shown every day this month, it's not that hard for me to publish writing for the public. I do sometimes procrastinate a little on finishing it, but not much.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It feels like this is because the action of writing it is atomic in some way - the writing I do is generally something that is short enough that I can do it in one sitting (although I do often take breaks) and so it's just "one" task. The things that are hard to finish are composite, often done over many sittings.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why does this happen? I honestly don't know. The best I can describe it is that there's a sort of ugh reaction as the finish approaches. It feels a bit like being tired of the task, but as I've noted before, I think tiredness responses like this are often fake.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe this is a difficulty with transitions. The sharp end of a task is something to fear, in a way that a gradual drifting away from it is not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wonder if there's something comforting to a part of me about an unfinished task. As long as there are things to do, I don't have to confront &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-08-08:36.html"&gt;the real choice of what I do next&lt;/a&gt;. I'm always able, in principle, to return to an unfinished task, and that anchors me against having to make broader and scarier choices.
I don't return of course. That would require finishing them, and abandoning the comfort of having something concrete to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't really know if this is it though. There's a sharp and unpleasant feeling to the idea of a completion that I can't really articulate at the moment, and whatever the reason the result is myriad unfinished and half-completed tasks around me at any given time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All I really know is what I said at the beginning: Some part of me rebels at the notion of completing a task. I can feel it even now - it's insisting that I shouldn't publish this piece until I've got to the bottom of why. I shall resist its demands.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-18-13:15.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-19-16:42.html</id>
    <title>The usefulness of things you don't use</title>
    <updated>2022-01-19T17:22:29+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The usefulness of things you don't use&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right before writing this post, I took the recycling down to the recycling bins.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Wait, sorry, that doesn't quite convey the right significance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right before writing this post, I took the recycling down to the recycling bins &lt;em&gt;for the first time in a month&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is stupid, I know it's stupid. But I really procrastinate on taking down the recycling a lot. I've tried various systems, and they often work for a time, but basically taking the recycling down is just &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt; too annoying. I don't particularly like going down to the basement car park where the bins are in the first place, and then on top of that sorting the recycling into the different bins for it is just quite fiddly. The whole thing takes about 10-15 minutes tops unless I've &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; let it build up (which absolutely happens), and isn't objectively that bad, but inevitably it's always a task that is easier to leave to later than to do now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the thing that got me take the recycling down is that I've implemented a new productivity system.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Wait, no, don't go! I promise the bit about the productivity system will be really short.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The new system is actually &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-11:33.html"&gt;an old system&lt;/a&gt; with a twist. The old system is just a simple daily list of things it would be useful for me to do today, which gets shredded without rollover at the end of the day (or, more typically, the beginning of the next day when I remember). I call them day plans. Day plans are very good for me, and I often remember that for weeks at a time and then stop using them. The twist is that I read &lt;a href="https://slimemoldtimemold.com/2022/01/18/todos-from-paper-systems"&gt;Slime Mold Time Mold's post about TODO systems&lt;/a&gt; earlier and I really liked their point about systems which create pride in your use of them, and the calendar with crossed out days looks perfect, so now I've got a calendar up on my fridge which I cross out days that I've used a day plan. This is day one, so that part isn't really relevant except in the sense that this is the first day I've done a day plan for in months.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the interesting thing about taking the recycling down is that the thought process that lead to me taking the recycling down is that I was just coming back from a walk and I had the following sequence of thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While I have my shoes on I should take the recycling down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I guess I'll add that to the day plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Or I could just take the recycling down?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So in fact I did this without actually using the day plan system.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does this mean that I didn't need the day plan? No, I don't think so. The day plan was very useful for this, despite not being used for it, because its existence turns the problem of putting off taking the recycling down from one that I can't solve into one that I can. I've talked about such things as &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-05-11:27.html"&gt;existence proofs&lt;/a&gt; before - they let you conclude that a solution exists, now all you need to do is figure out what a good enough solution looks like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this case the solution was "just do it", but sometimes you do actually need to figure out an alternative solution. An example of this for me recently is sleeping pills. I've talked about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-04-14:48.html"&gt;my recent problems with sleeping due to anxiety at night&lt;/a&gt;. One of my solutions to this is drugs. Initially the doctor prescribed some drowsy antihistamines, because they don't like to prescribe the good drugs because they're addictive. I decided it was better not to argue and just took the prescription, and hated them about as much as I expected - I feel &lt;em&gt;awful&lt;/em&gt; the next day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I had another conversation with a GP where I asked for some better sleeping pills. He explained that they don't like to prescribe those because you really shouldn't take them every night due to the addictive nature. I, in turn, explained that god I didn't want to take them every night. Ideally I'd &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; take them, and that having them beside my bed and never taking them was really the optimal use of sleeping pills in my view.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;See, the worst thing about anxiety at night is that it very easily escalates. If you're feeling slightly anxious it very easily turns into "oh no is this going to be another of &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; nights again? I really don't want to be awake all night, that would be awful" etc. This rapidly turns into a much greater level of anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, if there are some sleeping pills next to the bed, the problem is solved. I've put a cap on how bad it can get, because the answer is just that it can get bad enough that I have to take a sleeping pill, and that's not that bad. The problem with the drowsy antihistamines is that it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; that bad to take them because the next day is going to suck.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as curbing the initial anxiety loop, this also opens up the opportunity to experiment more with other solutions. Get out of bed and have a chamomile tea, put on a Slay the Spire video, read for a little bit longer and try again, etc. A problem that you can guarantee is solved is one you can experiment with, because it lacks the sense of sense of desperation that surrounds a problem that is urgent, important, and possibly unsolvable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the GP was very relieved to hear me say this and prescribed me some better sleeping pills (I've not actually picked them up yet though).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A third example relevant to me today is that I have an absolute rule that I don't have to write anything I don't feel comfortable writing. This month has mostly been &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-01-13:23.html"&gt;writing from the heart&lt;/a&gt;, and the process for that is that I rummage around and find something that feels important to write about, and then write about it. Or I safeword out - if the thing that feels important to write about is something where I go "No, absolutely not", I don't, I can just write something else. That happened today, but it hasn't otherwise happened. On the other hand, many of the topics I've written about probably wouldn't have felt safe to write about if I didn't have that out available to me. This is essentially a variant of &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/believing-that-you-can-stop"&gt;Believing that you can stop&lt;/a&gt; - the ability to stop helps ensure that you don't have to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this sort of situation is very common, and often results in critical things that look like slack getting cut. If I can get things done without the day plan, I don't need the day plan, right? If I can get to sleep without taking a sleeping pill, why do I need the sleeping pills? As a result, often you get rid of the thing you weren't using, and then are suprised when everything gets worse, because what the thing was doing for you was providing you with the ability to not need it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-19-16:42.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-21-16:38.html</id>
    <title>Projects that you can't run out of</title>
    <updated>2022-01-21T17:13:28+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Projects that you can't run out of&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-21&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was working on my new &lt;a href="https://consulting.drmaciver.com/"&gt;consulting website&lt;/a&gt; yesterday. I can't say it's the most exciting thing in the world, but one of the interesting things about working on it was that it gave me a project of a sort which I don't think I have that often, and that felt quite good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't have a good term for such projects, but let me see if I can articulate what I'm pointing at.
They have the following characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They can usefully absorb pretty much as much work as you're willing to put into them - they may plateau, but the work never becomes pointless or harmful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They don't &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to - you can stop pretty quickly and walk away and you'll have done something good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What you've done stays done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They feel neutral to positive to work on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example writing a blog isn't this, because it fails (1) - after a certain level of effort, a post starts getting worse rather than better, and if you write too much you just overwhelm the audience (people who want to keep up are already behind on reading my notebook, and I'm only writing daily! That's no more than an hour of work a day).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Projects that take a very long time to pay off also aren't this. e.g. a PhD, or even a paper, very much isn't this because if you walk away from it before it's successful, you've failed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Cleaning and general maintenance aren't this, partly because you have an obligation to keep on top of them - you can definitely fail to clean - and partly because they fail (3) and just undo themselves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of paid work fails at (4) but more interestingly paid work also often fails at (1). Paid work fairly rarely is something you can sink all your time into, because it starts to feel really bad to do that eventually - unless you're billing by the hour, you're being exploited. It goes against norms of work-life balance. Your coworkers resent you making them look bad. That sort of thing. Sometimes your employer &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; you to put unbounded amounts of effort into your paid work, but that's a different (and usually worse) problem which rarely results in positive feelings.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Projects like this are really satisfying to me. I think it's partly because they don't trigger the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-18-13:15.html"&gt;difficulty finishing things&lt;/a&gt; but there's also something very satisfying about knowing that you can just give something your all and will be rewarded for it.
They give you a reliable way of turning hard work into positive feelings, and are usually a ready source of flow, and that's pretty great.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting things about such projects is that, contra my recent line of thinking, they're not very good as team projects, because the problem is that if you're reliant on other people for working on something then you can't put unbounded amounts of work into it - you can put work until you get to something where you're blocked on other people for. I think this is part of why personal software projects are often much more satisfying (or at least differently satisfying) than shared projects.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some other examples of work like this for me are Hypothesis (when I was still working on it) and, for a more trivial recent example, working on my Wordle solver. They're interesting problems that can be endlessly tinkered with to improve upon, but that I very quickly got to a point where it's good that they exist and would still be good even if I walked away from them now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another interesting, darker, class of examples is that I think everything that gets used to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-06-12:00.html"&gt;drift&lt;/a&gt; has this character, but in a less nourishing way. I think the key difference is something like short-term vs long-term positive feelings. If I spend time playing a game, that produces good short-term feelings. Depending on how much time it may also cause good feelings in retrospect. e.g. I genuinely enjoy Slay the Spire and think it's worth the time I spend on it, but if I sank 80 hours a week into playing it, I would not feel good about that looking back.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps drift is, partly, looking for something of this sort and, lacking a good source of it, turning to the least bad ones available to us?&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-21-16:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-22-17:13.html</id>
    <title>Holding yourself tightly</title>
    <updated>2022-01-22T20:57:10+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Holding yourself tightly&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-22&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing you might be surprised to learn about me if you only know me through my writing is that I'm actually very bad at expressing my emotions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This doesn't come across that much on the internet, because the internet primarily uses the one exception to this. To be more precise, I'm very bad at expressing my emotions &lt;em&gt;except in words&lt;/em&gt;. I can &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/labelling-feelings"&gt;label feelings&lt;/a&gt; just fine, but actually showing them is much harder. The result is a slightly comical situation where I say things like "I'm very sad" or "I'm quite annoyed about this" in a perfectly calm voice and with very little visible expression about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm slightly better at expressing positive emotions, although not much. I can laugh just fine (although I'm somewhat on board with the idea that amusement is not an emotion. At the very least, amusement is a particularly safe emotion). I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; I can show enthusiasm, but not particularly easily.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This particularly comes up with really physical expressions of emotion. I can't really cry around other people (I don't find it that easy to on my own either, but it's doable). I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-14-16:49.html"&gt;struggle to raise my voice&lt;/a&gt;. Plus a few other examples that I won't go into here. Instead my physical presentation, more or less regardless of what I'm feeling, is fairly reserved. Not emotionless exactly, but very heavily skewed in the direction of seeming... not exactly calm, in that I'm told I definitely often look uncomfortable, but controlled certainly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this often gets confused with alexithymia, but it's not. It's not that I don't feel things, or know what I'm feeling, when around other people, it's that it doesn't feel safe to express those things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often this feeling is accurate, honestly. A lot of people aren't safe to have emotions around - unless you have the officially approved of emotions in a situation, you're very rapidly judged as being a bad person for having the wrong emotions. This is especially true of being upset or angry about anything they feel you're not allowed to be upset or angry about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't hypothetical, I've lost multiple friendships this way. As I said (about the same incidents) in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html"&gt;Wanting (to) help&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They would no doubt tell you this is a grossly unfair summary of the situation. I would, in turn, tell you that yes they would say that and can get fucked as far as I'm concerned. This is as close as I am prepared to come in providing a fair and balanced summary of events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also very much a party of the internet discourse. A lot of people on the internet tell you that men should be more open about their feelings. Unfortunately they rarely remember to include the small print:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No, not those feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not to me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of this compounds with a lot of childhood problems for me. I don't know how much bullying you've experienced, but let me tell you, the basic tool of the bully (at any age) is to provoke you until you can't help but exhibit strong emotions. Gee I wonder why it's hard for me to express emotions after a childhood constantly at war with people against whom me crying or getting angry (and thus in trouble with the teachers) was their victory condition.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given all this, the confusing thing is actually not that I can't express emotions, but that I can express them verbally. There's definitely some inner conflict here, but I think of it boils down to two things: The first is just that some large part of me &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; to be emotionally open, and will find any means available to it to do that. The other reason is that talking about your emotions calmly isn't actually particularly vulnerable - it's a way to signal that this doesn't &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; matter and you can't hurt me with this information. Saying "I'm very sad" is stoically calm, crying is weak.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think of this as "holding myself tightly" around other people. It feels very much like that, right down to the muscle tension (my muscles are also pretty tense on my own, honestly, but the experience of emotional control is definitely partly muscular).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't endorse this as a way of being, of course. Given a choice about how to be, I would laugh, shout, cry, dance with joy, and generally show far more of what I'm feeling on my face and body. The problem is that I literally don't know how.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is that it doesn't feel like something I can selectively turn off.
Mostly I do not spend time with people who will punish me for expressing emotions and, hard as it is to find out when a friend has let you down, to the degree that I do I would like to not spend time with those people further. But it doesn't feel like something I can selectively turn off only around safe people - if I stop doing this, whatever part of me it is that maintains it feels like the habit will be gone for good, and is apparently terrified at the prospect of this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have some ideas for how to work on this, but honestly none of them are very good, so if anyone else has suggestions I'm all ears.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-22-17:13.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-23-13:27.html</id>
    <title>Other people's needs</title>
    <updated>2022-01-23T17:21:08+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Other people's needs&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a passage from Will Buckingham's "Finding Our Sea-Legs" that I think about a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From page 54-56:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us imagine another example. One day you are going home, and you see Mavis, a bad-tempered pensioner who is also your neighbour, struggling along the street with her shopping. Before you can stop yourself, and against your better judgement, you find yourself offering to help her. THe next day when you see her, you are displeased to realise that the demands upon you are greater, not fewer: the experiential imperatives are more urgent and more compelling precisely because the day before you assumed the responsibilities that were incumbet upon you. There is Mavis with her shopping, and you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; can't not help her after having helped her the day before... So once again you carry her shopping, and before you know it, you find that you are helping her unpack it when you get it home for her. Over the next few days, things begin to spiral out of control; by the time the week is out, you find yourself in Mavis's living room drinking a cup of weak tea and eating stale biscuits as she tells you interminably dull stories from the distant past. And you wonder: how did I end up here? The answer is that you ended up there precisely on account of the peculiar structure of responsibility that Levinas describes so well. Our responsibilities have the habit of increasing even more rapidly than we can assume them. We are, Levinas claims, infinitely responsible for the other person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Levinas explains, "The infinity of responsibility denotes not its actual immensity, but a responsibility increasing in the measure that it is assumed; duties become greater in the measure that they are accomplished".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The task of ethics, then, is undending; but because it is unending, there is always a possibility of freeing ourselves once again from the limited self-concern into which we, inevitably, fall. Here, I can do no better than quote the Talmudic passage with which Levinas himself was familiar:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rabbi Tarfon used to say: The day is short, the work is great, the workers are lazy, the reward is great, and the master is insistent. He also used tos ay: You are not called to complete the work, nor are you free to evae it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethically speaking, we are all incorrigible shirkers. When called upon to respond, we often walk past, as I walked on past the man in the marketplace in Darjeeling. But the demand does not go away. It is something with which we are continually presented in our relationships with others. Even ifwe do not have to save the world or complete the work, we are never free of the demand to respond. And when we do respond, there's no telling where we might end up. When you think about it - when you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; think about it - it is frightening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is frightening, but I reject the label of shirker. I'm not lazy, I'm a coward.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is the sort of negative self-talk I hear you're supposed to avoid, but if it helps I think you're mostly cowards too. I'm not sure there's any other way to survive as an individual, although degrees of cowardice vary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know if I'm unusually cowardly in this regard, or whether I feel it more intensely than others, or whether the way I experience it is normal. But part of why &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html"&gt;I think so much about help&lt;/a&gt; is that I know this Mavis dynamic intimately.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you one of the ways in which I'm a coward: I don't give money to people I see begging. Literally almost never.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could give you some rational argument as to why giving money to beggars is bad, and you should give money to more useful causes, or something like that, but it wouldn't be true. Both in the sense that I think the argument is wrong, and it wouldn't actually be relevant to why I don't do it. The reason I don't is something closer to Levinas's infinite responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;See, if I started giving money to them, I wouldn't feel able to stop. Especially with how I will usually see the same ones over and over again, but even for beggars who I won't see again, if I give to them I will feel like I have to give to the next one, and the next, and the next. And the ones I'm seeing regularly, now I've implicitly got a relationship with them. If I move, or go away, now they're getting less money. Also, now they're someone I know. I'll say hi to them, I'll talk to them, I'll start to learn about their problems, I'll want to help them more than I already am, and clearly they have vast needs or they wouldn't be in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear: This is a me problem, not a them problem. I'm not worried that because I give money to them they'll start demanding more. That might happen, but I could deal with it, it's not what I'm worried about. I'm worried that once I start taking responsibility for them, I will take on more. They need help, vastly beyond my ability to give, and I don't know how to take only finite responsibility for that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's too much, and I can't deal with it. If it were only one person, I could manage, maybe, but if you help one then there's the next, and the next, and the next... At some point you have to draw lines, deny your responsibilities, and sometimes the only line you can safely draw with someone is to disclaim responsibility for them entirely.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Would this scenario I worry about come to pass? I don't know. I've occasionally given money to beggars, and it's definitely moved me more in this direction - more acutely aware of the problem - and then I stopped because I couldn't face it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Believe me, I am fully aware of the irony here. Because I cannot take infinite responsibility for them, I am denying them the concrete benefit of the finite responsibility I could take for them. Giving them £5 here and there would be much better than giving them nothing, and is easily within my means, except that I don't know how to care only a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of the problem here is one of collective responsibility. These are people we, as a society, are failing, and any one person trying to take on responsibility creates a load on them that they can't bear, when it would be entirely collectively bearable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I have now set up a recurring donation to Shelter, which I should have done before but haven't. This doesn't help &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; with this problem even slightly, but at least it helps them)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think a lot about the question of whether it's possible to be a good person without a community sharing the load and honestly I don't believe it is. I've talked about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-03-08:59.html"&gt;moral disorder&lt;/a&gt; as a key feature of the modern condition, but maybe constantly feeling guilty is just the natural consequence of being beset by infinite demands without the capacity to meet them. The only alternative is to stop caring.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not even sure stopping caring works. I think mostly you just hide the part of you that cares, as best you can. It doesn't go away.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of why I'm writing this today is because of my neighbours. I talked about them being loud in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-14-16:49.html"&gt;Walls of people&lt;/a&gt;, but this was pure euphemism. What I really mean is that they shout at their daughter a lot. Occasionally each other too, but especially the daughter. I'm almost certain it's no more than shouting - certainly I have no reason to suspect otherwise, and I suspect given the thin walls I would have heard if so - but they do shout a lot, and I hear the daughter crying when they do.
I've never met them, but I've seen them around a bit, and I know the daughter can't be more than about five.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's nothing I can do about it really. Someone suggested I call the NSPCC to ask for advice, and I will probably do this, but I cannot imagine what advice they can offer. There's no evidence of "real abuse", and any heavy-handed interventions would almost certainly make her life worse. I don't know the parents at all. If I did I would try to talk to them - maybe directly about this, maybe just about how they're doing. The last few years have been rough, especially for parents, and they're probably having a very bad time. I expect they could use help too. They should be better than this, regardless, but it's probably still the most useful thing for the daughter that I could do, in this hypothetical situation where I could do anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could try to introduce myself to them, see if there's anything I could do to help, but I both am afraid of making things worse and also am, as mentioned, a coward. Or at least not brave enough for this. Also I desperately don't want to take on this responsibility. If we had a shared community, I would happily do my part, but I know full well my limits and this is beyond them, because it's not just something that even in an ideal case I can "fix" - it would need ongoing help and support, in the best case scenariowhere this actually worked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've spent a while trying to pretend that this is not my responsibility and that it's merely an annoying fact of living in a building with poor sound insulation, but the truth is that it breaks my heart slightly every time. There's a small child suffering, I even know her name because I've heard her parents calling it (and shouting it), and there's nothing I can do about it but her pain is impossible to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know why this has hit me particularly hard today. Maybe just that &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1485235704284200963"&gt;I tweeted about it earlier&lt;/a&gt; and this caused me to stop ignoring how sad this makes me, but I've spent a significant chunk of this afternoon crying about it. This is pretty unusual for me - I don't cry easily - but for some reason this hit me in a vulnerable spot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think it's that today was particularly bad next door - though it was on the bad side - I just stopped pretending for a minute that I didn't care and that other people's pain didn't hurt me, and that was enough to set this off.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is true in general really: Other people's pain, or even their need, hurts if I let myself feel it. Especially if I can't help, but sometimes even if I can. I spend a lot of effort pretending this isn't the case, but I'm not sure that effort actually helps. It doesn't really make the pain go away, it just buries it and I try to pretend that means it's not there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, perhaps, a piece I was missing in why I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-22-17:13.html"&gt;hold myself so tightly&lt;/a&gt;. Everyone is so full of pain and need all the time - virtually everyone I know spends a lot of their life depressed, tired, anxious, and generally struggling to keep on top of the world. If I let myself feel that too much, other people literally hurt to be around.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-23-13:27.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-24-17:12.html</id>
    <title>Seeing clearly</title>
    <updated>2022-01-24T20:03:20+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Seeing clearly&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-24&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For the last day or two I've doing something I haven't done for years, and it's making everything so much clearer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is to say, I've got my glasses on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They're not especially good glasses. Or rather they're very nice glasses that have the wrong prescription, because I got them in 2019 when I finally had to acknowledge that my vision was decaying and that ugh fine I should get some glasses. The prescription was &lt;em&gt;barely&lt;/em&gt; enough to matter - a mild astigmatism in my left eye, a little bit of short sightedness in my right - but it was enough that I was starting to notice and it seemed worth getting glasses to correct it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I didn't wear glasses for the next two and a bit years.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I still in some sense don't "need" glasses. I can function fine without them. My eyes are even driving standard still. But there's been an increasingly noticable amount of eye strain. It's not that I can't read signs at a distance, or look at fine details across the room, it's just increasingly obvious that this is hard work. I've had a lot of tired eyes and headaches recently.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've known for literal months that the lack of glasses was causing me trouble, so I did the obvious thing: I left them sitting exactly where they were, untouched. I certainly didn't put them on my face.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been wearing them for the last couple of days because I'm going to be driving a car tomorrow and that "driving standard" claim is, while technically true, not quite the standard I hold myself to when driving a car. I also don't drink when I'm going to be driving, not even an amount under the legal limit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I really am safe to drive a car at my current level of vision. But... honestly compels me to admit that I'd certainly be &lt;em&gt;safer&lt;/em&gt; if I had slightly better vision. It's probably not enough to matter, but being at the wheel of a deadly weapon certainly puts you in contact with the reality of the world in a way that is hard for me to ignore. I can much more easily pretend my refusal to wear glasses isn't causing me a headache than I can pretend that it isn't increasing my chances of killing people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This all makes me sound like a very nervous driver. I'm not. I'm pretty confident of my driving ability, and being nervous behind the wheel makes me less rather than more safe. So, I drive confidently, but when &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in the car I acknowledge that for all their upsides, a car has an unpleasantly high statistical murder-suicide rate, and I make decisions in advance that reduce that rate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Further, radically changing your vision for the first time when you get behind the wheel of the aforementioned statistical murder-suicide machine is, to borrow a technical term, &lt;em&gt;fucking stupid&lt;/em&gt;, so I've been wearing my glasses for the last few days to get used to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The prescription isn't quite right, as I mentioned, and so I have begrudgingly booked an optician appointment for next week, but it's still a lot better than without the glasses. It's not an "&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-09-10:00.html"&gt;oh that's what a tree looks like&lt;/a&gt;" moment - I can see trees just fine thank you very much - but it's a "Oh I'm supposed to be able to read signs at &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; distance am I?" moment. No doubt after I've had my eyes checked again and got some new glasses (or possibly just new lenses for these ones if that's an option) there will be similar revelations in my future for me to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know how good you are at reading subtext, but chances are good you might have picked up on the subtle hint here and there that I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don't want to wear glasses.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I should, perhaps, give you some context. Up until 2010 if I didn't have my glasses on I would have to hold a book several inches in front of my face to read. I probably wouldn't literally walk into things, because large blurry objects are still large objects that I can see coming, but if you were on the other side of the room from me I would be recognising you from height and colour palette only. Then in 2010 a nice man fired laser beams at my eyes and I acquired ~superpowers~ the ability to see things near-perfectly without further vision correction. Wait, no, I was right the first time. Superpowers. Compared to my previous state this definitely felt like superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, a decade passed, and during that time I failed to figure out a way to transcend the frailties of my mortal form, and as a result my eyes got older and weaker again, and now here I am with a need to strap an awkward contraption of glass and metal to my face in order to bring my basic functional capabilities up to human baseline and have fewer headaches.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My objection is not aesthetic. I look good in glasses. It's a very different look, especially given that the last time I regularly war glasses I had hair, but in many ways I look more like me in glasses than I do when not wearing glasses. Although, truthfully, that's maybe part of the problem - the me I look like is the me of my 20s. Maybe the me of my mid to late teens even. The me of my preteens and early teens wore awkward giant dorky glasses, before I started wearing thin frames and smaller rims, but I spent a long time with my face looking like this and a lot of it wasn't particularly good, and I'm not particularly proud of the version of me that existed back then. I want to reach back and give him a hug and tell him everything is going to be OK, but I don't particularly want to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; him.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know if this is actually my real objection. It might be just a clever theory. The actual complaints that are coming up are that glasses feel weird on my face. I'm not used to the weight and the feeling of htem, and I feel hyperaware of their presence on my nose, and of the slight reduction in peripheral vision. It's likely that I'll just get used to it, but I don't especially want to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another resentment is definitely that I don't like aging. Yeah, me and everyone else, I know. Glasses feel like a particularly cruel reminder of it though - you know that problem you thought you'd fixed? Unfortunately, bodies!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suspect some of this is also just a sort of... resentment at being forced to make a choice about a tradeoff? I've never really had to choose whether to wear glasses or not before. As a young child, I didn't know that seeing things was an option. As a slightly older child, I could choose between being able to see things and not being able to see things, so I went with the one that was obviously better. For most of the last 12 years, I've not needed to choose whether to wear glasses or not, because why would I I didn't need them?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now though, I'm caught like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buridan%27s_ass"&gt;Buridan's ass&lt;/a&gt; between two very similar options, except instead of choosing between two delicious bales of hay, I get to choose between two slightly crappy options.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm aware that many people are absolutely fine with glasses, and that I probably will once again become such a person and if not will eventually find another nice man (or woman, or other) to fire lasers at my face, but for now please forgive my petty resentments at the constraints placed upon me by my biology.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-24-17:12.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-25-07:18.html</id>
    <title>Failing to resist temptations</title>
    <updated>2022-01-25T08:03:25+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Failing to resist temptations&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am, as I've mentioned, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-18-13:15.html"&gt;bad at finishing things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You know what I'm not bad at finishing though? Crisps. You put a bag of crisps in front of me, it's gone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am fortunately saved from pringles by my dietary restrictions, because the following analogy that I used to talk about whether &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-06-12:00.html"&gt;drift&lt;/a&gt; was pleasant or unpleasant is 100% accurate to my experience:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drifting is unpleasant in the same way that eating a tube of pringles is unpleasant. You know you shouldn't start, but then you do, and you're not really enjoying it, but you keep eating it, and then you get to the end and you think "Ugh, why did I eat that?" and then the next time a tube of pringles is opened in front of you you do it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not even good at resisting the temptation of things I &lt;em&gt;don't particularly like&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/first-hard-choice"&gt;The first hard choice&lt;/a&gt; is my post about temptation and addiction, and it's an odd post to be sure, but one of the oddest things about it is that I feel quite so strongly about this subject given that I don't have any particularly scary addictions. I don't even smoke, I drink in moderation, I have minimal to no experience with harder drugs (and what minimal experience I have only in countries where they're perfectly legal, naturally). My worst addiction is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-12-00:46.html"&gt;coffee&lt;/a&gt;, and although that has this dynamic it also has other reinforcing problems. It's very much an addiction in the sense of it solving problems for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have, incidentally, given up giving up coffee again. I made it to about two months before I came up with a very good justification for drinking coffee again. The problem is basically that coffee solves some very unpleasant gastrointestinal issues for me, so about once a week I have to make a decision between having a very upset stomach or drinking coffee (yes, it's partly that coffee makes you shit, but it's not just that. Decaf has the same property and doesn't seem sufficient), and having coffee about once a week means I spend the rest of the week craving coffee. I had a morning when I spent about 10 minutes of arguing with myself about whether I was allowed a coffee and eventually decided that this was stupid and if this was going to be my experience then it was clearly better to deal with the problems coffee causes rather than the problems that it solves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another example of the temptation problem for me is that I don't usually keep my phone in the bedroom. My alarm is dead right now and I needed to be up early this morning, so I made an exception and had my phone by my bed. Naturally, because my alarm was set for 6:30, I woke up at 5:30, and equally naturally because it's fucking cold right now and it was 5:30AM I didn't want to get out of bed, but then my phone was right there and before you knew it I was on Twitter. This is precisely why my phone isn't allowed in my bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A really stupid example of this is that I often shave in the shower. It's not good for my skin, and it doesn't produce a particularly good shave, but it's easy and it lets me extend my time in the shower, and no matter how often I have this argument with myself I often find myself gravitating back to this habit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not particularly that I miss these things when they're not there. I do sometimes buy crisps despite knowing this, but mostly if I don't have crisps in the house I don't miss them. Coffee and Twitter solve problems for me, but not having Twitter in bed doesn't present a problem, and if you could somehow blanket ban shaving in the shower I would be completely fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, in the presence of these temptations, I often cave. I appear to be really bad at listening to even a weak and off-tune siren song. I think it's that I can't not notice the call, and once I notice the call it's a constant nagging presence that I want to make go away, and I'm not very good at dealing with ongoing discomforts like that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-25-07:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-26-19:35.html</id>
    <title>The kindness of strangers</title>
    <updated>2022-01-26T21:21:24+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The kindness of strangers&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hey, remember &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-05-13:01.html"&gt;that time when I got completely lost on the way to the hospital&lt;/a&gt; and had to be rescued by kind passersby giving me directions? Me too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway it turns out I wasn't remotely done relying on the kindness of strangers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I rented a car yesterday, picking it up not long after I finished writing &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-25-07:18.html"&gt;yesterday's post&lt;/a&gt;. It's technically not my first time renting a car, but the last time I was with an experienced other driver who did all the legwork, and I just signed the forms and paid (I was a last minute addition and, unlike the other two people in the car, I was coming back for the round trip, so it made more sense to be under my name). This time I did everything.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out renting a car is easy. I think it had been in my head as one of those complicated things that adults do and I didn't understand how to make work but, no, renting a car is easy. Apparently it's often not easy and many car rental places screw you over. I solved this problem by going to one of the more expensive ones (mostly because every other option was a &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; further walk from me) and being effortlessly charming and pretty at the staff, so everything went fine on the rental front (I've now returned the car, so the chickens in question are hatched and I shan't regret these words, although who knows what will happen the next time).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What didn't go so well was my ability to listen to instructions. The attendant who showed me the car did, I realise in retrospect, explain how to reverse the car correctly, but I misunderstood her directions, and foolishly didn't check before leaving the car park. Instead I discovered that I did not know how to reverse the car while trying to turn around on a hill, with the front of the car about a meter from shuttered entrance to an underground car park.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tried three or four times to reverse and each time the car rolled forward. At first I thought I was just doing a reverse hill start badly, but after the second time I was convinced I was doing something fundamentally wrong, but I couldn't figure out what.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After that fourth time there was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a lot of distance between the front of the car and the barrier (probably no more than about 20cm). At this point someone came out from the pedestrian entrance to the carpark and looked at me bemused. I explained my situation. "Would you like some help?", he asked. I very gratefully accepted, at which point he effortlessly reversed the car up the hill for me and backed it a bit up onto the curb. He explained how reverse hill starts need to use the handbrake. I said that I thought I had done that but clearly I must have done something wrong, and thanked him profusely.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd made two mistakes at this point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The car was, in fact, still blocking the entrance, it was just now in less dire straits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had not asked my saviour to show me &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what he had done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine it was at this point I learned that the problem wasn't hill starts (which I was pretty sure I was fine at and still maintain I am) but that I just didn't know how to reverse the car, and as a result could not easily get it out of the way of the car who arrived shortly after wanting to get into the carpark. I explained to her, very embarrassed, what was going on. She said no problem but didn't offer to help and I was too embarrassed to ask.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not long after this a timber merchant turned up to do some deliveries. The man driving gave me a confused look. I explained. He offered to help, and I again gratefully accepted.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He did what the first person did not, which was that he explained to me like I was five how to use a manual gear stick. I mostly didn't need this as I actually mostly have driven manual (I've driven an automatic precisely once in my life). What I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; need demonstrating was that this gear stick, unlike every other one I have ever used, required you to pull up on the shaft in a frankly bizarre way to put it in reverse. If you didn't do that, you went into sixth instead. This is some seriously unintuitive modal interface bullshit, and I say this as a vim user.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My second saviour did look very amused and exasperated at me, and explained in very small words and with elaborate gestures and demonstrations, and I did not begrudge him this at all because I surely deserved it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, there were no further problems with driving the car because I actually can drive just fine once I know how to reverse the car.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This piece was going to have more anecdotes about what driving was like, but then about a third of the way into writing it I had a sudden thought: "Wait, wasn't my passport supposed to be delivered today?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The answer is yes, my passport was supposed to be delivered today, and TNT claimed to have delivered it. They had photo proof and everything. Specifically, after having had my passport sent via the passport office using their dedicated passport delivery service, they had shoved it through some letterbox without getting a signature and then taken a picture of the door. Needless to say this wasn't &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; door, because I live in a block of flats.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was, as you may imagine, mildly displeased by this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway this was about 8PM so I did the obvious thing and went through every nearby door with a number 2 on it until I found the right one. This didn't take all that long (I got it on the second try). I knocked (no doorbell), but nobody was in, so I solved my problems the British way and went to the pub.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specifically I went to the pub right nextdoor to this one, where I explained to the bartender very nicely what my problem was. She got the owner, and I explained again. He got in touch with the person who lived there, and also he had a key to it, so he want in and got the package and gave it to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I then ordered a large glass of gin, and we all groused about how shocking the situation was, and I affirmed that I would be having words with TNT and the passport office tomorrow when they're open.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of this is to say... I've been complaining recently about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html"&gt;wanting and offering help&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-23-13:27.html"&gt;the difficulty of helping in atomised communities&lt;/a&gt;, but actually it's worth remembering that strangers are usually &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; helpful when you ask them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something simultaneously very easy and utterly pure about helping a stranger. There is no reason to help a stranger except pure altruism and the hope that one day someone will help you back. Help offered freely to strangers can never be paid back, only forward, and it's easy to forget that we do in fact live in a world where people do this, and do this freely.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This doesn't always work. There's a privilege element to this, as with all things, and you run into difficulties with some problems - especially money ones, or other common requests for help (my emotional difficulties giving money to beggars for example). But nevertheless very often you can, in fact, rely on strangers to help you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In many ways, it's easier to help a stranger, because there's no expectation that you'll have to help them again. Levinas thinks we have infinite responsibility to our fellow humans, but this isn't entirely true. Someone you will never see again and can help is that blessedly rare thing: A finite responsibility to others that you can discharge, and know that thereby you have done good in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-26-19:35.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-27-18:13.html</id>
    <title>Irritation and fascination</title>
    <updated>2022-01-27T19:02:55+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Irritation and fascination&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was talking to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/drossbucket"&gt;Lucy&lt;/a&gt; the other day about the book &lt;a href="https://vajrayananow.com/spectrum-of-ecstasy"&gt;spectrums of ecstacy&lt;/a&gt;,
and she mentioned the concept from it that "anger is distorted clarity".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I found this puzzling, but am not going to do anything ridiculous like actually read the book to find out what they mean, so instead I'm going to riff irresponsibly off the idea.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I may read the book to find out what they mean later)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not entirely in line with my experience, in that anger certainly doesn't seem like it comes with clear &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt;, but what I eventually decided was that anger is a form of clarity of purpose. Anger draws a straight line from where you are, to where you want to be. It is a form of value clarity that is not easily accessible in the real world - a straightforward desire to win.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've definitely found this while writing sometimes. There are a lot of things I write because I am annoyed that they don't exist for example. Sometimes I'm even straightforwardly angry that they exist, usually &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-13-04:16.html"&gt;on behalf of my past self&lt;/a&gt; who needed them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fascination is another thing that feels a bit like a line pulling you in a coherent direction. When I have a problem to work on, my thoughts drift towards it of their own accord. There's a problem to solve, and trying to avoid solving it is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-25-07:18.html"&gt;like resisting temptation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, in fact, I don't know that this isn't just another form of anger again. It's certainly &lt;em&gt;irritation&lt;/em&gt;. Often the thing that draws me to a problem is that it's a worthy opponent, and that I want to defeat it. I think this is part of the appeal of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-21-16:38.html"&gt;problems that you can't run out of&lt;/a&gt; - you can challenge them again, and again, honing your strength against the impossible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fascination and irritation definitely feel similar in many regards. If you watch me playing a hard level on Celeste, you'll see me scream in rage and frustration a lot, followed by jubilation when I win.
It's precisely this dynamic where the thing that drives me forward is a furious desire to defeat the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's what I'm seeing with my current efforts with automated Wordle solving too. There's a core irritation with the problem. It has challenged me, and I must defeat it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-03-14:16.html"&gt;I wondered where the curiosity went&lt;/a&gt;, and maybe this is it. I used to be a very angry person, and this had its problems for sure, but I have not been kind to the angry parts of me, and maybe when they hid they took my ability to be truly interested in things. Perhaps there is a burning furious fascination required to drive you forward to the efforts required to truly invest yourself in a project. If so, I need to find a way to rekindle that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-27-18:13.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
