<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-03-30T23:12:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-21-12:35.html</id>
    <title>The Inner Game of Celeste</title>
    <updated>2020-03-21T15:59:47+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The Inner Game of Celeste&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-21&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2wszUzR"&gt;The Inner Game of Tennis&lt;/a&gt; recently, on the recommendation of my Alexander Technique teacher. I was surprised by how much I enjoyed it - both because it's always a bit weird when classic self-help books are actually good, and also because I am under a vow to never play Tennis so it didn't seem that relevant to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of it I liked. I'm particularly interested in the chapter on competition, which I intend to write more about later, but most of the book is about how you relate to yourself,
and how to stop overthinking your actions and let your verbal mind get out of the way and let your body do its thing. Verbal processing is in many ways much smarter than the body,
but it is slow and not particularly good at coordinating the things you need to do to move in the right way as you focus on the task you're trying to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The Inner Game of Tennis suggests that we consider ourself as divided into two parts, a self 1 and a self 2, and I've &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; forgotten which is supposed to be which because thing 1 and thing 2 terminology is bad and only terrible people use it, so I'm going to call them the speaker and the doer. The speaker is your verbal self, the doer is your self that moves your body.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Particularly in Western cultures we tend to overidentify with the speaker, and think of it as being in command of of our actions.
In reality the opposite is more likely to be true, with the speaker being a thin layer on top of a much deeper web of decision making in the doer, but one thing is certain: The speaker has the ability to fuck you up.
The Inner Game of Tennis talks about how an overly judgemental and opinionated speaker tries to take direct control of your actions, and then shouts at you for getting it wrong.
The doer knows how to play tennis without the speaker's intervention, so the solution is to silence the speaker and act as a pure doer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this all makes me think of Celeste.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Firstly it makes me think of Celeste because Celeste is much like tennis in this sense:
If you try to think too much while playing it, you will die horribly, probably impaled on spikes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(That's how tennis works, right? I haven't played it since I was about twelve, when I swore the vow, so my memory is a bit fuzzy)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Playing Celeste very much teaches you to act solely as the doer. If you try to think during a complicated wall jump and dash sequence, you will die. You have to be in flow state while playing Celeste if you want to make any progress.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But Celeste also teaches you to act solely as the speaker. Celeste levels are quite small, so you can see the route you want to take, and plot it out in advance. You don't have to, but particularly on the harder levels you will often want to pause and think about what you're doing, and talk things over with yourself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Both of these parts of yourself are important to playing a good game of Celeste, as they probably are to playing a good game of tennis (certainly it wasn't the doer part of W. Timothy Gallwey who wrote a book about tennis).
The problem is not the speaker any more than it is the doer, the problem is that one of them is trying to run things, when a healthily functioning mind is a collaboration between the two. Your speaking self is good at planning, your doing self is good at acting, and these are not the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Celeste has more to teach us here, not through play but through its plot.
Celeste is ultimately a game about shadow work, and embracing our inner demons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Celeste's plot centers around the protagonist Madeline's attempts to overcome her anxiety, by climbing a death trap of a mountain that wants to kill her at every turn.
Quite early on, she encounters a magic mirror, which brings out a part of her that sometimes gets called Badeline (the game never uses this term except internally, she's always referred to just as "Part of Madeline").&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've always felt Badeline was a rather cruel thing to call her, particularly as the game progresses, but in defence of the name she does spend a significant portion of it trying to kill Madeline, including by firing giant laser beams at her and throwing her down to the ground from on high, and generally being rather mean.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things that she repeatedly tells Madeline is that she is not a mountain climber and that she will fail.
Again, Celeste is a giant death trap, so this is not an unreasonable concern, but she's very mean about it.
Badeline's role is to personify Madeline's fears and anxieties,
and to tell her all the things she should be afraid of,
and to give external voice to all of the negative things that Madeline tells herself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually after quite a lot of this, Madeline says the following to Badeline:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're everything I need to leave behind.
You're cruel, paranoid, controlling...
I understand now.
I don't need you any more.
I'm setting you free.
We'll both be so much happier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How would you feel if someone said that to you?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this goes about as poorly as you might expect it to, and Badeline casts her down to the base of the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Later, climbing out of the pit she's fallen into (this is literal, although she's in a bad enough mood that it's also metaphorical), she encounters Granny, the wise old lady who lives at the base of the mountain (who is a real jerk). She gives Madeline the following advice:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sounds like she's holding you back.
Talk to her. Figure out why she's so scared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Madeline follows this advice, tracks Badeline down, gives her a big hug, and tells her it's OK to be scared.
After that, they work together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't imagine the authors of Celeste have ever read &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2J3N60V"&gt;Feeding your demons&lt;/a&gt;, but there is a lot of similarity in the approaches.
Rather than treating your inner fears as demons who you should exorcise, you ask them what they need, and you give them love, and you turn them into your allies.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Feeding Your Demons is a weird book and I like it but I don't know that I recommend it exactly)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way Madeline talks to Badeline is exactly as bad as the way Badeline talks to Madeline.
You could argue that Badeline deserves it because she started it, but even if that were true it is unhelpful,
because the way the game actually refers to Badeline is more accurate: She is &lt;em&gt;part of Madeline&lt;/em&gt;.
Madeline's attacks on Badeline are attacks on herself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you have an inner voice that is harsh and critical towards you, the problem is not that you have an inner voice, but how it talks to you. You need to &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/01/a-crash-course-in-having-feelings/"&gt;learn how have a better relationship with it, and how to talk to yourself in a healthier way&lt;/a&gt;, rather than treat it as being intrinsically the source of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-21-12:35.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-22-18:01.html</id>
    <title>Leaving knowledge in the box</title>
    <updated>2020-03-23T21:49:51+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Leaving knowledge in the box&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-22&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-24-10:37.html"&gt;All knowledge is connected&lt;/a&gt;.
It might be tenuous, but the connection is there. You will probably learn something about cooking in studying ancient Greek culture, and you will probably learn something about mathematics by studying feminism,
possibly via some intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A consequence of this is that whatever problem you are working on at the moment, you will never learn everything that might be relevant to it, because everything that might be relevant is... everything.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even with more restricted areas, knowing everything is impossible.
In software development we talk about "full stack" developers, but nobody actually understands the whole stack,
at best we can do a reasonable job across a reasonably broad subset of it.
Certainly nobody actually understands how the whole stack works if you all the way down from the user interface to the hardware.
Modern computers are too complicated for any one person to understand the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fortunately you don't need to actually learn everything relevant to a problem to act. You can just flip a coin, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;or do anything strictly better than that&lt;/a&gt;.
The goal of learning is often to &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2013/08/how-did-you-get-started-so-quickly/"&gt;learn just enough to solve the problem&lt;/a&gt;, and often you're better off learning enough &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, this is a major &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-15:59.html"&gt;cut out switch&lt;/a&gt; you need to install: The ability to reflectively go "I don't need to know this", and treat some areas of knowledge as black boxes that you're never going to open.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This requires developing skills of discomfort tolerance: Relying on something mysterious that you don't understand how it works is scary, but you're going to have to get used to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It also requires learning the skill of working with black box knowledge.
Typically you deal with a black box in one of two ways:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn just enough about how it works to use it and taboo understanding it. I don't need to know how the London Underground system works to ride the tube (although also don't ride the tube right now if you can possibly avoid it).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask for help. Find someone whose problem it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; to understand this, and let them solve it for you. You may need to develop &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2015/02/what-are-developer-adjacent-skills/"&gt;adjacent skills&lt;/a&gt; for their job, but you don't need to develop anything like the whole skill set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If neither of these work, maybe it's time to open the box after all.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-22-18:01.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-23-15:52.html</id>
    <title>Life as an anytime algorithm</title>
    <updated>2020-03-23T16:18:50+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Life as an anytime algorithm&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In computer science we have the (slightly obscure) notion of an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anytime_algorithm"&gt;anytime algorithm&lt;/a&gt;.
This is an algorithm that is trying to find some solution to a problem (say, a configuration of a problem that gives the highest score, or a plan that minimizes a cost) and will run to completion if you let it, but also at any point when you get bored you can stop it and ask it for its current best answer and it will give it to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An important feature of anytime algorithms is that although they are trying to achieve a specific goal, they make meaningful progress towards that goal along the way, and are designed on the assumption that they might be interrupted at any point and fail to achieve that goal, so do their best to ensure that regardless of when you stop them the effort has not been wasted.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is often a good way to structure goals in life as well as in algorithm design.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For one thing, this is a partial antidote to &lt;a href="https://www.fvathynevgl.com/momentum/"&gt;the problem of grind&lt;/a&gt;.
Grinding for a goal in the distant future is unrewarding, but grinding where you are seeing meaningful progress along the way which makes things progressively better on an ongoing basis.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1229061018019651587"&gt;daily notebook blogging&lt;/a&gt; I am doing at the moment is an example of this approach. I think it is likely that I will turn some large fraction of it into a book at some point, but if I were to just work on the book then it would be a giant project that would fail to motivate me due to its size and lack of feedback, while by posting these daily people will riff off them, and respond to them, and they will be useful to the world almost immediately even if I never write that book.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another example is that of properly investing in capabilities rather than just making a beeline for the goal. Do more or less the opposite of the &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2013/08/how-did-you-get-started-so-quickly/"&gt;how to quickly become effective&lt;/a&gt; strategy, and invest carefully in the skills that will allow your goal to be more readily achievable. That way if you abandon the goal, for whatever reason, you will retain the skills and may repurpose them in other contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-23-15:52.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-24-09:46.html</id>
    <title>Trust beyond reason</title>
    <updated>2020-03-24T12:42:43+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Trust beyond reason&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-24&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To quote from &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Uewqdp"&gt;one of my all time favourite books&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"You? I know you! You trust beyond reason."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Yes. It's how I get results beyond hope. As you may recall."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a very powerful strategy, and as a result of following it (and, it must be said, a great deal of luck) almost everyone who is important to me is someone I trust.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't trust them all the same amount of course. They're also not important to me to the same amount.
But, by and large, the more important someone is to me the more I am able to trust them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's back up. What do I mean by trust? And important?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A good rule of thumb for what "trust" means that I came up with a while ago is this: Central to trust is the ability to tell someone true things, especially about yourself, and be confident that this will not go badly for you.
It's not that their interests are perfectly aligned with yours, but they are in some relatively fundamental sense on your side and will not use your confidence against you.
There are many other senses of trust, many of them well correlated, but this is the one I will focus on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Unfortunately it turned out that I could not, in this sense, trust the friend who I came up with this definition in tandem with, and we are no longer friends. Trust is a powerful but high risk strategy).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importance in the sense I'm talking about is how much power you have over eachother's lives, how intertwined they are with you, how much you &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to care about what they think or do. A stranger is low importance. A friend is higher importance. A romantic partner potentially higher yet (but not necessarily! It depends a lot on the friend, or the partner).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importance in this sense isn't about moral worth (a stranger is unimportant to me in this sense, but that doesn't mean they lack moral significance. They're still important &lt;em&gt;as a person&lt;/em&gt;, but that doesn't make them important to you). It's also not about love - your boss is very important to you in this sense, but that doesn't necessarily mean you even like them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Having people who are important to you but whom you don't trust is a very bad thing. Your life becomes unsafe, and you are constantly hiding from them, worrying about how they will use their power against you if they discover your secret. This is an awful place to be in, and it is one that &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; people find themselves in to some degree or another.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a lot of people, family are among the most important people. They have a huge impact on us, and on our emotional lives. In this sense, my strong link between trust and importance is luck: I have a great family, and I trust them. This was probably foundational for me in being able to build trust with other people. For a lot of people, this is not true, and that is where they learn &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html"&gt;about trust and learn to avoid it&lt;/a&gt;.
I had my own problems in this regard, mostly school related. It took me a long time to learn that more people were trustworthy than I thought.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given the freedom of adulthood, you don't have to have the same problems,
because of one very simple observation:
It is much easier to make people who you already trust important to you than it is to learn to trust people who are already important to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If someone has power over you, revealing information to them is high risk. If they can use that information to harm you, and they have the power to harm you, you are literally putting yourself in danger by revealing this information.
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;Safety&lt;/a&gt; is very important to being able to grow trust, and people who are important to you but untrustworthy are not safe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means that you need to start by trusting people much earlier than you are inclined to do so,
&lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; they become important to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In Mark Manson's surprisingly good book about dating, &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Ur16XG"&gt;Models&lt;/a&gt; he talks about polarising as a dating strategy: People are in one of three categories "Not interested", "Interested", and "Unsure". When they are in the "Not interested" category it's not worth trying to move them out of it. Your job when dating is to move people from the "Unsure" category into one of the other two. And, to a first approximation, moving them into &lt;em&gt;either&lt;/em&gt; category is a success, as long as you do so by being authentically yourself in ways that they would find out anyway later.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Polarizing is not a dating specific strategy, it's fairly general purpose: It's a specific implementation of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;doing something as a cheap experiment to learn about the world&lt;/a&gt;.
However, it does rely quite heavily on one specific feature of dating: Early on in the dating process, the people you're trying to date just don't matter to you that much. You need to behave decently towards them, but their opinion of you isn't actually very important. If they decide they don't like you, that's fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this sense, trust is a polarizing strategy, and it's one that is important to apply early on in the relationship before someone becomes important to you. If you trust someone excessively and it goes badly, but they don't matter to you, you can just kick them to the curb.
In general, trusting someone at a level that seems slightly excessive for their level of importance to you will help you sort people in your life who you want to be more important to you than they are from those who you want to be less important than they are.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it does need to be excessive. It needs to be trust beyond reason. Not beyond &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; reason, but somewhat beyond what currently seems reasonable. If it is not, then unless they are prepared to take the first move, you will never find the signs you need to move to a higher level of mutual trust.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes this will go badly, but &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-22-11:37.html"&gt;you need to be able to try bad things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's important not to be reckless (especially when physical safety is concerned), and it's easy to fall into the trap of oversharing. This strategy is scary, not simple, and definitely not easy, but when you can pull it off it provides amazing rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-24-09:46.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-25-16:02.html</id>
    <title>Notes on Running a Mutual Support Group</title>
    <updated>2020-03-25T20:05:50+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes on Running a Mutual Support Group&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've talked about this a little bit in places, but one of the better things I've implemented in the last year is starting
a mutual support group where myself and a number of other friends get together and talk about our problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's great, and I strongly recommend it. Especially while the world is on fire.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our support group is tailored for us, and you should tailor yours for you, so I'll explain the general format,
and then go on to talk a bit more about what ours is like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How to form a support group:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decide what style of group you like. I'll talk about how ours works, but yours may be different.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find some people. I picked friends of mine with whom I regularly had good conversations of the sort I wanted. Four is a good number of people. Three is doable but slightly too small, six feels like an absolute upper bound. It's important to pick people you can &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-24-09:46.html"&gt;trust&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discuss the remaining details together until a support group plan emerges.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A support group needs the following features:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A group agreement, about what the group is for, and how you will talk to eachother. This should be written down, and you should all agree to abide by it, and you should point out when you are not doing it. YOU NEED THE GROUP AGREEMENT I CANNOT STRESS THIS ENOUGH IT WILL BE VERY BAD IF YOU DON'T HAVE IT. You should also explicitly write it yourselves and agree what is actually important to you, not just pick up a canned one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A decision on how often you want to meet and where. We do every three weeks on Tuesday evening, meeting for dinner in one of our flats. Now that we're on lockdown, we'll probably do Zoom or something (we did it via text on WhatsApp once. This was a bad idea)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way to communicate outside of the meetings (we use a WhatsApp group, it's relatively low volume)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A format, but you should use ours for a bit and then tinker with it to suit you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The specific format we use is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We take turns to set a topic, usually a problem that we'd like help on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We set a ten minute timer in which the person explains the topic and then we all discuss it. After the timer goes off we don't cut off dead, but we wrap up, make closing statements, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We use a talking object which you have to be holding to speak beyond very minimalist agreements etc. Ours is a stuffed rabbit. We rely on good etiquette (don't hog the talking object, pass it to people who want it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Theoretically you can wave at someone to suggest that it's a good time to stop talking but we never really need to use it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our specific group is a group of queer, lefty, intelligent, emotionally self-aware, analytical problem solvers (if you ever need to answer the question "Who does David consider to be His People?" that's a pretty good description).
Our style and our topics are very heavily based on that, and based on a heavy amount of therapy skills in the group.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our group agreement is designed to support this. In particular, our basic rules are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This isn't a format for venting. If you're bringing something up it's because you actually want advice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also not a format for debating. It's OK to disagree, but if it's turning into an argument, stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extend good faith. Assume good intentions, and that the person who is speaking has a good reason for saying what they do (this one is really important - it doesn't work in groups of strangers, but everyone here should be someone you can trust).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be someone deserving of (3). When you're not sure, say so. Don't claim more confidence than you have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chatham house rule: it's OK to mention that something came up in support group, but it needs to not be clear who said it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My recommendation would be to try something like these rules and see how they work for you,
but they're definitely skewed towards our desire to treat these problems analytically.
You might want to tinker with (1) and (2) in particular if you're less inclined towards coolly (but empathetically!) discussing your problems and want something that is a bit more emotionally engaged.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something really nice about sitting together in a room with people you trust and talking about your problems in ways where you know that they will be taken seriously, and that people there are invested in helping you solving your problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's also something really valuable in helping other people solve their problems. I think most of us get at least as much out of helping others at support group as we do out of being helped. The process is one that gets us in the mindset of taking problems in our life seriously, and as things are both solvable and worth solving.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-25-16:02.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-26-09:48.html</id>
    <title>Pragmatic Problem Solving (aka Kludges)</title>
    <updated>2020-03-26T10:05:21+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Pragmatic Problem Solving (aka Kludges)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1243110036341248000"&gt;On Twitter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guiding principle: If you can't solve a problem it's probably because you've not tried an ugly enough kludge yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our shower broke this morning. It's been running in a degraded state for a while, but the knob for controlling water flow finally stopped working entirely. We could get our landlord to fix it, he's pretty good about fixing things, but unfortunately we're under quarantine for another week so that's not a viable option.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I fixed it, of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From flatmate WhatsApp this morning:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shower is, in a sense, fixed now. It is probably a temporary fix and will likely break again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fix consists of two ingenious solutions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I returned the missing plastic gizmo to the inside of the shower knob (it came out a while ago and the shower was difficult to make work with it in, so I didn't return it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, in the event that you find you do not have enough grip strength to operate the shower in its current configuration (and you will find this), there is a tea towel hanging on the shower door and you should use that to grip the flow control knob and will find it much more manageable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behold, science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is, in fact, not science, but engineering. More on that in a later post).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I live with other very smart people, and I am not the most practically minded of souls, so why was it me who fixed the shower?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Probably the answer is timing and coincidence as much as anything else. I'm sure someone else would have come up with something eventually. However I think I had a couple of straightforward advantages that lead to this being a thing I just shrugged and solved almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These were:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had some ideas of things to try and was prepared to &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2017/02/thinking-through-the-implications/"&gt;just hit things with them&lt;/a&gt; until something worked. I was originally going to try these two independently (either put the gizmo back, or take the knob off entirely and use the tea towel on the control shaft directly). Neither quite worked, but together they work fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn't care about fixing the shower, I just cared about being able to have one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Another flatmate adopted a bucket shower solution. I considered this unacceptable as long as the possibility of an actual shower existed)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-05-11:27.html"&gt;often worth having bad solutions to demonstrate that a solution is possible&lt;/a&gt; but there's another case in which it's worth having bad solutions:
Often you &lt;em&gt;don't care whether the solution is bad&lt;/em&gt;, you just care that the problem is solved.
If you can't solve the problem, you might just be being limited by good taste.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Use a tea towel to operate the shower" is not a good taste solution. It's ugly, it's kludgy, and for now it's more than good enough, and I can assure you that the way my flatmates and I would smell after a few days without access to a shower is also not in good taste.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-26-09:48.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-27-08:18.html</id>
    <title>Competence is sexy</title>
    <updated>2020-03-27T22:37:11+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Competence is sexy&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Up front disclaimer: I am treating my personal experiences as universal in this post. I think the things I am saying in this post are fairly universally true, but there are obviously going to be people who experience this differently)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Be attractive, don't be unattractive" sounds like trite advice, but actually it contains an important insight (or at least can be read in a deep way): In order to attract people you need to &lt;em&gt;not turn them off&lt;/em&gt; (don't be unattractive) and you need to &lt;em&gt;draw them in&lt;/em&gt; (be attractive).
Sexiness is what draws people in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What is sexiness?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, to a large degree, sexiness is competence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm serious.
You must have noticed how sexy people being good at things is.
This is a general thing. There's something intrinsically attractive about competence, and most forms of sexiness can be framed as competencies.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(An example of a non-competency sexiness is that someone being attracted to you is also sexy, and is not a competency per se unless you're self-assured enough to view it as evidence of them having very good taste)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Experiencing someone as sexy is about fascination. You see something about them, and it draws you in, and makes you want to learn more about them and to explore it. It makes you want more of it. And nothing does this like looking at someone and noticing just how phenomenally &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; they are at something.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not all competencies are equally sexy of course. An amazingly good ballet dancer is (for most people) intrinsically sexy than an equally amazing chess player. But... the latter isn't &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; sexy, as long as you're well placed to appreciate their competence (If you don't understand chess you probably won't find it sexy).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, even for most people who understand chess, the ballet dancer is probably still sexier.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is true even independently of body type. If you somehow had someone who was both an expert ballet dancer and an expert chess player, almost everyone would experience watching them perform ballet as sexier than watching them play chess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which competencies are perceived as sexy is highly individual, but by and large physical and emotional components of competencies are sexier than mental ones. The reason for this is pretty straightforward: For most (but by no means all) people, the physical and emotional components of sex take precedence over the intellectual ones, so this sort of competence is intrinsically more sexual.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You may, of course, be puzzled at the fact that I am talking about sexiness and ignoring physical appearance.
But actually physical appearance is a perfect example of what I'm talking about:
Physical appearance is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; much a competency.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some people are, of course, unambiguously better at physical appearance than others. Some people really are just going to be &lt;a href="https://www.fvathynevgl.com/effortlessness/"&gt;effortlessly&lt;/a&gt; attractive. The rest of us have to work at it, to a greater or lesser extent.
However, this is a normal part of competency. Someone who is an amazing ballet dancer has worked incredibly hard at it, but they also probably have intrinsic advantages (strength, balance, body type) that others who are less good do not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you do competence at physical appearance? You do it by &lt;em&gt;performing an aesthetic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Different aesthetics will appeal differently to different people, but unless the aesthetic is utterly absurd (clowns aren't sexy no matter how good they are at performing the clown aesthetic. No shaming intended if you're into that, but I am never going to understand your mindset on this subject), performing it well is always going to be fairly sexy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Edit to Add: OK fine a friend has convinced me of the possibility that sufficiently competent clowning might be sexy too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is why gender is such a big thing in most people's experience of sexiness: Aesthetics tend to be heavily gendered, and a great deal (not all, maybe not even most, but a major component) of what gender &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; for most people is conformance to a specific gendered aesthetic.
It would be an exaggeration to say that gender is intrinsically sexy, but performance of gender gives people many exciting opportunities for exhibiting sexiness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this is true even for aesthetics that are "wrong" for your gender. Competent performance of an aesthetic designed for a gender different from your own can be &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; sexy if you can pull it off, it's just easier for most people (both through training and through how the aesthetic was designed) to perform sexiness with an aesthetic that matches their gender. It's the performance of the aesthetic itself that is sexy, your appearance just defines how easy it is for you to perform any given aesthetic competently.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is at this point I must tell you a fact that I, as a card carrying bisexual, am all too acutely aware of:
in western anglophone cultures, women are on average substantially more attractive than men.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Before I continue, let me show you an extremely attractive man.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A spanish soldier" src="/images/spanish-soldier-2.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JillFilipovic/status/1241857598778900481"&gt;From a thirst tweet&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sexy, right? (Dear Spanish soldier man: In the extremely unlikely event that you're reading this, I'm very sorry for objectifying you in this way. Well... mostly sorry. It's in a good cause.).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why is he sexy? It's because he is performing an extremely masculine aesthetic &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; competently.
You don't need to be nearly this good at masculinity to perform it competently enough to be sexy. This is fairly upper tier.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, if you read the comments, a lot of people are coming to an inescapable conclusion: He looks really gay.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is bullshit of course. Maybe he is, I don't know him, but just based on weight of numbers I'm going to say probably not. He certainly &lt;em&gt;reads&lt;/em&gt; as gay in our (western, anglophone) culture, but there's a very specific reason for this: We treat competent performance of most masculine aesthetics as gay (there are a few exceptions, but they mostly tend to be for celebrities or people who can pretend to be doing it on natural talent alone, and even then there's a bit of it).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic reason why women are more attractive on average is that they are better at performing an aesthetic than men are. This is for reasons that are actually quite bad, for both men and women but in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Women are punished (through misogyny) for not performing an aesthetic competently, while men are punished for trying to excel at it (through homophobia). The result is that there is vastly more cultural knowledge around how women can perform feminine aesthetics competently than there is for men performing masculine aesthetics competently, and also strong incentives for women to apply that knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The incentive structure is bad (women should not be punished for not wanting to invest effort in their aesthetic if they don't want to), but the lack of widespread cultural knowledge for men on how to improve their aesthetic is also a major problem for us.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In addition to men being punished for success, everyone is punished for failure. The problem is that with aesthetic competence, trying and failing is much worse than not trying. This is especially true for men, not because men are punished more for trying and failing (this is something we are terrible about for people of every gender), but because men are punished less for not trying. It is safer for women to experiment with their aesthetic not because the punishments for failure are less, but because they start from a less safe place so the difference is less. It is more dangerous for men to experiment with their aesthetic not because the punishments for failure are greater, but because they have fewer resources available to them for achieving success.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is that men are &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html"&gt;socially punished for trying to be good&lt;/a&gt; at sexiness, and exist in an environment that is mostly &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;extremely unsafe&lt;/a&gt; for them to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;experiment&lt;/a&gt;, and consequently there is a kind of massive cultural learned helplessness where men want to develop their aesthetic competency in sexy ways but honestly don't know how to.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-27-08:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-28-10:26.html</id>
    <title>On having different thresholds</title>
    <updated>2020-03-28T11:28:42+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;On having different thresholds&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Observe the following behaviours:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not expressing your wants or needs until they become essential for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not talking about your feelings until you can't cope with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not telling someone that their behaviour is bad until you can't deal with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not expressing an opinion until you are certain it's true.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not articulating a thought process until you've fully understood it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These share the following major features:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are about where you set a &lt;em&gt;threshold for action&lt;/em&gt;. How X does a thing have to be before you do Y?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are very common.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are really really unhealthy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For most people, lowering these thresholds will significantly improve your experience of and behaviour in the world.
That's not to say that the thresholds should be set at zero, and there are definitely people who have them set too low, but by and large the norms around where they &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be set are much too high.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why? Well because if you don't do anything until something breaks then you will be constantly &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-04-11:18.html"&gt;skirting the edge of disaster&lt;/a&gt;. For example if you don't express needs until they're essential, none of your non-essential needs are going to be adequately met. You'll maybe not be in crisis, but you'll be low-grade miserable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, once you learn healthier behaviour and set these thresholds lower, you're going to run into a huge problem.
You've suddenly become &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-02-09:31.html"&gt;illegible to other people&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is this: Other people do not have access to your internal state. They do not know how X the thing is, they only know that you have done Y. This will cause them to assume that when you do Y, the thing is as X for you as it would be when other people do Y. This means that if you express an emotion, people will think it is a big deal. If you complain about a bad behaviour, people will think you must be really bothered by it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A concrete example is that I was trying Capoeira last year. About halfway through my second lesson I realised that actually this really isn't for me right now, and that I could cope with the rest of the lesson but it would be moderately unpleasant and I definitely wouldn't be coming back for another one, so I made my apologies and left.
I realised afterwards that people probably thought I was in quite a lot of distress, because that felt like a major move to them. I wasn't. I was just making what for me was a perfectly sensible decision, but most people wouldn't have made it until breaking point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is why talking about feelings often feels like high drama / making a big deal out of nothing. It's not. Talking about feelings is great, and is in fact how you avoid drama and making big deals out of things that don't need to be. But because people are used to not talking about feelings until they absolutely need to be dealt with, when you talk about feelings before they need to be dealt with people assume you're making more of an issue of it than not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Differing thresholds are like &lt;a href="https://sambleckley.com/writing/church-of-interruption.html"&gt;the church of interruption&lt;/a&gt;. People have incompatible conversation norms, and they don't realise that they do or don't know how to fluently speak the other's, so they are constantly miscuing off each other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The solution, I'm afraid, is more talking. It has long been my stance that you need to have conversations about how to have conversations with people, and a crucial part of that is talking about what bringing things up means and how best to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-28-10:26.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-29-21:16.html</id>
    <title>Everything is a teachable moment</title>
    <updated>2020-03-29T22:24:23+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Everything is a teachable moment&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Previously I have written blog posts about:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2017/02/thinking-through-the-implications/"&gt;A cat who can open doors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-26-09:48.html"&gt;Fixing a shower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2013/08/how-did-you-get-started-so-quickly/"&gt;How to get started in a new code base&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Except that's not what any of these are about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They're actually about:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolkitized thinking&lt;/em&gt; - how to apply things that you've learned in other contexts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pragmatic problem solving&lt;/em&gt; - how to let go of the desire to solve the problem properly and just solve the problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Efficient learning&lt;/em&gt; - how not to get distracted by &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-22-18:01.html"&gt;the impossibly large number of things to learn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Each of them are of course about both these things: Something happened, and by looking at what happened you can learn something generalisable about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Typically of course, you don't actually see a single thing and get the general insight, you acquire the general insight after seeing many different things, but often a specific example is exactly what you need to &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/10/how-to-explain-anything-to-anyone/"&gt;explain the point&lt;/a&gt;, possibly to someone else, possibly to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The important feature of these generalisations is that by doing this you learn beyond the specific circumstances you encounter and &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1758026/"&gt;experience the world richly&lt;/a&gt;, letting you draw on your past experience more effectively in novel situations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One way of looking at mathematics is that it's about taking a look at an argument and paring it down to its bare essentials and generalising it. Trying to take something hyper specific and turn it into a simple reusable principle that can be applied, by asking what about the problem actually matters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our interactions with the world are like this too. Everything is a teachable moment, all you have to do is look at it through the right lens and use it to teach something.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-29-21:16.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html</id>
    <title>Desire as a driver of growth</title>
    <updated>2020-03-30T23:12:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Desire as a driver of growth&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-03-30&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wrote before about how &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety is the enabler of growth&lt;/a&gt;: The thing that allows you to grow is to be safe to experiment, so you can learn new ways of being.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is true as far as it goes, but it has a big problem: If you're safe, it's very easy to just stay where you are.
The possibility to grow exists, but you have no particular reason to take it, so you don't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can see this in the stereotype of the spoiled rich kid (although often they're not exactly in safe environments either, so this is weak evidence. Consider it an illustrative example).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic problem is that growth is hard work. You have to want to do it. You have to actually &lt;em&gt;desire&lt;/em&gt; to grow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One key to doing this is what I wrote about in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-23-15:52.html"&gt;life as an anytime algorithm&lt;/a&gt;: Designing goals so that you gain partial benefits as you go. This ensures that you're getting feedback on growth as you proceed, and it doesn't feel like &lt;a href="https://www.fvathynevgl.com/momentum/"&gt;a long hard slog with hopefully a reward at the end&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't enough, because it depends on what type of progress you're making. In particular, I reliably find that progress that just makes things less bad doesn't have the right shape. 
The nagging urge is always there to backslide and just fall back to the old ways. The old ways weren't good, but they sure were easier, and stable, and stability is comforting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to create a desire for growth you need the changes you see to be an actively positive thing.
It makes you hungry for more, and the work feels less like work and more like achievement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two examples where I have encountered this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In my various work on &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;emotions&lt;/a&gt; one of my specific goals has been around the experience of positive emotions. I don't just want to be less miserable, I want to be happier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've been working on my diet. This means I no longer have a permanently upset stomach. That's great and all, but it sure is tempting to backslide because pizza is delicious. But... I must admit, I'm really enjoying the weight loss. I know, I know, body positivity, but I feel &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-27-08:18.html"&gt;a lot better about my body&lt;/a&gt; than I have in some time, and that's really nice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You need to clear out the negative stuff too (more of my emotion work is on anxiety than joy, but the two feed into each other). It's important not to overfocus on the positive, but without the positive to drive growth you will often give up, and that means you end up doing less work on the negatives in total.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
