<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2024-01-28T16:21:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-20-11:18.html</id>
    <title>Shared frustrations</title>
    <updated>2024-01-20T12:00:45+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Shared frustrations&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am, it will shock you to know, annoyingly finickity about things
being done correctly. It hurts me somewhere deep in my soul when people
do things in obviously suboptimal ways.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Importantly I’m fine with people doing things less well
because it’s easier. What annoys me is when people are obviously failing
&lt;em&gt;by their own standards&lt;/em&gt;, getting worse outcomes for a worse
experience of doing the thing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I try to reign this in. I don’t actually like telling people off, so
I’ll often be silently frustrated rather than telling someone about
it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is a bad idea for anything recurring, because as a
result I sound super annoyed by minor things when I finally break and do
say something about it. I’m not saying I don’t do that, I’m just saying
I do that and I know it’s a bad idea. If you will, an obviously
suboptimal approach that is failing even by my own standards…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you two instances of this recently and something
interesting I learned from them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is this: We have an instant pot. Its pressure cooking mode
gets used for roughly two categoires of things: Making stock (usually
beef, sometimes chicken), and what you might think of as “normal
cooking” - stews, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Crucially, these take very different times. Stock takes about four
hours, normal cooking takes somewhere between 20 and 45 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Adjusting the time on an instant pot is very slow. This makes
switching between these two times irritating. Fortunately, the instant
pot has a feature for this: The pressure cooker remembers two previous
times, and you can press the pressure cook button to switch between
them. So you can have it remember a four hour time and a half hour time,
and everything is fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At least, everything is fine if people use this feature and don’t set
both timers to four hours, forcing me to do the slow adjustment process
every time I used the normal cooking mode. Very annoying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did eventually explain this feature to the others in my house, and
of course neither of them knew about this feature - it’s not like they
would have been maliciously setting the timer wrong, and it’s a pretty
non obvious feature until you know about it, and I only found out about
it relatively recently. Problem solved. But I’d been vaguely annoyed
every time I used the instant pot for the entire several month period
between discovering this feature and telling people about it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;To be clear I don’t use the instant pot &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;
often, so we’re talking about maybe 3 or 4 times at most.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More on this in a moment, but now let me tell you about another
kitchen irritation: Someone has been stacking the pots wrong. This means
that the cupboard doesn’t close properly because the pot stack is too
tall.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s a specific stacking order to the pots. If you get it right,
the pot stack is short enough for everything to work fine. If you get it
wrong, they don’t nest and it’s too tall. Someone had been placing pots
in a non-nesting order, and this was causing problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually we were in the kitchen together at the time when the pots
needed stacking, and I showed them how to do it. “Oh, that’s how you
stack them! I had no idea those nested, they look exactly the same size.
That’s been so annoying.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are two interesting things about this response:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They were in fact correct, it was slightly non-obvious. The pots are
&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; exactly the same size, but they do look pretty similar from
the outside, it’s just that one has much thinner metal than the other so
although they look similar in size the slightly smaller one nests easily
in the slightly larger one, because the interior of the slightly larger
one is much larger relative to the slightly smaller one than their
exterior would suggest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They’d been annoyed by this too, and I hadn’t shown them how to
solve their annoying problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This recontextualised some things for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That instant pot thing? Adjusting the timer to four hours from half
an hour is just as annoying as adjusting the timer from four hours to
half an hour. I shared it as a “this is a thing you do that is annoying
to me and here is how to not do it” but in actual fact it was probably a
thing we &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; were finding frustrating, and that I could easily
have shared as “Hey you know that annoying thing? I’ve figured out the
solution!”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing about being annoyingly finickity is that because I care
about doing things right, and because I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-18-10:00.html"&gt;debug
everything so reflexively&lt;/a&gt; is that “obviously suboptimal ways” is not
actually obvious to others. It’s obvious to me because I’ve &lt;em&gt;figured
it out&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes through careful problem solving and sometimes
because I accidentally pressed the button twice and noticed what
happened when I did.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I’ve done that, I can share this knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The silly thing is that I’m actually very good at sharing knowledge a
lot of the time. I have a sort of habitual attitude of teaching when
people ask me for help. e.g. a great habit of mine that you should
definitely steal is that when people can’t find a link and I find it
using search, I give them both the link and also tell them how I found
it. This is a great way of helping people be better at search, which is
a surprisingly deep and hard to learn skill.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;The downside of this habit is that it sounds a bit too
“let me google that for you” if you’re not careful. I usually &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/telegraph-your-moves"&gt;telegraph&lt;/a&gt;
why I’m doing this quite carefully, and am very explicit that it’s not a
problem if they apologise for not googling for it themselves.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I’m good at sharing information spontaneously - you’re
reading this on one of my outlets for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But volunteering information to someone specific, in response to
something that they’re doing wrong, feels different. Like I said, it
feels like telling them off, and I don’t like doing that. It feels bad
for me to do it, and I’m worried about people reacting badly to it. Most
people don’t like unsolicited advice. Not that I expect anything to go
terribly wrong from telling partners about minor things, but it might
hurt their feelings and I don’t actually like doing that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think this fear is somewhat real - a lot of the time people
don’t like being told they’re doing it wrong, and often wrong is
subjective. Sometimes &lt;em&gt;I’m&lt;/em&gt; wrong because the suboptimal way is
in fact optimising for some preference I don’t know about. I suspect
it’s exaggerated in my head, but it is a real possibility.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I think a lot of the time, the fear is largely the result of a
skill issue on my part, and I need to stop thinking in terms of “argh
you’re doing it wrong” and more “boy it looks annoying to do it that
way. Can I show you a thing?” and see how people respond.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-20-11:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-20-12:01.html</id>
    <title>Developing new capacities</title>
    <updated>2024-01-20T12:44:36+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Developing new capacities&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s a general phenomenon that I think of as “capacities” - your
ability to do things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A capacity can be anything. It can be a broad skill, it can be a
narrow trick that you know how to solve some particular problem with. It
can be a physical item. It can be someone you know who you can do the
thing for you. It can be some complex emergent combination of all of
these thigns.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A capacity is not just that you can or can’t do the thing. It’s
&lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; you do the thing, and a crucial part is how easy it is for
you to do the thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A good illustration of this for me is cars. I’ve owned a car, for the
first time in my life, for a bit over a year. Previously, whenever I
needed a car I rented one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From a financial perspective, I’d probably still have spent less
money on my car if every time I used it over the last year I rented a
car instead. We’re getting to a point where it might be close, but I
think I’d still have spent about 50% less money.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In actual fact I’d have spent a lot less than that of course, because
most of the times I’ve used the car over that year I just wouldn’t have
bothered. It’s not just about the financial cost, it’s about the fact
that my car is literally right there and I can just get in and drive.
Renting a car adds a significant effort overhead that makes small
transactions not worth it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Yes, I’m aware of Zipcar and the like. In my experience
they’re exactly optimised for use cases I don’t have, and end up
strictly worse for almost anything I care about.&lt;/span&gt; In theory, owning the
car doesn’t make me able to do anything that renting a car wouldn’t, but
in practice the different effort levels involved make it a very
qualitatively different capacity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, as well as the cost and convenience, having the ability to
casually drive means I get better at driving because I do it more
regularly. This makes driving less stressful, so I’m more willing to do
it. Having the capacity teaches you to use the capacity, and thereby
enlarges it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did know this prior to owning a car, but I probably still
undervalued it. The main thing I bought a car for was to be able to
drive to and from my parents’ house - it’s about an hour’s drive from me
by car, and essentially has no public transport options to get there in
under three hours.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In actual fact, I would probably still just about be
ahead on cost if I’d taken a taxi to and from my parents’ every time
I’ve visited them since buying this car. It would come to maybe £200 for
the round trip, and I’ve probably visited them maybe 20 times since
then, which is only £4,000. But also many of the trips would not have
happened at this price tag - it’s easy to pop around for dinner on a
whim with a car, but that wouldn’t happen with a £200 price tag and the
need for advance planning that comes with a taxi.&lt;/span&gt; It was very much a response to a
particular problem I had.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But once you have a car, you can just use it for easy things. I use
it for shopping from time to time, I use it for moving big things. I can
bring a giant stack of firewood back from my parents’ place if I want,
which a taxi would side eye me on. I can pop over to the next town
easily.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I probably still underutilise the car to be honest. Part of this is
that I feel at some level I shouldn’t be driving too much (I think this
is true but that I’m probably overstating it). Part of this is just that
I’m still used to a mindset that I’ve had for most of my life, where I
don’t own a car and can’t do car things as a result.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems like something I should fix. The car is useful, and
expensive to maintain, so I might as well figure out how to make use of
it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a much more &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/why-is-it-hard-to-choose-what-to"&gt;proactive
mode&lt;/a&gt; than I often remember to deploy. I’m all about “That does seem
like a problem. Have you tried solving it?” but this is much more “That
does seem like a solution. Have you tried finding problems to solve with
it?”. It’s worth doing, I just don’t habitually do that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly: I don’t know that I could have done it nearly so well
without owning a car and starting to recontextualise how useful they
are. Once you have the capacity and you figure out how to use it well,
you unlock a lot of hidden value that just thinking in terms of what
problems you already have that could be solved with it, because it
doesn’t just solve existing problems for you, it opens up things that
you don’t even think of as problems because it doesn’t occur to you that
you can do them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of why I’ve been thinking about this recently is that my income
has gone up a lot over the last year, and money is very much a capacity,
and I’ve been trying to figure out ways to deploy that capacity for life
improvement recently. It’s going pretty well. There are fairly modest
low hanging fruits available that you just don’t think about when money
is tight, and aren’t even that expensive once it’s loosened up a bit.
For example I paid for an ironing service recently, because I like
wearing collared shirts&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although I haven’t actually started wearing them again
yet. Lost the habit and I’ve been busy.&lt;/span&gt; but hate ironing. It cost about £20
to get literally every shirt I own ironed. Not free by any means, but
very affordable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another capacity I’ve been working on that flows out of this recently
is that I realised that my household would very much benefit from some
additional help with admin, so we’ve hired a part-time PA&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;How did I find a PA? I posted on the local Facebook
group asking if anyone was available for such work. Another thing I
recently discovered existed, and thereby developed a capacity I
previously lacked.&lt;/span&gt; on
an experimental basis. We’ll basically give her odd jobs and pay her
weekly at a rate of £15/hour for however much work she’s done during
that week. This is an &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; early days experiment, so there
are loads of things that may or may not work about it, but I’m very
happy to have done it nevertheless.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting things about this decision is that I don’t
really know what sort of tasks we’ll give her. The specific prompt was I
wanted someone to offload a search for a good cleaner to, but that’s
totally something I could do myself&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And has been totally something I could do myself for
months…&lt;/span&gt;. We’ve got a bunch of
other small tasks like that, but there’s a very real possibility that
we’ll just work through a TODO list and then by done.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I don’t think so. I think having someone like this to offload
tasks to is going to be a really good capacity to have, and I’m looking
forward to finding out ways to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-20-12:01.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-21-09:41.html</id>
    <title>Drawing on resources</title>
    <updated>2024-01-21T10:24:34-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Drawing on resources&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-21&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Complementary to the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-20-12:01.html"&gt;capacities&lt;/a&gt;
view of things, another useful broad label is “resources”. Resources are
essentially anything you can draw on to do stuff. Possibly, though not
necessarily, in a consumable way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s some overlap between the two concepts of course, in that
every resource implies a capacity of stuff you can do by drawing on that
resource. e.g. I talked about money as a capacity, and money is
obviously also a resource.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the places I find this view most useful is creativity in
general, and writing in particular. When you are writing, you have
essentially all of your existing pool of experiences and knowledge as a
resource to draw on. All of the e.g. conversations you’ve had, books
you’ve read, idle thoughts you’ve had, things you’ve done, previous
material you’ve written, sit together in your head as a kind of pool of
inadequately articulated material that you can pull on and refine out
into something that you write about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m a big fan of the view that creativity isn’t really something you
generate, but is instead a (skilled and difficult!) exploration of the
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-things-come-to-be-as-they-are"&gt;adjacent
possible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. The resources available to you define your adjacent
possible because you draw on them to elaborate and combine them into new
material.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that seems to be common with creative resources is that
they become stale. You see this with some authors who, for example, draw
on their professional experience and produce really good work, but the
more they become writers and the further divorced they are from that
professional experience, the more shallow their writing becomes. I liked
Lethain’s &lt;a href="https://lethain.com/writers-who-operate"&gt;writers who
operate&lt;/a&gt; as an expression of this problem. This was definitely part
of my concern with my consulting business too - I was a bit too far
removed from the professional experiences I was drawing on, and as a
result I’m appreciating going back into more senior IC level work. It
definitely feels like I have a much richer set of renewing experiences
to draw on now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You also see this thing in fiction. For example, hypothetically, you
might have a science fiction writer who is clearly drawing on his
experience as a software developer who has dealt with a lot of office
bullshit, but the longer he’s a science fiction writer the less relevant
any of that experience becomes. Hypothetically.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also came up during the pandemic I think. I don’t know if you
noticed, but it feels like a lot of material that was written in
2020-2021 is a bit… flat. As if the day to day experience people were
drawing on as stimulus for their writing was no longer there. I might be
imagining this - it’s certainly at least partly a reflection of
&lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; mood during those times as anyone else’s.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One general strategy that I think is worth doing is to seek out
activities that cause you to generate new resources. For example, it’s
good to have regular conversations with people about the sorts of things
you might like to write about.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;A non-trivial number of my posts in general are sparked
by conversations on discord.&lt;/span&gt; I also use &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-16-13:11.html"&gt;journaling&lt;/a&gt;
as a place to generate half formed thoughts for drawing on.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-21-09:41.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-22-07:54.html</id>
    <title>Landmarks</title>
    <updated>2024-01-22T08:10:54-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Landmarks&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-22&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think part of why I like solving problems so much is that they
serve as landmarks in the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you’ve got a problem you don’t know how to solve, then solving it
necessarily involves learning something new.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That’s not a deep insight. It’s just what “don’t know how to solve”
means.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But the flipside of this is that the fact that you have the problem
means that you know something about that discovery: It has to solve the
problem, and you do understand the problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Discovery is about walking up to the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-26-09:00.html"&gt;edge
of the familiar&lt;/a&gt; and stepping over.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You start from where you are, and then you go to something new.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Normally, this is bewildering. You step out of familiar territory and
are in a bewildering landscape with a million directions you can go in,
and no clear way to choose between them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After all, if you knew where you were going then it wouldn’t be
unfamiliar territory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But when you have a problem to solve, it gives you a clear sense of
direction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s as if you can see the shape of the solution towering in the
distance, telling you which to go: This way. Towards me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can evaluate your unfamiliar discoveries against your problem -
do they solve it? Do they help understand it? Do they at least do
something interesting with it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem does not, exactly, tell you which way to go. There will
be dead ends, there will be detours. The landscape of the unfamiliar is
mysterious and hard to navigate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But you can tell if you’re getting closer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People aren’t for any one simple thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But one of the things I’ve always known I am for is expanding the
boundaries of human understanding.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’d like it to be in large ways. I certainly haven’t managed this
yet, but I have managed many small ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m not exactly content with that, but I am pleased that I have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But one of the difficulties is knowing where to start, what to
do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The unfamiliar is vast, and “expand the boundaries of human
knowledge” isn’t exactly a clear mandate. How can you possibly pick a
direction? I don’t know where to start.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I of course know the answer, even if I haven’t always been good at
executing on it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because there’s a little voice in my head that when it hears the
question, answers thus:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yes, that does sound like a problem, David. Have you tried solving
it?&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-22-07:54.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-23-06:57.html</id>
    <title>I don’t wanna</title>
    <updated>2024-01-23T07:36:45-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;I don’t wanna&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s a particular feeling that I think of as the “I don’t wanna”
feeling. It’s a kind of sluggish resentment, of the sort you get when
someone asks you to do something when you’re tired, or ill, or
hungover.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s the sort of feeling where &lt;a href="https://the-toast.net/2014/02/13/woman-has-to-do-the-same-shit-tomorrow/"&gt;Woman
Amazed And Horrified She Has To Just Keep Getting Up And Doing The Same
Shit Again Tomorrow&lt;/a&gt; starts to become extremely relatable:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This isn’t an actual problem,” this woman tried to tell herself.
“The fact that I have to…do things to exist, that isn’t an actual
problem.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Which, oh God,” she realized, “means there’s no actual
solution.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I definitely find the frequency with which this feeling comes is a
depression sign. Feeling like this regularly and about regular things is
absolutely not a sign that you’re in a healthy emotional state.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I think it’s interesting to note the places that it comes up even
when I’m &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; especially depressed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, it’s often the specific feeling underlying &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/you-cant-solve-procrastination"&gt;procrastination&lt;/a&gt;
for me. Especially on certain classes of task. e.g. I hate cleaning my
room. I’m aware this is childish.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And probably if I dig deep there’s some &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/parts-of-you-havent-grown-up-yet-004"&gt;child
part&lt;/a&gt; expressing some specificoutrage there&lt;/span&gt;. That’s often how “I
don’t wanna” feels.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But another more interesting place it comes up is tasks for which it
feels like this way &lt;em&gt;sometimes&lt;/em&gt;. Writer’s block is a very “I
don’t wanna” feeling for example.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I leave it as an exercise to the interested reader to
infer why I picked this particular topic to write about today.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s often possible to work past this particular instance of “I don’t
wanna” with a sort of gentle self-coaxing, but it tends to be a bit like
pulling teeth, with every step along the way requiring a constant level
of coaxing. “You don’t have to do very much, just write a short piece”
or “If you can’t think of anything, why not use this prompt…?”. These
strategies work as long as I &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/believing-that-you-can-stop"&gt;believe
that you can stop&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Of course to a degree that promise is to some degree
fake. e.g. I really am going to write a notebook post every day
regardless of how I feel about it, and I’m not going to abandon a post
literally midway through, though I might cut it short.&lt;/span&gt; sometimes, but there’s a sort of low
bubbling resentment at being made to do the thing throughout the entire
experience.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting things about the feeling of “I don’t wanna” is
that it very much comes with a feeling that the thing being requested is
&lt;em&gt;too hard&lt;/em&gt;, but this is clearly fake. You can tell it’s fake
because the internal response to making the thing easier is a sort of
“Fuck you”, and because a great deal more effort than the thing itself
would take is spent resisting it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Again, leading credence to the idea that it’s some sort
of child part.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think a more accurate reading of this “it’s too hard” feeling is “I
don’t wanna do the thing, so I’m going to &lt;em&gt;make sure&lt;/em&gt; that it’s
too hard to be worth it”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The feeling is also sortof recursively resistant to introspection.
The feeling that comes up when I try to introspect an “I don’t wanna” is
an “I don’t wanna!!”.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I probably don’t need to keep pointing out how extremely
literally this seems like interacting with a child.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things that’s interesting is how often the “I don’t wanna”
isn’t exactly wrong and is more of an “I’m not ready”. There have been
enough instances of having this sort of feeling on something - writing a
thing, fixing a bug, etc. where all I needed to do was sleep on it and
the next day was able to easily and fluently work on it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in the other direction waiting for the next day is
often actively unhelpful, because it can let the I don’t wanna feeling
really take hold and a long period of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-06-12:00.html"&gt;drifting&lt;/a&gt;
can easily begin. That’s the sort of time when an I don’t wanna feeling
is secretly depression. I don’t think my model of depression as a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-19-10:53.html"&gt;consistent
bias towards inaction&lt;/a&gt; is the whole of the picture&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Especially because depression is multifaceted and this
is only one type of depression I’m talking about.&lt;/span&gt;,
but it does seem to keep rearing its head.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One place this feeling really comes up, no matter how depressed or
not I am at the moment, is anything that feels like it’s trying to
“force” creativity. If I’m in a creative mood, being creative is easy,
but it’s not like I stop being able to be creative when I’m not in the
mood - I understand creativity well enough that I have systems that
would absolutely let me do it if I could bring myself to use them when
blocked, but unfortunately most of the time I very much don’t wanna.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-23-06:57.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-24-22:09.html</id>
    <title>Layers of being bad at things</title>
    <updated>2024-01-25T06:00:45-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Layers of being bad at things&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-24&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you about a very specific series of realisations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First, an observation: I am bad at standing on one leg. Not awful,
just bad. I can do it, but not for long, and I wobble.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For most of my life I just thought of this as an intrinsic fact about
me. Not very good balance, bit uncoordinated, has flat feet, therefore
bad at standing on one leg. It’s only natural.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it turns out that if I clench my core muscles and the glute
muscle of the leg I’m standing on, I instantly stabilise. I don’t
completely stop wobbling, but I go from very unstable to pretty stable,
with only a minor wobble.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a me thing, that’s normal. Those are just the muscles you
use to stabilise that position, so if you want to stand on one leg you
need to engage them. But, apparently, if I just try to stand on one leg
I don’t engage them enough.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an &lt;a href="https://celandine13.livejournal.com/33599.html"&gt;errors vs bugs&lt;/a&gt;
thing. I’m not “bad at standing on one leg”. There is a specific defect
in how I’m trying to stand on one leg, where I’m not doing one of the
things required.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some level I find this very counterintuitive. Aren’t muscles just
supposed to… do the thing? Like when I’m walking, I don’t think about
what muscles I’m using. And that’s not just because walking is easy. I
also don’t think about what muscles I’m using when I’m lifting something
heavy.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Though I bet some weight lifter reading this just winced
and went “Of &lt;em&gt;course&lt;/em&gt; you’re supposed to pay attention to your
muscles when lifting, you idiot.”&lt;/span&gt; You just do the thing and the
muscles you need to do the thing automatically engage, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Apparently not, though, at least not for me when it comes to standing
on one leg. Or with many other movements. I’ve been doing pilates
recently, and it’s remarkably easy to do almost the right movement while
using completely the wrong muscles to get the desired effect.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do expect that people who are good at standing on one leg just do
this automatically. There’s no conscious attention to those muscles,
they just do the thing. This is the unconscious competence stage of the
skill, and I’ve just entered the conscious incompetence stage of the
skill, where I’m still bad at it but I know why I’m bad at it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there’s another interesting layer to this: When I stand on one
leg this way it’s &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. I’m better at it, but I can’t
necessarily do it for much longer. The limitation is no longer my
balance, it’s pure muscle strength. Those muscles don’t like clenching
that way. I’m sure this is just a practice thing and is pointing at some
good exercises for me to be doing, but right now I’m weak in a way that
means that even knowing how to do this I’m not actually that much better
at it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is probably part of why I’m doing it wrong in the first place:
Doing it right feels much worse. Of course, this is a vicious cycle
where in doing it the “easy” way, I never learn to do it right, and as a
result it never becomes easier because I never develop the strength to
do it the right way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The solution to this is to practice &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-07-08:50.html"&gt;doing
things the hard way&lt;/a&gt;, but I think it’s important to notice something:
If I’d just practiced standing on one leg the way I was doing
previously, the results would have been mediocre at best, because the
way I was doing it was not engaging the right muscles and thus was not
something that would have developed strength over time. In order for it
to be useful to practice doing things the hard way, I first had to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-18-10:00.html"&gt;figure
out what it was that wasn’t working&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-24-22:09.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-25-19:45.html</id>
    <title>Noticing things as life happens</title>
    <updated>2024-01-25T20:44:24-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Noticing things as life happens&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was at an event recently where someone tried to kill me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m being a little overdramatic here. It wasn’t &lt;em&gt;personally&lt;/em&gt;
directed at me. Also I wouldn’t have died even if they had succeeded in
their attempt, it would just have ruined my day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Probably very few people indeed would have died from the specific
thing they did. Plenty would be hospitalised, certainly, and even among
those not hospitalised, many would have had a much much worse time than
I did.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But only slight variations on what they did could absolutely have
been fatal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am, of course, talking about the catering.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To be less vague, here’s what happened: I was having the pleasant
experience of looking around a buffet and seeing a lot of things I could
actually eat, all clearly labelled with allergens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’d actually already eaten, so I didn’t get much, but I did wander
over to the desserts section. There there was a selection of delicious
looking creams. Unfortunately, I cannot eat delicious looking creams, as
they’re made mainly of wheat and dairy, my two big dietary nemeses.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But! They had vegan cashew creams which, unlike their non-vegan
neighbours, were not listed as containing gluten. Hurrah, dessert for
me. I piled a small plate with them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I looked at them, and I looked at their gluten-containing
neighbours with a literally identical shell to the allegedly gluten free
ones I was holding, and a little voice in my head said “hmmmm. I have
doubts.”I queried with the staff, and they confirmed that yes in fact
the vegan cashew creams were, while vegan, not gluten free.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Side note: It’s an ongoing bugbear of mine that “vegan”
is often treated as maximally inclusive. Big fan of there being vegan
food for vegans, but it’s actually quite a lot harder to make vegan food
compatible with other dietary requirements and also still be good and
massively limits your options.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I put down my plate, sulked away, and kicked up a fuss with
the event organisers. They, thankfully, took it very seriously, and
raised it with the vendor.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there are a couple of interesting things about this
story.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is: This error is really really bad. The dish in question
listed allergens, and other dishes listed the allergen I was looking out
for, but this dish did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; list that allergen despite
containing it. This about the most dangerous possible way to be
unreliable with your allergen info, because it’s practically guaranteed
to create a false sense of security. Doing this is much worse than not
including allerrgen info at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I say, I’m lucky in that my dietary problems just aren’t that bad.
I’d have had a bad day if I’d eaten these. People with celiac disease
would have had a much much worse time. And if someone had a really
severe allergy to an ingredient they’d done this on, they could have
died.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I do expect that anyone with that severe an allergy is
even more cautious than me and would have caught this, but I sure
wouldn’t want to count on that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second is: Boy did I not take it seriously enough given that. I
should have stayed with the tray until it had a big sign saying
“contains wheat” on it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is that I’d had a day of petty food annoyances at
this point. Nothing serious, just a mix of bad luck, oversights, and
mild inconsideration from various people. This sort of thing makes me
disproportionately annoyed, because an already stressful experience of
trying to navigate food is made more stressful, I’m extremely picky
about meal plans being disrupted, and I have to deal with all of this
while hangry.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What this meant is that when this happened to me I went “Oh, another
bloody petty food annoyance. Fuck sake”. It was only when thinking about
it some more and reporting it to the event staff that it dawned on me
quite what a big deal this actually was.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another interesting thing about this was that apparently it was
relatively common knowledge among the attendees that this vendor was not
trustworthy in this way. I was just left ignorant of that as a relative
newcomer. I don’t quite know what could have been done to communicate
that to me (especially as I hadn’t made a big deal of my dietary
requirements, which I usually don’t), so I don’t really blame anyone for
that, but it’s interesting context.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It probably also means that the event was safer than it
seems due to the relative lack of people who could be affected.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yet another interesting thing is that I noticed this at all.
Visually, the shell of these creams wasn’t &lt;em&gt;blatantly&lt;/em&gt; wheat
based. It’s totally plausible they could have been made out of some sort
of gluten-free flour. Without the reference point of other similar
things that were clearly made of wheat, I could easily have fallen for
it. But there was that moment of looking from one to the other and
paying attention to a dawning suspicion that made it worth checking. I
think this would have been easy for me to overlook, but I didn’t.
Possibly this is because my bad food day had primed me for suspicion,
possibly this is just because this is the kind of discrepancy I look for
in the world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But the final interesting thing is just how many interesting things
there are about this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something I’ve been thinking about recently is storytelling. My
ability to write fiction is often a really good barometer of my mental
health.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Pay no attention to how long it’s been since I’ve
written any fiction. I’m fine! Fine, I tell you!&lt;/span&gt; I think it’s partly because in order
to write fiction I have to be able to tackle questions like… what sort
of life is worth paying attention to? Like sure I could write some sort
of &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/psychology-of-litrpg"&gt;trash
litrpg&lt;/a&gt; but I probably couldn’t because the whole point of litrpg for
me is disengagement, and story telling requires you to engage with the
lives of the characters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which uh, requires engaging with life at all, and as you may be
picking up a certain vibe from recent&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And not so recent. I keep looking at random notebook
posts and finding posts from years ago about depression that are
annoyingly relatable.&lt;/span&gt; I’m a bit depressed at
the moment, which makes that difficult. Mostly what I want is stuff to
hyperfocus on so I can ignore all… this (gestures broadly).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was rereading this old post of mine about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-03-14:16.html"&gt;relearning
curiosity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;On the subject of old posts about depression…&lt;/span&gt; and it strikes me that the precursor
to curiosity is &lt;em&gt;finding things interesting&lt;/em&gt;, and cultivating the
skill of doing that and applying it broadly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And, depressed or not, I’m actually quite good at finding interesting
things. It’s the same skill as the one that let me spot the secretly
wheaty cashew creams, or &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-24-22:09.html"&gt;write
a post about standing on one leg and generalisable lessons from
that&lt;/a&gt;. You look at stuff, you notice how it fits in with other
things, and you notice how it doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the foundational realisations that set me on my current path
is this: You’re allowed to find your own problems interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this perhaps doesn’t go far enough. You’re allowed to find
&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of your life interesting, whether it has problems in it or
not. Paying attention to what happens and engaging with it is probably
very important, and learning to tell interesting (to you) stories about
what happens in it is probably a really important tool.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-25-19:45.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-26-06:32.html</id>
    <title>The Candle Exercise</title>
    <updated>2024-01-26T07:53:36-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The Candle Exercise&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did an A Level&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;The last two years of school before university in the
UK.&lt;/span&gt; in Chemistry. I mostly disliked
it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There were however a couple things I liked that occurred in it. I
think they were all despite the curriculum rather than because of it -
one of my chemistry teachers was pretty good, and she set us a bunch of
work that was off curriculum (and largely I think about teaching us a
more general scientific attitude than chemistry itself).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing was that quite early on she set us an exercise in
observational writing which stuck with me. The exercise is this: Take a
candle, light it, and then write down everything you can observe about
it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What you will quickly find is that you can observe quite a lot. I
don’t have a candle with me right now, but here’s a picture of one (from
&lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Candle_flame.JPG"&gt;wikimedia
commons&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Picture of a candle" src="/images/candle.jpg"/&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I won’t do the exercise in full but, for example, notice how the
candle flame has quite a complex structure. It’s more transparent around
the wick and becomes yellow as you move up. You can also notice that
only the tip of the wick glows.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can try to generate hypotheses about why these things are
happening, and it can be enlightening to do so, but importantly
&lt;em&gt;that’s not part of the exercise&lt;/em&gt;. You’re here to observe. Write
down everything you see, with as little interpretation as possible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What you find is that there is an awful lot to observe about a
candle. Even just looking at it, a candle has a lot of detail. Some of
it general to candles, some specific to the one you’re looking at.
e.g. where does wax run down the side? What’s the structure of the lip
near there and far away from it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also use your other senses. Touch it!&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;You probably shouldn’t touch the flame, but it might be
informative to put your hand near it.&lt;/span&gt;
Where is the candle warm? How does heat conduct through the wax? You can
also smell it (though if it’s a paraffin wax candle like most are it
probably won’t smell like much). You can listen to it - what does a
burning candle sound like?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also interact with it. What happens when you tip the candle?
What happens if you blow on it briefly? What do you observe if you blow
it out? And then relight it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For my chemistry class I only wrote a page or two, but I think you’d
find you can probably easily write 10,000 words or more about a single
candle.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it’s a very interesting exercise that as you can see has
stuck with me for a very long time. It’s a very good and immediate way
of experiencing the fact that &lt;a href="http://johnsalvatier.org/blog/2017/reality-has-a-surprising-amount-of-detail"&gt;reality
has a surprising amount of detail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn’t super specific to candles. Any object will do, but a
candle is particularly good for it with its range of sensory experiences
and the fact that it’s an actual dynamic object doing something.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m thinking about this as a follow on to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-25-19:45.html"&gt;my
recent thoughts about noticing interesting things&lt;/a&gt; about your life of
course. If there’s this much interesting detail to notice about a
candle, surely an entire day has at least as much interesting
detail?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t always feel like it of course. It’s very common to get to
the end of the day and go “What even happened today?”, particularly on
days I end up spending &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-06-12:00.html"&gt;drifting&lt;/a&gt;.
If anything, drifting feels like a strategy to deliberately achieve
that, and basically pretend the day isn’t happening. But even a drifty
day has a lot in it, you just may not like what’s there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was an exercise I was doing from &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Making-Magic-Together-Everyday-Extraordinary/dp/1683642481"&gt;Making
Magic&lt;/a&gt; that I committed to doing for thirty days and then… didn’t.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This happens a lot.&lt;/span&gt; - I probably only managed about 8 -
which is that each morning you try to journal about what happened the
previous day. I think this would be a good exercise for me to revisit,
but with a focus on trying to identify small numbers of things to write
about in detail rather than trying to provide a full account of the day
like I did previously. The goal isn’t to remember everything, but to
identify things worth remembering.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-26-06:32.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-27-13:16.html</id>
    <title>Restrictions</title>
    <updated>2024-01-27T13:39:05-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Restrictions&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m staying on the 16th floor of a hotel at the moment. When I
arrived, this was a pleasing novelty. Buildings are rarely this tall at
home so I thought it was neat to have this casually be a thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then the fire alarm went off yesterday and I had to walk down 16
flights of stairs. I was less pleased by the novelty after that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(It turned out to be a false alarm, but I only found that out on the
ground floor)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It occurred to me belatedly that in actual fact I probably
&lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt; stay on the 16th floor of a hotel, because there’s no
guarantee of my ability to walk down 16 flights of stairs. As I
sometimes half-joke, it’s not that I’m disabled, I just sometimes can’t
walk. It doesn’t happen often, but maybe once every few months with no
warning my right knee goes and I can barely walk on it, and I would have
really struggled to make it down all those stairs if that had
happened.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that, today I am paying the cost of that with a significant
increase in the chronic pain in my right leg. My hip in particular
really doesn’t like me right now. Although I was able to walk, it comes
with genuine consequences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t thought about this before because tall hotels are largely
outside of my experience, so the thought never occurred. But not it has,
and I am aware of the risk. So, taking this new knowledge into account,
in future I should probably make a particular request when staying at
hotels to stay on a lower numbered floor. It’s the safe and responsible
thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m not going to do that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this is just not wanting to overcorrect on rare events. I
think this is the first time I’ve had a fire alarm in a hotel I’ve
stayed in, and I’ve stayed in quite a few hotels. A rare event happened
and no terrible consequences occurred. This is a lousy prompt to create
a policy. Life doesn’t need more organisational scar tissue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Granted, asking to be on a lower floor isn’t a big deal (though it
would have required significantly more interaction with the hotel than I
did before arriving), but the aggregate effect of many things that are
individually not big deals adds up to quite a lot of effort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But more than that… adding many little restrictions and
accommodations results in a much smaller life. In the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-20-12:01.html"&gt;capacities&lt;/a&gt;
post I talked about how having a car lowers the activation energy of
many things, and so it’s not just that it’s easier to do the things you
were doing before, you do things that you wouldn’t previously done.
Adding restrictions makes many things that would previously have been
worth it not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Food is like this for me. I love eating out, and I love trying new
cuisines, but the difficulty of satisfying my dietary restrictions means
that I lose a lot of upside (many delicious things I can’t eat) and
experience a lot more downside (risk of digestive problems, awkward high
effort interactions with staff) and this means that many things are not
worth the effort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Individually, the losses are small. In aggregate though it makes
quite a meaningful impact to my life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve no great attachment to staying in tall hotels, but it’s quite
nice - it’s a pleasant novelty, and I enjoy the view. It would be no
great loss if I never did it again, but I do think the aggregate effect
of choosing to avoid these sorts of minor risks for an increase in
effort and a decrease in novelty would end up large, and would result in
a smaller and less lived life.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-27-13:16.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-28-16:21.html</id>
    <title>Visible parts of internal states</title>
    <updated>2024-01-28T16:21:00-08:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Visible parts of internal states&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I write a lot about feelings, emotions, etc. I’m well known for it,
and people say they find my writing on it helpful. So, let me tell you
something that I’m genuinely quite concerned about: What if everything
I’m saying is basically fake?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m very good at theorising and coming up with plausible explanations
for things, much better than I am at being reliably correct about them&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Not through any deep personal failings or idiosyncracies
you understand. Being correct is just hard.&lt;/span&gt;, so I’d probably be able to write
all this stuff even if actually it didn’t work at all and I was just
kidding myself about what had happened to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I don’t think this is the case. I’m &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt;
convinced that it’s not 100% the case. I’m… less convinced that it’s 0%
the case. A specific percentage is hard to pin down, but I do know that
I’m missing some important things, and I suspect some of them are in
areas that I’m pretty convinced I understand.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem with &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/describing-imaginary-experiences"&gt;describing
internal experiences&lt;/a&gt; is that there are no external reference points
that you can point to as a shared object. Part of why my &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/labelling-feelings"&gt;explanation
of labelling feelings&lt;/a&gt; focuses so heavily on externally visible
behaviour is that those are the bits that you can see. They constitute a
shared object you can talk about together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is a good partial measure of emotional progress. You
know that someone shouting and shaking their fist at you about how good
they are at anger management, how dare you say they’re not, is probably
fooling themselves.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;They could just be lying, but it’s such a bad lie that
fooling themselves seems more likely.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an extreme example, but I think you see a lot of this in the
self help space. e.g. I’ve seen plenty of people talk about how to
become less neurotic whose behaviour I’ve observed and, well, will not
be taking their advice too seriously.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Is it plausible that this is just because of their high
starting point and the thing they did is a genuine improvement?
Definitely! But it tends to be coupled with a lack of self awareness
about where they’ve ended up that makes me suspicious.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For my part, I think some of my claims to improvement are more
credible than others. I’ve definitely reduced my anxiety levels,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although experiences of attending dance classes have
definitely demonstrated that some claims I’ve made in the past to have
“fixed” my social anxiety are at best suspect. It does feel like a
different sort of thing - I find the experience stressful rather than
anxiety inducing - but I’m not sure the externally visible behaviour is
that different.&lt;/span&gt;, and I think a lot of my
presentation is more confident than it used to be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If, on the other hand, I claimed to have fixed my depression I think
you should look at a lot of my recent writing and put on your best
skeptical face.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’m working on it, OK?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think there’s a sort of general… knowing myself better, and
being better able to act on what I want, that I have improved at but am
still not good at. I can’t articulate this in a way that’s very
convincing though. It’s enough that I think it’s real, but maybe not
enough that you should too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The point is not, however, that you should only believe things are
real if you’ve got really clear visible evidence that they are. A lot of
purely internal things are real. It’s just hard to have full confidence
in them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means it’s &lt;em&gt;really nice&lt;/em&gt; when something nebulous and
internal that you’re trying to improve has some really clear externally
visible correlate. If nothing else, it makes it much easier to improve
the thing because you can just track whether the visible thing
improves.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Though beware &lt;a href="https://philarchive.org/rec/NGUVCH"&gt;value capture&lt;/a&gt;. No visible
improvement at all is suspicious, but once you start getting some
visible improvement more visible improvement will not continue to be
better indefinitely.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, one interesting handle I found on all of this recently is,
oddly, pilates.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried doing pilates and things like it in the past and I was bad
at it. Most of why I’m doing much better this time is not through any
deep personal progress or growth as a human being, I’m just paying a
really good teacher for one on one lessons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there is one specific thing that I’ve noticed that I can do now
that I don’t think I used to be able to do, which is that when I’m told
to do a movement and I can’t do the movement I can &lt;em&gt;figure out how to
do the movement&lt;/em&gt;. Most of the time anyway. There’s a specific sort
of introspection which feels a bit like… mentally rummaging around in
the relevant body part, wiggling it a bit and seeing what happens, until
I figure out how to use the right muscles to do the thing. I’m almost
certain I didn’t use to be able to do this, and now I can, and it feels
very much adjacent to the sort of introspection skills I’ve picked up
when doing Focusing or IFS or the like. This isn’t strong evidence for
any of that being useful of course, but it’s at least an interesting
link.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this observation of visible versions of internal goals
extends a lot into the exercise space more generally, although of course
most forms of exercise are visible to some degree. My overall exercise
goals are very internal in that they’re largely centred on being less in
pain. But subjective comparison of pain over time is hard. Sure I can
tell the difference between being in pain and not being in pain, but can
I tell the difference between being more in pain and less in pain? Not
reliably.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can, on the other hand, tell the difference between being able to
do an asian squat better or worse, or measure how long I can stand on
one leg for, and these are pretty good visible versions of the internal
experience of having better leg strength and mobility, so work well as
things to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-28-16:21.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
