<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-06-11T14:00:31+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-02-08:25.html</id>
    <title>Being friends with your coworkers</title>
    <updated>2020-06-02T15:54:17+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Being friends with your coworkers&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2WYeYew"&gt;Talking About Machines&lt;/a&gt; by Julian Orr, page 35:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;their [team] has developed personal bonds in addition to their professional association, including friendship outside the job. His narration reveals a division among technicians over the propriety of such bonds, and while he clearly values them, he is wary of revealing them to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The question of whether you should be friends with your coworkers is an interesting one.
For me the answer is "Obviously yes, except it's kinda problematic."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At a personal level, being friends with your coworkers is good. You're going to spend a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of your time together, and your life will be improved if you actually like spending time together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At a professional level, being friends with your coworkers is also good: It significantly improves your team productivity. One of the things that is clear from Orr's book is that talking to each other, swapping war stories, sharing technical problems and advice, is almost inseparable from having a friendly conversation with each other. This isn't the equivalent of having a daily standup or a team meeting, it's a conversation, and it's much easier to have conversations with your friends. These conversations are an essential part of learning together and sharing important information.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being friends with your coworkers makes literally everything better, and it is very hard to have a functioning company without a certain amount of bonds of friendship.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also... this is how marginalisation works and reinforces itself, because not everybody can easily be friends with their coworkers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm reminded of &lt;a href="https://www.ft.com/content/da6a33be-bd8f-11e8-8274-55b72926558f"&gt;this piece from the FT&lt;/a&gt; (apologies for the paywall):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an instant, if brutal, reminder of the value of smoking at work. It is one of the cheapest and most effective ways of finding out what is really going on in the office. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am indebted to a reader for my favourite ploy: an office beer fridge. A man from the US who has started and managed several companies wrote to tell me on-site grog had several proven benefits. Everyone got to know each other quickly, he said, “from production worker to the CEO”, and that made a big difference to the way they worked with one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These sorts of nonwork activities that promote socialisation end up being extremely good for establishing lines of information and common knowledge within the company that run orthogonally to formal lines of information.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, both smoking and drinking are hugely exclusionary ways of setting up those lines, right? They're &lt;em&gt;effective&lt;/em&gt;, but they're effective for the people who are willing to participate them. Personally, I don't mind office drinking (but no thanks on the beer), and will find the presence of smokers around the office actively unpleasant, never mind &lt;em&gt;joining&lt;/em&gt; them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Many people have had bad experiences with alcohol, or avoid it for religious reasons, and above and beyond not drinking will not be at all comfortable around people who are drinking. It also tends to exacerbate other ways in which a group is exclusionary - if you're part of an underrepresented minority, people who are on their best behaviour while sober may start to show their true colours while drunk (and even if it turns out that their true colours are actually that they're perfectly nice people and there are zero problems, it's hard to know that in advance and this prevents the event from being relaxing and enjoyable).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of criticism of the tech industry's reliance on alcohol for social bonding on grounds of it being exclusionary, and this criticism is entirely correct.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the criticism tends not to get listened to, for one very simple reason: Drinking as a way of socialising works really well, and without something to replace it, this criticism asks the majority to make a significant personal sacrifice for the minority's comfort. This doesn't tend to go well. Should the majority do it? Well, maybe. But you need to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-19-09:35.html"&gt;work with the audience that you have&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even if you overcome this and find a perfectly innocuous way of doing team socialisation,
you end up with issues of conflicting identity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was at a London &lt;a href="http://www.liberatingstructures.com/"&gt;Liberating Structures&lt;/a&gt; meetup group right before lockdown started, and someone there suggested that on Mondays they tried to get a lot of discussion going between people about what they'd done over their weekend, as a kind of ice breaker / social bonding exercise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I gently suggested to them that this might not work so well because you're trying to force people to disclose things they may not want to disclose. People don't generally want to tell their coworkers that they spent the weekend at a sex party (this is a common problem among my friend group).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn't have to be a sex party either. People are probably equally unwilling to tell their staunchly atheist coworkers that they spent the weekend at a bible study. Telling people that they spent their weekend at a protest risks office politics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More innocuously, you have a divide between parents and non parents. If a parent talks about how they spent their weekend with their kids, the other parents in the room may join in talking about their kids, while the non-parents sit there twiddling their thumbs. Or, equally, if you're the only parent in the room and everyone is talking about the fun things they were up to this weekend and you were mostly doing childcare duties.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think part of the problem here is that we are too used to playing friendship on easy mode and largely lack the skill of having heterogenous friends groups. It's much easier to be friends if you can find strong points of commonality with each other and minimise points of conflict. When your main point of commonality is that you work together, you will often lack that easy mode.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem gets worse when you take into account that some people actually just may not be able to make friends that easily. They may be lacking in social skills, or they may just be kinda traumatised and find it difficult to trust people. Many of these people are lovely, brilliant, people, and even those who aren't probably need to work &lt;em&gt;somewhere&lt;/em&gt; - because, alas, capitalism. How do we make a system that works for them?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, when you try to deliberately help those people integrate, this may seem like an attack on them, because it reads like a social test that they can fail.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these problems are, I think, even worse at a small company. I wrote about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-25-10:40.html"&gt;the problem with not fitting in in small towns&lt;/a&gt; before, and small companies are like that but more so. If you work in an office with a thousand other people there are probably others like you there (whether you can find them is another issue). That doesn't necessarily solve your problem if you're not on their team, but it at least &lt;em&gt;helps&lt;/em&gt;. If you work at a company of five other people, chances are good that you have a number of traits that are unique to you, and some of those may be ones that result in you being excluded.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is at this point that I reveal the easy, brilliant, and obvious solution that will solve all of these problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Err.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe it's not. I was kinda hoping you would do that for me. Because this problem seems like a giant insoluble mess and I barely have any idea where to start - any solution seems far too contextual for me to propose any general principles.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mostly I'd like people to start by acknowledging the problem: Being friends with your coworkers is important and valuable, and currently we only make it accessible to people who get to play friendship on easy mode.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-02-08:25.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-03-09:56.html</id>
    <title>Some Useful Emotion Management Principles</title>
    <updated>2020-06-03T14:52:31+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Some Useful Emotion Management Principles&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was talking about anxiety management a bit on Twitter, and it occurred to me that it would be useful to write down a bunch of general principles that I use for understanding emotions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These principles aren't necessarily &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt;, but I've found them useful. I'd say that they're probably... about 90% true. They're worth using as defaults for understanding things, but they probably have some hidden preconditions and missing features that I have not fully mapped out yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the primary features of emotions is a disposition to act in a particular way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A disposition to act is not an obligation to act.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These dispositions are experienced, at least in large part, through your body, so paying attention to your body helps you understand your emotions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no "bad" emotions, in the sense that there always a situation where the disposition prompted by the emotion would be appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a given context, an emotional reaction may or may not be appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotional reactions are learned pattern matching in response to particular events.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When an emotional reaction is active, you can retrain those patterns into ones that better suit the situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retraining requires you to acknowledge that the emotion might, in principle, be a valid reaction in context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you ignore an emotion, it will tend to increase in intensity to get you to act on it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning to act competently on dispositions can improve emotional experiences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If an emotion is debilitating or otherwise interferes with your life, that's often a sign of some sort of dysregulation in how you are managing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me unpack each of these.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Emotions as dispositions towards action&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A disposition in this context is an inclination towards a certain class of things, an inclination to act in a particular way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you are angry, it is because you are being prompted to act angrily. You are getting ready to have a fight, and you are orienting yourself towards actions that are useful for that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some people (e.g. Antonio Damasio I think) argue that emotions &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; these dispositions. I'm somewhat agnostic on this question, in that I think our use of the word "emotion" is variable enough that it's not clear to me that "What are emotions?" is a well-defined question, and any attempt to promote it as a definition is probably a lost cause.
However, regardless of what theory of emotion we end up with, understanding the dispositions associated with an emotion is key to understanding that emotion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some other examples of disposition:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anxiety might dispose you to reducing the uncertainty in a situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fear might dispose you to getting out of a situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guilt might dispose you towards repairing some damage you've done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curiousity might dispose you to learning more about something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contentment might dispose you towards luxuriating in something you're enjoying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delight might dispose you towards immersing yourself in a particular activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Side note: I realised while writing this that it was much easier for me to figure out what the dispositions associated with negative emotions are. Given that part of my goals right now are to improve my experience of positive emotions, I find that very interesting)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Dispositions are not obligations&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you get angry, you are not being &lt;em&gt;forced&lt;/em&gt; to act angrily. You can feel angry without acting angry (although people will probably be able to tell that you are angry. This is not necessarily bad). But the emotion of anger includes, as a key feature, a dsposition towards angry action - you are inclined to shout at someone, to attack them, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An important skill in emotion management is to acquire a bit of a separation between disposition and action. To pause and say "Actually, I know that emotionally this is the way I am disposed to act, but &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; I do that?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly, this is not &lt;em&gt;suppressing&lt;/em&gt; the emotion. That has to be an honest question, to which it is possible that the answer is allowed to be yes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Dispositions are experienced bodily&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We act in the world through our body, so experiencing a disposition is, in large part, experiencing an arrangement of our body (including our senses) to act. If we are disposed to fight, we will feel our body tensing to fight. If we are curious about something, we might feel our attention physically drawn to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Learning this is basically what &lt;a href="https://focusing.org/"&gt;Focusing&lt;/a&gt; is - learning to pay attention to your bodily dispositions towards particular actions, as a preliminary step towards understanding the emotional reactions that underly them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;There are no bad emotions&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We have these dispositions because &lt;em&gt;they are useful&lt;/em&gt;. If you are experiencing a disposition, there are circumstances under which that disposition is the right one. If you feel afraid, that is not bad in and of itself, because there are circumstances under which a disposition to get out of the situation is a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We (for some suitably culture specific value of we) tend to think of negative emotions as being bad for a couple of reasons:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They might frequently be inappropriately deployed (anger).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They might be overused, or misused, against us (guilt, shame)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We might have unhelpful habits built up around them (anxiety)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These all give us a bad relationship with a particular emotion, but they primarily result in a conflation between the disposition, the situation prompting it, and the actions it prompts. The disposition &lt;em&gt;in and of itself&lt;/em&gt; is neither bad nor good, and sometimes it will be exactly the right thing to have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Emotions may promote inappropriate action&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you say something, and I mishear you and think you have insulted at me, and I respond in kind, and a fight results. That is an example of an inappropriate reaction - I have misunderstood the situation, I have acted in a way that is (arguably) appropriate &lt;em&gt;if the situation were as I understood it&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is what an inappropriate emotional reaction is like: You have responded with a disposition because the situation makes you think it is the appropriate one, but you are in some way mistaken about the situation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Emotional reactions are learned pattern-matching&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Generally your emotional reactions are based on very simplified models of the world.
For example, social anxiety might be a learned reaction that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; social situations are unsafe and you have to be on high alert and monitor for threats. A bad experience with men might cause a disposition to be on your guard around &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; men.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You don't necessarily have access to these simplified models. There's not necessarily a conscious part of your brain that goes "This is a party. Parties are THE WORST. Therefore I now decide to be anxious." - the anxiety generally starts preverbally, and the thoughts come after (although the thoughts can in turn promote action).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It can be useful to think of your mind having a subsystem that is "the bit that decides to be anxious" (or angry, or delighted, or...) which is monitoring the world for certain features and putting you into the particular disposition when its conditions are met. The subsystem is not necessarily particularly intelligent, and you have a lot of these subsystems going on so they don't necessarily have a lot of resources available to them, so they're trying to do the best they can on a limited budget, and they sometimes get it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Active emotional reactions can be relearned&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because emotions are learned pattern matching, changing your emotional reactions is a matter of relearning that pattern matching. You want to take the subsystem and get it to respond better in some circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems to be &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; easier when the emotional subsystem is activated. I don't want to say you &lt;em&gt;can't&lt;/em&gt; do it when it's not activated (and certainly you can lay useful groundwork for this process), but it's not something I've been able to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Activated" doesn't necessarily mean when you're in the situation in question (although I do often use it there) - it can through a process of imagination, talking it out, thinking about the prompting situation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once you're in this state, you can gently start to question the premises of the emotional reaction. Draw your attention to certain aspects of the situation, explore whether this is the right disposition for you to take in this context.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, social anxiety can be relearned around people you have much stronger evidence are safe. The level of anxiety you experience when talking to a close friend should be lower than the level of anxiety you have talking to someone at a party, and drawing your attention to the things that make it so can help relearn the emotional reaction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Ignoring an emotion intensifies it&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that &lt;em&gt;doesn't&lt;/em&gt; seem to work is to try to suppress and ignore the emotion.
Emotions are there to dispose you to act, so will often rise to the level of intensity required to get you to act.
If you repeatedly suppress an emotion and pretend it's not there,
it will tend to get worse over time rather than better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Relearning starts with accepting the emotion in principle&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because ignoring the emotion doesn't work, and because emotions are dispositions to act,
you need to acknowledge it as potentially valid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What this means is that you need to start from the premise that if this is the correct disposition to have in this scenario, you would act on it. If you're actually being attacked, it's OK to be angry and act angrily. If there's genuine risk in the situation, it's OK to be anxious and act to reduce that risk.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Starting from the premise that the emotion &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be valid, and exploring the question of whether it is, allows you to work with yourself rather than creating internal conflict, and maximises your chance of successfully retraining the emotion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Learning to act competently on dispositions&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the big problems we often end up with emotions is that we're not very good at acting on them not in the sense that we ignore them, but we act on them in ways that don't actually improve the situation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anxiety and guilt are two big examples of this. If anxiety causes us to panic and make the situation worse, we have &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; reduced the risk in the situation, so our level of anxiety goes up rather down. If we feel guilty and avoid the whole situation to avoid feeling that guilt, we end up feeling more guilty rather than less.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Learning skills in a safe environment (when the emotion is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; active) that we can apply in these cases helps us fix this: If cleaning makes us anxious, creating a safe environment in which to learn a bit of cleaning skills will help the next time we have cleaning anxiety. If we feel guilt about a particular situation, talking through the situation and deciding on some practical steps you can take to improve it (or indeed deciding that you don't need to feel guilty about it at all).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The ideal situation is that we have the emotional responses that dispose us to act in the right way in the right context, and learning to act in the right way is a key part of that that we can manage separately from the emotional responses themselves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Debilitating emotions are probably dysregulation&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If your emotional reactions are so strong that they prevent you from acting, something has gone wrong (except in the rare specific cases where preventing you from acting is what they're &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to do, as in the freeze trauma response). Emotions are dispositions towards actions, but if those dispositions get too overwhelmingly intense they may stop you from acting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't have too much experience with this side of things (my problems are, if anything, at the opposite end of the spectrum - I don't tend to have intense enough emotional reactions), so I'm wary of offering too much advice in this space. I think all of the above principles are still likely to be useful to you, but I'd recommend also looking into &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dialectical_behavior_therapy"&gt;Dialectical Behavioural Therapy&lt;/a&gt; and possibly the literature on cPTSD. &lt;a href="https://www.rewriting-the-rules.com/self/trauma-and-cptsd-101/"&gt;Meg-John Barker's piece on the subject&lt;/a&gt; is good, and provides pointers to further literatures.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(The literature on cPTSD may also be useful even if you &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; experience overwhelming emotions. Certainly I've found it so.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are the principles underlying most of my emotion work right now. You can read some more of my thoughts on the subject in:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;Emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html"&gt;Your emotions are valid but probably wrong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-17:58.html"&gt;How I fix anxiety triggers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you'd like to read more qualified people's thoughts on the subject the books I've read that are most directly relevant to this are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2AUQ2vW"&gt;Descartes' Error&lt;/a&gt; by Antonio Damasio is largely theoretical but is good for understanding the mind/body link.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Mnm1Hx"&gt;Focusing&lt;/a&gt; by Eugene Gendlin helps understand how to use a sense of your own body to understand your emotions. People recommend &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3gMG3cB"&gt;The Power of Focusing&lt;/a&gt; as a better introduction but I haven't got around to reading it yet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3gQUdcT"&gt;Unlocking the emotional brain&lt;/a&gt; is in theory the source of a lot of my work on retraining emotions, but I must admit I never get around to reading it. I just read &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/i9xyZBS3qzA8nFXNQ/book-summary-unlocking-the-emotional-brain"&gt;Kaj Sotala's review of it&lt;/a&gt;, went "Oh right", and immediately incorporated it into my own practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Axf1W0"&gt;The Emotion Machine&lt;/a&gt; by Marvin Minsky was useful for thinking about how the mind organises itself around resources which create dispositions to action. I'm suspicious of whether the book is actually &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;, but it's proven a useful source of metaphors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't necessarily promise you'll get the same things out of these resources that I did - there's a lot of surrounding additional reading, discussion, and experimentation, but they're all good books that I've found quite helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-03-09:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-04-08:42.html</id>
    <title>Popular Culture Reference, David</title>
    <updated>2020-06-04T09:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Popular Culture Reference, David&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(A quick post today, due to needing to get on with other things very shortly)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2yzEkGq"&gt;How to talk about books you haven't read&lt;/a&gt; by Pierre Bayard, page 61:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common literary confrontations are those that occur in our social lives, and of these the most vexing are those in which we are expected to express ourselves in front of a group. On such occasions, the conversation may turn to a book we have not read. If the book in question is assumed to be known by all cultivated individuals [...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing that struck me about this is how much it doesn't happen to me. I don't think I have ever had a conversation in which someone is surprised that I haven't read a particular book, except very occasionally as a joke because they assume I've read everything. I can't think of any examples of books that have that level of cultural penetration among people I know.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most of this is probably a difference between me and Pierre Bayard - he's coming from a French literary scene. His friends' notion of "all cultivated individuals" probably doesn't include me or my friends.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He's also quite a lot older than me, and my suspicion is that he's describing an event that is genuinely less common these days, because instead our shared cultural objects seem mostly to be TV shows and movies.
And there I get that a lot. It's a running joke: "Popular culture reference, David, you wouldn't understand."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not, I hasten to add, because I'm too classy for TV and movies. Movies don't really work well for me as a format, but I do watch a lot of TV, most of it not very good. I just skip out on a lot of mainstream stuff because it doesn't work well for me (for example I cannot stand embarassment based humour and have no interest in watching things that make me whole body cringe).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm generally OK just saying that I haven't watched it. This does, often, result in a bunch of pressure to watch things. "You absolutely must watch it! It's amazing!" is somehow perfectly socially acceptable, despite a single season of a TV show probably being at least twelve hours of watching, but people get edgy and defensive when I recommend books to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I understand why this is. It's easy to find twelve hours to watch TV, it's hard to find five hours to read a book, because the latter requires focus and causes people to confront all sorts of unpleasant emotions about their relationship with reading, while the former allows them to palliate by fast-forwarding their brain through those twelve hours.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(There's nothing wrong with doing that if that's what you want to do, but I think people are kidding themselves about this)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think in some ways TV shows also just work better as a shared cultural object than books, because there are so many fewer of them. It's very expensive to produce a TV show. It's not cheap to produce a book, but it's cheap enough that there are several orders of magnitude more books than TV shows. Even best sellers rarely have the penetration of a moderately popular TV show (with a few outliers like Harry Potter).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately creating sharedness of our cultural objects by making them expensive to produce isn't so great. It creates a very high barrier to entry on whose voices become part of our shared culture, and it creates an incentive to make it accessible to as broad an audience as possible. It prioritises relatable over insightful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That's not to say that TV shows are necessarily &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; shared cultural objects. There are some very good ones. I'm genuinely very grateful to The Good Place for existing. Trigonometry (which I still need to finish watching) is some great representation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not going to say Stargate is a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; shared cultural object (or, frankly, a particularly shared one - it's not unpopular by any means given how long it ran for, but it's not something I can reasonably &lt;em&gt;expect&lt;/em&gt; people to have watched), but I still like it and will enjoy talking Stargate with people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it does leave a popular culture that is strangely anemic. Fandom fills in the gaps, fleshing out the world of shared culture with the voices it lacks. Fandom is its own popular culture, building a richer world on top of the shared cultural objects provided to us. It is, however, a relatively niche thing that most people don't seem aware of or participate in - I'm only on the outskirts of it myself, and I don't really know how I would go about participating more deeply (or whether I want to).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't really have any closing thoughts, except that it'd actually be quite nice to have a group where there was a shared canon of books that actually I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; assume everyone in that group had read.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-04-08:42.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-05-09:08.html</id>
    <title>The Virtue Ethics of Potato Growing</title>
    <updated>2020-06-05T11:34:20+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The Virtue Ethics of Potato Growing&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2ZB2wmE"&gt;Seeing Like a State&lt;/a&gt; by James C. Scott, page 303:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An explicit set of rules will take you further when the situation is cut-and-dried. The more static and one-dimensional the stereotype, the less the need for creative interpretation and adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the environment can be simplified down to the point where the rules do explain a great deal, those who formulate the rules and techniques have also greatly expanded their power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is all part of a rather interesting discussion of potato growing in the Andes, and about how the local growers are engaged in an extensive process of adapting cultivars to the particular soil and growing conditions of their farm ("landraces" - breeds that are highly adapted to a local environment). Rather than having a small number of legible potato breeds, they have hyperlocal varieties which are only found mostly on the farm they're grown on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a great deal of swapping of these varieties and trying them out in different locations, so the line of any given type of potato is not restricted to the farm, but each farm will the interate on the potatoes it receives, crossing them, selecting them for new conditions, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is contrasted with the "scientific" mode of potato production, where a cultivar is selected for particular properties in ideal conditions, and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; you find out where it grows well, and to some large degree try to make it so that the land matches the conditions (e.g. through irrigation, fertiliser) rather than trying to match the potato to the land.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Brief aside: I'd like to use this to point out a way that I, and others, have I think done James C. Scott in general and "Seeing Like a State" in particular a bit of a disservice. I've been on record in the past as saying that Seeing Like a State is much longer than it needs to be and that you can get most of the important information out of one of the relevant blog posts. &lt;a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2010/07/26/a-big-little-idea-called-legibility/"&gt;Venkatesh Rao&lt;/a&gt;'s, &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2017/11/shaping-the-world/"&gt;mine&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/03/16/book-review-seeing-like-a-state/"&gt;Scott Alexander&lt;/a&gt;'s for example. This is in some sense true, but it's also in some sense false.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Seeing Like a State is not so much "too long" as "detail rich". If you're just interested in having the idea of legibility in your conceptual toolkit, it's too long and you should just read one of the blog posts. If you're interested in learning a lot of details about how the world works, both historically and geographically, it's about the right length, because it's packed with lots of these details, using legibility as a unifying theme and lens to look at them through.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do you need to know about potato farming in the Andes to understand legibility? No, of course not. But potato farming in the Andes is, it turns out, &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In an act of mild irony, casting "Seeing Like a State" as "the legibility book" is an attempt to make it more legible than the detail rich view on the ground would show it as.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, that being said, I'm going to return to the high level conceptual toolkit now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been reading Rosalind Hursthouse's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3dyWLu8"&gt;On Virtue Ethics&lt;/a&gt;. It's excellent and I highly recommend it. I'm currently doing a &lt;a href="https://jmestn.com/15485/naval-doesn-t-take-notes"&gt;high level first pass read&lt;/a&gt; so I can't necessarily fairly summarise it, but one of the things I like about Virtue Ethics in general is its emphasis on becoming the sort of person who takes good actions over and above teasing out the right thing to do in any individual action, trying to come up with some sort of schema or set of rules.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular, it feels like a lot of attempts to understand ethical reasoning try to pin down things into exactly these cut and dried scenarios so that you can say "Look, here's a rule that works!".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Teasing out these scenarios itself isn't necessarily bad in that it can be useful for understanding what traits lead to good decisions, and what those good decisions look like, but they inevitably come with some fairly massive simplifying assumptions. For example, trolley problems work precisely by narrowing the field down until you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to pick one of two unpalatable options.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That being said, even these situations fail to make the world as simple as they'd like. I've previously proposed that the solution to trolley problems is relatively easy if you allow the possibility of incurring guilt for doing the "right" thing. If you kill the individual to save the many, you still have to deal with (at least some of) the consequences of killing the individual.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, I think, one of the high points of virtue ethics is that it is good at acknowledging that although you can reason about ethics, a lot of actual ethical behaviour has to come down to the person dealing with the messy situation on the ground, and that this problem is contiguous with practical reasoning (virtue ethicists use the word "Phronesis", meaning a sort of practical wisdom oriented around getting morally good result). Virtue ethical reasoning very much resembles the sort of messy practical reasoning that people engage in in practice with problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting things in the section about potatoes is how even the idealised scientific tools get folded in to the messy practical realities of making the world work for the farmer:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] the vast majority of Andean cultivators are neither purely traditional cultivators nor mindless followers of the scientific specialists. They are, instead, crafting unique alamagams of strategies that reflect their ams, their resources, and their local conditions. Where the new potatoes seem to fit their purposes, they may plant some, but they may interplant them with other cultivars and may substitute dung, or plow in green manure (alfalfa, clover) rather than apply the standard fertilizer package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The practice of scientific development of potatoes is very good for optimising for things that you would not necessarily find in the wild. Essentially it's the output of a bunch of potato &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html"&gt;nerds&lt;/a&gt; and we can always learn interesting things from nerds we wouldn't otherwise have encountered. But when we take the nice, idealised, potato and bring it into the real world, we find out all sorts of ways it doesn't fit, or where it's a bit precious, and we learn to adapt it as such.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wrote before in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-10-08:54.html"&gt;How to be a better person&lt;/a&gt; that we need a practice of ethics more than a theory of ethics, but the theory of ethics stuff is good too, we just may need to heavily adapt it as we bring it into the real world of practical decision making. Possibly by substituting dung instead of its standard fertilizer package.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-05-09:08.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-06-10:11.html</id>
    <title>Testing Positive For vs Having</title>
    <updated>2020-06-06T11:36:21+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Testing Positive For vs Having&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2A9stPS"&gt;Sorting Things Out: Classification and its Consequences&lt;/a&gt; by Bowker and Star, page 176:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...it was decided that those who tested positive did not &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; [tuberculosis], they were "considered to have tuberculous infection but not the disease" (&lt;em&gt;Diagnosis&lt;/em&gt; 1955, 15). Only those who could bring other evidence of disease to the table would be considered worthy of the classification of pulmonary or nonpulmonary tuberculosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting distinction. It reminds me of the distinction between HIV (the virus) and AIDS (the condition caused by the virus).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More generally, and tangentially, though I think we are seeing people becoming increasingly aware of the distinction between testing positive and having a disease in another way: You might test positive and just not have the disease. Equally, you might test negative and still have the disease.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've written before in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/02/theres-no-single-error-rate/"&gt;There's no single error rate&lt;/a&gt; about how you need to think about error quite carefully, and that for any classification scheme there is an error rate per possible answer. In this case you can incorrectly say that someone does not have the disease, and you can incorrectly say that they do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMp2015897"&gt;This is a good article about the error rates in testing and what they mean&lt;/a&gt; for diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I know at least two people who have tested negative for COVID-19 but still seem pretty likely to have had it, due to symptoms and circumstances. That's not to say that you should &lt;em&gt;ignore&lt;/em&gt; the fact that there's a negative result - it should certainly make you seem less likely to have it - but it's far from indisputable proof.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I'm pretty likely to have had it. I'm currently saying 90% likely (this is a made up number, but I'm pretty good - albeit far from perfect - at making up numbers to gauge my level of confidence).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So what would it mean if I got tested with an antibody test for whether I've had it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although I'm generally quite thumbs down on Bayesianism, this is an example where Bayes rule (well, conditional probability anyway) is obviously the correct thing to do as a way to reason about testing. If we make up more numbers and assume that the probability of a negative result given that I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; infected is 10%, and the probability of a negative result given that I'm &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; infected is 95% (i.e. 5% of noninfected people will falsely get a positive result), then I assign 9% confidence to being infected and getting a negative result (90% chance I'm infected multiplied by 10% chance that if I'm infected I get a negative result) and a 9.5% chance that I'm not infected and get a negative result (90% chance of not infected, 95% chance that if I'm not infected I'll get a negative result), so for a total of 18.5% chance of a negative result.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note that, because of my high prior confidence that I've been infected, it's almost as likely that I get a negative result but still have it as that I get a negative result and don't have it. Specifically, if I get a negative result the chances of my having it are \(100 \times \frac{9}{9 + 9.5} \approx 48.6\%\). i.e. despite the negative result I'm only barely more likely to not have it than I am to have it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does this mean that the tests are useless?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, maybe. Certainly a negative test result doesn't tell me much, but there's also not much I'd do with a negative test result anyway: A negative test result just means that I have to keep doing what I'm already doing, which is maintaining a sensible level of caution about catching the virus. Whether that's because I actually haven't had the virus, or whether it's because I've had the virus and the test wrongly reports that I have not, it doesn't really matter for my decision making - I've got no new information that would allow me to change behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A positive test result is potentially more useful. Suppose similar numbers: 90% of people with the virus test positive, and 5% of people without the virus test positive. After a positive result I'd be about 99% certain I'd had it, and thus that I was pretty likely immune.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I still wouldn't be &lt;em&gt;certain&lt;/em&gt; that I had had the virus, or even that if I'd had the virus I would be immune, but behaviours that were previously unacceptable risks would now become acceptable risks.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This wouldn't change my behaviour much in that I'd just go out and start licking people, but it would change some of my risk profiles (I'm currently being significantly more careful than the government guidelines suggest, with one or two exceptions) and so I can use that to adjust my decisions.
I'd probably still keep away from supermarkets, but I'd probably be a lot more willing to hang out with friends outside.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another use case is that even if tests are quite inaccurate at an individual level, they might be useful at a population level: If you know the false positive and false negative rates pretty well, and you implement mass testing, you can be pretty confident of the percentage of the population who have had the virus, and plan accordingly, even if you've got significant question marks about any individual person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the other direction, the government was criticised (somewhat correctly) early on for the lack of widespread testing, and widespread testing is good and important, but there was at least some reasonable logic behind not testing everyone with symptoms: If you have acute symptoms, you need to go to the hospital regardless of whether you have it, and if you don't have acute symptoms, you need to stay home regardless of whether you have it, so the test did not (at that point) add that much useful information. It is, at best, lightly informative of treatment and of the decision of whether you should be admitted to hospital. Often effective action requires triaging what information is worth acquiring.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is not to say that I think that the UK government response to COVID-19 has been anything less than shambolic, but some individual actions are not as obviously unreasonable as they seem, especially given other constraints caused by the rest of the response)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ultimately I think this highlights two important things about knowledge:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is absolutely no certainty, only degrees of confidence (some of which may be so high that they might as well be certainty, but often you cannot wait until you are that certain).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The acceptable margins of uncertainty significantly depend on what you're going to do with the knowledge, and you'll often have to just be comfortable with the fact that you might be acting on wrong information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-06-10:11.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-07-09:33.html</id>
    <title>A Meta For Computers</title>
    <updated>2020-06-07T10:55:32+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;A Meta For Computers&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I use metaphors of legacy code and refactoring a lot, and this works very well but is comprehensible more or less in direct proportion to how well you understand software development.
It turns out that a lot of people I know understand software development well enough to benefit from this, but by no means all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was trying to think about how to explain this to other people, and I ended up with what I think is a reasonably pleasing way to explain how computers and software work in general.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, here's the metaphor I want to use: Think of a computer as a kind of archive, but you're not allowed in to the archive, you can only access it through someone at the front desk. We'll call him Steve.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Behind the scenes the archive has a bunch of people working in it. When you ask Steve to do something, he doesn't do it himself, he just passes on appropriate orders to the people working there, they carry out the orders, bring something back to him, and he hands it over to you. Steve is not the one who is fulfilling your commands, he's just the interface to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now due to regulations, the archive runs on &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; strict rules. There's a rule for everything, a protocol to every request. Steve and the workers in it &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; not violate the rules, no matter how much you plead. It's more than their job's worth, don't you know?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As long as you stick within the scenarios the rules are designed for this is mostly pretty well.
You bring Steve a document and ask him to file it. He says "Certainly, I'll file this as document XYZ-1234" or some other ID, hands it to the a clerk, who files it appropriately.
When you want it back you say "Steve, can I have document XYZ-1234?" and he passes on the request to a relevant clerk, they fetch the document and hand it back to you. The system is working as intended.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose one day you come in and you've forgotten the ID of the document you want. "Steve, can I have the document I gave you on Wednesday?".
Steve can't do that. "The document I gave you on Wednesday" is not a request that the system has rules for, so he's not allowed to fulfill it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually, after consulting the rule book as to what sort of queries you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; allowed to make, you ask Steve to give you all documents filed by you on 2020-06-03. You filed only one document on that date (the Wednesday in question), so Steve hands you the document on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is what interacting with a computer is like: The computer is a system of rules that is there to do things you find useful, but everything you want to do with it has to be thought of and accounted for in advance.
Sometimes the rules are so complicated as to &lt;em&gt;seem&lt;/em&gt; more sophisticated than that, but they're not they're just a really complicated rule system. Sometimes the rules contain rules for changing the rules (this is what programming is), but you're still constrained to follow the rules.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The fact that they're rules doesn't mean they're perfectly predictable of course. You can have rules for things like "Give me a random file" which involves a clerk drawing a card, rolling dice, etc. You can also have rules like "Send two clerks to do A and B and give me whichever result comes back" and the result will depend on which workers implement the task, whether they're having good days, etc. The rules can, in general, &lt;em&gt;underdetermine&lt;/em&gt; the result, but they do specify how the result must be obtained.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What does a crash look like?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One day you go to Steve and you say "Steve, can you attach this note to document QP-567?". As per usual, Steve sends a Clerk off to get the document. As he goes through the procedure to attach the note to it for you, he pauses, a horrified look crosses his face, and he breaks down crying, without attaching the note.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You ask him what's wrong, but he can't tell you: There's no rule for that. Also, Steve now won't answer any of your other questions, because the rules don't allow him to proceed until he's completed your request.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually, frustrated, you go to Kim, the administrator, who is in charge of managing the rules of the archive and ask them to look into it. After a while of investigating (they have a bunch of special privileges that allow them to ask Steve WTF is going on) they tell you that the problem is that the document you've asked for doesn't have an associated date or author, and that as part of their procedures Steve has to record those as part of the log of your request when handing you a document. The document you attempted to attach a note to came from before they were recording that information on entry, and the recording rules came in after recording that information was mandatory, so don't account for this possibility.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Kim updates the rules and tells you they've fixed the problem. You ask Steve to attach the note to QP-567 again. He informs you that you don't have permission to do that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are less than impressed by this response and ask Kim what's up with it. They inform you that this seemed like the logical fix: If attaching a note a document requires this information, you must not be allowed to attach notes to documents that lack it. You patiently explain that this is all very well but you need to attach the note to the document from and don't actually care about their recording requirements.
Why is that rule even there?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Kim consults Janet, the interface to their archive where they record information about the changes in the rules of the archive you want to manage, and after a number of queries comes to the following conclusion: The recording requirement doesn't seem to have been introduced for any particularly good reason, but all sorts of &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; rules and procedures depend on it now, so it's really hard to change.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After a bit of back and forth and arguing about how important it is for you to be able to actually add notes to documents in the archive anyway, you hit on a solution: When attaching a note to such a document, Steve will record it as having been authored by "Unknown" at the date of the creation of the archive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can now attach the note to the document.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What does legacy code look like?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One day you request a document and you get the wrong one back.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You go to Kim and ask what's up with that. "Jesus, I have no idea, document retrieval is &lt;em&gt;complicated&lt;/em&gt;."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You express a certain amount of surprise about this. From your perspective you just give Steve the ID and he comes back to you with a document. What could be simpler?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So Kim sits you down and explains to you the realities of archiving.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First you have to understand, an archive is not some abstract place. These documents you're handing to Steve? They have to &lt;em&gt;go&lt;/em&gt; somewhere. There are all these big rooms where the documents have to literally, physically, go. Although those rooms are big, there are a lot of documents, so sometimes rooms fill up and you have to build other rooms.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, when you look up a document, first someone has to look up in an index somewhere to find out what room to look in for it. This was reasonable simple up until a couple of years ago when the size of the index got too large for the room they were storing it in, so now the index is split across multiple rooms. So first they have a procedure to figure out which index to look at.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is all made more complicated by the fact that the ID system has changed multiple times over the lifetime of the archive, so depending on which room it's in and what ID system was in use when the item was entered into the archive you need different ways of looking it up (some rooms the documents are stored ordered by author, some by title, some by publication year, and this affects how you find a document there and is taken into account in the ID).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to illustrate their point, Kim shows you the rules for looking up a document. They span three books. They are not small books.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually after making yourself enough of a nuisance, Kim acknowledges that yes of the dozen things they had to do today obviously your document is the most important thing they could be working on,
and so they go to Steve and ask him to walk them through how exactly the document was retrieved.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually, after much deliberation, they determine that the problem is that it was looked up using the wrong ID system.
You see, the way they determine which ID system to use is based on the date the document was entered into the archive. If there is no entry date, they try all of the different ways in which it could have been entered (there are three from before the system started requiring recording the entry date) and if there is more than one document they ask the person requesting the document to resolve the ambiguity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But the last time someone atached a note to this document, Steve noticed it didn't have an entry date, so as per the new rules implemented in response to your complaint before, set its entry date to the beginning of the archive. So now there is no ambiguity in what ID system it is using, but unfortunately it's a much more recent document than that, so it's unambiguously using the wrong one.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-07-09:33.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-08-10:11.html</id>
    <title>A Guide to Starting a Daily Writing Practice</title>
    <updated>2020-06-08T20:46:36+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;A Guide to Starting a Daily Writing Practice&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Apparently I'm now &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1265999121057546242"&gt;that guy who gets people to start daily writing practices&lt;/a&gt;, so here's a daily writing about daily writing practices.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The short version&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The daily writing practice I'd advocate for is to write at least one sentence, as close to every day as you can manage, in a location that gives you the opportunity to easily write something closer to a short essay should you choose to do so. Ideally this would be in public, under a pseudonym if you prefer, but if you can't bring yourself to do that it's also find to write &lt;em&gt;as if&lt;/em&gt; it were intended for other people to read but to do it somewhere in private.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post will be some guidance on how to make this work for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What is the purpose of the practice?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the practice is to write every day and enjoy doing so. That's it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are some &lt;em&gt;additional benefits&lt;/em&gt; of the practice, but the practice is in and of itself supposed to be an enjoyable thing which puts something out into the world that would otherwise not be there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additional benefits include:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will improve your writing skills, and your communication skills in general, by giving you a place to practice writing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will help resolve writing anxiety. You are probably much better at writing than you think you are, but writing feels hard not because writing &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; hard but because you have a lot of associated anxiety with it (school does that to you). By getting to regularly experience writing as relatively easy, you'll start to drain some of that anxiety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will likely find you have a lot of thoughts that were not getting expressed, and a daily writing practice gives you somewhere to express them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daily writing is a good place to think. It doesn't &lt;em&gt;force&lt;/em&gt; you to think deeply, but it gives you a place where you can develop your skills for deep thought should you choose to do so. You will almost certainly become a better thinker through a daily writing practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By writing daily you'll start to notice themes across your writing, and you can begin to draw them out, connecting up your knowledge and thouhts better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you share it, people will find your writing useful. They probably won't find &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; your writing useful - the point of a daily practice is that you get to write stuff that's not very good, and that's fine - but I'm sorry to inform you that if you write every day over a sustained period of time (months, certainly, but probably even within your first week) you're doomed to write something that people actually like.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is good for them, obviously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's also good for you. People will say nice things about you. You will like that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It may also spark interesting conversations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Success criteria&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Success is writing one sentence, almost every day, and feeling neutral to positive about having done so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most days you will probably find yourself writing more than one sentence. If you only ever write one sentence you should probably try to write more some days, but I find writing more tends to come naturally for people and writing only a sentence every day is probably a sign that you're not enjoying the practice rather than a problem in and of itself,
so I wouldn't worry about length too much.
Success on any given day is just the one sentence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn't even have to be a good sentence.
Success in your daily writing practice does not require any quality. If you're putting it in public somewhere you can explicitly signal that it is &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; - a lot of us are using blogs like this one labelled "notebook" to indicate that the writing is just some thoughts that we're writing down. You can write high quality stuff if you want to from time to time, but it's not required for success.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You probably won't write literally every day. Missing a day is fine. If you're missing a lot of days (more than about one a week on any sort of recurring basis, say) then something is up and you should figure out what that is and what to do about it. Don't beat yourself up about it - it means something about the practice isn't working for you, and you should treat figuring that out as a practical problem to solve. Chances are you're setting too high a bar for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You shouldn't hate your practice. If you hate your practice, you're probably either setting your standards too high, or you're uncovering some uncomfortable feelings around writing that it might be worth examining (may I recommend &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-03-09:56.html"&gt;some useful emotion management principles&lt;/a&gt;?).
If it's the latter, remind yourself that this practice is successful if and only if you hit this incredibly low bar, and that it's a good practice to do, and that you can set aside your normal standards for writing while doing it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Failure criteria&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to be very clear on this: It is OK to try a writing practice and give it up. Beginning a daily writing practice does not oblige you to continue a daily writing practice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My recommendation would be that if after a month you have not been able to make it work for you in the sense above - i.e. writing almost every day and enjoying it - then you should quit. Additionally, throughout that month you should be actively looking at any problems you run into and trying to solve them. If you get properly stuck feel free to ask me for advice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The month is just an arbitrary deadline. If prior to that point you decide that the writing practice is making you miserable, and you cannot figure out how to solve that, quit earlier obviously. I'd recommend perseverance if it's at worstnot quite working for you, but I'd also recommend trying to figure out why it's not working for you and seeing if you can fix that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Prompts&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the most important things to maintaining a daily writing practice is that there should never be any uncertainty if you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do the writing today, and the key to that is to have a good set of prompts for writing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My favourite prompt is to find some interesting passage of writing, copy it out, and add commentary. The commentary can be any sort of thought prompted by it, or if you're stuck for what to say you can just explain what the passage is about, provide context, etc. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This passage can come from anywhere - something you've read recently, a tweet you've seen, a conversation you've had, but my personal favourite procedure is to use random pages from books. This goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick a book, ideally one that you've read. I prefer using physical books for this, but it's doable with ebooks. I randomize the book selection but it might be helpful to set aside a favourite novel for this as the default if you don't have anything you want to use on a given day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick a random page within that book, either by flicking through it or using a random number generator such as &lt;a href="https://www.random.org/"&gt;random.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find an interesting passage on that page and use that (possibly continuing on to the next page, or scanning back to the previous one for the start of a passage). If nothing catches your eye, pick another page. If still nothing catches your eye, pick another book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I find this is a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; reliable prompt for being able to write something even when I'm not feeling it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another prompt that I've been enjoying reading but haven't tried myself is that Lisa has been doing &lt;a href="https://notebook.lisamcnulty.co.uk/series/drabble/"&gt;drabbles&lt;/a&gt; - picking a topic in philosophy (you can pick your own area, Lisa is a philosopher) and writing 100 word explanations of that topic.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another useful thing is to keep a file of things that you could write about at some point and if you're stuck on any given day, scroll through that file and see if any of them catch your eye. I've not been using this much recently since I started using the book prompt as my default, but it's been very helpful in the past and if the book idea doesn't work for you then try this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;How long should it take&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You should tailor your writing to how long you have. If you don't have long, the prompts are important.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For me I rarely spend less than 15 minutes on it, and even more rarely spend more than an hour on it (this post is unusually long to write because I'm trying to explain something specific rather than just rambling on a prompt, so it might take almost an hour to write).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Key to this is the low quality aspect. Daily writing involves almost minimal editing. If you want an editing practice, that's separate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Things to watch out for&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The notebook blog is supposed to be an enjoyable thing that you can keep up indefinitely. It can stop being this long before it "fails" and in order to avoid it,
it's worth watching out for some things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;taking too long over posts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;starting to put off writing posts, or not wanting to write them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doing a lot of editing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to have this is by writing too many good posts! It's very easy to let your standards creep too high, and you won't be able to sustain that indefinitely. It's good to write good posts from time to time, but you're not going to be able to do it every day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My recommendation is that to counteract this you should deliberately half-arse your posts at least a couple days per week. Pick a prompt and do the bare minimum amount of work needed to fulfill it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You should avoid any nontrivial activation energy for getting started and just start. Pick wherever to write is the lowest effort for you to do so, don't try to do anything complicated to get set up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Social media is not generally a good choice for this. Twitter, or Facebook, are not very good for the essay format, and I do think it is important to write somewhere where you could write longer posts if you wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My ideal recommendation is to start a blog or a newsletter somewhere. I've been enjoying Substack for &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/"&gt;my newsletter&lt;/a&gt;. If you're at all programmery doing a static site on GitHub pages is also a good way to go, otherwise &lt;a href="https://wordpress.com/"&gt;wordpress.com&lt;/a&gt; is a good option. &lt;a href="https://reading.supply/"&gt;reading.supply&lt;/a&gt; seems nice but I haven't used it (and it's currently difficult to subscribe to if you've not got an account there, but that may be a feature depending on how shy you're feeling).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, you should get started now. Step away from this post, set up a place to write, and then write something.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-08-10:11.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-09-10:23.html</id>
    <title>A Book is a Tool for Thinking With</title>
    <updated>2020-06-09T11:11:42+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;A Book is a Tool for Thinking With&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2WYeYew"&gt;Talking About Machines&lt;/a&gt; by Julian Orr, page 106:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...documentation is not just a representation of the machine and its prescriptions but must be regarded as a mechanism in and of itself. A service manual is a device which someone constructs to convey information to someone else, and choices of inclusion and exclusion significantly constrain what can be done with the manual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is an underappreciated point, especially when writing technical documentation, but I would go further than this: A document is not just a device for conveying information, it is a tool for thinking with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can see this in, well, the current post where I'm using &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-08-10:11.html"&gt;the random book prompt I described before&lt;/a&gt; (although I actually picked page 107 and scanned backwards for context and found this passage was the one that I wanted to write about).
The random prompt isn't really "conveying information" per se (I've already read this passage and am already aware of the general theme), but I am using the book as a way to have thoughts that I wouldn't otherwise have had, by picking a random passage from it and writing about it, which causes me to have thoughts that I would not otherwise have been having.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I talked about in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-13-09:56.html"&gt;How to read a book&lt;/a&gt;, the actual physical design of the tool (the book) matters quite significantly for its use. If you just think of it as a document for conveying information, the information is all that matters, but the physical design constrains its usage. &lt;a href="https://ramble.rixx.de/2020/06/08/a-blog-upon-the-deep.html"&gt;As Tobi discovered yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, if all you've got is a library of ebooks you're significantly constrained in your ability to pick random passages from it (unless you create your own programmatic tooling on top).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Over the next few pages, Orr talks about the corporation's use of "directive documentation" - documentation which goes through explicit procedures that you are supposed to follow exactly in the course of debugging the (photocopier) machine:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The directive documentation is designed not to provide information for thinking about the machine and its problems but to direct the technician to the solution through a minimal decision tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He then goes on to explain how this doesn't really work, because reality is irreducibly messy. The technicians use the documentation anyway, because it is often the result of knowledge they don't have (e.g. about the specific workings of a specific machine), but they do so in their own way:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...a system that fixes the machine without either customer or technician knowing how or why is unlikely to be acceptable. Consequently, when the technicians use the directive documentation, they try to determine the purpose of the various tests, to understand what the documentation is testing, to know what they are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not done just so they can reassure the customer; the technicians are also developing their understanding for future problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I keep saying &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;the fastest way to learn something is to do something&lt;/a&gt;, but often you run into the problem is that you have no idea what to do in order to learn something. Working through a preset procedure is often a good way to go.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of people were complaining at me recently because I had the audacity to suggest that you could learn programming from books. Obviously you learn programming from doing programming, and the idea of learning programming from books is ridiculous (except for all of these books that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; about programming that you should read to become a better programmer, because apparently it's perfectly possible to learn about programming by reading as long as you pretend you're not doing that).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suggest that one reason why people think this is that they are using books wrong. They have this wrong-headed idea that the way a book is supposed to work is that you read the book, you now have the book's information, and you now know the subject. Because this is not possible with programming (you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have to program to learn to program, there really is no way around that), it must be impossible to learn programming from a book.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, obviously nonsense, because this is a fully general argument against learning &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; from a book. Everything you learn has to be actively engaged with in order to learn it - even books which are pure information content you still need a much more active process of learning than that or the information will mostly disappear from your brain as soon as it enters, leaving only a vague sense that there's a there there (which is still useful of course - this is a form of &lt;a href="https://jmestn.com/15485/naval-doesn-t-take-notes"&gt;reading to maximize your exposure to ideas&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead, books about programming (or any other subject) should be thought of as tools you can use as part of your learning process. Just reading a book won't help you any more than thoroughly learning the details of a hammer will. You have to actually hit things with it. &lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-09-10:23.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-10-10:45.html</id>
    <title>Don't anthropomorphise fate, it hates that</title>
    <updated>2020-06-10T11:29:25+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Don't anthropomorphise fate, it hates that&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From Brewer's Dictionary of Phrase and Fable:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fate. Fates, the: The Greeks and Romans supposed there were three Parcae or Fates, who arbitrarily controlled the birth, life and death of everyone. They were CLOTHO, LACHESIS and ATROPOS. They are sometimes called the 'cruel Fates' because they paid no head to anyone's wishes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looking up each of these individually:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atropos (Greek, 'not turning', 'unchangeable'). In Greek mythology the eldest of the three FATES, the the one who severs the thread of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clotho (Greek klothein, 'to draw thread', 'to spin'). One of the three FATES in classic mythology. She presided over birth and drew from her distaff the thread of life. (See also Atropos, Lachesis)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lachesis. One of the three FATES, and the one who spins life's thread and determines its length. Her name represents Greek &lt;em&gt;lakhesis&lt;/em&gt;, 'destiny'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing I notice is how utterly inconsistent the formatting is on the three fates. Only Clotho references the other two. Lachesis has a different formatting for the Greek representation of her name.
That's by the by though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(By the by. Incidentally. 'By-' can often denote something subsidiary or secondary, such as: by-election, an election in a single constituency; by-play, the secondary action in a play; by-product, a subsidiary product; and byroad, a minor road)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've talked about &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2TCbsoa"&gt;Random Justice&lt;/a&gt; before (e.g. in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-23-07:48.html"&gt;Proportionality and identity&lt;/a&gt;), and about its point that one of the problems with lotteries for decision making is that they are a bit too arbitrary and impersonal in their fairness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I still haven't got around to reading The Secret of our Success but reviews of it (e.g. &lt;a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/04/book-review-the-secret-of-our-success/"&gt;Scott Alexander's review&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://scholars-stage.blogspot.com/2018/08/tradition-is-smarter-than-you-are.html"&gt;Scholar's Stage's review&lt;/a&gt;) exposed me to its idea that one of the historic functions of divination is to introduce randomisation into your decision making, and the personification of it as a message from the gods was part of how you got over the unfairness of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given that, it's interesting (if not entirely surprising) that the personifications of chance are the &lt;em&gt;cruel&lt;/em&gt; fates,
who you can't argue with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It seems like often one of the ways we deal with things is to personify them - treat them as an actual person. This works varyingly well. Sometimes it drives you to do useful activities like divination, where the reason it works is unrelated to the claimed purpose driven by that personification, but sometimes is causes you to treat objective reality as if it could be argued with, and that doesn't work out so great.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Facts don't care about your feelings" is a bad meme because facts are socially constructed statements about the underlying reality. But it's true that the underlying reality does not, necessarily, care much what you think of it - a volcano is going to erupt no matter what you sacrifice to it, a pandemic is going to pandemic regardless of whether you're bored of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think part of the problem is that we're used to the giant impersonal powers that control our fates being made out of people. Politics, capitalism, etc. aren't necessarily any less prone to crushing us with utter indifference to our lives, but that's because it feels like that's because the people involved in those systems &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; care. They could, in principle, be made to care if we exerted enough power over them (e.g. via protest). Whether or not that caring would result in systemic change is a bit more of a question mark, but the possibility is at least there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A natural disaster has no such potential to care. Yellowstone could erupt tomorrow killing us all, and it really doesn't matter how problematic we think that is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The temptation to personify is still there, and I think as long as we don't take it too seriously it's probably fine and maybe useful (omg coronachan is so mean), but it's important to remember: Fate is not cruel, fate is not kind, she isn't a person at all. The fates don't care about your feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-10-10:45.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-11-13:02.html</id>
    <title>Losing the story for the style</title>
    <updated>2020-06-11T14:00:31+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Losing the story for the style&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-06-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2LYdFGs"&gt;100 Ways to Improve your Writing&lt;/a&gt; by Gary Provost, page 57:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no subject that cannot be made fascinating by a well-informed and competent writer. And there is no subject that cannot be quickly turned into a literary sleeping pill by an incompetent writer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is as part of a section on style)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't true, and the fact that Provost thinks it's true is heavily informed by sorts of things he writes about,
which tend to be of more general interest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is that fascination is a question of audience/writing fit. In a similar way that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-08-08:53.html"&gt;you can't teach everything to a layperson&lt;/a&gt;, you cannot fascinate someone who refuses to be fascinated,
and some people are just never going to be fascinated by some subjects, and you may well need to write about those subjects (possibly because of the people who &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; going to be fascinated by it!).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's true that there is a fascinating story to be told about most subjects for most people, but often you shouldn't tell that one because it's not the important bit.
This reminds me of Zinsser's fucking terrible advice to tell a story about your engagement with the subject matter rather than the subject matter itself. There are circumstances under which that is the right thing to do, but those circumstances require me to care about you personally rather than the thing that I was expecting to learn.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's certainly true that any story can be told in a way that fascinates the maximum number of people who are capable of being fascinated by it, and that style has a huge part to play in that.
I'm in favour of good writing style, of course I am, and of not writing in a style that bores your audience, but it's important to not overstate the importance of style: You can't &lt;em&gt;make&lt;/em&gt; people fascinated by your writing, except by writing about a subject that they will be fascinated by when properly told, and sometimes that's not the subject you're there to write about.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-11-13:02.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
