<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2025-04-16T18:31:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-07-18:38.html</id>
    <title>Python has structural pattern matching</title>
    <updated>2025-04-07T18:47:25+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Python has structural pattern matching&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hey, did you know that this works?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class="pycon"&gt;&lt;code&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; from dataclasses import dataclass
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; @dataclass
... class Foo:
...     x: int
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; @dataclass
... class Bar:
...     x: str
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; match Foo(x=1):
...     case object(x=x):
...         print(x)
...
1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; match Bar(x=1):
...     case object(x=2):
...         print(x)
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; match Bar(x=1):
...     case object(x=x):
...         print(x)
...
1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; match Bar(x=1):
...     case object(x=2):
...         print(x)
...     case object(x=1):
...         print("hello!")
...
hello!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can use “object” as a matcher to match based solely on whether a
value being passed in has a particular field, and you can descend into
the value of those fields with other match expressions as you like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Python’s pattern matching is a bit of a weird beast because those
things in a case expression that look like constructor parameters are
nothing of the sort, they’re just fields, and they don’t have any
relationship to the type you’re matching on, they’ll just bind to the
field of that name on the object being matched &lt;em&gt;and the match will
fail if the field is not present&lt;/em&gt;. The type you’re matching on is
just an instanceof check&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And, of course, &lt;a href="https://www.hillelwayne.com/post/python-abc/"&gt;that instanceof
check doesn’t have to be a real instanceof check and can use ABC
subclass nonsense&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and doesn’t have anything to do with
the fields.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, you can use an &lt;code&gt;object&lt;/code&gt; match (or any other
type you want to match on) with arbitrary fields, and the match
expression will check for the presence of the field.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In some sense this is how it &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; to work but it was
non-obvious to me that it would work. In particular I thought there was
a decent chance that this would raise an AttributeError if you tried to
match on a missing field, but instead it handles that and you get
arbitrary structural pattern matching on record types if you want
it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can’t decide if this is cool or gross or both. More importantly, I
can’t actually think of a case where I’d actually need to use this
feature. I think it definitely straddles the line between “weird hack”
and “genuinely interesting language feature”, but because we’ve mostly
moved away from duck typing in Python, and because most of my usage of
pattern matching is effectively with closed algebraic data types, I
can’t actually immediately think of many places I’d want to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-07-18:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-08-09:56.html</id>
    <title>Asking for purpose disrupts action</title>
    <updated>2025-04-08T13:46:24+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Asking for purpose disrupts action&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was feeling unmotivated by my back collection of suggested writing
topics so I decided to try flicking through Hasok Chang’s “Realism for
Realistic People” for inspiration, and I found a useful distinction that
I think helps untangle one piece of what I was pointing at in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-04-13:33.html"&gt;Why do
you do things?&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He makes the distinction between the “inherent aim” and “external
functions” of an activity, using the example of lighting a match. If
asked why you are moving a match in a particular way across a surface,
your answer is simply “to light the match”. You can explain things in
more detail - why holding it at this particular angle helps, why you
have to move fast rather than slow, etc. but it is all relative to to
the specific goal of trying to get a match lit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also ask “Why are you lighting a match?”, to which the answer
might be “I’m trying to light a bunsen burner” or “I’m trying to figure
out how matches work” or “I like the pretty flames”. These are the
&lt;em&gt;extenral functions&lt;/em&gt; of the activity of lighting a match.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is as part of trying to point to what a well-defined activity
is, and the inherent aim is part of what constitutes something being a
particular activity. There is an action of “lighting a match” that you
can do more or less well, independently of the external functions of the
activity.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is of course not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; true. If you’re
trying to learn how matches work, your external function actually
includes lighting matches badly as well as well, because you want to
know what doesn’t work as well what does work. In contrast, if you’re
trying to light a bunsen burner, you just want to light a match well. I
think this is fine though - “lighting a match badly” can I think
legitimately be argued as a distinct activity that you can succeed or
fail at, even if it can externally look the same as trying to light a
match well and failing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In “Games: Agency as Art”, C Thi Nguyen talks about games as an
example of taking on &lt;em&gt;disposable ends&lt;/em&gt;. A game is an adoption of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lusory_attitude"&gt;the lusory
attitude&lt;/a&gt; - a voluntary attempt to overcome unnecessary obstacles.
This lusory attitude is one of voluntarily taking on the activity of
playing the game. With that activity, the &lt;em&gt;inherent aim&lt;/em&gt; is to
score the most points (or achieve some other victory condition). The
external function of the game might be to have fun, to spend time with
your friends, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you focus on those external functions of the game as primary it
can disrupt your abiltiy to play the game, which in turn can disrupt the
ability to achieve those external functions.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Except this isn’t quite true! For example, when Dave and
I play Root together, we often will go “This is probably a bad plan, but
it would be funny…” and take a move that from the perspective of the
game is clearly a suboptimal choice. I also do this in Slay the Spire
pretty regularly. The external function can inform choices in the game,
but I think it does this by changing the game you play. After making a
funny but suboptimal move, you go back to sincerely trying to win the
game.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nguyen points this out as an interesting and unusual feature of
games, but actually I think maybe it’s not. I think it is &lt;em&gt;often&lt;/em&gt;
the case that focusing on the external functions of the activity is
disruptive to the activity itself.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Sometimes that activity needs disruption of course. If
you’re doing the wrong thing, thinking about the external functions will
help you realise that and stop you doing the wrong thing. That’s
disruptive, because you’re doing something that should be disrupted!&lt;/span&gt; Being able to focus on a
singular goal and smoothly trying to achieve it allows you to enter an
effective flow state around that goal, and only when it is completed do
you find yourself returning to the question of why you were doing this
in the first place. If you try to act with the full set of external
functions of your activity in mind, most of the time you’ll fail to act
fluidly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This, to me, I think does a better job of capturing the right sorts
of distinctions that I want to make about why we do things. You can talk
about activities, and their aims, and how they fit together, and having
the notion of an activity effectively creates boundaries in the chain of
whys. Every end is terminal &lt;em&gt;while you are immersed in an activity
with it as its aim&lt;/em&gt;, and only on emerging from the activity (either
at its natural completion or as the result of some disruption) do you
ask how it fits into the broader patterns of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-08-09:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-09-18:44.html</id>
    <title>When I learned to read</title>
    <updated>2025-04-09T19:57:09+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;When I learned to read&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently Dave, Lisa, and I, were all helping sort through my parents’
giant boxes of books that have been sitting untouched for years to
decades. We were sorting them into various dubious ontologies - roughly…
worth keeping, worth trying to sell, worth giving away, bin. Dave and
Lisa in particular were trying to hunt out any gems that looked worth
selling.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point, Lisa hands me this tiny battered book of some cheap
adventure novel and said “Well, this one isn’t worth anything to
anyone.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She was, I think, unprepared for the look of absolute delight on my
face as I grabbed it off her. “I’ve been trying to find this for so
long!” I said.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let me backtrack 35 years or so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s extremely on brand that one of my first really coherent memories
is of learning to read in my head.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My school had a reading system. It was a whole thing - there was a
box of books, you picked what book you wanted, then you had to read it,
log your reading of it, and return it when you were done.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It may surprise you to know that I &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt; this. I dragged my
heels over it and had to be nagged into reading. Couldn’t stand reading,
me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, one evening I was reading out loud to mum, begrudgingly, and
complained about this. I don’t remember my specific complaint, but she
told me that I didn’t have to read out loud to her if I didn’t want to,
I could just read books in my head. I said “Oh, OK!” or words to that
effect, sent her away, and finished the book.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It didn’t take me long to finish the rest of the books in that box
after that, and I quickly turned from a kid who hated reading to one who
was regularly getting through giant doorstopper books.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Not, you understand, good ones. I read a lot of Robert
Jordan and Brian Lumley (don’t tell my parents about the second one.
They were not age appropriate) and other authors of similar quality
levels. My love of SFF trash continues to this day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was a pretty life-defining moment - I’m sure I’d have had it at
some point, but that was the specific point at which I had it, and it
sticks in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could even tell you quite a lot about the book that I was reading.
It was quite a short book, about some British soldier who is trying to
ship logs down from a mountain and wants to pass them through some
underground river, but they get lost in the middle, so he rides a log
through and finds a giant whirlpool there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried multiple times over the years to find it - asked around on
reddit, did a bunch of searching. Never could find it. I can’t remember
if I ever asked Claude or ChatGPT, but just testing it now Claude
straight up hallucinates an answer.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It says that it’s Rudyard Kipling’s “The Man Who Would
Be King”. It’s not.&lt;/span&gt; I’d asked my parents
about it but they had no specific memory of this event at all, let alone
what the book was.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was for a while half-convinced this was a fake memory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And then, totally unexpectedly, Lisa just handed me the book.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;“But David”, you may ask, “if it was a book from the
school reading box, why did &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; have it? That is an excellent
question. I have no idea. But it does have a sticker on it with my
school form so I’m pretty sure I should have returned it to a box and
didn’t.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is another variant on the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-07-17:35.html"&gt;digital
object permanence&lt;/a&gt; thing. If I’d read this book on a kindle, there is
no chance that I would ever have found in this way,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I mean I could have searched in my kindle library, but
do you want to take a bet that Amazon will maintain another 35 years of
continuity of archive? Admittedly they’re doing OK with the 15 they’ve
got so far, but I am not wildly confident. They also have a history of
disappearing things that you’ve bought.&lt;/span&gt; but
because the book just exists as a physical object in the world, it could
just stick around in my parents’ house until I found it again.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It wasn’t even the only book I found this way! I was
also trying and failing to remember the name of Karen Traviss’s &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wess%27Har"&gt;Wess’har books&lt;/a&gt;, and
found “City of Pearl” there, which helped me track down the whole
thing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The book is “The Cave of Death”, by Ian Serrallier. It’s very little
wonder that I couldn’t find it, because it barely exists. It’s part of
the “Wide Horizon Reading Scheme”, which I can provide very little
evidence of being a real thing that really existed other than a
scattering of other books with the same labelling. It’s a retelling of a
story originally written by J. H. Williams, in “In Quest of a Mermaid”.
I originally thought it was an extract, and felt moderately grumpy about
Ian Serraillier taking credit for it by being the only name on the
cover, but actually having now acquired a copy of the original, it seems
to be the same story entirely rewritten. I assume to make it more
self-contained and accessible to children, but I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s in many ways quite an interesting story. It’s very “boys own
adventures” and quite colonialist, but… fundamentally it’s a children’s
story about an engineering problem, and that feels rare to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even the colonialism is surprisingly interesting - yes, it’s a book
about a white British soldier leading a team of “natives” in Burma,
assisted by a bunch of itinerant Chinese workers. Yes, there’s a whole
bunch of racial stereotyping going on it. But… the fundamental message
about race relations in it seems to be “different cultures have
different beliefs, but they’re generally still good people, and you’ve
got to respect their beliefs in order to work with them”. I’m not going
to claim it’s completely unproblematic - the author would certainly get
cancelled for writing such a book today - but it genuinely seems like
quite a positive message for its time and probably quite a lot better
than many things written today.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And way less bad than, say, Narnia. All of this would
have completely gone over my head at the time though, as evidenced by
the fact that I was &lt;em&gt;living in Saudi Arabia&lt;/em&gt; when reading the
Narnia books and didn’t notice the islamaphobia. In my defence I also
didn’t notice the Christianity.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I think the really interesting thing for me about this whole
thing is not the specific book, but the degree to which figuring out
your past is just intertwined with actual mundane history, and how much
of history is bordering on lost because it’s not, as Lisa said, really
worth anything to anyone. This is an obscure book from an obscure
series. Of course I couldn’t find it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Except, of course, I totally could have. I bet you if I found a
research librarian and gave them a couple hundred pounds, they’d have
found the book for me in a few weeks, especially these days. I’m not
sure this possibility even really occurred to me as a live one, but in
retrospect it was very possible. I find these sorts of questions
interesting - things which clearly have an empirical answer, and finding
out the empirical answer is entirely within your means,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although! This is only true in this case &lt;em&gt;if the
answer is positive&lt;/em&gt;. If it turns out I’d dreamed the whole thing and
the book didn’t exist, establishing that with any degree of certainty
would be very costly.&lt;/span&gt; but
it’s just not clearly worth it. My go to example of this is look at a
random person passing you on the street, what’s their name? You could
just go ask them. It would be weird, but they’d probably tell you.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And if they don’t, you can probably still find out!
Probably not ethically, possibly not without being arrested, but you
can.&lt;/span&gt; And yet you don’t do it, because the
question is just an idle fancy, and the effort isn’t worth it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it’s often worth doing things that seem like they’re not
worth it, and this seems like a potentially good learning opportunity.
Even if the answer to the question isn’t worth the cost, maybe the
experience of figuring out how to answer it is. If I’d thought to ask a
research librarian of some sort about this, yes they’d have found the
book, but also I’d have learned more about how to interact with research
librarians, and that would in and of itself been worth it even if
finding the book was not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if going to ask a random stranger on the street their
name would be a good experience in the same way, but it seems like it
might be. It seems harmless, and I think generally figuring out how to
take greyed out options is good for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think that, perhaps, it would be good to notice such questions as
they arise, and every now and then even if it doesn’t seem worth it to
try to answer the question, answer it anyway, and see how that changes
you.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-09-18:44.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-10-16:38.html</id>
    <title>The scent of reality</title>
    <updated>2025-04-10T17:37:31+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The scent of reality&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes when I’m alone, I like to smell myself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Usually I sniff my hands or arms (sometimes my armpits) because
that’s the most easily accessible way of doing this.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although, prompted by writing this, I did try sniffing
my foot. It’s an interesting experiment but not nearly as pleasant. I
probably won’t repeat it often. Also maybe I need to wash my feet more
thoroughly and/or go around barefoot more.&lt;/span&gt; I
also like smelling other people, but generally only do that with
partners.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why smell myself? Well, it’s weirdly comforting, for starters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think sometimes that’s because I smell of me - certainly that’s the
big benefit of sniffing my arms - but that’s not all of it. Hands often
pick up scents from what I’ve been interacting with, and that’s often
even more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, whenever I’ve been using a measuring tape, I’ve noticed
that my hands always end up smelling of a sort of metallic oil scent
that I pick up from it. I think that may even be where this habit
started. It’s an oddly charming smell. I could tell a story about
associating it with my father’s workshop and that might even be true,
but I mostly just think that it’s interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I get a similar effect from using the typewriter - my hands often
pick up a smell of typewriter from it. Typewriter and measuring tape are
very similar smells, although I think I could probably tell the
difference if I compared them side by side. I don’t know if different
typewriters smell different - very likely. I’ve got two measuring tapes
here next to me but they smell the same. They are from the same brand
and of similar vintages, so that makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right now, my left and right hands smell different, because prompted
by thinking about scent I put on my essential oil vaporiser with some
sandalwood and bergamot. I got some of the bergamot on my hands when I
was doing this, so on my left hand the scent is textured between
measuring tape and bergamot.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Sandalwood is a much thicker oil which will barely come
out of the bottle willingly, so doesn’t get all over you in the same
way.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Except… actually I’m not sure that’s bergamot I’m smelling. I don’t
know what it is. Some sort of essential oil fusion from the various
outsides of the bottles mixing together. I had a sniff of the vapouriser
directly (it’s not yet vapourising enough to give off the scent very
far) and it smells like earl grey tea, because obviously that’s what
bergamot smells like. I think what I’m getting off my hand is maybe…
lemongrass? Certainly seems plausible. I do have a lemongrass in my
collection, and I rarely use it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My ability to discern individual scents is surprisingly bad. I feel
like I should train it more.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At about this point in writing, the vapouriser got up enough heat
that I suddenly got hit by a wave of very recognisable earl grey
scent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, smell and taste have a lot of range, and I think it’s
actually quite easy to detect, it’s just that you very rarely receive
much training in it. I’d like to do more.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in, I think, 2019, I did a blind gin tasting for my family for
Christmas, where we tried a number of different gins.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And, because I’m a jerk, one vodka and one Seedlip
non-alcoholic spirit that I didn’t tell anyone were in the mix.&lt;/span&gt;
Many of my family believed previously they couldn’t tell the difference
between different gins, but when actually comparing them side by side I
think it quickly became apparent that actually all of the gins had quite
distinctive tastes, and they did have genuine preferences among them
that they hadn’t previously noticed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every time I do a blind gin taste testing we come to two
conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tanqueray is everyone’s first or second favourite gin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We do not agree about what our favourite gin is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, in the gin taste testing we did then, the one I liked
the most was Mason’s tea gin. I don’t think anyone else put it in their
top 3, but I thought that the addition of the tea flavour was really
interesting.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This post is perhaps suggesting that I’m more into tea
than I am, but on the other hand I am British so maybe it’s just
accurately reflecting my love of tea.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think, in general, with scents and flavours I’m drawn to
interesting and complex. There’s a running joke with my paretners that I
don’t like nice things, especially in drinks, because &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/meditations-on-taste"&gt;I’m drawn
to complex bitter herbal flavours&lt;/a&gt; but this is partly because there’s
so much going on in them and I really like that. In contrast, I find a
lot of ostensibly “nice” things just a bit boring.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This comes up a lot in scent as well as spirits. Air freshener scents
and other highly artificial scents are often very upsetting to me. Air
fresheners in bathrooms are often actively upsetting to me - I can
handle the naturally unpleasant smell of a bathroom, but I can’t handle
the fake floral scents that are being used to cover it up.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’m actually not wild about floral scents in general, at
least not inside.&lt;/span&gt;
Fake fruit is even worse - I had to ask my partners to change washing up
liquids quite early in our relationship because I absolutely couldn’t
handle the “apple blossom” scented atrocity that they used.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Complexity isn’t enough though. My personal vision of hell is walking
into a Lush, because I just get bombed in the face with a complete
cacocophony of scents. It’s certainly complex, but it’s just noise, it’s
got no depth to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this point by the way the candle in my vapouriser burned down (it
had a weirdly short wick from previous use and hadn’t been doing well)
so I replaced it with a new candle. This gave me a chance to smell the
hot wax. It’s standard paraffin wax rather than beeswax - I’ve
previously experimented with beeswax candles and learned to my surprise
that I actually prefer the smell of paraffin wax. I think of paraffin
wax as pretty odourless, but a good up close sniff makes it clear that
this isn’t the case. It’s a mild smell, but actually quite a pleasant
one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don’t know exactly what scent is doing for me in these cases. It
feels something like… connecting me up from the world I’m in. The world
feels real, and I a part of it, when I’m able to smell it, and it feels
like the strongest counter I have to just regarding myself as a pure
information processing unit that happens to exist in a physical
world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given that, it’s interesting that the scents I prefer seem to have
relatively little connection up to the “natural”. It feels like some
sort of expression of what the world I want to be connected up to is.
It’s real, and complex, but it’s very much the world that we built
rather than some pristine state of nature, and it feels good and real to
be a part of that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-10-16:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-11-11:41.html</id>
    <title>Stable state</title>
    <updated>2025-04-11T12:06:42+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Stable state&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes people come to us from the City.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s not common, but it’s not rare either. Most years we see one,
maybe two, people stagger out of the door that opens in the shining
silver wall.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Usually we take them in. If the harvest is good and we have food to
spare, we will, but if they come to us in lean winter months when we
have nothing to spare, their mere presence takes food from the mouths of
others who need it. Better that they return to their City than that one
of us go.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And we do go. The sick and the dying go to the City. When the harvest
has been poor and the winter months draw in, the elderly often go. Some
people go simply because they are curious, or because they do not fit in
at home.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of those who do go in, some promise to return. They never do. Some of
the visitors tell us that once they came from the village, but if so
they did so long before anyone now alive can remember.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not everyone goes to the City eventually. Many choose to die rather
than go into the City. Some despite what the visitors from the City tell
us of it, some because of the same.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because if you ask a visitor what the City is like, they all say more
or less the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first thing they tell you is that it is heaven. There is no want
for any material thing - endless food of endless variety, warm homes all
year round, no need to toil each day in the field - and endless delights
and diversions, from parties and idle games to intellectual pursuits and
competitions of skill. There are millions of people in City, and you can
always find the perfect ones to spend your time with. Whatever your
desire, it can be fulfilled in the City. It is heaven.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second thing they tell you, if you press and ask them why then
they left to come to the village, where our lives are defined by want
and toil to survive, is that &lt;em&gt;something is missing in
Heaven&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The haunted looks on their faces at the second are almost as
disturbing at the look of bliss on their faces at the first.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The City is a place of wonders, there is no doubt. Many of the
visitors bring us gifts. Some of them we reject, and ask are returned to
the City - delights and diversions that beckon us with the promise of
more - but some are of a more practical sort. We still use the water
purifier that was given to us a generation back, and the village’s oven
is powered by a source of endless heat provided to us by the City. Many
of our knives and other tools are City-made, and of far superior quality
than we can buy from the travelling merchants. Living near to the City
gives us many things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it also takes many things from us.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We mourn for those who go to the City, perhaps more so than those who
die, because we know they are still in there, and we wonder what their
lives are like in there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The visitors who come to us tell us of the delights of the City and
how many wonders there are in there and how blissful they found it, but
if you ask them if they were happy there, they go quiet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People who come from the City rarely stay. Sometimes it’s the first
winter that does it, sometimes the second, but more often they leave in
the height of summer. They rarely say much about why other than that
they miss the City, but I can only imagine that they look a life of toil
and simple pleasures and decide that, whatever was missing from heaven,
at least it was still heaven.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I long ago decided that I would not go into the City, but sometimes
when I pause in my work, I find myself looking upwards, staring at the
shining walls, and wondering what heaven is like.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-11-11:41.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-12-16:30.html</id>
    <title>Anytime Projects</title>
    <updated>2025-04-12T17:57:44+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Anytime Projects&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-12&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something I’ve found over and over again is that there is a
particular way of structuring projects that, when you can manage it,
works very well. I call them Anytime Projects.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Named after &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anytime_algorithm"&gt;anytime
algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, which are algorithsm which you can interrupt at any
point prior to completion and they will tell you their current best
answer.&lt;/span&gt;
I’ve written about it &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/completing-completable-projects"&gt;a
bit before&lt;/a&gt; but never really fully articulated what Anytime Projects
are and why they work so well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The distinguishing feature of an Anytime Project is that can stop at
any point, and little of your time will have been wasted.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You make an anytime project as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You make a minimum viable version of the solution as quickly as
possible. This might just be the status quo, or it might be some initial
basic implementation of the thing you’re aiming at.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You proceed in a series of individually relatively small steps, each
of which leaves the project better off on completion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Optional features:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The project may not even be possible to finish. Many projects are
amenable to constant improvement over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be helpful to prioritise, so that you get a lot of the high
reward to effort tasks done first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, the way I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-23-21:48.html"&gt;clean
the kitchen&lt;/a&gt; structures it as an anytime project. There &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a
well-defined end state, but it’s done in a series of stages, where each
stage is fairly completable in its own right, and each stage being
completed is an improvement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, I recently converted my office in our house into a spare
bedroom&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;The office moved into the “box room” which is basically
a wide corridor joining the landing to the bedroom, and that I used as a
slightly awkard storage and study room before, so this is no great
hardship, except for the actual process of doing the rearrangement. I
actually like my new desk position better than my old one.&lt;/span&gt;, and the priority was getting the
new room usable in time for someone to use it, so my first step was
rapidly extracting everything from the office, much of which got dumped
in my bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an anytime project, because although I made
clear progress on getting the office ready to become a guest room, I did
not leave the system in a state where it was interruptible if I wanted
to be able to sleep that night.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, I think, one of the key feature sof an anytime project: At
any given point, you are a relatively small amount of work from just
being able to stop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why didn’t I do it that part as an anytime project? Too many moving
parts, too many dependency chains. I probably could have if I’d put in a
bit more forethought, but it would have been more work and taken longer
on the most important metric, which was getting the room ready.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is true in general I think: Unless something is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt;
naturally an anytime project, it’s usually going to be more work to do
it as one, and there will often be a faster route to any particular
point than doing it that way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So why do things as anytime projects?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One reason is just the definition: Whenever you end up abandoing the
project, you’ll still have ended up with something usable and worth
doing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But secondly, it’s actually been my experience that anytime projects
are &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more motivating, and the result is that you’re
&lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; likely to abandon the project! When there’s a huge amount
of work in front of you before you see any results, it can be quite
daunting. If in contrast you are presented with a constant stream of
easy ways to improve the situation, it’s easy to keep going until you’re
done - it always feels worth it to do one more thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s also possible to have many anytime projects on the go and pick
them up and put them down as and when you’re motivated to do a bit of
work on them. A blog is an anytime project, as is most software once
it’s in a releasable state - you can sit down, do something to it, and
make it better by publishing an article or adding a feature or fixing a
bug or something. This makes anytime projects &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-23-15:52.html"&gt;a more
natural part of your life&lt;/a&gt; than many larger more monolithic
options.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some things you end up wanting to structure them partially as anytime
projects. e.g. right now in the room move, dealing with the fallout of
it is an anytime project. After I tidied up the worst of the stuff I’d
moved into my bedroom, my bedroom and new office are usable, but there’s
still a lot to do, but I can just do it in small life-improving chunks
each day.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Sometimes I even do that.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there’s often a very natural split of a project into two
phases: An initial prototyping or drafting phase where you do whatever
is needed to get some usable first version, and then an Anytime Project
of finishing it off. e.g. I’ve often used “writing a book” as an example
of something that isn’t an anytime project, but I think this is only
sortof true. &lt;em&gt;Writing a first draft&lt;/em&gt; is not, but after that draft
is written there’s a long process of editing and improvement which does
mostly naturally fit the anytime pattern of project design.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve thought of myself as bad at completing projects in the past, but
I think perhaps what I need to get better at is &lt;em&gt;completing
drafts&lt;/em&gt;. In &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/i/136296748/mode-shifts"&gt;Completing
Completable Projects&lt;/a&gt; I identified the idea of a &lt;em&gt;mode shift&lt;/em&gt;
in projects where the sort of activity you need to perform changes as
the projet nears completion. I think at the time I didn’t notice the
transition to anytime as a mode shift because the project I was talking
about didn’t have an editing phase, but I think this is notion of mode
shift is perhaps a good way of thinking about project planing: The first
stage of a project is to get it into anytime mode, as quickly and easily
as possible, and then after that you mode shift it into an anytime
project.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-12-16:30.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-13-14:46.html</id>
    <title>An improvised meal</title>
    <updated>2025-04-13T15:58:11+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;An improvised meal&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-13&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Due to a series of communication mixups where different people
thought it was someone else’s turn to cook, I got home the other day at
7:15 to discover that dinner had not even been started. We normally eat
dinner at 7:30, and the planned meal for the evening (bolognese) takes
several hours to cook. So I sprung into action and 45 minutes later we
had the following entirely improvised meal for five:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stir fried mixed greens with garlic and chilli&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thai omelettes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ground pork and tofu with fermented soy beans, garlic, and
chilli&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stir fried peppers with ginger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sausages&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I did think about doing something more interesting with
the sausages. e.g. turning them into tiny sausage meat balls and cooking
them in something that would flavour match them to the rest of the
dishes - they’d have worked pretty well with ginger and chilli and a bit
of honey added at the end for example. But that sounded like work and
the the child wouldn’t have eaten any.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sliced raw pepper&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Mostly for the child who wasn’t going to eat either the
cooked peppers or the stir fry green because they had too much flavour
and “the texture is weird”.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rate limiting factor was the rice really - our rice cooker takes
about 45 minutes to make enough rice, so the rest was just down to what
I could make while the rice cooked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this demonstrates a couple of interesting things about
improvised cooking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is that there’s a base meal there that I can just do on
autopilot: Rice, stir fried mixed greens, and thai omelettes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The stir fried mixed greens are &lt;a href="https://strongroots.com/en-gb/products/stir-fry-greens"&gt;actually
just from a packet&lt;/a&gt; but it’s a genuinely good product to have in the
freezer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thai omelette is something of a staple dish in our house because the
child loves them and everyone else likes them, and because they’re very
easy to make. You should probably use &lt;a href="https://www.seriouseats.com/thai-style-omelet-khai-jiao-recipe"&gt;the
serious eats recipe&lt;/a&gt; but ours is an extremely simple one: Take some
eggs, add a nonspecific amount of fish sauce, whisk with a fork, and
then fry in a hot pan with lots of oil.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m sure I’ve written about this before but I can’t come up with an
immediate reference,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Maybe &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-05-11:27.html"&gt;Seeking
out existence proofs in everyday life&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/span&gt; but a good general principle is that
you should first make sure you can solve the problem adequately, and
only then worry about improving on that. Having these sort of baseline
meals that you can throw together and then build around is, to me, key
to improvisational cooking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After the base meal, the next important question is “What do we have
that needs using up?”. e.g. you might notice that the sausages are a bit
out of place in this meal. I cooked them anyway, because they were
really on the last day they were still good, and we figured that they’d
keep for another day cooked if not eaten and also they would definitely
get eaten. They were.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The peppers were there partly because we had a large thing of sliced
raw peppers in the fridge from a previous meal where we’d sliced way
more peppers than we ended up eating. I dry fried them to get them nice
and charred, then added frozen diced ginger, sugar, salt, and oil, then
when they were cooked transferred them to a small bowl in the oven to
keep warm and moved on to cooking the pork.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty easy example of improvisational cooking I think:
Take a base ingredient, cook it in a normal way, and add some flavours
that would make it good. A lot of vegetables respond well to this
treatment, including many you wouldn’t necessarily expect. e.g. I’ve
stir fried leftover roast potatoes with ginger and soy sauce before and
that works great.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Not &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; vegetable will work this way of
course. Some vegetables don’t stir fry well, and some have such a
distinctive flavour that doesn’t fit this style of cooking. e.g. I would
not use leftover beetroot this way.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The pork and tofu was a bit more of a genuine creation. We had about
half a bag of tofu king deep fried tofu puffs left that were going off
that day, and about a quarter of a packet (so, I guess, roughly 75g) of
pork mince left over from a meal the other day that would have kept a
bit longer but didn’t have an obvious job associated with it. I’ve
enjoyed Mapo Tofu in the past, which is a completely different dish
combining pork and a different style of tofu, and decided that this was
worth an experiment, so I stir fried the pork with garlic and chilli
from the freezer and some salted fermented soy beans I had in the
fridge,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;A completely normal ingredient to have to hand, right?
No, honestly, I picked them up on a whim the other day when passing a
Chinese supermarket in Cambridge. But they’re really nice, I recommend
them. &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/ZHENG-FENG-Salted-Black-Soybean/dp/B0792GLN3S"&gt;These
are the ones we have&lt;/a&gt;. A nontrivial part of the motivation of this
dish was an excuse to experiment with them.&lt;/span&gt;. This is another appliation of the
“Take a thing and stir fry it with some flavours that would be good with
it”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While that was cooking, I cut the tofu in half (as I’d noticed it was
a bit chonky to cook well when I used the other half bag), and then
added it to the stir fry. Once that was all looking cooked, I also put
that in a bowl in the oven to keep warm, and cooked the greens (add a
bit more sesame oil to the wok, pour the packet in, done).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, all of this was of course only possible because I was in
my own kitchen, which has been stocked with a bunch of things that I
know I can improvise around. We almost always have rice, eggs,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;We’ve got &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; many eggs at the moment, because
we traded our fridge for some recently.&lt;/span&gt; and stir fry greens available, so
there was always a base meal to build around. Similarly, it’s a lot
easier to take a baseline and add some flavours to it if you know you’ve
got a ready supply of flavours to hand.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, preparation seems to be the key to improvisation: You
prepare a solid base of skills to improvise around, and a variety of
tools and resources that you know how to draw from, and the rest is just
elaboration on whatever you have to hand using that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-13-14:46.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-14-21:32.html</id>
    <title>Lessons from win streaking: Learning reliability skills</title>
    <updated>2025-04-14T21:55:14+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Lessons from win streaking: Learning reliability skills&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-31-18:47.html"&gt;still
working on win streaking&lt;/a&gt;. Recently, I got my win streak up from two
to nine.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I was about as annoyed not to make it to an even 10 as
you might imagine, but my actual goal was 5, so I’m still pretty pleased
with myself..&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, uh, I switched characters. I’m much better at Ironclad than
Defect&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;So is almost everyone else. Ironclad is just an easier
character.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This brings up my win streak for an obvious reason, which is that
it’s easier, but I think it also brings it up for a non-obvious one:
Because it’s easier, I can more readily tell what I’m doing wrong. It’s
very hard to learn from failure without good feedback loops, and in
easier games your feedback is clearer because there are fewer things for
you to do wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In doing so, I’ve noticed a couple of interesting things. They are
somewhat obvious in retrospect, but they were at least a little
non-obvious to me in foresight.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is: Once I try to win streak, my appetite for risk changes
significantly. That is, previously I would take risks that had a small
(say, 5-10%) chance of killing me, because they seemed fun or because I
thought I needed to. If you take a few of those chances per run, they
add up pretty rapidly and your win streaks are cut short.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why take risks at all? Because risks are how you get rewards. In Slay
the Spire the biggest instance of this is fighting elites - hard
monsters that drop a lot of treasure. If you don’t fight enough elites,
you don’t gain enough strength, and then you die to the boss fights
(which you can’t skip). So you want to take as many elites as you can,
but you also want to not die, and success is about balancing this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means that one of the most important skills for learning to win
streak in slay the spire is to be able to accurately assess the current
strength of your deck: To ask “Can I beat this elite?” and also “Can I
beat the upcoming boss?” and weigh your chances accordingly, and make
contingency plans.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, since starting to win streak, I’ve skipped a lot more
elite fights,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;On average probably 1-4 per game. In some cases because
I deliberately swerve before the elite, in others because I’m forced
onto a path with fewer elites.&lt;/span&gt; because I’ve looked at the upcoming
elite, gone “Can I take it?” and thought “Nah”. The streak I lost, I
actually knew I was likely to lose, because I’d correctly assessed that
I couldn’t take an elite fight and wasn’t offered a path that let me
skip elites for long enough.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of this process of assessment is just vibe play writ small -
I’ve got a good intuitive sense of what fights the deck can and can’t
take, and that has a better feedback loop than the game overall - but
some of it is being able to ask more specific and concrete questions
like “How much damage are Slavers going to do to me in the first two
turns and is that more than my hit points?” or “When Nemesis attacks me
for 45 damage, what exactly am I going to do other than block it with my
face?”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also informs the game more broadly, because when you realise
that the answer is “No, you can’t take it”, it tells you how your deck
needs to improve.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An interesting side effect is that it’s also improved my potion
use,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Potions are one-time use resources that grant you
specific effects when you use them. A &lt;em&gt;remarkable&lt;/em&gt; amount of Slay
the Spire skill seems to come down to knowing when to use a potion and
when to hold it.&lt;/span&gt; because sometimes the answer when I
ask this question is “Probably not, but you can spend potions to fix
this”. I’ve used potions more aggressively to win elite fights and
bought more potions in shops than I normally do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think, in general, improving reliability looks like this. It’s easy
to think of reliability as just a number, but it’s actually composed of
specific situations, and improving your reliability is about identifying
those situations. You improve reliability by &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-03-13:40.html"&gt;figuring
out what you should worry about&lt;/a&gt;, and come up with specific plans for
avoiding or handling those situations.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-14-21:32.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-15-22:18.html</id>
    <title>Real examples are messy</title>
    <updated>2025-04-15T22:53:15+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Real examples are messy&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading “On Caring” by Milton Mayeroff today. It’s a mostly
pretty good book, outlining a theory about what it means to care for
something, but it has an example quite early on which set me off.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obligations that derive from devotion are a constituent element in
caring, and I do not experience them as forced on me or as necessary
evils; there is a convergence between what I feel I am supposed to do
and what I want to do. The father who goes for the doctor in the middle
of the night for his sick child does not experience this as a burden; he
is simply caring for the child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think that this example is obviously made up, and I think that you
can partly tell that because of the straightforward lack of detail, but
I just think it’s also not true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If your child is currently in desperate need and on the way to ER
then sure, obviously, you’re not going to experience this as burdensome,
because your mind is focused on the immediate emergency, but that’s not
even particularly because it’s your child. In the middle of an emergency
I mostly find that I’m too focused on the actual crisis at hand to think
about how burdened I am by it, although I might have a moment of
thinking “Oh, what a pain” right at the beginning.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And, in real emergencies, have.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast if your child is up with, say, a stomach bug, and has
been vomiting, and you’ve just got off a long shift and you’re exhausted
and want nothing more than to go to sleep, then &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt;
you’re going to experienced this as burdensome. You’re exhausted, the
whole thing is a pain, and you want to go to bed. You (hopefully) do it
anyway, because its your child and you love them and you &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-29-10:40.html"&gt;do
things because you gotta&lt;/a&gt;. But that doesn’t mean you will never
experience it as burdensome, only that you bear that burden mostly
willingly, albeit sometimes begrudgingly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And I think that the idea that this devotion and caring in the
context of a child means that you don’t experience any burdens just
completely fails to capture the very normal experience of parenting. And
I think that if you were to look at many actual concrete examples of day
to day parenting you would find that parents experience those children
as burdens fairly often. And typically they will regard those burdens as
worth it, because they want what’s best for their child, but that
doesn’t mean that they never experienced these “oh gosh, my life would
be so much easier if I didn’t have to deal with this shit.” moments.
Most importantly, having these sorts of thoughts &lt;em&gt;doesn’t mean they
don’t care about their child&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And this is a big part of why I care quite a lot about this example
and its basic failure to capture the essential humanity of real
situations. If you’re in a parenting situation like this, where you’re
exhausted and have to deal with a minor medical crisis or other such
problem with your child, there is definitely going to be some part of
you that goes “oh god. Yet another fucking thing.” And, when it does,
there’s another part of you which looks at that part and goes “Gosh. You
must be a bad parent for feeling that way.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And this seems to me to be what happens when you start with these
tidy narratives, theories of how things should be rather than looking at
specific concrete examples of things as they actually are. You try to
understand your experiences through that lens, and you fall short
because you fail to be the perfectly spherical human in a vacuum that
the theory predicts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If, on the other hand, you talk to other parents about their
experiences, pretty inevitably what will happen is they’ll tell you that
yeah of course they feel like that sometimes too.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I can’t find a single biographical detail about
Mayeroff, so I don’t know if he had kids. If he did, maybe he had an
unusually saintly degree of equanimity. But I doubt it. I think he just
had a theory and made up an example to fit it without thinking about
whether it was true.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you instead listen to things as they actually are, as told by
people who actually been through the experiences, what you’ll find is
that there is a richness and a messiness to them that doesn’t conform to
sort of very tidy theories that say how things should work. And I think
this is key to personal growth, to self forgiveness, to navigating the
world in a humane manner, and being kind to both yourself and others.
You have to encounter humanity in all its messy complexity, rather than
humanity as you would like to idealise it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a smaller context, I’ve been sort of developing this theme
recently because I’ve been writing a bunch of really mundane blog posts.
These are things like &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-23-21:48.html"&gt;here’s
how I clean my kitchen&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-13-14:46.html"&gt;I had
to cook something on short notice in 45 minutes&lt;/a&gt;, or even just &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-14-21:32.html"&gt;here’s
some stuff I learned playing Slay the Spire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Each of these starts from a very concrete experience, talking about
how I navigated it and what I’ve learned in doing so. It’s not purely a
narrative about a specific thing - it sort of tries to point out where
I’ve used some idea that I think generalizes or some oddly useful
principle, but it is still fundamentally the story of that particular
event.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think these pieces are in many ways much more useful because they
are forced to grapple with the concrete reality of the task at hand. So
they contain a lot of details and how those details were dealt with that
would not have been present if I had started from some much more general
theory. I do then tend to write a little bit about generalisable lessons
from them of course, but I think starting from a real and detail-rich
experience and trying to figure out how to transfer it to other similar
situations gets you a lot further than trying to start from a tidy
theory and forcing your life into its procrustean view of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-15-22:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-16-18:31.html</id>
    <title>Recovering desire with care</title>
    <updated>2025-04-16T18:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Recovering desire with care&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-16&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently finished reading “The Reasons of Love” by Harry
Frankfurt.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;“By the author of the best-selling”On Bullshit”“. Harry
Frankfurt is a very respectable philosopher who writes really
interesting things about motivation and desire and how we live our
lives. He also wrote”On Bullshit”, which while genuinely excellent, ends
up being his Cherry Pie, and is the main thing people think of when he
comes up. I mentioned this book to a friend and her immediate response
was “Is that the bullshit guy?”. I imagine him grimacing every time
something like this happens, but I find it very funny.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s… one of those books that I don’t know whether or how to
recommend, because I got a huge amount out of reading it, but I don’t
know how much of that was actually in the book and how much of it was in
the context which I was reading it in. It’s short, well written, and
about as engaging as a moderately dry work of analytic philosophy can
be. I also cried multiple times while reading it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;But this is part of the context, and I’m easily brought
to tears at the moment. Don’t worry about it, I’m fine. Well, I’m not
fine, but things are trending in an upwards direction and the people who
need to know why I am sad do.&lt;/span&gt; So,
I guess I recommend it, and if you don’t like it then oh well it’s very
short.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things it discusses is what it means to care about some
outcome, and how this contrasts with desiring it. He says you can desire
some outcome without particularly caring about it. e.g. When bored, you
might watch a movie to alleviate that. You desire to watch the movie to
alleviate the boredom but that doesn’t mean you particularly care about
the movie. You can care about your work, but be so burned out that you
can’t manage any desire to do good work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Frankfurt suggests that caring consists, in part, of wanting or
thinking that it is important to desire the end. When you care about
something, and also desire it, that desire feels harmonious with your
intentions. When your desires - either their presence or their absence -
conflicts with what you care about, you desire (or perhaps just will) to
change your desires. When things are going well, your desires are the
same as (or at least compatible with) your cares, and when things are
going badly, the two diverge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this view, part of what enables the “&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-29-10:40.html"&gt;you
gotta&lt;/a&gt;” attitude is that you care about the thing that needs doing
(you think it’s important) even if you don’t want to do it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This isn’t entirely true of course, because sometimes
what enables it is that you care about something that acts as a standin
- what Agnes Callard calls a proleptic value. For example when H doesn’t
want to do something and I tell her to do it anyway, she may also not
care, but it’s still important and part of the role of a parent is to
help her understand that it’s important, and your good opinion as the
parent acts as the standin.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This distinction between desiring and caring is interesting
contrasted with some things I’ve thought and written about caring
before. Back in ancient days I wrote about &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;burnout as
acedia&lt;/a&gt;, in which I said:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acedia (pronounced a-seed-ee-a) is a state of feeling unable to care.
It’s not the mere absence of caring about things, but the feeling that
caring is difficult or impossible. As a sense of hopelessness is to
hoping, a sense of acedia is to caring.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Wiktionary gives the much simpler definition of
“spiritual or mental sloth; apathy.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think that when I wrote this, I was very much conflating desiring
and caring. I actually think the post works &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; with
Frankfurt’s notion of caring,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And its conclusions tie in very well with Frankfurt’s
later in the book.&lt;/span&gt; but at the time I think
I was very much implicitly conflating an inability to &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;
things and an inability to &lt;em&gt;care about things&lt;/em&gt;, and I think these
are actually pointing at very different experiences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have pretty longstanding issues with depression, and I’m not very
good at being happy. I’ve often found it’s hard for me to really desire
things in any stable way - I’m certainly not unable to have desires, but
they tend to be short lasting and not particularly intense, and tends to
be oriented much more around comfort and reducing distress than in
seeking joy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this difficulty in desiring things would previously have
seemed to me like acedia in the sense I outlined, but this clearly
conflicts with the idea that what I struggle with is &lt;em&gt;caring&lt;/em&gt;. If
you look at how I actually behave it’s really obvious that I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;
care about things. I care a lot, and I care quite stably about them. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-23-13:27.html"&gt;I care
so much it hurts&lt;/a&gt;. Whether I manage to act on that caring is highly
variable, but a lot of what I do is driven by a burning sense that &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/this-is-important"&gt;this is
important&lt;/a&gt;. Some of the things I care about are clearly in conflict,
but I don’t know that they have to be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Frankfurt says that when you find yourself caring about something but
not desiring it, you desire to desire it and will seek to rekindle your
desire for it. I think that’s true, but I’m left with a question…
how?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the answer is that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-22-21:54.html"&gt;there
is no sludge&lt;/a&gt;. There is no generalised failure to desire. What there
is is a collection of individual desires, all of which I have thorugh
one reason or another lost the ability to express.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I still care about them, and given that I should be able to
express them again. Starting from the care, and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;tracing
the pathways out from there&lt;/a&gt; and seeing where they are blocked, you
should be able to find the ability to want that thing again, or at least
acknowledge that you really do no longer care about it and also &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;don’t
believe you should&lt;/a&gt; and start to let that go.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-16-18:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
