<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2021-07-17T14:20:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-07-14:11.html</id>
    <title>Studying the mundane</title>
    <updated>2021-07-07T17:53:39+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Studying the mundane&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things that you might notice about the things that I write is that they're often about really mundane topics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/telegraph-your-moves"&gt;Telegraph your moves&lt;/a&gt; contains a significant discussion of why you should tell people when you're running late.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/you-should-complain-about-it"&gt;You should complain about it&lt;/a&gt; is about complaining (obviously).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-do-everything"&gt;How to do everything&lt;/a&gt; is almost entirely about this (I do briefly talk about mathematics and writing, but mostly it's not about that) and touches on profound topics such as how to catch a ball, how to clean your bathroom, and how to open a bag of rice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do not write about mundane topics because they are sources of deep philosophical insight. I write about them because I am actually trying to solve mundane problems. I said in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-03-13:55.html"&gt;No shortage of things to write about&lt;/a&gt; that "in order to run out of things to write, I'd have to basically have life solved. I'm uh a little ways away from that". This is true. But necessarily a significant number of the problems I have not solved in my life are mundane, because most of life is mundane, and I still think these problems are worth writing about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't to say that I'm &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; interested in mundane problems, but mundane problems are important, and often &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/life-complete-problems"&gt;life complete&lt;/a&gt; in interesting ways, and by their very mundanity will often have high impact. I don't know if my writing has ever made anyone blissfully happy, but I do know multiple people who have improved the way they cleaned their bathroom and had a slightly less annoying rice opening experience as a result, and that too is part of the good life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A particular reason I study and think about mundane things is that I think that there's often a lot of low hanging fruit available for improving them. People don't spend much time thinking about mundane problems, and even less time on how to communicate improvements in them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To a large degree this is rational: You essentially improve until what you've got is "good enough" and it's not worth figuring out how to improve further.
Importantly though, the effort that isn't worth it is that of &lt;em&gt;figuring out&lt;/em&gt; how to improve further. Often doing better is lower effort than what you're doing now, or very high benefit. Once you know how to do something the better way, it's clearly worth doing it that way (if it weren't, it wouldn't be a better way, it would be a way with a different set of trade offs), but that doesn't mean it's worth inventing that better way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(It may also still not be worth learning that better way, or you may not want to, and that's fine. I'm both not that great at tying my shoes and know full well I could fix this with a couple of hours spent studying &lt;a href="https://www.fieggen.com/shoelace/ianknot.htm"&gt;Ian Fieggen's Shoe Lace website&lt;/a&gt;, but have I done that? I absolutely have not)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I on the other hand am perfectly happy to put in that effort, because I find it interesting, and I have time to spend, and also there's a lot of stuff that other people seem to be "naturally" good at that I've had to figure out the hard way, so once I've invested all that mental infrastructure in learning this stuff I might as well keep going.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And... it turns out it's not that hard. There are some core skills that it's worth developing, but they're generally useful core skills for life, mundane or otherwise. Mostly you just need to learn to break out of habits, spot patterns, and identify where you've taken problems as immutable when they're actually easily fixable things. I'm not claiming this is &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt;, but it's not rocket surgery or anything, and almost by definition it's a skillset for making most parts of your life better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It does take time and energy, and I'm aware those are both often in short supply, so I don't expect too many people to do as much thinking about this as I do, but that's fine. I don't mind having a niche, and I expect I'll keep it. After all, literally nobody else is ever going to &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/refusing-to-learn"&gt;explain how to keep your flat clean in terms of the work of James C. Scott on the early development of agrarian states&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Although I could totally see &lt;a href="https://goula.sh/"&gt;Meekaale&lt;/a&gt; doing this with Hubert Dreyfus and Alasdair MacIntyre instead)&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-07-14:11.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-08-15:18.html</id>
    <title>Heading towards the ouch</title>
    <updated>2021-07-08T15:57:23+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Heading towards the ouch&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's an interesting therapeutic technique that I've synthesized out of various practices.
It's not exactly a &lt;em&gt;safe&lt;/em&gt; practice, but I do think it's a useful one.
I deployed a bit of it earlier in a coaching session (after extensive checking in with the client that this was really what they wanted me to do, including asking "This is going to require me to be an asshole to you. Are you sure you want me to do that?"),
but I haven't quite got a handle on how to facilitate it for someone else yet because I don't generally do it for other people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The technique is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Say something that you don't want to say (or possibly think it clearly. Saying it out loud is supposed to work better, but I sometimes find the opposite).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does it hurt? Good. Identify why it hurts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take the part that hurts and say something new based on it. If that hurts more, switch to that as your new starting point. If not, stick with the current one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep doing this until you run out of "improvements" or it gets too much and you need to stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use wherever you've ended up as a prompt for introspection. Explain why it feels so bad, in depth, what you're worried about, evaluate whether the statement is actually true, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, such a sequence for me might look like:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I should get a real job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm just kidding myself about being able to make writing work as a career.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm not going to see it through anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'll just quit as soon as it gets too difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think this is necessarily true (I sure hope it's not!), but there's definitely some part of me that believes that,
and I can notice a real physical discomfort increasing as I move down the list. I really don't like the last entry at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is roughly a shadow work / Focusing hybrid. It's designed to help you uncover emotionally painful beliefs that you're trying to ignore.
Generally these sorts of statements don't hurt unless some part of you believes on some level that they are true,
and this process gets you to a point where you have identified a specific acutely painful belief to interrogate (and ideally do something like coherence therapy to to defuse it, if indeed that belief is false. See e.g. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;Emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also, I think, probably quite a good tool for learning Focusing because of how unsubtle it is. This is not staying with a fuzzy unclear feeling until it makes sense, this is confronting you with exactly what a felt sense dialled up to 11 is like. It's oddly similar to the strategy I outlined in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-06-13:53.html"&gt;Start from amazing&lt;/a&gt;, in that it dials up the feelings until they can be clearly identified so you know what to look for, rather than leaving you in a fuzzy in between space where you're not sure if anything is going on there or not.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-08-15:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-09-12:43.html</id>
    <title>What does one do on bad days?</title>
    <updated>2021-07-09T14:49:42+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;What does one do on bad days?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today is not a particularly good day for me. I guess it would be a stretch to call it a bad day, but I'm tired and out of sorts, struggling to focus as a result, and generally not at my finest. Not particularly depressed or anything, just a bit meh.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm writing this piece anyway, because I wanted to write something every day and I think it's good for me to stick to that - both in the sense that I'm able to do it and I committed to doing it, so I should, and also in the sense that I want to do it and I think it's helpful for me to do so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But at the same time, I have some actually involved writing projects I want to do. I'm still figuring out a (paid) newsletter issue on taste that I have to finish, am planning to write up a lot of my old notebook posts on emotions into a more coherent form, and am still reading "Technology and the Character of Contemporary Life". None of that really appeals today, nor does the slightly more sophisticated notebook post I was going to write instead of this one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And honestly it's reasonable that they don't appeal today. I could do them if I had to, it's not that I'm literally incapable of them, but possibly I'm impaired enough that I shouldn't: the benefit is reduced from me at my peak performance, and the cost increased. They're things that are definitely worth doing on a good day, but maybe they're not today.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is something of a recurring pattern for me. I couldn't really tell you how often it happens (I probably should be able to, but I'm not sure what counts as "it". Also I hate data entry. Please don't give me advice on this, I don't want your advice, and I will shout at you in my &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/no-backseating"&gt;No Backseating&lt;/a&gt; voice), but certainly it's not an unusual occurrence. I'd guess I have a day at least this bad most weeks, sometimes more often than that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And this often leaves me thinking about the question of what to do with those days.
Or, I guess, more specifically how to avoid losing them to dissociative activities. It's very easy to get to the end of a bad day and go "Wait, what did I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; today?" and discover that the answer is that you spent all of it on Twitter, or playing games, or watching youtube videos, or something else of that ilk.
This seems bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If I had a real job of course (and sometimes even when I've not had a real job and it was purely self inflicted) what I would do with such days (if they fell on a weekday) is to sacrifice them on the altar of the god of presenteeism. Can't do anything useful today? Tough luck. We'll punish you for taking the day off, but turning up and being miserable and not getting any work done is fine, so...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's relatively far down on the list of complaints I have about society, but definitely one of the failings is that we treat human beings as more reliable than they are, and then make it their problem when they fail to live up to that impossible ideal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Setting that aside... In an ideal world, what would we like such days to be like?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've suggested to coaching clients that it's good to build up a sort of library of things they can do for breaks, or when feeling bad. Going for a walk is one, doing some meditation or lying semisupine another, but these feel more like pause activities than fulfilling. Also I often don't &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to do these things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe I'm just being melodramatic due to my low mood, but it feels like this question is butting up against foundational questions like "What is life for?". Having a day where one is feeling tired and low motivation feels like one is butting up against the "&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vS-zEH8YmiM"&gt;We've got both kinds of sources of meaning, production &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; consumption&lt;/a&gt;" that it feels too easy to settle into. You end up stripped of access to meaning, mostly by laying bare how limited your access to it was in the first place, and are forced to ask what's left. It's no wonder it's easy to lose these days in activities that are designed to help you fast forward life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reading that paragraph back to myself does rather feel like I was lying when I said I wasn't having a particularly depressed day, doesn't it? Oh well. I'm going to go for a walk and pretend to be thinking deep thoughts while I do.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-09-12:43.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-11-11:03.html</id>
    <title>You open one of the 999 boxes on this floor and find...</title>
    <updated>2021-07-11T12:53:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You open one of the 999 boxes on this floor and find...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening I was, for reasons, talking to someone and coming up with strange and unsettling things you could do with surplus rooms in a house. Here are some of my entries:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One room has all the walls mirrored but one of the mirrors is secretly a screen and doesn't flip the image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One room is perfectly normal but for some reason the ceiling is a map of England. There is a "You are here" label on it. The label is, confusingly, pointing at a completely different city.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a pool room. We couldn't decide whether this was the sort with water or the sort where you hit a ball with a stick, so it's both.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room with a microphone and speakers that generate an artificial echo that is on very slightly too long a delay to be comfortable, and also sometimes you'd swear there's another voice in the background.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An entire room which is just a giant playground for cats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls are an ant farm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could keep going pretty much indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One room has many cupboards, but all the cupboards doors look identical to doors to other rooms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room with a window in it that on closer inspection looks out on the wrong side of the house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A perfectly normal living room in which all the furniture is for some reason clad in brightly coloured padded foam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room with central heating that automatically adjusts to a temperature the current occupants will find uncomfortable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room where all the walls are lined with drawers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room that generates a slightly unpleasant noise every time someone talks, gradually training people into silence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room that is perfectly normal but all the wall sockets are that of a different country.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Each of these took me no more than a couple of seconds to come up with, and I feel like I could do this for longer, though I expect I'd start to get a little repetitive at the 100 mark.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls are all different colours. When the room is occupied and nobody is looking at a particular wall, its colour changes very slightly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls "wrap around" visually so that looking at a wall you see the view from the opposite wall, stretching out into infinity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's only so much you can do with walls.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A reading room with several comfy chairs. Next to each is a small table with a pile of books on it. When you take a book off the pile, another one emerges from underneath to replenish the pile. Putting a book back on the pile does not cause any books to disappear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two identical rooms in separate parts of the house that are "sound linked". A cunning arrangement of microphones and directed speakers means that not only do you hear everything happening in the other room, you also hear it as if it were coming from the corresponding place in this room.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm using screens and speakers a lot, but that's because they're so versatile. I'm sure I could do without.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls and floors are a giant jigsaw puzzle. The pieces are lightly magnetic so they stick to the wall easily. The puzzle is of the view you would see from the outside of the house looking in that direction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room where all the furniture is metal and is very gently electrified so you get a light tingle when you touch it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room filled with tiny ballerina dolls. As long as the lights are off, they will dance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason I'm able to do this is that this sort of idea generation is something I just practiced a lot as a child. It's easy to the point of being slightly surprising that other people can't do this so easily.
"How do you come up with all of these things?" "IDK I just think about the subject matter and reach for the place where ideas come from".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of example is particularly easy because "normal" is so tightly constrained. Everyone does most things in broadly the same way - there's variation, but even the variation is within pretty tightly defined bounds. As a result it's easy to generate interesting ideas by moving at right angles. It's easy to make weird things - you just do something that makes people go "Sure, you could do that, but why would you?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of where I learned a taste for this sort of thing and developed this skill is, I think, in &lt;a href="http://basement.warehouse23.com/"&gt;the Warehouse 23 basement&lt;/a&gt;. Someone on Twitter described the Warehouse 23 basement as a kind of proto &lt;a href="http://www.scpwiki.com/"&gt;SCP&lt;/a&gt; and that's not wrong but I think misses something important about it: The things in the Warehouse 23 basement are really quite low effort, and that's part of their virtue. It's seconds or minutes of work, not hours, and so you can iterate on the skill of generating them quite easily.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of idea generation is what Edward de Bono calls "lateral thinking". As with all Edward de Bono books, his book of the same is quite annoying, but it is genuinely useful. I'm particularly a big fan of his suggestion of making lists of a fixed size. Committing to generating, say, 100 ideas, forces you to come up with things that you wouldn't otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lateral thinking is foundational to a lot of creative processes, because often the way to come up with a good idea is to generate many bad ones and see what resonates, then improve on some of the best or most interesting parts of it, and practicing the ability to do it in a generalised sense is useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often when I think about developing useful general skills I think in terms of very sensible reasonable exercises that develop the skill. The warehouse 23 basement is a nice reminder that you can also just develop skills by having fun.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is an elevator room. It doesn't contain an elevator, it's just got lots of pictures of interesting elevators. A low voice is playing in the background, telling you endless interesting facts about elevators.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a room in which every time you say something a small child's voice plays, asking you "But &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;?"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a room in which anything is possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-11-11:03.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-12-17:36.html</id>
    <title>A library of recurring ideas</title>
    <updated>2021-07-12T18:10:35+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;A library of recurring ideas&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-12&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is a quick piece that I am writing because I realised I'm not going to finish the long piece I was writing today)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A thing I notice that I do more than many other people is that I just have a lot of ideas in my head that I pattern match to new situations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Like e.g.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Market_for_Lemons"&gt;Market for lemons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satisficing"&gt;Satisficing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Positive_deviance"&gt;Positive deviance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pluralistic_ignorance"&gt;Pluralistic ignorance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2010/07/26/a-big-little-idea-called-legibility/"&gt;Legibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodhart%27s_law"&gt;Goodhart's law&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuart_Kauffman"&gt;The adjacent possible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These seem to come up time and time again. I'm only mentioning these ones because they're all things that have come up recently,
I'm sure there are dozens if not hundreds of others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are also plenty I've come up with too. e.g. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-04-11:18.html"&gt;Skirting the edge of disaster&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/a-fractal-of-lies"&gt;Fractal of Lies&lt;/a&gt; have both come up recently.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't really have any good evidence that I do this more than other people, but it sure feels like it. I think I even do it more than other people who have some of the same ideas - a lot more people know about the market for lemons than go "Oh, a market for lemons" whenever they encounter the pattern in the wild. I talk about "Things that you can't unsee" but really I might just mean "Things I can't unsee".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of my evidence that I do this to an unusual degree is that I am unusually good at explaining things (at least, I think so, and other people seem to agree), and I think having this sort of library of recurring ideas is part of that: When presented with something to explain, I probably have a ready tool to hand to reach for to take it apart and reveal interesting things about it (&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/fragments-intellectual-diy"&gt;Intellectual DIY&lt;/a&gt; of course being another of my recurring ideas).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another recurring idea that doesn't have a catchy name or something I can refer to, but which I think about a lot, is that anything someone can do is a skill that almost everyone can learn to do better (this doesn't deny talent, although I'm a low-key talent sceptic in a number of ways, I just have a lot of faith in people's ability to learn skills given the right environment).
So if this &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; something I do to an unusual degree, how can people learn to do it better?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2017/02/thinking-through-the-implications/"&gt;Thinking through the implications&lt;/a&gt; I suggested a couple of things that might work:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When learning by doing, write down interesting things you learned so you remember them later explicitly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you learn new things, try to come up with at least one application of them outside the context you’re learning them in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you encounter a new problem, see if anything you learned recently applies to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you re-encounter a problem that you previously believed was hard or impossible, spend at least 5 minutes thinking about why it is hard or impossible and if anything you’ve learned since then changes that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is all good advice, but discounts the explanatory aspect of it. Perhaps the real thing to do is to just use them a lot - building up a conceptual framework in the way I discuss in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-05-10:30.html"&gt;Why do we need new terminology?&lt;/a&gt; by writing things that they enable you to write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, maybe writing is just the best way into this. Perhaps the reason I'm unusually good at this skill really is just writing? Or at least, writing in the way I write. In which case, perhaps the key to developing this skill is contained in:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/10/how-to-explain-anything-to-anyone/"&gt;How to explain anything to anyone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-02-09:29.html"&gt;People are bad at defining things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-03-13:55.html"&gt;No shortage of things to write about&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-06-08-10:11.html"&gt;A guide to starting a daily writing practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By writing about things as we encounter them, and connecting them to our library of ideas, we train ourselves to recognise these patterns as they occur.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-12-17:36.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-13-11:49.html</id>
    <title>Source: The noosphere, impersonal communication</title>
    <updated>2021-07-13T12:54:01+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Source: The noosphere, impersonal communication&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-13&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently writing a newsletter issue in which I'm explaining a lot of stuff.
Very little of it is original to me, although a lot of it is my own idiosyncratic conception of it, but instead something that I have synthesized from many sources.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What sources?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly, beats me.
Could be anything.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Kirsten3531/status/1412896229378379777"&gt;a recent conversation with Kirsten&lt;/a&gt; in which she'd made a popular tweet and was trying to figure out where she got the idea from, and thought it might be me. Could have been, we're not sure. I've certainly not said exactly the same thing as she did, but I've said a number of things vaguely in that space.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't much care, honestly. The idea isn't mine. If it did come from me, I would have put it together out of ideas I'd picked up from other people. I might have combined some things, I might have tweaked it a bit, but ultimately I'm just a conduit for the flow of ideas. Words come in, at some point later words come out, and there's some relationship between the two but I can't really say that I got the latter from specifics of the former.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example in the piece I'm writing at the moment (probably out some time next week) I'm talking about a bunch of ideas about how learning works. Are they original to me? No, absolutely not, I've read probably a dozen different books that have informed them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But the way they informed them is mostly not traceable to a particular book. I read some books, they informed my practice, and I then wrote something based on that practice and my conception of it. The books left a significant trace, and some of them have been a significant influence on me, but I couldn't necessarily tell you what that influence was any more than I can tell you exactly when and how I learned English, I just did.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What to do in these cases?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well I can mention some of the books I read, but even at a dozen there's no real chance of me remembering all of them (I recently bought a copy of "How children fail" only to discover I'd read it more than a decade ago. I still plan to reread it, and revisit it in a new light, but it's definitely ended up influencing me in ways I have no chance of recreating).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I'll often be saying things that are at odds with those books, or frame things in a different way, or which you'd have to go through the entire multi year long process of digesting the contents of the books before you can squint at them the right way to see that they're deeply instrumental to what I'm saying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And what to do about the books that are even less connected to the topics I'm writing about? My thoughts on education have definitely been influenced by reading anarchist and ethnographic writings from James C. Scott, but it would probably take an entire extra essay to unpick those links.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these problems are soluble. I could keep a detailed log of books. I could go through any books I've read that seem relevant an pick out the connections. I could carefully trace out the lineage of every thought I had in the essay and where its influences come from. None of this is unachievable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It does, however, have one crucial problem: It's hard and boring and I don't wanna.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also not that useful. The reader doesn't care, and the authors I'm citing probably don't care either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may sound like excuse making, and perhaps it is, but I think it's an important consideration. If you raise the bar to writing, many pieces that were previously worth writing no longer are, and this loses out on significant value. Having to carefully attribute everything or else you're bad and you should feel bad will inhibit me, and others, from writing many things that would improve the world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Norms of scrupulously crediting all your sources mostly come out of academia, where they're largely important because credit for ideas is a key part of the academic status game, and publications are supposed to be very clear about what their novel contribution is as a result.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Outside of academia you can just... not do that. It's mostly fine. There's no need to tie credit-assignment to citation like our lives depend on it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead I propose the more modest set of citation norms:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you already clearly know where something comes from, obviously you should cite it and give credit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not explicitly claim ideas as your own unless it's really overwhelmingly clear when in possession of the full facts that they are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If someone attributes an idea to you that is not yours and you notice, politely correct them (for example I'm often credited for the term "life-complete problems" due to my article of the same name, but credit is due to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mechanical_monk"&gt;Mechanical Monk&lt;/a&gt;, as I explicitly highlight in the piece).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recommend sources that you have found valuable, both casually and in your writing, regardless of whether they're directly the source of the idea you are writing about. For example I thought &lt;a href="https://summerbrennan.substack.com/p/discourse-person"&gt;Discourse Person&lt;/a&gt; was an excellent piece about related issues recently - I don't know if it informed this piece much, but it's worth a read either way!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Everything is a remix, we're all riffing off each other, and worrying too much about the credit assignment game within that ruins the flow.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-13-11:49.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-14-11:44.html</id>
    <title>A lack of shared projects</title>
    <updated>2021-07-14T19:07:29+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;A lack of shared projects&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been visiting my parents out in the country recently,
and as a result I was &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1414139777654431744"&gt;talking on Twitter the other day&lt;/a&gt; about an idea I have from a book called "The Art of Frugal Hedonism" (though the idea is hardly revolutionary and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-13-11:49.html"&gt;definitely isn't something I feel like I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to cite&lt;/a&gt;) that a great and commonly underrated way to spend your time is to have a mundane task to do with your hands while sitting around a table with your friends and loved ones chatting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Their example was podding peas, in our case the event that prompted me thinking about it was picking and processing red currants with my family. Honestly, I think they're spot on. Having the shared task to focus on made the conversation flow very smoothly, and there was a satisfaction to doing a task that would have been slightly tedious without the company. They pair very well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This got me thinking how few things in modern life look like this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that's interesting about it is the physicality of it, and indeed we don't do a lot of work with our hands.
Much ink has been spilled talking about this sort of thing. I too have read Shop Class as Soulcraft (and I suppose recommend it, maybe, sortof), and various takes in this space. I won't be talking about that today.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead the thing that struck me as anomalous is that we were doing something useful together,
and that's surprisingly rare. We do it at work, we do it when living together as a family. Those honestly seem like the main widespread examples to me. I can think of a few others, but they all feel in some way unusual to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not saying nobody does practical projects with their friends, obviously people do, but it seems anomalous to me? Like it's a relatively rare thing, and it so easily gets coopted by work. e.g. open source projects are kinda this, but they sure mostly feel like free work rather than a practical project with friends done for our own sakes.
Sometimes you ask friends for favours and they help you achieve something, but even that feels rare and socially discouraged.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doing things with friends is certainly a thing, but when we do things with friends it tends to be leisure activities.
We mostly do things because we want to spend time together, not because we're trying to achieve something.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wonder if this is related to the longing some people have for community? In &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/communities-construct-a-sense-of"&gt;Communities construct a sense of purpose&lt;/a&gt; I suggested that a lot of the function of communities is structure our emotional evaluations of what matters, and thereby construct a sense of purpose. This certainly seems related to that - trying to achieve things in tandem with people you care about feels like an almost central example of purpose.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't really have a firm conclusion here. I just find I'm staring at this in vague incomprehension going "No, this must be a thing, right? What am I missing?", and feel very strongly like something weird is going on here.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-14-11:44.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-15-10:56.html</id>
    <title>Spiraling outwards</title>
    <updated>2021-07-15T11:12:58+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Spiraling outwards&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to describe a problem that I have. I have not yet found a good solution for it, and this is why you are getting a very nominal post today in which I describe that problem and think out loud about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is this: I start with something small, and then I think "Oh this is really good, I should do it justice". &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doing it justice makes it... not small. Often it increases the work of doing it by a factor of ten or more. Suddenly it becomes a thing that I need to spent much longer on than I had time allocated for it, and moves it up a project size category.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In concrete terms what happens is that I now have two pieces that started out life as notebook posts and are going to be newsletter issues that I need to finish. They should be pretty easy to finish but I probably won't have time to do so prior to the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often they languish unfinished. This was very much my problem with writing papers. It felt like in order to write an academic paper I had to publish something that was substantially worse than the state of the art that existed in my head, because in order to get to the point where it was publishable I either had to stop thinking about the problem (impossible if I were to be interested enough to finish writing it) or publish something that I felt was worse than I could have done.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't really a problem for many things which feel like I can just snip off a thread. The notebook is good for that, but often I end up wanting to write things which have a certain minimum size without which they would end up incomplete.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think part of the problem here is really not that things become large, but that I need a better way to work on large projects. The paper problem felt like a mismatch between the sort of incrementalism I wanted to do and the sort of incrementalism that academia wanted me to do. The newsletter issue problem is more manageable, and I think I just need to get better at managing my draft backlog and allocating more time to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I can treat drafts as an inbox problem and apply the &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/triage-your-inboxes"&gt;How to triage your inboxes&lt;/a&gt; method to it?&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-15-10:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-16-10:12.html</id>
    <title>Clearing hurdles in learning</title>
    <updated>2021-07-16T10:51:31+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Clearing hurdles in learning&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-16&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The following is not true, but it's often close enough to true that it's worth using as a working model.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When learning a skill, the level of effort required to get to a given point typically looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/effortskillgraph.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This corresponds to the following difficulties of improvement at any given point:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/difficultyskillgraph.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(These numbers are made up imaginary units, obviously)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is, the difficulty of getting better is usually pretty easy, but occasionally there are spikes where the difficulty rapidly increases. The gentle bits are the places where the way to improve is to just do the thing, the spikes are the bits where &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-do-everything"&gt;there's some insight you need to figure out to progress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A very simplistic model of human behaviour is that people do things that are worth the effort of doing. As a result, what often happens when people are learning a skill is that they progress as long as it's easy, and then they hit a part where it's difficult it's no longer worth it to them to keep progressing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result what you end up with is people who stall out particular points in their skill progression, thinking they have reached the limit of their talent, when in fact all they needed was a sustained period of effort at which point they would have started getting better again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think people generally solve these problems in one of three ways:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being smart tends to lower the effort in one of these spikes. I don't know how much of this is "intrinsic" smartness and how much is having already learned the right skills of learning, but if smartness is a thing at all it certainly reduces the effort of generating insights when you're blocked on skill development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being very into the subject makes more effort seem worth it, so someone with exactly the same level of "talent" but more interest will often get better because they reach a spike in difficulty and it's still worth it to them to overcome it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a good teacher &lt;em&gt;hugely&lt;/em&gt; reduces the difficulty level of these spikes, because they already know the insights you're struggling to come up with and can help you discover them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believing in this model will often motivate you to put in more effort than seems reasonable until you've overcome the hump, banking on the promise of future reward (I think, to the degree that they do, this is a lot of why "growth mindset" interventions work).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is what I tend to mean when I say that almost nobody is bottlenecked on talent. They're probably just at a point in their skill development where it wasn't worth it for them to get better on their own, and nobody provided them with the right external support they needed to overcome the current spike in difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is then compounded by the fact that the messaging they get about skill tends to convince them that this is evidence that they lack talent and will never be good at the thing, when in fact they're probably not substantially less talented than many people who end up way better than them due to a mix of luck, privilege, and motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-16-10:12.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-17-14:20.html</id>
    <title>Would you like some advice?</title>
    <updated>2021-07-17T14:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Would you like some advice?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you wouldn't, too bad. You're here reading my writing, advice is one of the main things my writing is for. If you don't want my advice, don't read my writing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Conversation, however, is different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is a good rule of thumb: When a wide variety of people get annoyed at you for the same behaviour, it's more likely that you are behaving in an annoying way than that there is some bizarre conspiracy in which everyone has decided to behave irrationally for no good reason.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems obvious to me, and yet people persist in offering advice in contexts in which it's obviously unwanted and then getting surprised when people get annoyed at them for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/you-should-complain-about-it"&gt;Complaining about things is good&lt;/a&gt;, and has many virtues above and beyond problem solving. People complain to process their feelings. People complain as a bonding activity. People complain because they're angry and want something to direct it. Sometimes people complain because they're mentioning something annoying in passing as part of a broader point. Complaining is normal, and it is not intrinsically a request for advice on how to solve the thing you are complaining about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Notably: Often people complain about things where they have thought a great deal about the solution space already.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And then people offer advice anyway, and are surprised when this is &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/no-backseating"&gt;just as unwelcome as unrequested advice usually is&lt;/a&gt;, and get all huffy about how they were just trying to help.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The prompting incident that made me think of this is that I was in a situation where someone was describing a problem they had. It was a category of problem I was pretty familiar with and was pretty sure I knew how to solve, but they hadn't asked for my help.
This happens to me a lot, as you might imagine, because I listen to a lot of people and also problem solve professionally.
Must be frustrating, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No it's not, the solution to this problem is very simple, to the point of being blindingly obvious.
I said "I might have some useful advice on this if you'd like it?",
to which he politely thanked me and said he would love some advice, and we had a good conversation about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is what usually happens. Sometimes people say "No thank you", and I respect that, and we have a good conversation about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You know what never happens when I ask something like this though? Nobody ever gets mad at me. Because it's an &lt;em&gt;obviously reasonable thing to ask&lt;/em&gt;, and everyone is pleasantly surprised that I asked rather than leaping in with my opinion, and thanks me not only for my advice but also for checking if it was welcome.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this is my advice: If you want to give someone advice in response to something they said which was not clearly a request for said advice, ask them if it would be welcome, and if they say no then respect that. Also if they're obviously going to say no, don't bother asking and just stay quiet about it rather than wasting their time and yours.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-17-14:20.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
