<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-05-16T12:06:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-08-10:06.html</id>
    <title>Separating Impulse from Action</title>
    <updated>2020-05-08T13:04:37+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Separating Impulse from Action&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's a trick I figured out yesterday. It solves quite a specific problem that I have, but you might have similar problems, and even if not I think it demonstrates some useful general principles that could be applied in other circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is this: I buy too many books.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not a &lt;em&gt;disaster&lt;/em&gt; because I also read a lot of books, but I buy books at a higher rate than I read them, and I often buy books that I later decide that actually I'm not realistically going to read.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is basically that when I encounter an interesting book whose ideas I would like inside my brain, I often impulsively buy it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of this is a problem of impulse control, for sure, and I could definitely fix it by being better at impulse control, but currently I'm trying to be &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; good at impulse control, so that seems counterproductive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An additional complication is that the correct amount of books for me to be buying is not zero. I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; just blanket ban myself from buying books. I would experience it as unpleasant, but it's manageable, but that would not result in my buying the right number of books.
I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; read a lot of books (typically between one and three a week, not counting fiction which are a separate category because I read them as ebooks), and I like having new books around, and I can definitely afford to spend a certain amount of money on books.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The additional complicating factor is that my bookshelves serve as a kind of... thoughts I want to have later? They're a TODO list for reading, and my experience is that I will lose track of digital TODO lists for reading - they will get too large, and I will forget about them and leave them to rot (I am even worse at digital &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-30-15:20.html"&gt;care work&lt;/a&gt; than physical).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, I:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a constant impulse to buy books, and suppressing it will be unpleasant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do actually want to buy a non-zero amount of books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need a way to keep track of the books I may want to buy later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, there's an easy solution, and it's &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-07-07:57.html"&gt;kinda stupid&lt;/a&gt; that it's taken me this long to realise it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The solution that satisfies all of these is to have:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a default Amazon list of books I wanted to buy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a scheduled task every Sunday to buy a book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now when I want to impulse buy a book I instead just click the add to list button instead of the buy now button. Then, every Sunday, I go through the list and decide which of these books is the one I want to buy the most right now. In the course of doing so, I remove any books from the list that I'm definitely sure I won't want to buy later.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This solution is actually very good, because it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;puts the rate at which I buy things under my conscious control independently of the impulse to buy things (a thing I learned the value of from years with &lt;a href="http://beeminder.com/"&gt;Beeminder&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gives a direct and (almost) equally satisfying replacement for the impulse activity by pressing a different and equally accessible button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fights the digital rot that lists normally have for me by coupling it to a regularly scheduled activity that I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to do because I get rewarded with a book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In addition I think it will significantly increase the quality of the books I do buy, because each book I buy will be a measured choice between alternatives where invest some effort in ensuring that my book this week will be a good one. I don't intend to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;avoid all error&lt;/a&gt; and I of course &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-17-10:16.html"&gt;can't ensure I always pick the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; one&lt;/a&gt;, but I'm pretty sure that investing about twenty minutes of thought into the question will result in me improving on impulse decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-08-10:06.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-09-11:26.html</id>
    <title>Initial Notes Towards a Manifesto</title>
    <updated>2020-05-09T13:57:51+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Initial Notes Towards a Manifesto&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mechanical Monk &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/i/status/1258738843630678016"&gt;invited his mutuals to write a manifesto&lt;/a&gt;. This is my response to that, though given that this is a notebook it's a more modest attempt to gesture in the direction of what a manifesto would look like when I'm a bit more ready for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So what do I want? How do I want to change the world?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well I'd like to be able to claim some high minded ideal like universal love and cosmic oneness but that's not what I'm about. What I'm about is this: Dear humanity, we are &lt;em&gt;fucking this up&lt;/em&gt;, and it's annoying me and I'm embarrassed to be a part of it. I really shouldn't be the one to have to tell people how to sort their shit out because I'm terrible at this but apparently nobody else is going to do it right, so &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by this?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I mean that we are universally lacking in the basic systems, skills, and ethics, of being functioning, healthy, happy, human beings, and we need to fix that, and instead we are making it worse. We do not have a society that supports the development of those, and in many ways &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html"&gt;we actively punish their acquisition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An incomplete list of things we are bad at include thinking, feeling, moving, communicating, decision making, organisation, and helping each other out more broadly. Some of us are good enough at some of these things, but essentially nobody is at what I would like to consider the bare minimum standard for all of them (I sure as hell am not!).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Currently I think we have roughly the following models for acquiring these skills:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dumb luck and/or privilege in having the right role models (unreliable).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School (monstrously bad at this, not really designed to do it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therapy and coaching (limited scope, expensive)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weird borderline cults (tend to overfocus on an aspect of the problem and convince you it solves everything. Also, are cults)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-help books (similar problems to cults, also mostly very bad)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these are grossly inadequate to the task.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I'm trying to push back on it. I cannot, at present, fix society and reshape it into a more pleasing image (though if you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; me to do that and can hand me the keys I uh have one or two ideas), but I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; provide people with tools that may help them under the current circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm acquiring the parts of these skills that I can figure out for myself, or with help, and I'm trying to be a model of how I think this should work. I'm helping other people around me take steps towards the same same, by writing about it, and by building relationships that support each other's growth.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And this &lt;em&gt;isn't going to work&lt;/em&gt;. You cannot rely on me to teach you all the skills you need for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The notebook is pretty good, and I hope to do better writing about this in future, but the really high value work is in personal relationships, and there's only one of me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My work is intrinsically built around my particular strengths and weaknesses - I'm a weird, queer, hyperverbal, nerd and so the problems I'm solving and the tools I'm using are designed with that in mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am, as alluded to, &lt;em&gt;not very good at this&lt;/em&gt;, and I'm going to miss things, get things wrong, or communicate them in unhelpful ways, and we need many different voices doing the same sorts of things if we are to have any chance of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-28-06:45.html"&gt;climbing out of the crab bucket&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(2) doesn't mean that you can't benefit from my writing if you're not like me, but it does mean that my tools are built in a very particular way for a very particular set of problems. They might or might not work for you (possibly with modification), but even if they work for you they might not solve all your problems because they're designed to solve &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; problems (and, to a lesser extent, the problems of people I know well enough to help). You need to build your own tools too! And then, once you have, I want you to share them with other people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And I want you to share them with other people while &lt;em&gt;understanding that their tools might not work for others&lt;/em&gt;.
When I wrote &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-08-10:06.html"&gt;yesterday's post&lt;/a&gt; I very clearly spelled out why this was a good solution for me, and that these might not be the same for you. All tools will be like this, but right now people tend to get very evangelical about how their tool is the one size fits all to all problems, and this is extremely wrong, both factually and morally.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm losing steam on writing more of this right now, so I'm going to just end with a list of things I want people to do:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut people some slack. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-06-15:20.html"&gt;Create&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety&lt;/a&gt; for those around you. Sign non-aggression pacts in the goddamn &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2019-06-04-09:58.html"&gt;legibility war&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Treat the problems in your life as interesting and worth solving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join and learn from &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-07:38.html"&gt;nerd&lt;/a&gt; communities who can help you solve them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-26-07:28.html"&gt;growth relationships&lt;/a&gt;, where everyone involved helps everyone else be better versions of themselves. I'm particularly a fan of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-25-16:02.html"&gt;the support group model&lt;/a&gt;, but this is one of those tools that might not work for everyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/10/how-to-explain-anything-to-anyone/"&gt;Explain&lt;/a&gt; these things to others. Obviously I'm a fan of the notebook blog format, but again that might not be what works for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I understand that what I am asking of you is difficult, and I understand that for some of you it may not yet be possible, but I'm trying my best to make it possible, and easy, for as many people as I can, and I hope that some of you will do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-09-11:26.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-10-08:54.html</id>
    <title>How to be a better person</title>
    <updated>2020-05-10T12:24:24+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How to be a better person&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In response to my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-09-11:26.html"&gt;Initial notes towards a manifesto&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/joxn"&gt;@joXn&lt;/a&gt; quite reasonably asked how I would avoid falling afoul of the problem that, contra The Good Place, learning ethics doesn't actually make one more ethical. Eric Schwitzgebel has a lot of great research on this (see &lt;a href="https://faculty.ucr.edu/~eschwitz/"&gt;his publications&lt;/a&gt; and in particular the section "The Relationship Between Moral Reflection and Moral Behavior").&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of these, I think &lt;a href="https://faculty.ucr.edu/~eschwitz/SchwitzAbs/MoralMediocrity.htm"&gt;Aiming for Moral Mediocrity&lt;/a&gt; is perhaps the most important:
Schwitzgebel argues that most people probably aim to be about as moral as their peers, and that this is mediocre (neither great, nor terrible) to do, but that most people could manage to be better than they are with no great hardship.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Schwitzgebel's claim is basically right, and the paper is a very good one, with two major caveats:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He is underestimating the hardship, because (I think) he is missing one of the reasons why this happens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He has fallen afoul of precisely the reason why learning ethics does not make you a better person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there are approximately four reasons why people fail to behave ethically:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They do not care to do the right thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are discouraged from doing the right thing by external factors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They do not know what the right thing is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They do not know how to do the right thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Behaving ethically is a skillful practice, and most people are either not very good at the skill, not very motivated to practice it, or do not have an environment that enables them to practice it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ethicists primarily study what the right thing to do is, but I think for most people this is not the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-21-10:04.html"&gt;constraint&lt;/a&gt; on the skillful practice of ethics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I will, for the purpose of this post, assume that people &lt;em&gt;care&lt;/em&gt; to do the right thing. I think fixing that is a whole different question. This leaves the other three. Given that we know from Schwitzgebel's work that knowing the right thing to do is also not enough, lets assume for the moment that you, in most practical circumstances if not necessarily in general, know what the right thing to do is. Why don't you do it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, lets take a look at Schwitzgebel's theme of Moral Mediocrity: Why do people aim to be morally mediocre?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I propose that there's a very straightforward reason: Moral Mediocrity is the option that won't get you punished.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you behave badly, people will be judgemental towards you. But they will also react badly to you if you are especially moral. It's not just that you're not a saint it's that, in actual practice, we don't &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; saints, because they make us feel bad about ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the examples in the paper is vegetarianism. Suppose you were reasonably convinced that, ethically speaking, you should be a vegetarian or vegan. Now, all your interactions with people around you around food come with extra friction. Even if you never say anything judgy about it, it's impossible for people to not know you're vegetarian (if they're sharing meals with you) and many of them will respond defensively or aggressively about it. You'll experience a constant, albeit low grade, pressure of the people around you trying to drag you back down to their moral level.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You'll see this with other things too: Someone who is unusually ethical will constantly have people telling them to relax, take things less seriously, etc. Being unusually ethical is weird, and triggers the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html"&gt;social obligation to be bad at things&lt;/a&gt; in a big way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not, I hasten to add, a moral justification for being morally mediocre. It doesn't change what you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; do. If anything, the tendency of people to norm their behaviour to those around them creates a stronger moral obligation to be good, because it influences others to be good. It is a &lt;em&gt;practical barrier to ethical behaviour&lt;/em&gt;, and any theory of ethics that does not teach you to overcome such practical barriers will not result in more ethical behaviour any more than a detailed understanding of thermodynamics will allow you to build an internal combustion engine. A theory of ethics is all very well, but you need a &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; of ethics, which is what Schwitzgebel's paper (along with most theory of ethics) misses: Telling people to behave a particular way tends not to work unless you tell them &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to behave that way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's another practical barrier: If you realise that you are behaving badly, and decide to be better, you have to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-07-07:57.html"&gt;reconcile yourself to the fact that you could always have been better&lt;/a&gt;, which is very painful, so you would much rather rationalise your behaviour as just fine the way it is to avoid that pain.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And for another, consider the following scenario: Suppose you decide to be vegetarian, and you're really good about it for about a month, virtuously resisting the temptation to eat meat, and absolutely hating how bland all your food has become because you don't know how to cook interesting vegetarian food and the cafeteria where you mostly eat has awful vegetarian food. After about a month, you go out for a meal with some friends, and you look at the incredibly disappointing vegetarian menu and your eyes are drawn to the cheesburger selection... and after that you're no longer vegetarian.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This actually demonstrates &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; problems: Firstly, you don't know how to be vegetarian, and are trying to overcome that limitation with pure willpower rather than treating it as a practical problem you need to solve, and the second is that you don't understand behaviour change so you tried to go all in on the new behaviour and then gave up as soon as you failed once.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are the three main practical barriers to overcome: Social norms, emotional difficulties, and missing skills, and all of these are emimently solvable problems that you can learn to overcome, and that you will find personally beneficial to learn to overcome regardless of whether you use them to become more ethical.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More, I think once you have acquired these skills, you will naturally become more ethical (or at least, more in line with your own values): If you can change when you feel like you should, and you feel like you should behave a particular way, then you'll just do that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this is my answer to how I'm intending to avoid this problem: I don't plan to try to persuade anyone of the rightness of a particular position, I'm just doing my best to convey some fragments of useful prosocial skills, and trusting that as you get better at those skills you'll become a better person automatically.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mostly, at least. You'll probably still be bad occasionally. That's OK. It's more fun to be a bit evil from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-10-08:54.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-11-09:32.html</id>
    <title>Building and Rebuilding Foundational Skills</title>
    <updated>2020-05-11T12:01:22+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Building and Rebuilding Foundational Skills&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have a problem: I'm kinda OK at statistics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why is this a problem? Being kinda OK seems... kinda OK, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, it would be, but the problem isn't that I have an intermediate level of statistical skill. The problem is that I have a broad range of statistical skill, all of which I'm kinda OK at. I'm kinda OK at elementary statistics, and I'm kinda OK at advanced statistics too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a real problem for learning more, because it is &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt; to relearn basics because they feel too basic for my skill level.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have another problem: Climbing is a fun sport that makes a good social activity and works on a number of strength skills that I would like to work on. Also I give myself a back injury 100% of the time I do it, because my ability to climb is much greater than my skill at climbing, because I'm hypermobile and have a decent strength to body weight ratio, and the result is that despite some things feeling easy, I do them badly and this results in me inadvertently harming myself while doing them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these share a common theme: It is possible for something to be easy while still being bad at it, and this is especially true with foundational skills, where you've built capabilities on top of them, and going back and relearning the basics is hard and boring.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to get good at statistics, I'd need to grind a bunch of exercises that I frankly feel are beneath me.
I'm probably going to try (despite my &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-03-09:09.html"&gt;complicated feelings about mathematics&lt;/a&gt;) because being good at statistics is important for me professionally and spiritually, and I'll never get good at it until I sort out the basics, and also being bad at those basics risks me tripping up in stupid ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to get good at climbing, I'd need to very carefully (and probably with supervision) try far easier routes than I can manage, and stop far sooner than it seems like I can. I'd have to deliberately hold myself back until I was much better at the basics than I am, despite my ability to do more. I don't value climbing enough at present to do this, so I probably will just avoid climbing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is is why I'm currently restarting the first week of Couch to 5K despite having completed it relatively easily.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's another problem: I obviously breathe badly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not fully sold on the Buteyko method, which encourages you to breathe less and entirely through your nose, but I obviously mouth breathe at night based on my sleep quality and dry mouth in the morning, and my peak flow numbers aren't great. I'd like to work on this to the point where I breathe through my nose unconsciously and easily, even while sleeping. It probably won't change my life in the way that the Buteyko method promises (though it sure would be nice if it did!), but at the very least it might improve my sleep quality.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Breathing is definitely a foundational skill, and it's one I'm bad at, so I'd like to work on it, and working on breathing is &lt;em&gt;deathly&lt;/em&gt; boring.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is where I link in three previous tools:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can nose breathe just fine while at rest. I can complete couch to 5k week one (consistent of eight repetitions of a 60 second run followed by a 90 second walk) just fine. What I absolutely cannot do is complete Couch to 5K week one while nasal breathing. I can just about manage the first run and then I am &lt;em&gt;wrecked&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is the way to rebuild foundations, and one of the core reasons why &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-21-10:04.html"&gt;learning a different skill&lt;/a&gt; is often essential for progressing at your current goal: By transferring to a different context where the foundational skill is no longer easy, it becomes a thing that you can now actively work at. Working on a foundation in its existing context is often too easy to be possible, so &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:12.html"&gt;the way to work on it is to make it harder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was in fact, already considering restarting week one of Couch to 5K, for two other reasons, both of which are also about foundational skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as breathing, I'm also bad at walking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yes, I'm aware that these are both ridiculous things to be bad at. I think a lot of you reading this are probably bad at them too though. As I said, we have &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-09-11:26.html"&gt;a widespread lack of the basic skills of being a human being&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specifically, I have quite flat feet and weak arches, and a bunch of (probably) related joint pain. I've tried wearing arch support shoes and my considered opinion is that it was an expensive waste of time. (Well, it was a good &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;experiment&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A slightly less fringe (but still fringe) opinion is that the solution to this is actually to have &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; arch support, and to wear barefoot shoes that are designed to protect your feet without supporting them,
because this causes you to actually develop your muscles rather than weaken them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems worth a shot, and I was noticing that my ankles were already starting to hurt a bit as a result of week one. I don't want to end up in the situation like with climbing where my ability to do a run exceeds my ability to do a run without injuring myself, so this too seems like a thing I could reasonably make harder in order to work on the foundational skills of.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even without these foundations of breathing and walking, I was still thinking it might be worth repeating Couch to 5K, because I disagree with some of its philosophical premises.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Couch to 5K is designed to ramp up the difficulty level by making you run more, and more consistently. I personally think it ramps up the difficulty too quickly. I basically agree with Sarah Perry's point in &lt;a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2017/08/03/body-pleasure/"&gt;Body Pleasure&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] people enjoy exercise up to a certain level of intensity, which varies for each person. Most people who do low-intensity exercise feel better during the mild exertion. At the point when the body can no longer maintain levels of oxygen and (separately) lactate in the muscles, the exercise becomes so intense that basic affect (feeling good or feeling bad, the lowest-level evaluation of anything) plummets. Everybody feels terrible when they exercise too hard. Once people rest for a few minutes, they start feeling good again. However, this may not be enough such that people evaluate the entire experience as pleasurable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, most on-ramps to exercise are at an intensity too high for previously-sedentary people to find them pleasurable. If people go to a fitness class, or focus on running a particular distance at a particular speed, they’ll likely miss the pleasure zone entirely. Refocusing on exercising only for one’s own individual pleasure, as slowly as one prefers, and only at intensities that are pleasurable, is more likely to motivate repeat and habitual exercising. At that point, the enjoyment of exercise pleasure can build on itself, motivating longer and longer intervals of experiencing the pleasure. I summarize Ekkekakis et al.’s result as: “learn to exercise out of extreme selfish laziness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was a little skeptical about doing Couch to 5K because one of the things I'm trying to work on at the moment is to enjoy exercise, and honestly I don't enjoy running. I'd already been vaguely considering restarting week one so that I could get to the point where it was pleasurable rather than merely endurable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I liked &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/davidklaing/status/1258846038552489984"&gt;David Laing's point the other day&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advice on how to get better at a given thing should often be replaced with advice on how to take more pleasure in doing that thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pleasure doesn't lead directly to learning, but it leads to &lt;em&gt;volume&lt;/em&gt;, which leads to learning. Also pleasure is an end in itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know exactly how to create pleasure in a thing, but I suspect fluidity is a huge part of it. There is something intrinsically pleasurable about being good enough at something hard that you can do it automatically and reliably, and I think fluidity is extremely helpful for being able to play with a skill.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suspect this points to a general reason why we are so often bad at foundations: We treat the point at which we should progress as to when we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do the thing, when in fact we should be progressing when it's &lt;em&gt;pleasurable&lt;/em&gt; to do it (or at least fluid where pleasure is impossible). This ties in to the idea that you are not good at doing a thing until you are able to do it reliably rather than able to do it at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you progress as soon as you clear some minimum bar of being &lt;em&gt;able&lt;/em&gt; to do it, then what happens is that the skill will get progressively more and more frustrating as you move up it until you hit some "natural" limit where your frustration exceeds your willingness to progress, and you can no longer easily go back and work on the foundations, so you conclude that you're now as good as you're goign to get.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For reasons, I was reading about &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloom%27s_2_sigma_problem"&gt;Bloom's 2 sigma problem&lt;/a&gt; recently, which is often used as evidence for the superiority of private tutoring over general classes, but I found the description of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mastery_learning"&gt;mastery learning&lt;/a&gt;, which is the specific system being compared, especially interesting:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mastery learning maintains that students must achieve a level of mastery (e.g., 90% on a knowledge test) in prerequisite knowledge before moving forward to learn subsequent information. If a student does not achieve mastery on the test, they are given additional support in learning and reviewing the information and then tested again. This cycle continues until the learner accomplishes mastery, and they may then move on to the next stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In comparison, I think most of our school based learning techniques are like Couch to 5K: They assume that there is some straightforward time frame on which you can expect people to progress, and you should progress as long as you can just about manage the previous level, and failure to progress is a sign of significant failure.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How much of the 2 sigma system is about the benefits of individual instruction, and how much of it is just about giving people the time to build their foundations before progressing?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This all fits in well to the framework of the &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/05/how-to-do-hard-things/"&gt;Fully General System for Learning to Do Hard Things&lt;/a&gt;, but I think I have previously neglected something important: It's not at all obvious what &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt; mean in this context. I suspect the threshold for progression should be set much higher than I previously would have set it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Couch to 5K fits pretty well into the Fully General System, in that it repeatedly takes something that you can do (Week N) and makes it slightly harder (Week N + 1), eventually culminating in being able to do a half hour run. It seems pretty good, for a lot of people, in that it gets them to do something that would previously have seemed unattainable, but I'm no longer convinced that either it or the Fully General System are good enough for that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this notion of foundational skills, and the question of mastery progression, point to a common flaw in Couch to 5K and the Fully General System: They are overly narrowly focused on the goal, and don't care about what possible future progress they burn along the way to getting there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I'm still going to try to do hard things, and I'm still going to complete Couch to 5K, but in doing so my aims are not merely to do a half hour run but to do a half hour run while breathing entirely through my nose, wearing barefoot shoes, and enjoying it, and all the while paying attention to the process and using it to learn more about progression and skill development in general.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-11-09:32.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-12-08:19.html</id>
    <title>Why are things hard?</title>
    <updated>2020-05-12T12:21:57+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Why are things hard?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-12&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've recently started a &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/coming-soon"&gt;Substack Newsletter&lt;/a&gt; called "How to do hard things", based on &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/05/how-to-do-hard-things/"&gt;my unexpectedly popular post of the same name&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There will be a lot of overlap between the newsletter and this notebook. I'm not quite sure how I'm going to use it yet, but I'm expecting there will be a bit of a back and forth, with the newsletter being a place I use to collect and develop themes I've written about here, which will in turn spark more notebook posts here. If you're enjoying the notebook, I'd also recommend subscribing to the substack. For now at least, you don't need to sign up for a paid tier - the content is the same for all subscribers, but with the discussion / community features turned on for paid ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this has got me thinking about The Fully General System For Learning To Do Hard Things. I still think it's a good framework, but I think it's missing a lot of important features - some of which only require additions to it, some of which might require some modifications.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the principle problems with it is, I think, the fact that what it &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; is extremely under defined. What is a "hard thing"? And how does one learn to do it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The principle assumption in the post is that things are hard because you lack the skill to do them effortlessly. It's true, some things are like that. But that's a relatively tiny fraction of the ways in which things can be hard, and most things that are hard in one way are hard in multiple, not necessarily easily distinguishable, ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The Fully General System as previously described really only admits three possible reasons why things might be hard:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might not know how to do them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might know how to do them but not be able to execute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might not know exactly what it is you're trying to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there are quite a few other ways in which things can be hard.
Here is a partial list:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might lack some simple trick.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might be &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; about what it is you're trying to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might lack resources that you need to do them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might lack motivation to do them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might find the whole subject of doing them aversive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There might be some &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-11-14:47.html"&gt;trivial irritation&lt;/a&gt; preventing you from doing the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might lack a foundational skill that they need but that isn't obvious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might be doing something foundational very badly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might lack awareness of or access to the expertise you need to learn how to do the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might need someone to help you do them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might be rusty at the relevant skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone else might be trying to stop you doing them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The thing you are trying to do might have unacceptable consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There might be social norms making it hard to do the thing in the easy way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It might not be worth doing the thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The thing might be intrinsically hard in ways that require you to just do a lot of wor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The thing might be intrinsically uncertain, making reliable success impossible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The thing might be risky (and thus unsafe to experiment with while learning).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally there are a whole bunch of general reasons why doing &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; might be hard for you:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might not have enough time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might have a distracting environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might not be getting enough sleep.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might be depressed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might have ADHD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might have other mental health problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might have physical health problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might lack more general skills around learning and habit formation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might lack more general skills around debugging why things are hard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, most hard things are some mix of multiple of these things, and usually not a small number of them, and any truly general system for learning to do hard things must take this into account.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-12-08:19.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-13-09:56.html</id>
    <title>How to read a book</title>
    <updated>2020-05-13T10:54:07+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How to read a book&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-13&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have mixed feelings about Adler and Van Doren's classic &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2LqWf50"&gt;How to read a book&lt;/a&gt;. There's a lot I like about it, and my reading definitely improved after I read it, but I also disagree with a lot of it. I have not engaged with the book in a way that they think entitles me to disagree with it, but that's OK because I also disagree with their claims around when you are entitled to disagree with a book.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But that's not what this post is about. This post is about what one might think of the central failing of the book: Despite the title, it never actually tells you how to read a book.
It is not a book about how to read a book at all, it is a book about how to engage with the contents of a book.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not what reading is.
Reading is not an act conducted by a pure mind engaging with an idealised platonic flow of information.
Reading is an active engagement between a physical body and a physical object. The &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt; of reading is to engage with the content, but reading itself is a physical act.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the physical act matters, clearly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is obvious in the extreme cases. If you are in constant pain while reading you're not going to be able to concentrate on the reading, right? But I think it matters far more than we expect it to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People often are amused at how strong my opinions on book formats are, but this is because book formats are important.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Briefly my opinions on book formats are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audiobooks might be fine but I haven't been able to make them work for me (I should revisit this now that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-11-14:47.html"&gt;I have solved my problems with podcasts&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ebooks are a shit format for consuming hard material, but their convenience often outweighs their shittiness for lighter material.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most hardbacks are a bad format made by bad people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trade paperbacks and other large paperback formats are a blight on humanity and the people responsible for them should be put on trial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small, light, ideally paperback, books are the god tier format and are the only one that allows you to properly engage with difficult material.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You will tell me about textbooks etc that have too much content to be small and thus are better as large physical books or PDFs. I acknowledge those textbooks cannot be made smaller, but I contend that this is because they shouldn't have been written with that much content in the first place and should have been a series of shorter books. This is a separate argument.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason why ebooks are bad is twofold:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The physicality of engaging with a book is actually very helpful for organising knowledge (you've got an intuitive sense of where things were in the book, and also physical libraries are a much better exobrain that digital ones).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They add significant latency and inconvenience to many of the actions you take in the course of reading (paging, especially backwards, flicking through the book at random, etc).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason large physical books are bad is that it is almost impossible to maintain &lt;a href="https://learnmuscles.com/blog/2017/10/18/reading-writing-and-posture/"&gt;a proper reading posture while reading them&lt;/a&gt; without a book stand or something, which let's be honest literally nobody is using. They also can't be carried in your bag (and a book stand certainly can't), which means your opportunities to read them will be limited.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why am I telling you all of this?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm telling you all of this because if the physicality of reading matters, and you are struggling to read, then you may be able to improve your reading not by "improving your reading skills" in some sense, or by fixing whatever is stopping you from concentrating, but by simply changing actual practical physical details about your reading habits. It's possible that you're just fine at reading but are attempting to read in a way that doesn't work well for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some interventions in the act of reading that have all worked pretty well for me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading out loud. Reading out loud makes it &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; easier to engage with difficult material. It causes you to remember it better, and the act of reading out loud &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:12.html"&gt;makes it harder in a way that makes it possible to concentrate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explicitly structuring your reading into a 20/10 pattern (20 minutes reading, 10 minutes mandatory break) so as to manage fatigue and concentration better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix your reading posture so that you hold the book out in front of you rather than looking down at it. The looking down posture is not good for your neck and breathing in a way that I think disrupts the ability to concentrate and makes you feel more distracted while reading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading while standing up (with the book held in front of you!) and vaguely walking or pacing is particularly good. This combines particularly well with reading out loud.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading while &lt;a href="https://alexandertechnique.co.uk/learning-it/semi-supine"&gt;Semi-Supine&lt;/a&gt; with the book held out in front of you. This combines particularly well with the 20/10 structure, with your phone deliberately left out of reach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these seem kinda dumb and like they shouldn't matter, because we have become overly attached to the idea of books as pure sources of information that we engage with intellectually, rather than physical objects that we interact with physically as part of a process with an intellectual goal, and little things often have a much larger effect on such processes than we think they do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They're all also very easy, so if you really think they won't work, the fastest way to prove me wrong is to just &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-26-16:07.html"&gt;try them and see what happens&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-13-09:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-14-07:22.html</id>
    <title>Joy in Sadness</title>
    <updated>2020-05-14T11:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Joy in Sadness&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2T377tI"&gt;A Field Guide to Getting Lost&lt;/a&gt;, pages 118-119:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a voluptuous pleasure in all that sadness, and I wonder where it comes from, because as we usually construe the world, sadness and pleasure should be far apart. Is it that the joy that comes from other people always risks sadness, because even when love doesn't fail, mortality enters in; is it that there is a place where sadness and joy are not distinct, where all emotion lies together, a sort of ocean into which the tributary streams of distinct emotions go, a faraway deep inside; is it that such sadness is only the side effect of art that describes the depths of our lives, and to see that described in all its potential for loneliness and pain is beautiful? There are songs of insurgent power; they are essentially what rock and roll, an outgrowth of one strain of the blues, does best, these songs of being young and at the beginning of the world, full of a sense of your own potential. Country, at least the old stuff, has mostly been devoted instead to aftermath, to the hard work it takes to keep going or the awareness that comes after it is no longer possible to go on. If it is deeper than rock it is because failure is deeper than success. Failure is what we learn from, mostly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I find that I am reluctant to write about this passage, partly because I do not fully understand it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is there pleasure in sadness? Well, there can be of course. That which grounds you in your body is often easy to experience as pleasurable, at least until it becomes too intense, or you become bored of it, and you dissociate in order to numb yourself away from it. Feelings are experienced bodily, so can be a source of pleasure, even when those feelings are sadness - they connect you up with yourself, and you can revel in that connection.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But joy? I don't know. Sadness and joy &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; seem opposed to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the problem is that I don't really know what joy is.
I've been trying to figure out how to expand my positive emotional range, and this lack of understanding of joy is part of that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3bqscos"&gt;The Book of Human Emotions&lt;/a&gt;, Tiffany Watt Smith cites Spinoza:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Believing the stories of our lives were fundamentally beyond our control, Spinoza linked joyfulness to the accidental and unforeseen. It surges up when something is better than we can possibly have imagined. "Joy is pleasure accompanied by the idea of something past, which has had an issue &lt;em&gt;beyond our hope&lt;/em&gt;."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So perhaps there &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be a joy in sadness. We are bad at self-reflection, and an upswelling of sadness (if we do not ignore it) grounds us, shows us an aspect of who we are that we didn't know was there. Accompanied with the pleasure of being grounded in ourself, it's like the sudden appearance of an old friend. A joyous greeting ensues: "Hello, what are you doing here? I didn't expect to see you here at at all."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But certainly not all sadness prompts joy, as I think we are collectively discovering in the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/avyfain/status/1260832192030097409"&gt;Avy observed the following earlier today&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness is all about being fully present, and not letting your mind slip into thinking about past or future. It feels good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, months of isolation have been all about the right now. Living in an infinite present is awful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure how to reconcile this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this reading of joy has something to add here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness can definitely be experienced as pleasure - I do, and honestly it's usually a bit too much for me to handle for more than short periods of time - but fundamentally undifferentiated pleasure is &lt;em&gt;boring&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can see this when you use attention to turn off pain.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next time you're experiencing pain, focus your attention on it. You can often turn it off, or reframe it as interesting and enjoyable (whether this works is somewhat variable. For example I can't do this with headaches). But how long will you last doing it? If you're like me, lasting more than scant minutes is impossible - at some point the pain becomes preferable to the boredom.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is a lack of skill, and once one is at the point where one can sustain a two hour seated meditation, the boredom is entirely manageable, or perhaps even the boredom can be experienced as pleasurable. I don't know. Meditation is not among my skills.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I suspect most people lack the skill to reframe boredom as pleasurable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If joy is pleasure in the unexpected, then it is no surprise that mindfulness can bring joy in a way that the eternal now of pandemic time cannot, because mindfulness comes with a suspension of judgement that we, for the most part, cannot manage all the time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://meaningness.com/wonder"&gt;David Chapman recently wrote about wonder&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suggest that wonder occurs in heightened agendaless attention combined with suspension of habitual interpretation. Heightened agendaless attention allows and perceives unexpected patterning; suspension of habitual interpretation allows and perceives unexpected nebulosity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://meaningness.com/nebulosity"&gt;nebulosity&lt;/a&gt; is a term he uses in a technical sense idiosyncratic to his meaningness project. Nebulosity is the property of things that seem well defined to become vague at their boundaries)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I propose that this suspension of habitual interpretation is also one of the key differences between mindfulness and pandemic time. We experience joy because we are able to put aside, for a moment, our interpretation and thus our understanding, so whatever comes next will be equally surprising.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the pandemic we are not able to do that, partly because we are not able to maintain this suspension for long periods of time anyway, and partly because it is &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt; to suspend interpretation when we are under threat.
Interpretation is a key part of our threat assessment and merely &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;knowing&lt;/a&gt; that doesn't help us feel safe enough to do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And without this suspension of interpretation, without the perpetual surprise that comes with it, an eternal now is not a joyous experience. We experience only the sadness, without the ability to joyously revel in it, because we &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what is there, and we are bored of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And without that joy, the eternal now takes a darker turn, because although an eternal now is experienced in mindfulness, it is also a symptom of depression.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-06-07:46.html"&gt;written before&lt;/a&gt; about Matthew Ratcliffe's book, &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3fJk71w"&gt;Experiences of Depression&lt;/a&gt;, and his notion of &lt;em&gt;existential feelings&lt;/em&gt; - feelings which lack an aboutness, but are instead part of the background structure of our experience of reality. Feelings associated with the passage of time are a significant type of existential feeling.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ratcliffe proposes that much of the depressive experience can be thought of as disruption to existential feelings. Given that, it's not surprising that we can experience the disruption to the passage of time as depression. Also, for those of us already prone to depression, I suspect that some disruption to existential feelings can prompt a broader depressive episode, through trained associations and kicking off feedback loops that drive us deeper into this depression.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What defines the difference between whether a disruption to the passage of time causes depression or joy?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suspect part of it is &lt;em&gt;agency&lt;/em&gt;. In mindfulness, we are in a situation which we can choose to end whenever we need to. We have voluntarily entered into that state. It's a weird, inverted, image of the difference between a rollercoaster and a genuine threat: Because we are there voluntarily, the experience of the fear is qualitatively different even when the level of fear may be the same. Because we have chosen to suspend our experience of time, we can maintain an open curiousity, and can experience that disruption as joyous.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What does all this mean?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, it suggests at least three routes for dealing with the eternal now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is that we can end it. We can take steps to texture time for ourselves. I've been working on this a bit recently and so far my experience is that it's good but also doesn't work. Previously I was living day to day, now I'm living week to week. The world is textured but still small.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second is that we can cultivate agency without the eternal now. We may not be able to deal with it, but we can start projects, we can control that which we have access to. I think many people are taking this route.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The third, which is hardest and I barely know where to start, but ultimately may be the only option that works, is that we can try to learn to take joy in it. We can practice curiousity, reconcile ourselves to the endlessness in all of it, and try to explore the details of the world that is available to us. Maybe we'll be surprised by what we find there.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-14-07:22.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-15-09:54.html</id>
    <title>Teach me of your human notions of love</title>
    <updated>2020-05-15T10:49:03+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Teach me of your human notions of love&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2y3eU3x"&gt;Finding Our Sea-Legs&lt;/a&gt;, p 41:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is not the oldest philosophical question in the book, but is one of the most recurrent, at least once puberty has kicked in: "What is this thing called love?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, lets see what the book has to say about it. From Tiffany Watt Smith's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Lu4EEF"&gt;The Book of Human Emotions&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there anything left to say about love? Reams of poetry and songs, libraries' worth of philosophy, are dedicated to trying to express it, to understand and define it. The very volume of words tells us not only how much there is to say on the subject, but also how little can be said with any certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thanks Tiffany, that's very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Buckingham, on page 42, suggests that unlike philosophy (which asks questions like "What is love?"), storytelling tends to ask "What is love &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt;?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He is quick to point out the flaw in this question (on page 43):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, however, we need to be philosophically cautious. The way that this second question is phrased, "What is love like?" risks seducing us into thinking that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; in fact, a single thing, love, towards which this new question will lead us. But the more we ask this kind of question, the more it becomes apparent that love is no more a single thing than is death. What emerges from our storytelling is not Love, but a multiplicity of loves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This multiplicity of loves is, I think, part of the core of the practical problems of love. In reality, we are not so much interested in the question "What is love like?" any more than we are interested in the question "What is love?". What we want to know tends to be questions more like:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they love me?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I love them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I find someone who will love me?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I love myself?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think we will find that when we ask these questions they will not always mean the the same notion of love.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Love, like most things, doesn't really have a formal definition - you can look it up in a dictionary, but dictionaries describe use rather than providing authoritative definitions, and the dictionary's selection of meanings for love are particularly useless.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most words used in practice are defined &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ostensive_definition"&gt;ostensively&lt;/a&gt;, meaning that we point to a bunch of examples and hope that you can figure out the general pattern because we sure as hell don't know how explain it to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly tricky for things which are primarily phenomenological - purely or predominantly aspects of our subjective experience. We barely have a coherent vocabulary for talking about &lt;em&gt;pain&lt;/em&gt;, and pain is at least relatively easy to reproduce on demand. How is this supposed to work for things like love, which are vastly more complicated, and which you cannot easily point to an example?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Buckingham's answer is to let go of the question and embrace this plurality. I think this concedes too much, because it runs into a substantial problem: We can &lt;em&gt;disagree&lt;/em&gt; what love is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've talked about Bell Hooks's notion of love as "The will to extend one's self for the purpose of one's own or another's spiritual growth". I think this is a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; definition. It's not true, in that I don't think one can meaningfully assign a truth value to the question of whether that is what love &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, but I think that it provides a good starting point for reasoning about many of the positive aspects of love.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it's certainly not a definition that everyone can agree on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;David Chapman talks about &lt;a href="https://meaningness.com/nebulosity"&gt;nebulosity&lt;/a&gt;, the cloudlike nature of things - clouds are ill defined at the boundary. If you ask "What is the weight of a cloud?" you will end up with uncertainty that is in some sense fundamentally ontological (concerned with categories - which bits of matter do you consider "part of the cloud"?) rather than epistemic (concerned with knowledge - trying to pin down facts of empirical reality). Some parts of reality are clearly part of the cloud, some parts of reality are clearly not part of the cloud, but at the boundary there is a region where it's... kinda part of the cloud but it's not really clear, and the answer to your question about the mass of the cloud will depend on how we decide that question of categorisation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you ask "Do I love them?" you will experience this nebulosity of love: Some people the answer is obviously no, hopefully some people the answer is obviously yes, but if you are asking the question you are probably in that boundary zone where the answer is the rather frustating "It depends what you mean by love?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But when you ask "Do they love me?" the question is more complicated yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not everyone has the same notion of love. Some notions of love are different, and some notions of love are better than others (there's no total ordering here - it's &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-04-17-10:16.html"&gt;very unlikely that there's a single best notion of love&lt;/a&gt;). Many notions of love that we see in common use are coercive, abusive, or proprietary. "I would love you more if you changed to be what I want", "I hurt you because I love you", or "I love you, so you are mine".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In those cases the difficulty is still one of ontology. There are still questions about where the boundary of love is, but that boundary is now not merely fuzzy but contested. This is no longer a collaboration where you are trying to pin down an area of uncertainty, but a fight over the correct positioning of that boundary.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-15-09:54.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-07:43.html</id>
    <title>Truth and the Ghost Library</title>
    <updated>2020-05-16T10:22:04+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Truth and the Ghost Library&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-16&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ritual and its Consequences, p. 162:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Fundamentalism] equates truth, which is nonindividual and supraindividual, with its interpretation, which is invariably personal and conditional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this claim is interesting and mostly true, but also mostly false. That might be because of my interpretation of it, which is invariably personal and conditional.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm reading James C. Scott's "Domination and the Arts of Resistance" at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The book, as with most of Scott's work, looks at an aspect of how people behave in response to power imbalances.
In societies when one group dominates another, such as caste societies, or historical slavery in North America,
the way those groups talk among themselves is very different from the way they talk in public.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This leads to the idea of &lt;em&gt;hidden transcripts&lt;/em&gt;.
The idea is that there is a public transcript, which is the record (usually implicit) of what goes on in public,
and the hidden transcripts, which record how the groups talk among themselves.
Both the oppressed and the oppressor have hidden transcripts that are very different from the public transcript,
which can be thought of an elaborate ritual to maintain order, in which the oppressors perform strength and the oppressed perform deference.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hidden transcripts are a key part of the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-16-14:22.html"&gt;ghost knowledge&lt;/a&gt; that pervades society - knowledge that is built and widely shared inside a community of discourse, but is never written down and is not widely known outside of that community. Unlike much ghost knowledge, which is merely &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; shared, the hidden transcripts are actively kept from those outside of the community as a protective measure.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can think of knowledge about the world as being a kind of infinite ghost library, with different groups occupying (with varying degrees of jealousy) their territories within the library.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a key part my objection to the quoted passage I opened with: Interpretation is not just personal, it's very much driven by what you know, and who you talk to. People interpret in groups, and those interpretations become hidden transcripts within the ghost library.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Scott is careful to point out that these hidden transcripts &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; don't necessarily represent any sort of "true selves" of the oppressed, but are instead another social order, which may have its own barriers to authenticity, but I do think though that there is a gradient where the more hidden a transcript it is, the more sincere it is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Scott, on page 26, lists the following under "Hypothetical Discursive Sites, Arranged by Audience, under Slavery":&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harsh master/overseer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indulgent master or overseer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whites having no direct authority&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slaves and free blacks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slaves of same master&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Closest slave friends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Immediate family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;With the first three being part of the public transcripts, the last three being part of the hidden ones, and the 4th straddling the two. In the public transcripts you are very much participating in the ritual order of society, but in the private ones you can break character into sincerity and talk about what's &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; going on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From this point of view, fundamentalist social orders can be thought of as access control in the ghost library: The idea that this secret body of knowledge is in some sense &lt;em&gt;immoral&lt;/em&gt;, and that that which cannot be discussed in public should not be discussed at all.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-07:43.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-12:06.html</id>
    <title>Notes on Acedia</title>
    <updated>2020-05-16T12:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes on Acedia&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-16&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2X2QOP2"&gt;Leisure: The Basis of Culture&lt;/a&gt; which is a strange book, which I'll be exploring a different angle on in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/"&gt;my newsletter&lt;/a&gt; on Monday, but one thought from it that I thought was interesting and worth exploring further was the idea of &lt;em&gt;acedia&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This post is just some gathering of notes from different sources related to the subject, plus some vague thoughts..&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acedia"&gt;Wikipedia entry on acedia&lt;/a&gt; has the following to say:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acedia (/əˈsiːdiə/; also accidie or accedie /ˈæksɪdi/, from Latin acedĭa, and this from Greek ἀκηδία, "negligence", ἀ- "lack of" -κηδία "care") has been variously defined as a state of listlessness or torpor, of not caring or not being concerned with one's position or condition in the world. In ancient Greece akidía literally meant an inert state without pain or care. Early Christian monks used the term to define a spiritual state of listlessness and from there the term developed a markedly Christian moral tone. In modern times it has been taken up by literary figures and connected to depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The wikipedia article &lt;a href="http://www.hermitary.com/solitude/acedia.html"&gt;cites what is apparently a blog for hermits&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acedia (or accedie) has a narrow religious definition but is a far larger and wider psychological and spiritual term relevant to the history of eremiticism and solitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrow sense is that of sloth, indolence, laziness, as in the Western world's list of seven capital sins. Eastern Christianity is a little more comprehensive in referring to seven "temptations." Acedia is a psychological rather than moral condition, with implications for modern attitudes toward culture, conformity, and contentment. Acedia was a historical bane to monks, hermits, solitaries, and -- by extension -- to any one spiritually or intellectually inclined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of acedia begins with the ever-observant desert fathers and mothers who first perceived and diagnosed the condition. Their first impulse was to shoo it away like a pesky insect by keeping occupied, as in the narrative of Anthony beset "by many sinful thoughts" and cured by angelic advice to stay busy  plaiting rope. Poemen avers that "acedia is there every time one begins something, and there is no worse passion, but if one recognizes it for what it is, one will gain peace." And John Cassian adds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also good to recall what Abba Moses, one of the most experienced of the fathers, told me. I had not been living long in the desert when I was troubled by listlessness [i.e., acedia]. So I went to him and said: Yesterday I was greatly troubled and weakened by listlessness, and I was not able to free myself from it until I went to see Abba Paul. Abba Moses replied to me by saying: So far from freeing yourself from it, you have surrendered to it completely and become its slave. You must realize that it will attack all the more severely because you have deserted your post, unless from now on you strive to subdue it through patience, prayer and manual labor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly acedia is not willful sloth or indolence, less so "sin," but a spiritual lethargy or indifference, a turpitude that affects the well-intentioned. Amma Theodora says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should realize that as soon as you intend to live in peace, at once evil comes and weighs down your soul through acedia, faint-heartedness, and evil thoughts. It also attacks your body through sickness, debility, weakening of the knees, and all the members. It dissipates the strength of soul and body. ... But if we are vigilant, all the temptations fall away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A practical experience of acedia is described by the desert hermit Heraclides, who received a brother troubled by restlessness in his new cell. Heraclides advised him not to follow an extreme regimen of self-discipline but to eat, drink, and sleep as needed. He only asked that the brother not leave his cell. But, the narrator tells us, the brother fell "prey to acedia" and doubted the old man's advice. The brother followed his regimen but when he went to bed he found a demon lying on it, gnashing its teeth at him. The brother fled his cell to the old man's dwelling, imploring his help. Heraclides, seeing that the younger man had not followed his counsel to stay in his cell, refused to open, but the next morning, finding him still at the doorstep, Heraclides took pity on him. "Then, according to his capacity, he taught him the discipline of the solitary life, and in a short time he became a good monk."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Cassian went further than his conversation with Abba Moses to describe the physical symptoms so literally, even to the hour of the day when they peak, that acedia became known as the "noonday devil." He provides an excellent description of the psychology of acedia as well, indicating that acedia is a "tedium or perturbation of heart ... akin to dejection and especially felt by wandering monks and solitaries, a persistent and obnoxious enemy to such as dwell in the desert." He goes on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this [acedia] besieges the unhappy mind, it begets aversion from the place, boredom with one's cell, and scorn and contempt for one's brethren, whether they be dwelling with one or some way off, as careless and unspiritual-minded persons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The listlessness of acedia is akin to a feeling of inertness, John Cassian notes, producing no spiritual fruit, a sense of any practice being "empty of spiritual profit." John's remedy, following desert tradition, is a level of sustained activity approximating rigorous physical labor and what were to be called works of mercy, which fend off cynicisms. Physical labor as a solution is seen in the example of the first Christian desert hermit Paul, who regularly wove baskets of palm leaves. But being too far from a market to sell them Paul would burn his handiwork once a year and start over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In The Book of Human Emotions, page 16, Tiffany Watt Smith describes it as:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acedia (pronounced a-seed-ee-a) or sometimes called accidie, is an emotion that has no real equivalent today. It was a short-lived but disastrous emotional crisis, usually striking between 11AM and 4PM. Its first signs were listeness and irritability, but it didn't take long to turn into desolation and despair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the sixth century =, acedia was dropped from the list of mortal sins. Some of its symptoms were absorbed into the illness melancholia, a forerunner to our own states of depression and anxiety (see: MELANCHOLY). The rest became the moral vice sloth. Though people still spoke of feeling acedia, it came to mean something more like inertia - an equivalent, perhaps, to that listless feeling which descends on a rainy Sunday morning (see: APATHY).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In "Leisure: The Basis of Culture" acedia is introduced as follows (p27):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did the old code of conduct mean by idleness, by &lt;em&gt;acedia&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, it meant something other than we usually mean when we speak of the "root of all evils."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Idleness, for the older code of behavior, meant especially this: that the human being had given up on the very responsibility that comes with his dignity: that he does not want to be what God wants him to be, and that means that he does not want to be what he really, and in the ultimate sense, &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Acedia&lt;/em&gt; is the "despair of weakness," of which Kierkegaard said that it consists in someone "despairingly" not wanting "to be oneself". The metaphysical-theological concept of idleness means, then, that man finally does not agree with his own existence; that behind all his energetic activitity, he is not at one with himself; that, as the Middle Ages expressed it, sadness has seized him in the face of the divine Goodness that lives within him - and this sadness is that "sadness of the world" spoken of in the bible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In Voices: The Educational Formation of Conscience, Thomas Green has a slightly different take (p. 40):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[When one behaves correctly but does not care to be correct] the internal speech of the self would be: "It doesn't really matter, but this is the way they like it. I know what they want, so I'll go along with this senseless charade even though nothing vital is at stake." Such a posture of detachment is the perspective of the uninvolved, the apathetic. It is the condition of anomie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key to this interior speech is found in that indefinite, obscure, omnipresent, and distant 'they'. How remote, ho w disguised, 'they' always are! How senseless; yet, at the same time, how pervassive are the norms of everyday life when viewed simply as the edicts that 'they' deliver, and how thoroughly, under like circumstances, do those edicts lack even the most minute measure of moral authority! This condition, as nearly as I can describe it, is closely related to a kindred state that the medievals describe as &lt;em&gt;acedia&lt;/em&gt;. i.e., a kind of spiritual torpor or sickness that nowadays is often expressed as &lt;em&gt;ennui&lt;/em&gt; or boredom. The ancient idea extended, however, to something more fundamental even than mere boredom. It included the notion of a certain rebelllion, a conditon of being asleep to life, a resolute rejection of any possible contentment with being what one is, namely, a human being and thus essentially a creature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Both Green and Pieper seem to be framing acedia as a form of disconnection from sources of meaning. For Pieper this source of meaning is spiritual, for Green it is full participation as a member in a normative community.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's interesting that the hermitage site suggests working with your hands as an antidote to acedia.
I'm put in mind of Matthew Crawford's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3bzPSqt"&gt;Shop Class as Soulcraft&lt;/a&gt; where he argues that professions that are very hands on are in fact much more nourishing sources of meaning than office work (I do not especially recommend this book, although there are things I like about it).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm also put in mind of James C. Scott's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2X0qAN3"&gt;Two Cheers For Anarchism&lt;/a&gt;, where he argues that we should think about work not solely in terms of its productivity, but in terms of its effect on workers:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we were to ask a different question of institutions and activities than the narrow neoclassical question of how efficient they are in terms of costs (e.g. resources, labor, capital) per unit of a given, specified product? What if we were to ask what kind of people a given activity or institution fostered&amp;gt; Any activity we can imagine, any institution, no matters what its manifest purpose, is also, willy-nilly, transforming people:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[the assembly line] was deliberately designed to eliminate the artisanal-craft knowledge, and the power this knowledge conferred on workers, that characterized the carriage-making era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Lx4yMm"&gt;Talking About Machines&lt;/a&gt; Julian Orr describes such a community of artisanal-craft knowledge, in the form of photocopier technicians at Xerox PARC. These technicians clearly have both Scott's artisanal-craft knowledge and Green's normation to a community of practice. Reading Orr's descriptions of it, the technicians certainly &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; satisfied with their jobs, but it's also very clear that management would really rather not have to deal with the complex messy realities of depending on an actual community of experts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm additionally put in mind of Rebecca Solnit's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2Ar3MOL"&gt;A Paradise Built in Hell&lt;/a&gt; where she talks about the communities that arise in disasters, where she shows how people band together towards a common cause, and find it a powerful source of meaning - in many ways the aftermath of a disaster is a positive experience for people in these communities.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Pieper argues that Total Work is the source of this acedia, or perhaps that acedia is the source of total work, but it seems to me that communities of people working together towards a common cause, in ways that allow each of us to grow as a person, are in fact the &lt;em&gt;cure&lt;/em&gt; for acedia, and the problem is perhaps not work per se but the way that power has reshaped work into something that treats workers as a resource to extract value from instead of people to develop alongside.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-12:06.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
