<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2021-07-11T11:03:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-06-07-09:03.html</id>
    <title>High level objections to subjective expected utility theory</title>
    <updated>2021-06-07T09:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;High level objections to subjective expected utility theory&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-06-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-06-07-09:03.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-02-09:29.html</id>
    <title>People are bad at defining things</title>
    <updated>2021-07-02T14:25:09+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;People are bad at defining things&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently reading a philosophy book, and as a result I am cranky about definitions.
Like everyone who is not a mathematician (or culturally basically a mathematician, such as a computer scientist or theoretical physicist),
philosophers are very bad at defining their terms. The key sin of philosophers is that they love doing it anyway, and think they're good at it, but are for the most part terrible about it unless they've lucked into learning how to do it well from some source that wasn't a bunch of philosophers who think "language games" meant you were supposed to play language as a competitive sport where you score points for using words that nobody else understands.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I mean by "definition" here, is that when you introduce a new term (or even use an existing term in a specific or unfamilar way), you need to provide people with the ability to understand your usage of it. This doesn't require a precise definition that says exactly what the term means, like a mathematician would, though if you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; provide such a thing that is often helpful, but it does require you to introduce enough precision that people can understand what you're talking about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most people do not put in nearly enough work into defining novel terms in a way that is usable by the reader.
When you introduce a definition without adequate support, you have essentially put a road block in the reader's path until they have sufficiently understood your definition to proceed.
If you do not help them out in doing this, you have probably lost most of them as a reader,
and almost certainly many of those you retain will misunderstand your point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What a good definition is&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The purpose of a definition is to give people enough to grab on to to be able to understand your usage of the term.
As such, it should explain the term (see &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/10/how-to-explain-anything-to-anyone/"&gt;How to explain anything to anyone&lt;/a&gt;) and give them some material to work with in developing their understanding on top of that explanation. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A gold standard for definitions contains all of the following characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The term is well separated from surrounding text rather than buried somewhere. The mathematical convention is that we typically have a bolded "&lt;strong&gt;Definition:&lt;/strong&gt;" in front of it, often with a number you can refer back to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It provides an explanation of &lt;em&gt;why we need the term&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It provides an intuitive handle on the term.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It provides as precise an explanation of what the term means as is reasonable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is accompanied by at least one &lt;em&gt;positive example&lt;/em&gt;, an example of a thing that satisfies the definition, with an explanation of why it is an example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is accompanied by at least one &lt;em&gt;negative example&lt;/em&gt;, an example of a thing that is close to satisfying the definition but doesn't, with an explanation of why it is not an example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of these, the examples are in many ways the most important and the most overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;An example of a bad definition&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast the way most people do it is they shove a new term somewhere in the middle of a paragraph, gesture vaguely at what they mean by it, and then go on to use it in ways that completely fail to track the limited sense in which they've defined it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The definition that I am currently being cranky about comes from Albert Borgmann's is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early scientific theories of the Western world had both world-articulating and world-explaining significance. To articulate something, i.e., to outline and highlight the crucial features of something is also a kind of explanation. It is the kind of explanation that can satisfy the request for an explanation of a concrete thing or event. I will call it deictic explanation to distinguish it from deductive-nomological or subsumptive explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If I am being very very charitable, this just about satisfies (2) and (4). It explains why we need the term (it distinguishes a type of explanation that is different from the sort we are considering in the context of a modern scientific explanation), and it more or less defines it as being the sort of explanation that you get by outlining and highlighting th ecrucial features of something. Fair enough.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, on the very next page this is how the word deictic is used:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They do have deictic power in the sense of delimiting a set of possible worlds and ruling out certain impossible worlds. We can observe a similar pattern in the development from alchemy by way of chemistry to nuclear physics. Alchemy reflected in its laws a definite world of a limited number of stuffs and transformative forces and processes. Nuclear physics. being a microtheory, allows for an indefinite number of molar worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern in the progress of science has no a priori character. It is an empirical fact that the world can be explained in the powerful scientific theories that we now have. The pace of the discoveries of these theories is a matter of historical fact. But given these two facts, it was inevitable that the deictic power of the sciences waned and all but vanished. This is not a failure of science. Nor is it the case that the deictic achievement of the earlier sciences was unquestionable or unique. Art has always been the supreme deictic discipline. Art in turn has sometimes been one with philosophy, religion, and politics; at other times these disciplines have complemented or competed with one another as disciplines of deictic explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This subsequent usage &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; much makes me question whether I have understood his meaning.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As near as I can tell, "deictic" means something along the lines of "indexical", which means something along the lines of "pointing to a specific thing" (thanks to &lt;a href="https://carcinisation.com/2020/01/27/ignorance-a-skilled-practice/"&gt;a literal banana for explaining this&lt;/a&gt;). Something is deictic to the degree that it concerns a specific thing in all its glory, in contrast to something being apodeictic. An explanation is deictic to the degree that it is focused on explaining &lt;em&gt;a particular thing&lt;/em&gt; and what is interesting about it specifically, while it is apodeictic to the degree that it is focused on explaining &lt;em&gt;a general phenomenon&lt;/em&gt; and the conditions under which it emerges.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe. I can't tell for sure, because he doesn't provide me with any concrete examples to test this. Certainly I would very much not have thought of philosophy or religion as at all examples of things prone to deictic explanations. Art I will grant, certainly, and politics certainly is full of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wicked_problem"&gt;wicked problems&lt;/a&gt;, which by their nature require attention to the specifics of the unique thing involved.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of this confusion would easily have been cleared up with some examples and a bit more spelling out of his meaning.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;An example of a good definition&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, I think the following definition from Bernard Suits's "The Grasshopper", is very good:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To play a game is to attempt to achieve a specific state of affairs [prelusory goal], using only means permitted by rules [lusory means], where the rules prohibit use of more efficient in favour of less efficient means [constitutive rules], and where the rules are accepted just because they make possible such activity [lusory attitude]. I also offer the following simpler and, so to speak, more portable version of the above: playing a game is the voluntary attempt to overcome unnecessary obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This has both the precise definition and the intuitive handle on it. It then goes on for several pages more to investigate how this does and doesn't apply to specific examples, which I won't include here. It doesn't have a mathematician's "&lt;strong&gt;Definition:&lt;/strong&gt;" preamble, but that wouldn't really fit the style of the book, and it's still its own paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Appropriate levels of precision&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my gold standard for "good definition" I said "It provides as precise an explanation of what the term means as is reasonable".
The reason for the "as is reasonable" clause is that it is rarely the case that one can define something perfectly precisely,
at least outside of the realm of mathematics or constrained rule based environments (e.g. laws, rituals, games).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In reality many things cannot be this precisely defined, and we need more example-based (philosophers would say "ostensive") and sketch explanations. For example I can't really define "red" for you, but I can tell you that red is a colour (hopefully you don't need me to define "colour", because I'd really struggle with this one) and then point at examples of things that are red and things that are not red until you get the picture.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly common when you start talking about people, as people are reliably messy and complicated, and it becomes hard to precisely define a term rigorously. That's fine. We can still talk usefully about things like "love" without answering the question "What is love?", it just requires us to be a bit more careful about how we do it, and how we use examples. It may also require us to talk around a bit more about what we do and don't mean.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For an example of why one might need to do this, a question that came up in discussion recently is "What does 'unconditional' mean in 'unconditional love'?". It turned out everyone was using it differently (e.g. does it refer to how the love would change if circumstances change, or is it a character of the type of love felt in the moment?). This is the sort of confusion that comes up in the absence of a sufficiently precise definition. We cannot always solve it with that better definition, but we do need to navigate it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This ties in to the question of teaching tacit knowledge that I talked about in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-teach-the-local-style"&gt;How to teach the local style&lt;/a&gt;. These definitions cannot perfectly capture the thing you want to convey, but you can get the rough idea, and you can correct any errors along the way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that I think is important is that when you've introduced something this way you need to hold people's hands more when you use the term. Every time it comes up in future is an opportunity to refine their understanding of it, and it's worth taking many of those opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;How bad definitions thrive&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why do so few people meet my standards of good definitions?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think, primarily, people write bad definitions for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody taught them how to write good definitions, because the practice is so rare outside of mathematicians (and also nobody teaches mathematicians to do it well, they just hope they pick it up by example like everything else important in mathematics).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing good definitions is much harder work than defining things badly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing good definitions will often reveal that the emperor has no clothes and you're using big words for no goddamn good reason to make yourself sound clever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm hoping in this essay I have done at least some small part to offset the first, although it probably needs a longer essay with more worked examples and better explanations of the various moving parts to really work for that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second is, in fact, good. Writing definitions &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be hard, because every time you introduce a new term (even when you introduce it well!) you are asking the reader to do a bunch of work, and significantly harming their ability to understand your text. Often the best way to define something is to figure out a way to not need it at all, and where you do need it it's worth putting in the work to make sure that people can actually use it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The third is, I think, the most pernicious. I'm a big fan of Michael Billig's "Learn to write badly: How to succeed in the social sciences". I tried to find some good excerpts to include here, but it's not actually all that well suited to excerpting. In short, he argues that much of the use of jargon and technical terms in the social sciences is of an imprecise sort that &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; be defined precisely in this way, because that would lose its social function, which is more about marketing your ideas and protecting them from criticism than it is about carefully and helpfully communicating them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Charitably, I don't think most people are deliberately leaning into this incentive, but I do think many people are innocently writing in a style that these incentives have shaped, and demanding clear communication is a good way to push back on those incentives.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-02-09:29.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-03-13:55.html</id>
    <title>No shortage of things to write about</title>
    <updated>2021-07-03T15:04:38+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;No shortage of things to write about&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/fragments-intellectual-diy"&gt;Intellectual DIY&lt;/a&gt; I recounted a conversation with my father in which I explained that all of my reading and writing was more by way of a vast intellectual DIY project:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I had a conversation with my father in which he said how impressed he was with my memory and general breadth of knowledge and intellectual achievement, and that he could certainly never do anything like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I expressed polite scepticism at this claim and pointed out that his sheer breadth of practical knowledge far outstripped mine. He seems to know everything about DIY, and is generally prepared to wade in and do a good job on just about anything you might expect to do around the home, from heat pump engineering to building furniture. He's been building some stairs recently, as one does. He is finally starting to come around to the idea that maybe he doesn't have to do everything himself, but generally it's not a question of whether he can do it himself, but whether he can do this thing and all of the thousand other tasks he's taken on. This is of course all before we even start on his actual professional skill set (he was a banker before he retired).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He objected that this was not at all the same thing - he just figured things out as he went and refined his skills over time in the course of doing them. He didn't necessarily remember all these things, he just started with the problems he was trying to solve, had the confidence to try things out and see if they worked, and practiced them until he got the knack of it, and then builds on that prior experience for future problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well yes”, I said. “How do you think I do it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This analogy continues to bear fruit, as I had another conversation with him recently, in which he expressed how he was impressed and surprised by how I never ran out of topics to write about. "Well, would you have trouble coming up with things to do on the Mill?", I replied. "No, I guess not." "Same thing, basically."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(The Mill is my parents' house. It's a converted water mill. It's lovely but also a significant amount of work)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think when people think of writing, people think of it as trying to create something new in the world,
but actually most of my writing has very little creativity to its selection of topics, I'm just responding to a particular concrete thing I've encountered.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you look at &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-02-09:29.html"&gt;yesterday's piece about defining things&lt;/a&gt;, there was no primal act of creativity where I had to "come up" with a topic. I was experiencing a thing and I was annoyed about it, so I wrote about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the day before's piece on the newsletter, &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/telegraph-your-moves"&gt;Telegraph your moves&lt;/a&gt;, was a specific response to people's responses to some scheduling changes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Both of these were very mundane prompts, but based on my own evaluation and other people's responses, they both produce pretty top tier pieces.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, life is full of problems, and even where there are no well defined problems there's a near infinite amount of detail.
Almost all of that detail you can just look at and go "Huh. What's up with that?" and write something about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For me in particular a lot of my reading and writing fits into a sort of broad intellectual program of trying to help people get better at life, for values of "people" that first and foremost includes me. As a result, in order to run out of things to write, I'd have to basically have life solved. I'm uh a little ways away from that. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Generally the problem I have is the opposite: There is &lt;em&gt;too much&lt;/em&gt; to write about. This leads to two problems:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I decide which bits to write about?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I write a short piece without pulling in everything?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first part is genuinely hard, and I tend towards the less deliberate: I write about whatever happens to be particularly on my mind when I sit down to write. Sometimes I have to shuffle through a few topics until something clicks, but ultimately (as per &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-25-10:39.html"&gt;How to make decisions&lt;/a&gt;) when you've got a lot of things that could work the best way is to just pick something arbitrarily. This does result in my topics jumping around a lot, seemingly at random, but I'm OK with that and mostly don't care if other people aren't (and suspect, by and large, people enjoy the novelty factor).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For the second: The way I experience this is that I'm reaching into a giant tangle and tugging on a thread. I start somewhere that seems interesting (such as with a concrete problem), and as I pull related thoughts and information come along with it, constructing a linear narrative as I go. Eventually I find somewhere that feels like a natural stopping point, and I stop. Like right now.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-03-13:55.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-04-12:52.html</id>
    <title>The humour test for expertise</title>
    <updated>2021-07-04T14:05:45+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The humour test for expertise&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A heuristic I sometimes use is this: You understand something at a reasonably expert level if and only if you get the jokes at a level where you could find it funny.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I started thinking about this when I watched this video:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VD5I4l9oASg" title="YouTube video player" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This video is hilarious. If you don't play Slay the Spire much you won't understand why. I can explain why, and I can even explain why well enough that you in some way understand it, but I cannot explain it in a way that allows you to find it funny without teaching you to play Slay the Spire, because the humour derives entirely from an understanding of the game.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, &lt;a href="https://github.com/mame/quine-relay"&gt;the quine relay&lt;/a&gt; is hilarious, but if you're not a programmer you absolutely won't find it funny, it's just weird and pointless.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason for this link between expertise and humour is basically &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theories_of_humor#Incongruous_juxtaposition_theory"&gt;the incongruity theory of humour&lt;/a&gt;: You have a particular set of expectations about how the game is played, and the video repeatedly violates those assumptions by playing the game in slightly unexpected ways. This is not how a Defect build is supposed to work, but it's definitely how &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; Defect build works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because humour derives from incongruity, if you can get the jokes in a field then you must have a sense of incongruity. This means that you've internalised the sort of intuition about what the expected normal for the field is - the field's norms of taste, a working knowledge for how everything typically goes and fits together. These are all signs of expertise, that you've progressed to the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_stages_of_competence"&gt;Unconscious Competence stage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The humour test for expertise is itself a sort of joke, and the fact that I find it funny is probably an indication that I've at least started to get something of a handle on the expertise literature (or just that I'm weird), but it's also serious and I think probably points in a number of interesting directions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular, although you can't explain specialist jokes in a way that makes them funny, it may be worth explaining them, as it will often reveal interesting things about expert intuition that might not otherwise be readily accessible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another application of the test is that the jokes you find funny probably tell you something about your areas of expertise that you hadn't realised. This may be an uncomfortable realisation because e.g. it causes you to realise quite how much time you've spent playing Slay the Spire.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-04-12:52.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-05-10:30.html</id>
    <title>Why do we need new terminology?</title>
    <updated>2021-07-05T16:19:40+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Why do we need new terminology?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This piece is off the back of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-02-09:29.html"&gt;People are bad at defining things&lt;/a&gt;. You should read that piece first. You don't strictly &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to read that piece first, but this post will have a lot more context if you do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you try to write using only easy to understand words, it can be hard to say what you mean because you have to use many words where a smaller number will do. As well as making it harder to write, this can make it harder to read, because every time you want to use the thing that you talked about in many words you have to use all those words again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you do this it helps more people to understand what you have written, but every single person who could understand the shorter way of writing it will find it harder to understand the longer way of writing it because each time they read those many words they have to make sure it is the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it helps to make up new words that you can use instead of the many words that you would have to write. This makes it easier for people to read what you have written because you can use the word you made up each time you would have written many words and they know it means the same thing each time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wrote that in the &lt;a href="https://splasho.com/upgoer5/"&gt;upgoer five text editor&lt;/a&gt;, which requires you to write using only the ten hundred most common words (thousand is not in the thousand most common words you see), and it was kinda annoying.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I wanted to say is this: Using a small vocabulary helps more people understand what you write, but it makes the text much longer. As a result, every person who could understand the larger vocabulary easily will tend to find it easier to understand the version that uses it fully, because each new word replaces a concept that took many words in the smaller vocabulary. Reading that single word each time is faster and doesn't require people to read the longer phrase to understand that you mean the same thing each time. As a result, it's often useful to introduce new terms that represent complicated concepts you're talking about to give people a handle on the concept they can use while reading your text.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know that the version with the larger vocabulary is &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; much better than the version in up goer five. I'm certainly happier with it, but I think for short texts it doesn't matter that much and it's repetition over the course of a longer text that matters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also sometimes you have a thing that you don't totally understand yet and it is nice to have a word that you can use to mean that thing while you talk around it. You can show things that are not what you mean and things that are what you mean, but you can't say exactly what it is you mean. Here it's really important to have a single word for it so you don't have to keep saying "that thing that I mean and am talking around".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which, translated out of upgoer five, is to say: Sometimes you have a concept that you don't know how to define precisely and want to talk about, and you can't just keep saying "that concept that I haven't defined yet that I introduced back there", you need some sort of placeholder you can talk about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is why I talked about example-based definitions: You introduce the terminology, and you do your best to convey the rough sense of what you mean and provide examples to help refine it. By introducing a new word, you have given yourself the ability to talk about something that you would previously only have been able to talk around.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To summarise all of this: We sometimes need new terminology because, used well, it helps you communicate what you mean in a way that people will find easier to understand.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If this feels like an alien concept, very different to your experience of how people use novel terminology, yes that's right. That's why I'm complaining about people using definitions badly.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-05-10:30.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-06-13:53.html</id>
    <title>Start from amazing</title>
    <updated>2021-07-06T15:17:38+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Start from amazing&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm out of spoons for the piece about taste I was going to be writing today, so I'll finish it off some other day.
Instead, here's a short piece to think about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You know that thing that happens, where you say you don't like something, and someone tells you that you've probably just never tried a good example of it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's annoying, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it's annoying in that way where someone tells you that you should exercise more, get more daylight, eat your greens. That sort of thing. You know it, and you know it's true, but god it sounds like so much &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it's annoying because you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; tried versions that everyone tells you are good, and they still haven't worked for you.
Maybe they were kinda fine, maybe they still had something you didn't like, maybe something else. Either way, you've tried the examples that people have collectively decided are good, and you've concluded the whole thing just isn't to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First off, I should say, it's completely OK to not like something. This is allowed. Not everything has to be for you. There's not nearly enough time to like everything, and there's no obligation to like things you don't want to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But sometimes you find yourself in a position where you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to like something, but the things everyone suggests as good aren't really working for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is because the recommendation of trying good things is wrong. Don't try good things, try amazing things. When you're trying to learn to like something, anything short of amazing isn't going to cut it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ideally, try things that even people who are no more than passingly into the genre think are amazing, because that the scene thinks is amazing is often a bit esoteric and relies on things that you will not really appreciate until you are more familiar with the genre (in much the same way &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-04-12:52.html"&gt;that you won't yet get the jokes&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Really though, the goal here is not to use some external measure of amazingness - that's just a good way to find candidates - but to find things that &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; think are amazing, that are so good that all of your objections to the genre are blown away and you find yourself faced with the inescapable conclusion that &lt;em&gt;of course&lt;/em&gt; you like this, how could you not?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the long run, not everything you consume will be amazing of course, but finding things that are amazing lets you anchor your sense of what's good about what you are trying to learn to appreciate. The qualities that you experience in the amazing examples are the qualities you are looking for in subtler forms in the good. But it's easier to start with things that blow you away and work backwards from there than it is to spend a lot of time in an ambiguous space going "Am I enjoying this? I don't know? Maybe?" trying to appreciate the finer qualities of something that you are currently experiencing as merely OK.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Starting from the amazing examples is the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-05-11:27.html"&gt;existence proof&lt;/a&gt; that you need. You have demonstrated that you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; enjoy the thing, all you need now is to expand outwards Now you just need to work outwards from there using the &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/05/how-to-do-hard-things/"&gt;fully general system&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of the context for this is that I have an ongoing sense that I would like to learn to appreciate poetry. Not that I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;, but that I would like to. I'll freely admit I haven't tried very hard, but what I have tried hasn't worked very well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/LisaIRMcNulty"&gt;Lisa&lt;/a&gt; recently suggested that maybe I needed to listen to it instead of read it,
because really poetry is always intended to be experienced in spoken form, and suggested I try some of the videos on &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/ButtonPoetry"&gt;Button Poetry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I spent a while clicking through some no doubt perfectly good poetry that was doing absolutely nothing for me, and was just about to conclude this as a failed experiment when I happened across the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tFTASR8BMps" title="YouTube video player" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The experience of watching this was not unlike accidentally stepping out in front of a truck full of feelings, and left me shaking for about an hour. It may not hit you that way, that's fine. This reaction isn't for you, it's for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But this is the level of reaction you should be seeking. Something that takes your previous ambivalence and washes it away it away in a flood, a revelation leaving you with no choice but to say "Oh. I get it now."&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-06-13:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-07-14:11.html</id>
    <title>Studying the mundane</title>
    <updated>2021-07-07T17:53:39+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Studying the mundane&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-07&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things that you might notice about the things that I write is that they're often about really mundane topics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/telegraph-your-moves"&gt;Telegraph your moves&lt;/a&gt; contains a significant discussion of why you should tell people when you're running late.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/you-should-complain-about-it"&gt;You should complain about it&lt;/a&gt; is about complaining (obviously).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-do-everything"&gt;How to do everything&lt;/a&gt; is almost entirely about this (I do briefly talk about mathematics and writing, but mostly it's not about that) and touches on profound topics such as how to catch a ball, how to clean your bathroom, and how to open a bag of rice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do not write about mundane topics because they are sources of deep philosophical insight. I write about them because I am actually trying to solve mundane problems. I said in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-03-13:55.html"&gt;No shortage of things to write about&lt;/a&gt; that "in order to run out of things to write, I'd have to basically have life solved. I'm uh a little ways away from that". This is true. But necessarily a significant number of the problems I have not solved in my life are mundane, because most of life is mundane, and I still think these problems are worth writing about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't to say that I'm &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; interested in mundane problems, but mundane problems are important, and often &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/life-complete-problems"&gt;life complete&lt;/a&gt; in interesting ways, and by their very mundanity will often have high impact. I don't know if my writing has ever made anyone blissfully happy, but I do know multiple people who have improved the way they cleaned their bathroom and had a slightly less annoying rice opening experience as a result, and that too is part of the good life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A particular reason I study and think about mundane things is that I think that there's often a lot of low hanging fruit available for improving them. People don't spend much time thinking about mundane problems, and even less time on how to communicate improvements in them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To a large degree this is rational: You essentially improve until what you've got is "good enough" and it's not worth figuring out how to improve further.
Importantly though, the effort that isn't worth it is that of &lt;em&gt;figuring out&lt;/em&gt; how to improve further. Often doing better is lower effort than what you're doing now, or very high benefit. Once you know how to do something the better way, it's clearly worth doing it that way (if it weren't, it wouldn't be a better way, it would be a way with a different set of trade offs), but that doesn't mean it's worth inventing that better way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(It may also still not be worth learning that better way, or you may not want to, and that's fine. I'm both not that great at tying my shoes and know full well I could fix this with a couple of hours spent studying &lt;a href="https://www.fieggen.com/shoelace/ianknot.htm"&gt;Ian Fieggen's Shoe Lace website&lt;/a&gt;, but have I done that? I absolutely have not)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I on the other hand am perfectly happy to put in that effort, because I find it interesting, and I have time to spend, and also there's a lot of stuff that other people seem to be "naturally" good at that I've had to figure out the hard way, so once I've invested all that mental infrastructure in learning this stuff I might as well keep going.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And... it turns out it's not that hard. There are some core skills that it's worth developing, but they're generally useful core skills for life, mundane or otherwise. Mostly you just need to learn to break out of habits, spot patterns, and identify where you've taken problems as immutable when they're actually easily fixable things. I'm not claiming this is &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt;, but it's not rocket surgery or anything, and almost by definition it's a skillset for making most parts of your life better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It does take time and energy, and I'm aware those are both often in short supply, so I don't expect too many people to do as much thinking about this as I do, but that's fine. I don't mind having a niche, and I expect I'll keep it. After all, literally nobody else is ever going to &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/refusing-to-learn"&gt;explain how to keep your flat clean in terms of the work of James C. Scott on the early development of agrarian states&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Although I could totally see &lt;a href="https://goula.sh/"&gt;Meekaale&lt;/a&gt; doing this with Hubert Dreyfus and Alasdair MacIntyre instead)&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-07-14:11.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-08-15:18.html</id>
    <title>Heading towards the ouch</title>
    <updated>2021-07-08T15:57:23+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Heading towards the ouch&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's an interesting therapeutic technique that I've synthesized out of various practices.
It's not exactly a &lt;em&gt;safe&lt;/em&gt; practice, but I do think it's a useful one.
I deployed a bit of it earlier in a coaching session (after extensive checking in with the client that this was really what they wanted me to do, including asking "This is going to require me to be an asshole to you. Are you sure you want me to do that?"),
but I haven't quite got a handle on how to facilitate it for someone else yet because I don't generally do it for other people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The technique is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Say something that you don't want to say (or possibly think it clearly. Saying it out loud is supposed to work better, but I sometimes find the opposite).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does it hurt? Good. Identify why it hurts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take the part that hurts and say something new based on it. If that hurts more, switch to that as your new starting point. If not, stick with the current one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep doing this until you run out of "improvements" or it gets too much and you need to stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use wherever you've ended up as a prompt for introspection. Explain why it feels so bad, in depth, what you're worried about, evaluate whether the statement is actually true, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, such a sequence for me might look like:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I should get a real job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm just kidding myself about being able to make writing work as a career.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm not going to see it through anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'll just quit as soon as it gets too difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think this is necessarily true (I sure hope it's not!), but there's definitely some part of me that believes that,
and I can notice a real physical discomfort increasing as I move down the list. I really don't like the last entry at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is roughly a shadow work / Focusing hybrid. It's designed to help you uncover emotionally painful beliefs that you're trying to ignore.
Generally these sorts of statements don't hurt unless some part of you believes on some level that they are true,
and this process gets you to a point where you have identified a specific acutely painful belief to interrogate (and ideally do something like coherence therapy to to defuse it, if indeed that belief is false. See e.g. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;Emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also, I think, probably quite a good tool for learning Focusing because of how unsubtle it is. This is not staying with a fuzzy unclear feeling until it makes sense, this is confronting you with exactly what a felt sense dialled up to 11 is like. It's oddly similar to the strategy I outlined in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-06-13:53.html"&gt;Start from amazing&lt;/a&gt;, in that it dials up the feelings until they can be clearly identified so you know what to look for, rather than leaving you in a fuzzy in between space where you're not sure if anything is going on there or not.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-08-15:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-09-12:43.html</id>
    <title>What does one do on bad days?</title>
    <updated>2021-07-09T14:49:42+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;What does one do on bad days?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today is not a particularly good day for me. I guess it would be a stretch to call it a bad day, but I'm tired and out of sorts, struggling to focus as a result, and generally not at my finest. Not particularly depressed or anything, just a bit meh.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm writing this piece anyway, because I wanted to write something every day and I think it's good for me to stick to that - both in the sense that I'm able to do it and I committed to doing it, so I should, and also in the sense that I want to do it and I think it's helpful for me to do so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But at the same time, I have some actually involved writing projects I want to do. I'm still figuring out a (paid) newsletter issue on taste that I have to finish, am planning to write up a lot of my old notebook posts on emotions into a more coherent form, and am still reading "Technology and the Character of Contemporary Life". None of that really appeals today, nor does the slightly more sophisticated notebook post I was going to write instead of this one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And honestly it's reasonable that they don't appeal today. I could do them if I had to, it's not that I'm literally incapable of them, but possibly I'm impaired enough that I shouldn't: the benefit is reduced from me at my peak performance, and the cost increased. They're things that are definitely worth doing on a good day, but maybe they're not today.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is something of a recurring pattern for me. I couldn't really tell you how often it happens (I probably should be able to, but I'm not sure what counts as "it". Also I hate data entry. Please don't give me advice on this, I don't want your advice, and I will shout at you in my &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/no-backseating"&gt;No Backseating&lt;/a&gt; voice), but certainly it's not an unusual occurrence. I'd guess I have a day at least this bad most weeks, sometimes more often than that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And this often leaves me thinking about the question of what to do with those days.
Or, I guess, more specifically how to avoid losing them to dissociative activities. It's very easy to get to the end of a bad day and go "Wait, what did I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; today?" and discover that the answer is that you spent all of it on Twitter, or playing games, or watching youtube videos, or something else of that ilk.
This seems bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If I had a real job of course (and sometimes even when I've not had a real job and it was purely self inflicted) what I would do with such days (if they fell on a weekday) is to sacrifice them on the altar of the god of presenteeism. Can't do anything useful today? Tough luck. We'll punish you for taking the day off, but turning up and being miserable and not getting any work done is fine, so...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's relatively far down on the list of complaints I have about society, but definitely one of the failings is that we treat human beings as more reliable than they are, and then make it their problem when they fail to live up to that impossible ideal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Setting that aside... In an ideal world, what would we like such days to be like?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've suggested to coaching clients that it's good to build up a sort of library of things they can do for breaks, or when feeling bad. Going for a walk is one, doing some meditation or lying semisupine another, but these feel more like pause activities than fulfilling. Also I often don't &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to do these things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe I'm just being melodramatic due to my low mood, but it feels like this question is butting up against foundational questions like "What is life for?". Having a day where one is feeling tired and low motivation feels like one is butting up against the "&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vS-zEH8YmiM"&gt;We've got both kinds of sources of meaning, production &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; consumption&lt;/a&gt;" that it feels too easy to settle into. You end up stripped of access to meaning, mostly by laying bare how limited your access to it was in the first place, and are forced to ask what's left. It's no wonder it's easy to lose these days in activities that are designed to help you fast forward life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reading that paragraph back to myself does rather feel like I was lying when I said I wasn't having a particularly depressed day, doesn't it? Oh well. I'm going to go for a walk and pretend to be thinking deep thoughts while I do.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-09-12:43.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-11-11:03.html</id>
    <title>You open one of the 999 boxes on this floor and find...</title>
    <updated>2021-07-11T11:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You open one of the 999 boxes on this floor and find...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2021-07-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening I was, for reasons, talking to someone and coming up with strange and unsettling things you could do with surplus rooms in a house. Here are some of my entries:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One room has all the walls mirrored but one of the mirrors is secretly a screen and doesn't flip the image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One room is perfectly normal but for some reason the ceiling is a map of England. There is a "You are here" label on it. The label is, confusingly, pointing at a completely different city.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a pool room. We couldn't decide whether this was the sort with water or the sort where you hit a ball with a stick, so it's both.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room with a microphone and speakers that generate an artificial echo that is on very slightly too long a delay to be comfortable, and also sometimes you'd swear there's another voice in the background.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An entire room which is just a giant playground for cats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls are an ant farm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could keep going pretty much indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One room has many cupboards, but all the cupboards doors look identical to doors to other rooms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room with a window in it that on closer inspection looks out on the wrong side of the house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A perfectly normal living room in which all the furniture is for some reason clad in brightly coloured padded foam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room with central heating that automatically adjusts to a temperature the current occupants will find uncomfortable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room where all the walls are lined with drawers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room that generates a slightly unpleasant noise every time someone talks, gradually training people into silence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room that is perfectly normal but all the wall sockets are that of a different country.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Each of these took me no more than a couple of seconds to come up with, and I feel like I could do this for longer, though I expect I'd start to get a little repetitive at the 100 mark.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls are all different colours. When the room is occupied and nobody is looking at a particular wall, its colour changes very slightly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls "wrap around" visually so that looking at a wall you see the view from the opposite wall, stretching out into infinity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's only so much you can do with walls.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A reading room with several comfy chairs. Next to each is a small table with a pile of books on it. When you take a book off the pile, another one emerges from underneath to replenish the pile. Putting a book back on the pile does not cause any books to disappear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two identical rooms in separate parts of the house that are "sound linked". A cunning arrangement of microphones and directed speakers means that not only do you hear everything happening in the other room, you also hear it as if it were coming from the corresponding place in this room.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm using screens and speakers a lot, but that's because they're so versatile. I'm sure I could do without.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room whose walls and floors are a giant jigsaw puzzle. The pieces are lightly magnetic so they stick to the wall easily. The puzzle is of the view you would see from the outside of the house looking in that direction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room where all the furniture is metal and is very gently electrified so you get a light tingle when you touch it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A room filled with tiny ballerina dolls. As long as the lights are off, they will dance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason I'm able to do this is that this sort of idea generation is something I just practiced a lot as a child. It's easy to the point of being slightly surprising that other people can't do this so easily.
"How do you come up with all of these things?" "IDK I just think about the subject matter and reach for the place where ideas come from".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of example is particularly easy because "normal" is so tightly constrained. Everyone does most things in broadly the same way - there's variation, but even the variation is within pretty tightly defined bounds. As a result it's easy to generate interesting ideas by moving at right angles. It's easy to make weird things - you just do something that makes people go "Sure, you could do that, but why would you?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of where I learned a taste for this sort of thing and developed this skill is, I think, in &lt;a href="http://basement.warehouse23.com/"&gt;the Warehouse 23 basement&lt;/a&gt;. Someone on Twitter described the Warehouse 23 basement as a kind of proto &lt;a href="http://www.scpwiki.com/"&gt;SCP&lt;/a&gt; and that's not wrong but I think misses something important about it: The things in the Warehouse 23 basement are really quite low effort, and that's part of their virtue. It's seconds or minutes of work, not hours, and so you can iterate on the skill of generating them quite easily.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of idea generation is what Edward de Bono calls "lateral thinking". As with all Edward de Bono books, his book of the same is quite annoying, but it is genuinely useful. I'm particularly a big fan of his suggestion of making lists of a fixed size. Committing to generating, say, 100 ideas, forces you to come up with things that you wouldn't otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lateral thinking is foundational to a lot of creative processes, because often the way to come up with a good idea is to generate many bad ones and see what resonates, then improve on some of the best or most interesting parts of it, and practicing the ability to do it in a generalised sense is useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often when I think about developing useful general skills I think in terms of very sensible reasonable exercises that develop the skill. The warehouse 23 basement is a nice reminder that you can also just develop skills by having fun.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is an elevator room. It doesn't contain an elevator, it's just got lots of pictures of interesting elevators. A low voice is playing in the background, telling you endless interesting facts about elevators.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a room in which every time you say something a small child's voice plays, asking you "But &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;?"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a room in which anything is possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-11-11:03.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
