<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2022-06-05T14:53:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-27-14:08.html</id>
    <title>Leaving shiny things behind</title>
    <updated>2022-05-27T14:18:27+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Leaving shiny things behind&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-05-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something I've been thinking about recently is how useful it is to have names to describe crucial aspects of your problems.
Not that this is a new thought, but it's been on my mind.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result of this thought process, I realised I needed a name for a particular phenomenon: The way it is very hard for me to focus in the presence of my phone, which tends to grab my attention and lead to me checking Twitter without really meaning to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I propose the following name: The phone is a &lt;em&gt;shiny thing&lt;/em&gt;. Shiny things catch your eye with their glint, in a way that makes it hard to avoid looking at them. As long as they are in your field of awareness somehow, you have to put in active effort to not pay attention to them, because they have a natural gravity to them that distracts and captures your attention.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Shiny things aren't necessarily interesting or desirable.
Another example of a shiny thing is when the TV is on in a room, even with the sound off - even if you literally couldn't care less about what's on the TV, the fact that it is there with its attractive moving pictures tends to naturally draw your attention. Observe how much less engaged a conversation happening in a room with the TV on in the background is, even when you could in theory easily ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Shiny things aren't intrinsically bad - I like my phone, I like Twitter, I like watching TV - but they are bad to have around &lt;em&gt;when your purpose is not to engage with the shiny thing&lt;/em&gt;, because they entice and draw your attention. Even if you successfully avoid them, you expend energy on doing so that could be more productively used. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's possible that a sufficiently advanced set of mental skills could allow one to be immune to shiny things. It's not unlike &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/first-hard-choice"&gt;The first hard choice&lt;/a&gt;, where you would like to be able to listen to the sirens' song without being drawn onto the rocks.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But unlike the sirens, there is no virtue to being in the presence of a shiny thing that you don't currently want to use. It's just a pure cost. They can be there when you actively choose to use them, but they should be put away when you do not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lately I've been going on my stupid little walks for my stupid mental and physical health without my phone, and it has greatly improved the experience. Sometimes I bring a book, sometimes I bring a dictaphone, but neither of these are shiny in the way that my phone is, and so they do not distract me from doing whatever it is I choose to do in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-27-14:08.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-28-08:54.html</id>
    <title>The costs of being understood</title>
    <updated>2022-05-29T12:12:08+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The costs of being understood&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-05-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's another abandoned draft, which is about the costs that being illegible
impose on your interactions with the world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Many to one interactions&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me start with some experiences of mine that you may or may not share
that I think are usefully illustrative of a broader problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had a tweet, or blog post, or something similar become
unexpectedly popular? The &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/people-dont-work-as-much-as-you-think"&gt;People don't work as much as you
think&lt;/a&gt;
piece was this for me recently. To a much lesser degree, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1493181712427274241"&gt;this recent
tweet about many versions of a thing being evidence that none of them
are good&lt;/a&gt; is
another one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What happens is this: You get a lot of people responding in obvious
ways. Maybe they've misunderstood you. Maybe they're picking up on
something you missed, or didn't think was worth mentioning. Maybe they
disagree with you on ideological grounds. There are plenty of reasons to
make an obvious response.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At first, you can respond reasonably enough to these - pointing out
their misunderstandings, acknowledging that yes thank you for pointing
out that edge case but you were already aware of it and don't think it's
a problem, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the fifth time someone has made the same point at you, it's much
harder to stay polite, and by the hundredth message it doesn't really
matter if the observation is novel you just want these people to shut up
and leave you alone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can try getting cranky at them, and indeed it will probably be
incredibly hard work not to get cranky at them, but fundamentally it
doesn't work because the only reason crankiness can be a useful strategy
is when other people notice it &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; you have to get cranky at them
and modify their behaviour accordingly, and if the people doing this
were actually paying attention to others' behaviour they wouldn't be
repeating the same points you've already heard a dozen time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an example of an &lt;em&gt;asymmetric cost&lt;/em&gt; - although the cost of the
interaction is about the same for you and the other party, when you are
interacting with many people, the cost of their behaviour on you is
effectively much larger than any cost you can impose on them, because
they only have to pay it once, while you have to pay it once for each of
them. The cost of the interaction is effectively multiplied by the
number of people you have to have it with, which for you is large and
for them is you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not just a Twitter thing. Another (comparatively trivial)
example of this is that I have to explain my name to people over and
over again, and it gets tiresome. Yes that's a capital I, not a lower
case l. No, it's pronounced Mack-ee-ver, not Mack-ay-ver. Yes, it's
Scottish, but I'm not. No, it's not spelled or pronounced like the guy
with the paperclips. Yes that joke you've just made about it is
extremely witty and I definitely haven't heard if five hundred times
before. Ha ha.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not a big deal, and I generally remain polite throughout these
conversations, but there is definitely an internal sigh of resignation
as I think "Oh, we're having this conversation again are we?" each time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem with these sorts of asymmetric costs is that, like the
Twitter thing, they're almost by definition invisible to those who
impose them on you, because if they were there during That Conversation,
even if it was initiated with someone else, they wouldn't have to have
it again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Many to few interactions&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This comes up in more serious conversations too. Vegetarians are often
tired of having a conversation justifying their vegetarianism, people
are often tired of having a conversation justifying their religion or
lack thereof. Coming out as queer, poly, trans, etc. is something you
end up doing over and over again, and for most people it's tiring and
scary every time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The difference with these conversations however is that you're not the
only one having them and, as a result, chances may be pretty good that
someone you encounter outside of your group has already encountered one
of you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you're in a population with a 50/50 split between two groups (e.g.
gender), there is no asymmetry in the obvious conversations you have -
there is one man for every woman, more or less, so the number of obvious
day to day conversations you have is about equal. This falls apart in a
whole number of cases - e.g. in environments with large gender skews (In
either direction! There are large asymmetric costs in being e.g. a dad
in parental spaces dominated by mums, as well as e.g. being a woman in
software), and in situations in which the size of your demographic is in
some sense "artificially lowered" because of visibility (e.g. you'll get
to have all sorts of obvious conversations with men if you're a woman
whose tweet goes unexpectedly popular). But, by default, regardless of
how bad communication tends to be between the two groups there tends not
to be asymmetry of the sort that I'm talking about because the numbers
are broadly equal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, as the groups get smaller the asymmetry grows sharply. If
your group is x% of the conversation, then there are (100 - x) / x
people not in your group for every member who is. For example if you're
20% of the population, there are four of them for every one of you, if
you're 1% of the population there are 99 of them for every one of you,
etc. This means that, all else being equal, the smaller your group is,
the higher the asymmetric costs you experience as a member of it
interacting with people outside it are.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, all else is rarely equal. I am, for example, a member of the
group of people with weird names. We're a relatively small group, but
also the cost per interaction is relatively
low, (Once you reach adulthood anyway. Children are &lt;em&gt;brutal&lt;/em&gt; about this),
so even though the costs imposed are highly asymmetric, the total costs are still not that bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Necessary conversations&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of the time this problem can be solved by just ignoring it. I
don't have to correct people on my name, you don't have to tell people
about your vegetarianism, or your religion, or any other thing that
makes you unusual, unless it's directly relevant to the interaction.
This often brings down the rate enough to be manageable even if the cost
per interaction is relatively high.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This works great right up until the point where you need to do it. For
example, if you're vegetarian, you will often need to explain this to
people in order to be able to make sure you can eat something at a
location. If you have disabilities (visible or otherwise) you may need
to explain them in order to get accommodations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you need to be understood not for your sake, but because it's
the only way to get other people off your back. For example I think
about &lt;a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/why-is-it-hard-to-acknowledge-preferences?r=514ov"&gt;this Astral Codex Ten post about respecting
preferences&lt;/a&gt;
a lot:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently stayed at a B&amp;amp;B owned by a nice elderly couple. Very, very
nice. The moment I stepped in the door, they asked how my flight was,
where I was from, what I did, how I'd enjoyed my three minutes of
visiting their city so far, what kind of food I liked, what my
favorite color was, et cetera. I played along - no point in offending
people - but I warned that my friend, who would be arriving a little
later, was much more introverted, and would appreciate being
efficiently directed to her room without the welcome committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little later, my friend arrived. From my room, I could hear them
start welcoming her, ask her how her flight had been, start trying to
get to know her - until I ran out and rescued her, for which she
reports gratitude. For the rest of our stay, they continued to talk
both of our ears off, with my friend growing increasingly annoyed and
uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent the trip back dissecting what had gone wrong. Neither of us
believed the proprietors didn't care about her feelings: they were so
very, very nice. They couldn't have forgotten my warning; my friend
arrived less than an hour after I did. We concluded that they were
just inexplicably bad at some sort of mental gear-shifting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The worst part was, I knew this would happen. When I told them to
please respect my friend's introversion, there was a voice in my head
quietly adding "...even though you obviously won't and I have no
idea why I am even making this request".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think all that's going on here is a failure of understanding,
but I do think it starts with a failure of understanding. People hear
preferences and round them out to someone just making a fuss, because
they can't internalise what an extremely big deal that preference is for
the other person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think, to some degree, this is reasonable - people are constantly
imposing their preferences on us, and it's impossible to respect all of
them, so people tend to disregard a lot of things as unimportant, or as
something they're not obliged to respect. Just because you have a
preference to be referred to as Your Majesty and tithed 10% of my wealth
annually, doesn't mean that I have to do that. In order for me to
respect that preference you must either force or convince me to do so.
Generally we frown upon the "force" option unless you're &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; an
imperial power, so you should try to convince me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This happens with more reasonable preferences too - to continue the
vegetarianism example, there's a lot of work that goes in to persuading
people to respect your dietary preferences. Virtually everyone who has
such preferences have stories of them being argued with or ignored
(often covertly! Many people think it's perfectly reasonable to e.g.
sneak butter into something that they serve to someone who has said they
can't eat dairy. This is a really bad idea, but distressingly common).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can argue that people shouldn't need to understand your preferences
in order to respect them and you'd be, more or less, right, but the fact
of the matter is regardless of whether they should do that people mostly
do, and I'd argue that some degree of this is pretty much inevitable.
It's really hard to respect preferences you don't understand - it goes
against how memory works, you reliably fuck details up, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Certainly people should be a lot better at this than they currently are,
but expecting people to be maximally good at meeting preferences without
understanding them very much goes against how humans work, and besides
which can only possibly work at a very shallow level (though the shallow
level is still important for interactions with strangers).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;When you are hard to understand&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So you want to respect people's dietary constraints and preferences?
Thanks, that's great. I don't eat dairy, wheat (really most cereals in
its family are bad. "gluten free" isn't quite right but to a first
approximation is probably fine), brassicas, or lamb. Some onions are
fine if they're cooked but too many is likely to be a problem. Lentil
heavy dishes are probably a bad idea, but things that use lentil flour
seem to be mostly fine. Also I prefer not to eat fish for ethical
reasons, but don't worry about that as a one off.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You've probably almost immediately forgotten the details of that
paragraph. As well you should. Why would you memorise the details of my
food preferences if you're not cooking extremely regularly for me?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My experience is that almost nobody can keep track of my dietary
preferences, even before you get to the complicated ones. I normally
don't even mention anything past "No wheat, no dairy, no brassicas, and
you're probably fine but maybe check in with me if you're unsure?", and
this is usually still at least one too many details to keep track of
(people never remember the brassicas one, but unfortunately it's very
important).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is actually completely reasonable, because there are two different
asymmetric costs that are going on here: The first is the one to me, the
annoying conversation around dietary preferences that I have to have
with everyone who cooks for me. The second is the one that people have
when they cook for others, trying to keep track of everyone's food
preferences. Sometimes one cost dominates, sometimes the other, but
either way it's really quite a lot of work to keep track of everything
that everyone can and can't eat (I think I'm unusually good at this, and it's a lot of work to be good at
it and also I still get things wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem with my particular set of food constraints is that there is
no sensible organising principle to them. It's just a list of
empirically derived things that trigger my digestive system to freak
out. If there were a simple term that allowed people to check whether
something was suitable for me (e.g. gluten-free and dairy-free are both
examples of that, and people can usually stretch themselves to
remembering two terms) and that they could remember as being normal
problems for people to have, they would probably mostly
remember.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Though people absolutely can and do get these wrong. If you're not used
to doing it it's really hard to remember to check the ingredients list
and see if some asshole has snuck wheat into somewhere where wheat
really doesn't need to go.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even with more reasonable food constraints, you end up with a problem
that asymmetric costs are not always additive. It's much harder to cook
for someone who is both dairy-free and gluten-free than it is to cook
for someone who is one but not both. (It's also much harder to cook for
two people where one is dairy-free and one is gluten-free at the same
time, for much the same reason). It's not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; as hard to cook for
them if you don't have to do it at the same time (e.g. one guest one
night, one guest another), but it is easier to cook for two separate
gluten-free or two separate dairy-free guests than it is to cook for one
gluten-free and one dairy-free guest, because you learn skills and
habits with each - it's not just a matter of not doing the thing after
all, it's a matter of learning how to achieve your goal (producing a
delicious meal) while not achieving the thing, and that takes actual
effort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's easy to discount this effort, because you have curse of knowledge
around your own experience - it's hard to remember how hard it is to
understand something once you already understand it - but it is a real
effort that people have to expend to understand you. And it's not just
about diet, it's about everything else - things that annoy you, your
preferences for social interaction, triggers, pronouns, etc. All things
that it's completely reasonable to want other people to keep track of,
but also all things that contribute to the cognitive load of what others
have to keep track about us.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;The web of legibility&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this point the post basically turns into an attempt to integrate the
following two previous posts of mine here on the notebook:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-02-09:31.html"&gt;Legibility as a relationship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-23-09:37.html"&gt;Legibility privileges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is another one where I did all the framing work and ran out of energy by the point I got to the meat of the post.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-28-08:54.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-29-05:50.html</id>
    <title>What every programming tutorial gets wrong</title>
    <updated>2022-05-29T08:43:46+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;What every programming tutorial gets wrong&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-05-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another piece of draft bankruptcy. This is my attempt to explain a common
failure mode of programming tutorials. I got quite far, but eventually
abandoned it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Scene setting&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A while ago I was helping teach a coding workshop to a bunch of people
who had never coded before, and we were working through the written
materials which were very "Do this, then do that". Copy this code and
you should see this happen, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point a student asked me "OK, but what is actually going on
here? What does any of this mean? I can follow the steps, but I have no
idea what is going on."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was an incredibly reasonable question and I'm glad she asked it of
me, and that I could answer it, because I can't imagine that she would
have come away with any knowledge of programming without it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't remember the specific thing we were talking about, but I think
the example was something like:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"login"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"Bob"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"login"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;"Bob"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"some other key"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gt"&gt;Traceback (most recent call last):&lt;/span&gt;
  File &lt;span class="nb"&gt;"&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;"&lt;/span&gt;, line &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;, in &lt;span class="n"&gt;&amp;lt;module&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gr"&gt;KeyError&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class="n"&gt;'some other key'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is entirely clear if you're a programmer (especially if you're a
Python programmer, but it's sufficiently universal that probably most
programmers will have a pretty good idea of what's going on), but if
you've never programmed before it's just so much noise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In response to this question I would have said something as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The program you're using here is called the REPL(Read-Evaluate-Print-Loop,
but don't worry about that. It's pronounced
repple, like ripple with an eh). You're entering commands into it by writing statements in a
programming language called Python.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The interpreter keeps track of a number of "objects", which are a chunk
of data along with a particular set of commands that can you can use to
change that data, ask questions about it, etc. There are also commands
that let you interact with the computer more broadly (e.g. reading and
writing files) but we won't worry about them just yet in this tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here what we're doing is creating an object, giving it the name &lt;em&gt;user&lt;/em&gt;
that we can refer to it by, and issuing some commands and seeing what
happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specifically, we are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating an object of a specific type called a &lt;em&gt;dictionary&lt;/em&gt; and
    referring to it by the name &lt;em&gt;user&lt;/em&gt;. The curly brackets &lt;code&gt;{}&lt;/code&gt; create a
    new dictionary, and "&lt;code&gt;user =&lt;/code&gt;" is where we declare that we will
    refer to it as &lt;em&gt;user&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dictionary is an object whose job is to keep track of a table of
    information. It maps &lt;em&gt;keys&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;values&lt;/em&gt;, which are just arbitrary
    things you can put into it, so that if you tell it to associate a
    value with particular key, and then later ask for the value
    associated with that key, you get the same thing back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telling the dictionary we have just created (referred to by its
    name, &lt;em&gt;user&lt;/em&gt;) that it should associate the value "Bob" with the key
    "login". "Bob" and "login" are objects of a type called &lt;em&gt;string&lt;/em&gt;,
    which represents a piece of text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking up the key "login" and getting the expected value "Bob"
    back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking up the key "some other key" and getting an error that tells
    us that the dictionary has not yet been told to associate any values
    with that key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't a perfect answer, because I just made it up on the spot and
haven't tested it against students to see what questions they ask, but
it's probably pretty good. It certainly gives them more of a hook to
play around with dictionaries in the interpreter and see what happens,
and it gives them better questions to ask than "Help I don't understand
anything about what's going on".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Theory, examples, and ability&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm going to be using "theory", "examples", and "ability", in slightly
specific ways (which are possibly slightly idiosyncratic to me, although
I think compatible with normal use) in this issue, so I'll try to
explain what I mean by them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An example is just any concrete version of the thing being taught. For
example, "do these steps in the REPL" above is an example. Showing
someone a program is an example. Showing someone a mathematical proof is
an example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Theory" is the knowledge that you need to answer questions like "What's
going on here?" and explain the behaviour of a particular example. For
example, in the above, you need some sort of theory to answer the
question "Why did typing &lt;code&gt;user["login"]&lt;/code&gt; show &lt;code&gt;"Bob"&lt;/code&gt; but typing
&lt;code&gt;user["some other key"]&lt;/code&gt; showed an error message?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Ability" is the set of things the student can now do themselves. The
goal of teaching is to help the student expand their abilities. People
don't generally expand their abilities directly as the result of
teaching - you can only learn to do things by doing things - but
teaching points them in the right direction by giving them better ideas
of things to try. They still learn by trial and error, but teaching can
give them better things to try and help them understand their errors.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The goal of the above tutorial was to help them develop the ability to
write simple Python programs involving dictionaries, and to some degree
it succeeded. After going through this tutorial the student knows how to
launch the Python REPL, and has at least one example of something
reasonable to experiment with. Given a little bit of time to sit and
play with the REPL they might come up with a pretty reasonable theory
for explaining its behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why do they need to develop that theory? Because theory gives them the
ability to &lt;em&gt;generalise&lt;/em&gt;. If you have a theory that can explain why a
given action succeeded or failed, you now believe that any action that
matches that same explanation will also work or fail. This lets you try
out other things and see whether they confirm or deny your theory, which
is typically a much more productive model of trial and error than one
can manage without a theory of what's going on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Examples are vitally important&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I should be clear: It is very good that the tutorial we were doing was
dumping people in the REPL and getting them to play around with it. This
is not my complaint, it's the correct thing to do. My complaint is that
the tutorial did not then contain anything like my answer above.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of my pet peeves that has been coming out in places on the notebook
blog recently is that I hate people who introduce theory without
supporting examples in which to understand it. See e.g. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-02-09:29.html"&gt;People are bad
at defining
things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular it's often worth having examples &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; (this isn't
always possible), because then you can refer to concrete features of
them while introducing the theory. You saw a bit of that in how I
explained what was going on in the programming tutorial: I started with
an example, and then I highlighted specific features of it to ground the
theory (We're creating a thing called an object, it's a specific type
of object called a dictionary, then we're doing this to it, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The examples are particularly important. In order to understand a
theory, you need to be able to see how it applies to real concrete
things. Abstracting from concrete instances is literally the point of
theory, so without seeing how it relates to the things it abstracts
theory is just so many words.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that, examples are often key to developing abilities. People
do not, generally speaking, reason from first principles from a theory.
If you read the literature on naturalised decision
making, what people
tend to do is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recognition_primed_decision"&gt;recognition-primed decision
making&lt;/a&gt;. They
look at what's in front of them, they reason by analogy, thinking "Oh,
this looks like that thing I saw before, let me see what happens if I do
the same thing that I did there...". Having a rich and varied library of
examples is vitally important for this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I'd recommend Cedric Chin's &lt;a href="https://commoncog.com/blog/a-framework-for-putting-mental-models-to-practice/"&gt;A Framework for Putting Mental Models into
Practice&lt;/a&gt;,
but it's also worth reading Gary Klein's "Sources of Power" and maybe
some of his other work.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Theory helps you remember examples&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's look at our example again:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"login"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"Bob"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"login"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;"Bob"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"some other key"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gt"&gt;Traceback (most recent call last):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gr"&gt;   File "&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;", line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gr"&gt;KeyError&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class="n"&gt;'some other key' &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do you think you could recreate this example from memory? I certainly
could, and I think most programmers could with only a little bit of
thought. It possibly wouldn't be character by character perfect, but you
could certainly get the right general idea.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now consider the following highly readable example. Do you think you
could recreate &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; from memory?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; d"T{ o Bm&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; d"T{sn)gK[ena o n:g}n&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; d"T{sn)gK[ena&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;n:g}n&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; d"T{sn"gyT g](T{ tTuna&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;&amp;gt;{ilT}ilt kyg"] {TlTe] li)) )i"]'1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;   ,[)T nE"]h[e&amp;lt;n= )[eT b= [e Eyghd)T&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;FTuc{{g{1 r"gyT g](T{ tTur&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you haven't figured out the trick, this is the same example as above,
I've just jumbled all the letters through a mapping that replaces them
(e.g. &amp;gt; gets replaced with &amp;lt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do you think you could recreate this example from memory? I sure
couldn't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In some sense this contains exactly the same information as the
original, but because you're unable to easily turn it into a sensible
representation, it's much harder to remember and thus much harder to
understand. As well as the Python specific bits you also rely on e.g.
brackets matching, quotes matching, familiar understanding of the
meaning of the = symbol, the ability to clearly distinguish which bits
are identifiers because they're contained in quotes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When we know what's going on, we can describe the example as the
following sequence of steps:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a dictionary called user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insert the value "Bob" into "user" with the key "login"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look up the key "login" in "user" and get the result&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look up the key "some other key" in "user" and see an error from
    looking up a missing key&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;em&gt;high level representation&lt;/em&gt; of what's going on. It describes
the steps we are taking, not the specific details that we know. This is
easy to remember, because it's a set of comprehensible steps.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, we're not expecting students to actually memorise specific
examples, but ability to memorise is a pretty good proxy for how well
the example fits in their head - if you can't easily remember what
should be a fairly simple example, that's a sign that there's too much
going for you to really figure it out and you're trying to learn too
much at once.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of translation into a high level representation is what theory
does for you, and lets you organise your mental library of examples.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Theory helps you generalise&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as helping you remember examples you've seen before, theory lets
you &lt;em&gt;adapt&lt;/em&gt; those previous examples to your needs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This high level representation does a number of important things for us:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It allows us to understand the meaning of the thing we are writing
    in terms of what we are trying to do rather than the literal
    characters on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes it easier to remember because we can remember "Create a
    dictionary called user" separately from the literal syntax for
    creating a dictionary. We still have to remember both, but the
    latter is a fact we can more easily look up and will use often
    enough to remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It lets us make predictions for what we would see if we changed the
    example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Doing (the right) things is the most important&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This particularly shows up in the trial and error process of learning.
While you are still floundering around trying to figure things out, good
specific examples are especially important because you will lean hard
on emulating examples, so having good examples to emulate is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is where I stalled. I'm not quite sure why. I think partly the
post was getting too long, and I didn't know how to continue, or
I ran out of energy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's a known problem that I'm very bad at revisiting things once
I've stopped writing them, and as a result I tend to fail to
finish longer pieces. I would like to work on that but have not
yet managed.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-29-05:50.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-30-18:41.html</id>
    <title>Victims of metonymy</title>
    <updated>2022-05-30T18:42:36+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Victims of metonymy&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-05-30&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an outtake from an earlier version of &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/learning-to-walk-through-walls"&gt;Learning to walk through walls&lt;/a&gt; that I was vaguely planning to spin out into a full newsletter post, but I'm not going to do that, so here it is in its entirety.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I know a lot of people who think they're bad at reading books. They're
not, they're just victims of metonymy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Metonymy is when "&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metonymy"&gt;a thing or concept is referred to by the name of
something closely associated with that thing or
concept&lt;/a&gt;". In fact, to a very
large degree, this &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; happens when you talk about an action,
because most actions are vastly more
&lt;a href="https://carcinisation.com/2020/01/27/ignorance-a-skilled-practice/"&gt;indexical&lt;/a&gt;
than their symbolic representation would suggest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you say you are "bad at reading", reading is standing in for a much
more specific action that you are bad at. You are not &lt;em&gt;bad at reading&lt;/em&gt;,
you are &lt;em&gt;reading in a way that you are bad at&lt;/em&gt; (often in a way that
anyone would be bad at). The same is true of being bad at almost
anything else. Often when &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-do-everything?s=w"&gt;you have to find the trick of being good at
something&lt;/a&gt;,
what this really means is that you have to stop doing it the bad way and
stop doing the good way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it takes a very long time for this to occur to you, because until
this is pointed out in your head the name stands in for the action. This
is what is done. In your library of agency when you look up the action
"read a book", there is a particular physical action that comes up. You
do that, and it goes badly, and you conclude you are bad at reading when
the actual problem is that you are reading in a way that gives you
eyestrain, or is physically uncomfortable, or doesn't give you a way to
burn off nervous energy, or something else. Try experimenting with &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-13-09:56.html"&gt;how
to actually physically read a
book&lt;/a&gt; and
see if any variations are easier than others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is one of the ways that symbolization of the world lies to you.
Just because you can name something that doesn't mean that name has
predictive power. If I invent the word splorf to refer to either cats or
things that are coloured a weird vomity green, I can't meaningfully say
whether I like splorf or not, because cats are great and weird vomity
green things are not, but a lesser version of this is what you're doing
every time you conclude you are bad at a general category because you
are bad at some specific thing named by it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some categories &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; have predictive power and after you've tried a
number of variations it may be totally legitimate to conclude that you
really are bad at the thing named, but often we will jump straight from
the action to the label without bothering to test whether this is valid.
That's being a victim of metonymy.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-30-18:41.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-31-11:06.html</id>
    <title>Intelligence problems</title>
    <updated>2022-05-31T11:27:28+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Intelligence problems&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-05-31&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's a draft I abandoned basically because I find this subject extremely
stressful to talk about and low-key expect people to shout at me every time
I talk about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sucks, because it's an important subject to me that I genuinely think
most people I know would benefit from understanding better, so I've decided
that even if I can't bring myself to finish this as is I'm just going to post
what I've got and hope it's useful to people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Please don't shout at me about it. I'll be sad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Unspoken privileges&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I need to start with some theory, because it will help contextualise the
thing I want to actually talk about today.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The feminist concept of "privilege" is very important and useful, and
also tends to get people's backs up because people (including those who
are most willing to level it as an accusation at others) rarely like being
called privileged.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Ages ago I saw a proposal to replace the term with "blind spots", but it
never caught on. Unclear to what degree that was because it's kinda
ableist, and to what degree that was because it was much harder to hurl
it as an insult at your opponent in a fight on the internet.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tend to use a slightly modified version which replaces "privilege"
with "privileges". It's not a question of whether you are or aren't
privileged, but instead what privileges you do and don't have. We all
have privileges, but some of us have significantly more privileges than
others, and many of those privileges are in some way connected to shared
characteristics - e.g. I have male privileges, those privileges
associated with being male, or with being white, two of the main sources of
privilege typically discussed in feminist contexts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A "privilege" in this context just means any benefit I typically get or,
in particular, any source of problems that I get not to have. Anything
that makes your life easier or better, and is not reliably shared with
everyone else. e.g. due to the aforementioned being white and male,
there are a lot of contexts I can just walk into and assume (mostly
correctly) that I will be taken seriously and this does indeed make my
life easier and better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there are a number of privileges that I don't think get talked about
enough, because it's considered in poor taste to admit that you have
them, and I think this is a major problem because these are also
privileges that I think are among the best predictors of success.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The chief unspoken privileges of this form that I'm aware of are being
rich, being attractive, and being smart. You're not supposed to talk
about them because doing so seems like boasting. It's safe to talk about
white privilege, or male privilege, or to some degree middle class
privilege, because you're able to talk about them on the assumption that
these in some sense "should" be value neutral. But when you talk about
wealth, attractiveness, or intelligence, there is always an implied
subtext of "These are the privileges I have for being better than
you..." and that goes down about as well as you might expect.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This results in a peculiar norm in a lot of lefty spaces where you are
supposed to acknowledge all your privileges &lt;em&gt;except for some of the most
impactful ones, which you are encouraged to downplay&lt;/em&gt;. I consider this a
tad suspect.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More importantly, this results in a very distorted view of the world,
where people are not properly able to understand the advantages that
they have and others lack. I think it's important to understand these
clearly, both in order to have more empathy for others and the problems
they face, and also to understand &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-07-15-09:33.html"&gt;the nice problems to
have&lt;/a&gt; that
they bring you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What is intelligence?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The one I want to talk about today is intelligence. First I need to
convince you that intelligence is a real thing. Fortunately, you
probably already believe this really, but I'm going to spend some time
convincing you of it anyway so that we're on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First, let's talk about IQ, because a lot of misconceptions about
intelligence come down to politically-motivated (in both directions)
misunderstandings about IQ.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You've probably heard a lot about how IQ is bullshit. This is generally
coming from a very well-intentioned place, but is wrong. There are many
exaggerated or incorrect arguments made on the basis of it, but IQ
itself is extremely well-validated psychometrics which serves a
genuinely useful role, especially for diagnostic purposes during
education. e.g. the reason I've had a proper IQ test was to diagnose a
learning disability that manifested as having &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; large
differences in my verbal and spatial IQs (these gaps have mostly closed
now), which has been very helpful for understanding my own thinking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;IQ is not a perfect measure of intelligence by any means, but nobody
serious claims it is. I highly recommend the book "Intelligence: A Very
Short Introduction" by Ian Deary for a review of the literature, and the
strengths and limitations of IQ. It's also just an excellent and very
readable example of good science communication.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So... given that, what is IQ?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, first off, IQ isn't really one thing. It is a family of different
IQ tests all of which are trying to do roughly the same thing and which
are normalised to the same distribution of scores, but are imperfectly
predictive of each other. That means that if you took two different IQ
tests, you would not expect to get the same result on each. This is
fine, because IQ is not intended to be an absolute measure of anything
in particular, it's a score that indicates general tendencies and is
usefully descriptive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What's it describing? Well, "intelligence" obviously, but what's that?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is, again, not entirely one thing. And this makes sense, right? If
you consider, say, a brilliant scientist and a brilliant novelist, there
are clearly different senses in which you'd expect them to be brilliant
- e.g. one would be better with words and attention to detail, one with
numbers and abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, and here is the bit that is perhaps surprising, generally you would
also expect each of them to be better at the other's area of brilliance
than a typical member of the population. Although they are distinctively
brilliant in their different ways, they tend to be better at a whole
bunch of seemingly unrelated things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is the basic empirical claim that underlies IQ's utility: There are
a number of different tests we can perform that you might reasonably
consider "tests of intelligence" and, surprisingly, they are typically
positively correlated with each other. That is, good performance on one
test tends to predict good performance on another, despite the fact that
when you compare two people one person can do better on one and worse on
another.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A good analogy here might be strength. Someone who can bench press a
higher weight than me can probably also do more push ups than me, or
more reps in their deadlift at the same
weight (None of these are particularly impressive bars to clear, mind, because I
desperately need to start going back to the gym).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We could take a number of measures like this and turn them into an SQ, a
strength quotient, that measures your aggregate strength, and it would
function in very similar ways to an IQ as a general test of ability -
for tasks where you wanted someone strong, someone with a higher SQ is
typically likely to be better. For a specific strength task and two
people with relatively similar SQs it's not terribly surprising if one
is much better than the other, but when there is a very large SQ
difference you should at least be surprised when the person with the
lower SQ outperforms the larger. The world's best dead-lifter and the
world bench press record holder probably have quite similar SQs, but
sometimes one will be better at something and sometimes the other, but
they're both going to be better than me at almost everything strength
related.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;IQ is similar to our hypothetical SQ, but instead of things like bench
press weight, push ups, etc. we instead test things like memory,
performing complex tasks under time pressure, speed of generating
associations, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also different from SQ, in that different things are empirically
true about it. e.g. one of the surprising and deeply frustrating facts
about IQ is that it mostly seems pretty stable over your lifetime. Some
movement is possible (and there is also just random variation based on
the particular test you take and what sort of day you're having), but
generally IQ seems better at reflecting some underlying hard to
influence capabilities than SQ, which responds well to exercise. It's
possible that there are some better tests of underlying strength
capabilities that are less amenable to training that would make for a
similarly stable SQ, but if so I don't know what they are.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The following are things I think are characteristically easier for
people with high intelligence:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quickly picking up new information and skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Following complex arguments and instructions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Holding multiple things in mind at once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recalling relevant information to the current situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Facility with these things is something that people genuinely vary on.
Most of it improves with practice, but even the ones which improve with
practice tend to improve &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; with practice if you're naturally smart,
in much the same way that you get stronger with practice but your build,
nutrition, and general genetic makeup determines a lot about how well
that works for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A wrong but useful analogy here is that smarter people are running their
brains on better hardware - e.g. faster processing, more memory, larger
hard drive, etc. If you're less smart, you can probably still do
everything that a smarter person can do, but at some point the
"software" becomes unusably slow to the point where it's too frustrating
to be worth doing, at which point you might either have to ask someone
else to do it or find an approach better suited to your current
strengths (e.g. by externalising more of the process when you hit the
limits of what you can do in your head).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Intelligence isn't everything&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear, I don't think that your intelligence defines you.
Many people recognised as geniuses had fairly unremarkable IQs, and many
people with high IQs don't achieve anything particularly impressive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my anecdotal experience, very few people are bottlenecked on their
intelligence, because people tend to naturally gravitate to doing things
that are about right for them, so the result is that people are often
doing jobs that someone much less smart than them &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; be bottlenecked
on intelligence in, and someone much smarter than them would find very
boring, but there's usually a pretty wide band around any given job of
people who will basically be fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I think I wanted to include something about how intelligence also
doesn't determine your moral worth etc. I don't have anything non-obvious
to say here other than duh intelligence doesn't determine your moral
worth, and I'm not going to try something long about that now because it
will result in me not posting this instead)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Why am I telling you this?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am telling you this because, if you read my work, I assume you are to
some large degree like me. In particular I expect you are smarter than
average, possibly significantly so. I say this not to flatter you, it's
just really unlikely that you'd be interested in my
overly-intellectualised view of the world if that was not the case.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you're also like me politically or emotionally, you've probably spent
a lot of time in denial about the significance of this, and as a result
being quite unfair to both yourself and the people around you. &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-be-smarter"&gt;I've
previously made strong claims about the irrelevance of empirical
questions about
intelligence&lt;/a&gt; and I
think these are still &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; right, but miss an important point: It's
valid to have this sort of growth mindset attitude to intelligence for
your &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; abilities, but when interacting with other people it results
in being unkind and pushy in ways that do not help you or them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are things you need to know about how intelligence affects you and
others when you are smarter than most of the people around you, and
because of the unspoken privilege nature of intelligence probably nobody
has ever really sat you down and helped you understand those things.
Certainly I was well into my thirties before I finally properly started
internalising this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People are often impressed with things I do - this newsletter and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/HypothesisWorks/hypothesis"&gt;Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt; being major
examples - and I'm usually inclined to dismiss this. Anyone could do the
things I do, right? It's just a matter of hard work, a few tricks, and
an interest in doing it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do, in fact, think this is true to some degree. Given the right
training and willingness to apply themselves, I think most people could
do most of the things I do. Also I think it would be vastly harder for
them to do so, to the point where it might not be worth it. If I see
something instantly that you could see after sitting down for an hour,
or even a couple of minutes, it will often be worth me doing things that
it's not worth you doing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, this resulted in me being very impatient with
people. There were so many things that are so &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt; that it seemed like
nobody could be bothered to do. Did they just not actually care? Were
they lazy?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Over time I learned to be less of a dick about it, and just got better
at explaining things to others, helping them out, and generally
expecting less of them. This was certainly politer than my younger
behaviour, but I don't necessarily think it was fairer, because there
was always a sort of premise that if I show you how this works then
you'll be able to do it as well as me, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result was a great deal of low grade disappointment on my end,
because the answer is rarely that they can do the things I am explaining
as well as I can. There will be plenty of things they can do &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt;
than me, that play to their strengths and interests that I lack, but if
it's something I've spent enough time, interest, and effort on (even if
it felt this way) to get very good at it, chances are it's actually very
hard for them to catch up with me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the result is that over the years I've been, inadvertently,
rather discouraging to some people, by telling them that things are easy
that aren't easy, or that they can do things that realistically they're
never going to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"You can do it" is only a reassuring message if they actually can do it,
and if you've accurately conveyed the work that it takes to do it.
Without that, you're just setting people up for disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Chances are, you're probably making this mistake too. If you often feel
frustrated with the people around you for just not getting it, or for
being weirdly slow or bad at things you find easy, it's pretty likely
that they're not actually slacking off, those things are just much
easier for you than they are for them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;This sucks for you too&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you are significantly smarter than average, either uniformly across
the board or in some particular way, your mind literally works
differently from the people around you. There's a word for that:
Neurodivergence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a general phenomenon of "gifted kid syndrome" that Twitter gets
in a furore about every six months where a bunch of smart kids talk
about how traumatic they found their childhood experience of that, and
the rest of Twitter is about equally divided between calling them
entitled tech bros (regardless of whether they are male or work in tech)
and going "Oh man this is great I haven't had such a good opportunity to
bully nerds in years". Generally there's a large subtext of "You're
talking about an advantage, therefore you don't get to complain about
the negative consequences of having that advantage for you, because
other people have it worse". I am, to put it mildly, not a fan of this
messaging.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, one of the worst problems with problems that derive from
being smarter than the people around you is that they are almost by
definition unrelatable, and people try to make you feel bad for having
them. This is a central feature of what I call &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-07-15-09:33.html"&gt;Nice problems to
have&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we generally mean when we say "nice problem to have" is that
the &lt;em&gt;preconditions&lt;/em&gt; for having this problem are nice to have. i.e. you
cannot have this problem unless some other nice thing happens first.
This is not at all a reliable predictor of the amount of suffering
involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, by definition, "nice problems to have" are ones that
are not going to be shared by a lot of people (otherwise the
preconditions would just be normal behaviour and it wouldn't be a
nice problem to have). As a result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people probably won't be able to relate to it, because their
    lived experiences will be so different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People will be envious of you for the nice thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the defining characteristic about nice problems to have is not
that they are nice, but that you will be afforded no sympathy for
having them. Nice problems to have are the opposite of nice: They
isolate you from the ability to &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/you-should-complain-about-it"&gt;complain about
them&lt;/a&gt;,
which removes a major bonding activity with people who have not been
successful in the same way as you, and also causes you to feel worse
about the problems with those who do not share your burden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The distinguishing feature of high intelligence is that many things are
easy for you that are not easy for other people. On the one hand this is
great, on the other hand this has the knock on effect that you are
constantly under-stimulated, because the world is not designed on the
assumption that you find this easy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to get a sense of what this is like, imagine the following:
You, as you are now, are forced to attend class with a bunch of 7 year
olds doing their times tables. You are required to pay attention. If you
do not pay attention, you will be scolded for this. If you explain you
already understand the material, you will be scolded for disrupting the
class. You have no choice but to sit there, "learning" material you
thoroughly understand, day in day out, while those around you struggle
with it for reasons you can barely understand and wouldn't be allowed to
help with even if you did because that too would be disruptive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much my experience of most classes growing up, and I
think that's quite typical for anyone reasonably smart, because classes
at school are generally not that hard in the first place. This results
in a lot of complaints that are not particularly well received because
they sound like normal problems. A lot of modern childhood just &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;
boring, so when someone complains about that experience it sounds like
they're complaining about a normal childhood
experience (Which, to be clear, is very reasonable to do in its own right. It's
&lt;em&gt;extremely bad&lt;/em&gt; that childhood is boring), and easy to miss that they are
describing a much more boring experience than you're imagining.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This piece is definitely a combination of two problems: It's very stressful
to write, and also I as usual had to do a lot of work explaining what I consider
very 101 level context. I wish I could write a piece where I don't have to
spend the first half of it explaining both "Opression is a real thing" and
"Intelligence is a real thing", but a lot of people need one or both of
these, and most people who don't need one of these very much need the other -
partly this piece was born out of my frustration with having to explain to
so many very well intentioned friends of mine that no IQ isn't actually fake
I promise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is also a good example of explanation as defence - I do tend to over-explain
when I get stressed, on the hope that once people see how very reasonable I'm
being they won't be mad. This is exactly as bad a strategy as it sounds.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway I'd like to be able to write about things like this that are important
and stressful, but apparently I'm not currently able to do that. A pseudonym
might help, but it's not currently worth it to me to have writing that isn't
well integrated into my main body of work.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-31-11:06.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-01-08:19.html</id>
    <title>Abstraction and concretization</title>
    <updated>2022-06-01T08:21:34+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Abstraction and concretization&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-06-01&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is another draft bankruptcy post. It's the only section I actually wrote
from a longer piece called "opposing mental motions".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abstraction is when you take something concrete and make it more
abstract. Dually, concretization is when you take something abstract and
make it concrete. You can also think of these as "Zooming out" and
"Zooming in", which also captures the feeling of them pretty well: As
you zoom out, you see more but can make out fewer relevant details. As
you zoom in, you can see the details clearly but lack the bigger
picture.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abstraction is when you ask "What general principles is this an example
of?". Concretization is "What are some examples of this principle?".
When you abstract, you zoom out. When you reify,&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't just a single step. You can zoom out to more and more general
situations, or you can zoom in on more and more specific details.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, here's a zooming in series:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replacing complex systems from scratch is a fraught business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often you discover that many of the specific features of the
    original system were much harder and less well understood than you
    thought they were (zooming in on the problem from "fraught
    business").&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example in programming we've got the "second system effect",
    where second systems typically go
    badly and part
    of this is trying to recreate all sorts of tacit knowledge in the
    first system and maintaining bugwards compatibility with it for
    users' use case (This isn't the primary thing second system effect usually refers to, but it's still a thing that tends to happen in second systems).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;e.g. when Firefox replaced the original Mozilla web browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A specific thing that happened in that development...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Concretization here is a gradual move from general claim to specific
illustrative anecdote.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Concretization can fail. For example I think it's reasonable to argue
that Firefox is not actually a good example of the general principle
(it's also reasonable to argue that it is), and that maybe even second
system effect isn't really a good concretization because it tends to be
more about the second system trying to do too much (I think it's both).
A concretizing move is not unambiguously correct, and tends to work to
precisely degree that the audience finds it illustrative of the general
point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abstraction is often tightly coupled with looking for an explanation for
specific behaviours and responses.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a trivial example:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was watching Foundation. I hated it, it was super boring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why did I hate it? Well because it was mediocre. It was very well
    executed, but there was nothing interesting about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is an instance of a general pattern where things tend to try to
    polish off their flaws without finding a real strength to emphasise,
    and I tend to hate that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Like concretization, abstraction can fail if you try to move to a
general claim that isn't actually true, or that the concrete claim
didn't demonstrate well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, I was talking about how I hate Rincewind the other day
(Rincewind is the protagonist of most of the early Discworld books. He's
the worst, and is the primary reason you should skip the early Discworld
books). I might have claimed that I hated Rincewind because he was a
protagonist who so clearly didn't want to be there and didn't want
anything to do with the events of the story. This claim doesn't hold up,
and you can see that it doesn't hold up by considering that Bilbo
Baggins (the protagonist of The Hobbit) also clearly doesn't want to be
there, but I like him just fine. If this were the correct explanation
for why I hate Rincewind, it would also work for Bilbo, so it cannot be
entirely correct.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(The actual reason I hate Rincewind is probably that he experiences no
growth or progress at any point. He starts contemptible, remains
contemptible, and at no point has any desires other than the return of
the status quo. The fact that he doesn't want to be there is &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of
it, but it's more like a refusal to engage with his world)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here you can use the two opposing motions to check that your move in one
direction is correct. You zoom out to the claim, then zoom back in to
another example of that claim to see whether it works in the same way as
the original. It doesn't, so the abstracting move must have been wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also fact check in the other direction by going "You have
claimed that this concrete thing is an example of this principle, but is
it not in fact an example of this other principle?". e.g. the
counterarguments to my use of second-system effect as an example of the
complex systems thing have this form: They claim that second-systems go
wrong for different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this way, the two conceptual motions provide a stabilising effect on
each other: The fact that we can move in one direction helps ensure that
we can move in the other direction safely, without the process getting
out of control or away from us.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-01-08:19.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:11.html</id>
    <title>How can we create healthy geniuses?</title>
    <updated>2022-06-05T14:17:42+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How can we create healthy geniuses?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-06-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's another abandoned draft. I think this one was intended for the paid subscriber archives. It's clearly related to &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-do-we-treat-unique-talents-32a"&gt;How do we treat unique talents?&lt;/a&gt;, although I don't remember which one came first.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A recurring talking point in parts of where I hang out on Twitter is
something along the lines of "hypercompetence is a sign of trauma,
healthy individuals aren't hypercompetent". This seems to me to be
broadly true, but I think it's true for nonobvious reasons that I'd like
to explore.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What is Hypercompetence?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hypercompetence is some truly unusual degree of expertise in some
specific skill. People are not, generally, hypercompetent in some fully
general sense, they are hypercompetent at something in particular. This
might be a professional skill (mathematics, writing, golf, etc), a
hobby, a social skill, or something else entirely.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it is worth distinguishing hypercompetence from normal
expertise. Expertise is normal - you just have to work hard at getting
good at a thing, and eventually you will be. In the sense of &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/difficult-problems-and-hard-weeks"&gt;Difficult
Problems and Hard
Work&lt;/a&gt;,
for most people and skills, acquiring expertise in that skill is just
hard work rather than a difficult problem. The hypercompetent individual
however is somehow on a whole other level.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The distinguishing feature of hypercompetence is not that it is
&lt;em&gt;competence&lt;/em&gt; but that it is &lt;em&gt;hyper&lt;/em&gt;. You look at them compared to their
peers, and there is a major qualitative difference between them that
seemingly cannot be explained by normal skill development. I'm imagining
here someone like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Erd%C5%91s"&gt;Paul
Erds&lt;/a&gt;, who was just the
most ridiculously prolific
mathematician.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Also a good example of "healthy people aren't hypercompetent". If the
price for being as good as Paul Erds was that you had to be Paul Erds,
I cannot imagine many people would take that deal.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is a diagram. It may not make much sense because I am bad at
drawing diagrams, but &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; find it helpful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/genius-1.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this diagram imagine each vertical line is a person at their skill
level, so the width of the shaded area is proportionate to the number of
people at that skill level (not realyl to scale - the spike in the
middle is meant to be a single person, but I broadened it for clarity).
So you've got a normal level of expertise that gradually tapers off as
you go up, and then you've got the hypercompetent individual who is out
there on their own, as much above the normal experts as the normal
experts are above the average member of the population.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the following person is exactly as competent as the
hypercompetent individual in our above example, but the skill level
smoothly climbs towards their level:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/genius-2.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They are no less skilled than the hypercompetent individual, and they
are still the most competent individual in the population, but the key
difference is that they are surrounded by people who are only slightly
less competent than they are. There is a clear path to where they are,
with every step along the way populated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am fairly into the goal of helping everyone be the best versions of
themselves, so I much prefer the latter scenario. In the former, there a
sharp cliff where people have no real idea how to improve past other
than this one outlier who we don't know how to replicate. This seems
like a missed opportunity, and I would like to figure out how we can use
instances of the former to produce the latter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Social Superpowers&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At least some hypercompetence, especially with social skills, is learned
in response to suffering. The Ferret argues that &lt;a href="https://www.theferrett.com/2021/01/28/your-superpower-is-a-compensation-for-old-trauma/"&gt;"superpowers" are
compensation for old
trauma&lt;/a&gt;
- if you're, for example, super attuned to other people's emotional
states, it might be because you grew up in an environment where you
needed to be hyperaware of people's emotional states to stay safe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This seems obviously bad (although the competencies arrived at this way
are often good). It can be worth treating the superpower as somewhat
diagnostic of things to look at, but the superpower doesn't just go away
because you fix the underlying issue, you've still learned how to do it.
e.g. I'm very good at explaining things, this turns out to be partly due
to a somewhat inaccurate belief that if people are being mean to me and
I just explain myself really well they'll understand and stop being mean
to me. This works about as well as it sounds, but it appears to have
prompted some useful skill development.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Social superpowers are hard to learn because we're incredibly bad at
teaching social skills, to the point of not even trying. I suspect this
is a scenario where the solution to the problem starts with trying
literally anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Why is genius bad so often?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm more interested in the sort of hypercompetence that might reasonably
be called "genius", which I think tends to arise out of some amount of
baseline ability, adequate resources to make use of it, and some sort of
overriding obsession.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Of the three, I most clearly lack the obsession. I have a bit of an
internal debate as to whether this is missing the boat or dodging a
bullet, but I think for some of the reasons I discuss here my life is
the better for it. Which is not to say that I think I'd be a genius if I could be sufficiently obsessed, but I think I'm at least in with a chance)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being vastly better at something you care about than people around you
who also care about that thing is very unpleasant. It triggers many of
the norms I described in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-29-10:30.html"&gt;The social obligation to be bad at
things&lt;/a&gt;, and
it is the very definition of a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-07-15-09:33.html"&gt;nice problem to
have&lt;/a&gt;,
isolating you from those around you who think they would love to have
your problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is bad because being socially censured and/or isolated is bad for
people. It's also bad because it means they don't have peers they can
readily discuss their problems with to get a different perspective on it
- the run-of-the-mill experts can to some degree serve these functions,
but they can't really relate to the hypercompetent individual that well,
and in many ways are probably more resentful of them than your average
run of the mill citizen who didn't care that much about being good at
the thing in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other reason why it is bad is that it indicates that the
hypercompetent individual is someone who chose to do it anyway, and
that's probably not a sign of a healthy person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A useful heuristic is that, to the best of their abilities and
resources, people get the life they optimise for. A genius "could" have
chosen to just go hang out on the beach and drink margaritas, but that
is not the life they chose. Instead, they chose a life which
deliberately isolates them, because they have decided that they care far
more about their particular level of competency than they do connection
with other people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More than this, they are so far past the typical level of those around
them that what happened is that they got to the point of social censure,
looked around them, and kept going because it was that important to
them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can, perhaps, imagine a healthy person rationally choosing to do that
given sufficient positive motivations to do this. If that's you, no
judgement. But for most people I don't think that's what's happening:
Instead they struggle to connect with others, and as a result they end
up (either deliberately or emotionally) concluding that they can't, and
so they set it aside.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think what often happens here is something akin to the protective
mechanism I described in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/burnout-as-acedia"&gt;Burnout as
Acedia&lt;/a&gt;. People
learn that caring about social connection is not rewarded, and may be
punished, so they learn "not to" care about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know why this particular piece got abandoned. It's been sitting in the drafts folder for too long. I suspect it's simply that I don't know how to answer the question, and so didn't know how to wrap it up.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:11.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:26.html</id>
    <title>Historical contingency</title>
    <updated>2022-06-05T14:39:47+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Historical contingency&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-06-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's another piece from draft bankruptcy. I don't seem to have got very far with it and don't know where I was going with it, but what's here is interesting. The original title was "Life is made of found things" but that's too good a title to let languish in ddraft bankruptcy and I mostly didn't cover the relevant bits.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An early event that I can point to as crucial to how my life has turned
out was a Christmas gift from a family friend, of the GURPS second
edition basic set (the rules for a roleplaying game).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't because GURPS has been a particularly major influence on my
life (Though it was honestly quite good creativity training, and introduced me
to the warehouse 23 basement &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-11-11:03.html"&gt;which is also very good for grinding a
particular skill
set&lt;/a&gt;), it just set
certain wheels in motion. It got me into particular online communities,
where I made a friend, Greg, who was a couple years older than me and
already at Cambridge university. When it came to applying to Cambridge I
didn't honestly have much basis for deciding which college I went to,
and he made a good case for his (Pembroke), which checked out and so I
applied there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may seem like a pretty bad way to pick a college, and perhaps it
was, but I think the reality was that there were many equally good
options, and not much basis to choose between them, so picking one and
verifying that it works well isn't a bad way to do it. I can't say
Pembroke was the optimal choice, but it was a fairly respectable
&lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/10/vocabulary-building-satisficing/"&gt;satisfice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once at Pembroke, I met particular people, made particular friends, had
particular supervisors and life advice. Other colleges would probably
have been about equally good - in some ways better, in some ways worse,
but importantly they would have been &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt;. I'd have met different
people, who would have influenced me in different ways, and my life path
would have diverged substantially as a result.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given how large the effect of a single Christmas gift was, it seems fair
to say that at some point in those four years something would have gone
differently enough that I'd be a very different person today for the
change.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;historical contingency&lt;/em&gt;. The way your life turns out depends a
great deal on prior conditions, and on the choices you make, and the
type of person you are, but it also just depends on chance happenstance
and the knock on effects of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Two-road chances&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm a big fan of the book "Trickster makes this world".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I found this book because it's recommended in Chuck
Palahniuk's (Yes, the fight club guy) "Consider This", a
book about writing, where he lists it among a number of other books that
will fundamentally change your view of the world. I think he was right,
but I'd perhaps struggle to describe exactly how. Let me try.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Reader: I didn't try)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;More contigency&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was originally a very long footnote, but my notebook doesn't currently support footnotes (I'd like it to, but it's fiddly for various reasons)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I read "Consider This" because someone on &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/8GtRapR"&gt;bookchat
discord&lt;/a&gt; recommended it, in the #writing
channel. Bookchat discord exists... I don't remember exactly why. Doing
some research on Twitter identifies the seed of the idea here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.co/ky6KcwnCTN"&gt;https://t.co/ky6KcwnCTN&lt;/a&gt; gives me so many feels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A thing I've been finding deeply frustrating is the difficulty of talking about how much I read without making everyone around me (typically fellow readers) feel guilty about their comparatively smaller reading list.&lt;/p&gt; David R. MacIver (@DRMacIver) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1133686806711590912?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;May 29, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't remember exactly why I read that. Probably because I'd read "The
Year of Reading Dangerously", which I'd read... I think as a result of a
family Christmas present project I was doing? I think it was 2018 that I
created a small family library, which was well received but didn't
actually result in much increase in reading I think.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't actually publicise the discord until some months later:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;I've just remembered that ages ago I was talking about starting a book chat group and got as far as setting up a discord server for it and then got distracted. I still like the idea, so lets give it a go. &lt;a href="https://t.co/MoYdiUAne3"&gt;https://t.co/MoYdiUAne3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; David R. MacIver (@DRMacIver) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1203288683262218240?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;December 7, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I believe this was my first foray into discord, which I knew about
because of a conversation with a friend of a friend some time earlier
(probably in 2018?) in which he expounded on how discord was the future
of social and we were all like "What? Discord? Isn't that a gaming
thing?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can chart this lineage further, but it's not that exciting. Mostly I'm
pointing out that a lot of historical contingency happened here too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I apparently keep failing to write about "Trickster makes this world", as this was also the point at which I abandoned &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-25-09:47.html"&gt;How to be lucky&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general I am surprisingly bad at writing about books I've read.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:26.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:43.html</id>
    <title>How to use philosophy</title>
    <updated>2022-06-05T14:49:23+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How to use philosophy&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-06-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's another draft bankruptcy piece that was from a longer post in which I was apparently trying to puzzle out the meaning of life. This obviously went as well as you'd expect, but here's a section from it that I liked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I used to be part of a support group, where we got together as a group of
four people every three weeks and talked about our problems. In one session I found myself saying "If I never solve the problem and continue
this way for the rest of my life then I guess I would..." and I
couldn't finish the sentence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I know exactly why I couldn't finish the sentence, it was because the
words that I'd intended to say were "be fine with that". I couldn't say
them because as soon as I started I realised they would be a lie, and I
don't lie to support group.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a joke I'm a huge fan of. It goes as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A certain man was in quest of immortality. He read many occult books
on the subject, but none of them gave him any practical advice on how
to become immortal. Then he heard of a certain great sage of the East
who knew the true secret of immortality. It took him twelve years to
find the sage, and when he did, he asked, "Is it really possible to
become immortal?" The sage replied, "It is really quite easy, if you
do just two things." "And what are they?" the man asked quite eagerly.
"First of all," replied the sage, "from now on, you must always tell
the truth. You must never make a false statement. That's a small price
to pay for immortality, isn't it?" "Of course!" was the reply.
"Secondly," continued the sage just say, "I will repeat this sentence
tomorrow." If you do these two things, I guarantee you will live
forever."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(from The Gdelian Puzzle Book by Raymond Smullyan)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sadly I haven't mastered the second step yet, but I'm still working on
the first, and it comes with its own advantages.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After a certain amount of work (largely the sort of things I talk about in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/labelling-feelings"&gt;labelling feelings&lt;/a&gt;) you get to the point where it's really hard to unintentionally say
things you believe to be false, and attempting to do so is often a good
way to find out what you believes different things than you thought it
did.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Philosophy is at its most valuable when combined with this sense,
because you go through the philosophical argument, and you then identify
which parts of it don't feel right, and you use that feeling to guide
yourself to one or more of better self-understanding or better
philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; that you argue yourself into feeling differently,
but that by paying attention to the argument and your feelings about it,
you learn more about both the argument and how you feel about the
subject. Sometimes this changes your feelings, sometimes it changes your
philosophy, sometimes it changes both. The only way to fail is for it to
change neither.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:43.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:53.html</id>
    <title>Getting to know the right people</title>
    <updated>2022-06-05T14:53:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Getting to know the right people&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-06-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's a draft bankruptcy piece about how you solve the problem of finding good people in areas you lack expertise in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;It's hard to find good people these days&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you find a good plumber?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Easy. You ask a good plumber who they'd recommend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No, you can't just google for a good plumber. You'll find a plumber
but they probably won't be a good one. Good plumbers mostly don't
advertise, they've already got far more work than they need. Also
there's a market for lemons problem with unknown tradespeople - most
tradespeople are bad to OK (because most people in any job are bad to
OK), the ones that are good are worth their weight in gold, but you
don't know which you're getting and you don't want to pay the latter
like the former and the latter don't want to work for the rate you'd
be willing to pay the former.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Why do you need a good plumber if you already know a good plumber? Well
because they're a good plumber, and thus they're probably too busy for
you, or because you live on a boat and they don't do boats, or because
you live in a house and they don't do houses, or...)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This makes it sound harder than it is. You can also e.g. ask a good
joiner who they'd recommend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you find a good joiner? Well you find a good plumber and ask them
who they'd recommend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you make new friends? Just go to parties and find people you hit
it off with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you go to parties? Well, ask your friends to invite you along to
them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you find someone to date? Meet people through your friends.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you make those friends? Well if the parties option isn't working
out for you you can always find someone to date and make friends with
their friends.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How do you find a good plumber? Well you make friends with the sort of
people who need plumbers and ask them for their recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This mostly doesn't work in reverse, especially in the city. You
probably can't make friends with your plumber - not because it's
intrinsically impossible, but the interactions you have with trades
people are not necessarily conducive to this. I'm sure it works for
some people from time to time, but it's not a reliable strategy)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;It's all about who you know&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, the way to find the right people is to know the right
people, and the right people generally form a network of similar right
people, so as soon as you know some it becomes much easier to find many.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finding the first couple of right people can be almost impossibly hard.
For some of these things (e.g. plumbers) you can solve this problem by
throwing enough money at it - if you try 10 plumbers eventually one will
probably be OK. You might even have the skill to be able to tell
they're OK. For finding friends in a new city, you can't really buy
friendship, that's not how it works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Your relationship with a network goes in roughly the following levels of
strength:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can be completely disconnected from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can be&lt;em&gt;tenuously connected&lt;/em&gt;to it - you know a small number of
    people in it, but not necessarily particularly robustly. It's
    difficult to ask favours of them because you're in a&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-24-09:46.html"&gt;low trust /
    high
    importance&lt;/a&gt;scenario.
    You need these people to transition to stage 3, but also if you lean
    on them enough to do that they might get upset with you and
    disconnect you from the network entirely, putting you back in
    stage 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are&lt;em&gt;well connected&lt;/em&gt;to the network - you have no trouble
    accessing it, and can use it in the way that you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of the network - you don't just have access to it,
    members of it consider you one of them in some way, and people
    access you through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Moving from weaker to stronger connections to a network is what I think
of as the&lt;em&gt;network bootstrapping&lt;/em&gt;problem. Your future strength is built
on your current strength.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Transitions from (1) to (2) and (2) to (3) are both very hard, and
require quite different skillsets. I'm still myself only really figuring
out what those skillsets are, but I'll do my best to explain.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being in stage (4) is complicated and tends to vary with types of
network - with networks of friends there's a well defined transition (3)
to (4). With networks of plumbers the way you become part of the network
starts with being a plumber. I'm mostly not going to talk about stage 4.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Meet the network&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Suppose you want to connect to a network that you are completely
disconnected from. What do you do?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, first off, bear in mind that you might not be able to do that.
Many networks are Not For People Like You - you're the wrong race,
class, or gender. You didn't go to the right schools. Your family's
ancestors didn't subjugate the right people three generations back along
with the other members of the network. Or maybe you're just too weird
and the people in the network don't want to put up with that. Some
networks are just exclusive and nothing you can do will gain you access
to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is bad, obviously. I want to be clear on this: This is bad. It's a
major source of inequality. I mention it not because I think this is how
networks &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; work, but because prejudice is a real thing that
exists in the world and it's important to recognise that this problem is
linked in with that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But assuming the network is one that you could, in principle, connect to
if you knew how, how do you actually do that?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The common solution for the initial connection to a network is to
bootstrap it from another network. Ask your friends about plumbers, ask
your friends in one city about people to connect to in another. Turn
Twitter friends into IRL friends. This works great if you already have
networks you're well connected to, and those networks are ones that are
well connected to other networks. It requires going out on a limb and
asking for favours from people, which can be socially tricky and anxiety
provoking, but most people are happy to help in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specific tip: It's better to ask for introductions one on one rather
than e.g. posting a message on a shared group. You're more likely to get
an honest response that way, and often what will happen in a shared
group is that the least trustworthy member of the group will post a bad
answer and other people won't find it worth the effort of arguing with
you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If meeting the network via one of your other networks is not really an
option (e.g. because you don't really have any other networks, or
because nobody in your networks knows a good plumber), you need to work
harder.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've got to be honest, I'm still figuring out how this works. Here is my
very sketchy understanding of how things work:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have access to existing networks you are well connected to,
    you really really should be using them. Ask for favours and
    introductions. It's scary, but it's mostly fine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some networks are in some sense "open entry" in that you can gain
    access to them without knowing people. If you have a job, your work
    network is like this (Unfortunately &lt;em&gt;finding&lt;/em&gt; a job is quite network dependent. Chances are if
    you don't have good social connections your first job won't be very
    good, but you can use it to bootstrap to a better one. Recruiters are
    also a way of getting what is basically paid (by the company) access to
    a network and are less good than personal connections but cast a much
    broader net). There are also e.g. churches, activity groups
    (these haven't worked very well for me), professional networking
    events. These are often a good grounding for finding other higher
    value local networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often you can find people in the network you want to connect to and
    just cold approach them. This doesn't work for the plumber problem
    (because if you could find them without a network you wouldn't have
    the problem), but it does work for many other networks. e.g. if you
    want to know people in an academic discipline you can just find and
    follow some people on Twitter in that field who seem nice and start
    talking to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many networks are connected to other more visible networks. e.g. I
    have a hunch that if you walk up to a random house boat and say
    "Excuse me, I have an odd question", pause as they brace themselves
    for the inevitable "what's it like to live on a boat?" question and
    then ask "Can you recommend me a plumber?" they will be utterly
    nonplussed and then recommend you an excellent plumber because
    they're a house boater and they &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; know or know someone
    who knows a good plumber as a result. I suspect going into a
    builders' merchant (which tend to be more visible) and asking one of
    the staff members will have a similar result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general I think this is a problem that requires a level of
systematicity that people often feel uncomfortable bringing to bear on
social problems, and requires you to think about people in fairly
strategic terms. My recommendation is to treat every individual you
interact with as respect, and to otherwise suck it up and deal with it.
It's unpleasant, will result in a fair bit of low-grade rejection, but
generally nothing actually bad will happen and the problem is fairly
amenable to hard work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Starting from zero&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is... harder if you don't have any well connected networks,
which many people don't. It's been about 15 years since I've had this
problem, so I may not be the best to advise on it, but here is how I
understand the process to work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is that some networks are essentially "open entry"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In that case the solution is to build some networks from scratch and
just accept that everything is going to be much harder than it needs to
be until you solve this problem, but also accept that things will become
&lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; easier after you have solved this problem and thus that it is
worth doing (I think a lot of people get trapped assuming that they will
forever be isolated).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the solution is to essentially start with easier to join
networks. A lot of networks make it easy to attach to, because you have
a natural entry point into them. For example:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting a job gets you a professional network, which you can try to
    turn into a friend network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making friends on Twitter is much easier than making friends
    offline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joining a church is supposedly a good way to connect to a
    pre-established network, although this didn't work for me (it was a
    UU church, which may not be representative of the general
    experience).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of professional meetup groups that are basically
    explicitly networking events. Software development is particularly
    good for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People always recommend activity groups for this. This maybe true,
    but it didn't really work out that way for me. I think there's a
    skill to using them this way that I lack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's more support for bootstrapping a romantic partner than a
    friend network, so you can always find people to date using the apps
    and steal their friendship
    network (Personally I found online dating the absolute worst and cannot recommend this strategy at all, but I do know people for whom it's worked).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Connect to the network&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had an empty section here. No idea what I was going to write here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;So what?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm interested in this pattern for a couple of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is just that sometimes I need to actually find a good plumber,
or the equivalent thereof in some other field of expertise. e.g. I've
been vaguely intending to find a good singing teacher and didn't have
the faintest idea of where to start until one happened to attach to my
network of friends (I don't yet know if she's good or not - I start
next week), and I'd like to develop some general skills for doing this
better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think some of those general skills consist of just being better about
noticing this is a thing and asking for introductions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second is that I think it's a really underappreciated form of
inequality. Having a rich set of networks that you are well attached to
makes life&lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt;much easier, and almost by definition we don't really
notice the people on the fringes or who are not well connected to our
networks. Such people are both experiencing a much harder life than
people with better social connections, and also are deprived of an
environment where they can learn those skills of network bootstrapping
because they're not connected to anyone who can teach them!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This also scales way further upwards than I have access to - the
networks you get access to from having the right families, the right
wealth, etc. are things of immense power that I have only the vaguest
conception of)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One consequence of this is that if you're well connected to a network,
helping other people join it is almost certainly&lt;em&gt;hugely&lt;/em&gt;life improving
for them, much more so than you realise. Looking out for people who need
help being onboarded into a network that they might not even know
exists, and helping them connect to it, is one of the most
transformative things you can do for another person, and people should
do a lot more of it than they do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not really sure why this piece was abandoned. I think it was too large and I didn't quite know what I was building up to, partially because I was theorising about a problem that I haven't had a huge amount of success with personally.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
