<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2024-01-03T12:30:38+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-11-02-15:46.html</id>
    <title>Examples of missing support networks</title>
    <updated>2022-11-02T16:13:52+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Examples of missing support networks&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-11-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did a popular tweet:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;The modern condition is mostly trying to do things on your own that people have historically achieved with a large support network and wondering why you're tired all the time.&lt;/p&gt;— David R. MacIver (@DRMacIver) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1586850511726206983?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;October 30, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People are, quite reasonably, asking me for examples beyond the really obvious one of parenting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In truth, I do think my tweet is overly simplistic, and there's a lot more going on. I wrote it partly because I'm living on my own at the moment and really don't like it, and I'm soon going to be living in a much more extended household and very much looking forward to it, and just the general ease of being relied upon and being able to rely on other people for the little things, and the changes I'm expecting (not, I think, to an unwarranted degree - it's different, but it's far from the first time I've lived with others) are many and small, so pointing at specific examples feels almost beside the point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, here are a few big examples. It's not a terribly well thought out list, this is just off the top of my head. It feels more pervasive than these examples would suggest, as I think this is often an aggregate of many small things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the examples that often comes up that makes me think about this is that if you look at a lot of past (and to some degree current) examples of extremely successful scientists etc. who published a million books, it turns out the "trick" behind their productivity was that they certainly had their wife acting as their personal secretary and possibly an entire household because they were aristocracy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a super privileged position of course, but when you look at people trying to achieve similar things today they certainly aren't in that super privileged position but are trying to achieve the same things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You see this at work too - e.g. most positions you would previously have secretaries, admin staff, etc. helping you out, and you would be able to rely on your housewife keeping home for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't a "feminism is bad" take don't worry. But it's important to bear in mind that the workload and assumptions of most jobs are designed around the idea that keeping house, life admin, etc. is something someone else is doing for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also on the work front there was much more in the way of apprenticeships and mentorships, and the expectation that you would have a long-term career at a given place got you (in theory, and sometimes also in practice) a lot more support from a network of people at work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The gig economy in which everyone is an independent contractor is the ultimate version of stripping this community of support away at work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From the consumer side, companies were often part of your support network in a way they no longer are, with increasingly large amounts of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shadow_work"&gt;shadow work&lt;/a&gt; where things that you could previously get help on are now your responsibility, increasing your workload.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of this, there's plenty of absent general community support stuff - having friends you can call on to help you out with a task (e.g. my "&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1564603678484566019"&gt;oh shit how do I get a table upstairs?&lt;/a&gt;" recently), or who will check up on you when you're ill, or whatever is much harder than it should be and historically often was (and to some degree still is in smaller communities, but my impression is that even there it's much less of a thing now).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general one of the big functions of support networks is that they absorb variance - even things that you're fine to do on your own 90-95% of the time, you sometimes need someone else to pick up the slack when things go bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Emotional support is like this too. "Go to therapy" is a way of making an individual responsiblity of emotional problems that often need a whole community to support you. Often historically (and perhaps currently? I'm not very familiar with religious culture except second hand, but my impression this is at least &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; true than it used to be) this would be a religious community. You'd have your priest, but you'd also have other members of the congegration to help you out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the religious content, when you're having a bad time you should be able to draw on a community of people who have your back, and heart emojis on social media when you sadpost doesn't quite cut it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Distributed trust is another one. I've complained about the problem of e.g. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:53.html"&gt;how to find a good plumber&lt;/a&gt; before, but historically this is something you solve by asking your community. Communities maintain social knowledge and help you figure out how to navigate the world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the discussions in the replies to my tweet is about housework and cooking and such. I think this is ambiguously an example - an extended family living under one roof does absolutely count as a support network for doing this, but in the middle class UK/USA cultures I'm most familiar with the lack of these is only "modern" in the sense that it's a 20th century trend. The actual solution we've had more recently which is now also gone was generally housewives again. With both partners working, or someone living alone or with flatmates with whom they don't really share a life, you're implicitly trying to do the work of two people. Not a "large" support network, but support nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of these have "replacements" from technology or the market. I think it's good that those exist, and it's good that people can do more as individuals, but they are far from a complete replacement for a full support network, and based on the slightly overwhelming amount of responses this tweet got, it seems like other people feel similarly.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-11-02-15:46.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-12-08-20:25.html</id>
    <title>Notes on shaking</title>
    <updated>2022-12-09T17:14:30+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Notes on shaking&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-12-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other night I was failing to sleep, feeling very physically agitated and generally unable to relax.
So I followed through on the muscle tension, basically started shaking and shivering, and spent about 10 minutes writhing around on my bed, seemingly in agony (I wasn't, but I think an outside observer would very much have thought I was).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;About a month ago now, I was doing the washing up, and had a bizarrely strong emotional reaction to it, and ended up curling up into a ball on the floor right there in front of the sink.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is all a bit odd, but right now it's actually pretty normal for me. I'm hoping it will calm down as I work out whatever is going on, but so far it seems a moderately unpleasant and very weird but basically harmless and often quite helpful set of practices.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let me start from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Dear penthouse, a funny thing happened to me in bed recently&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A few months ago at the time of this writing, I had a scary conversation with my girlfriend, Lisa.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I knew it was going to go fine, intellectually, but it was about something I have a lot of insecurities around, and that it was very easy emotionally to imagine it going badly. It was quite hard for me to even get out the words for my end of the conversation. I had to bring out the big guns: Having the conversation while cooking and pretending to myself it wasn’t a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It went fine, obviously. Lisa’s great and it was never not going to go fine. We had dinner, and then went to bed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Shortly after we went to bed my legs started shaking. It started as a pretty comically stereotypical knees knocking type motion and gradually progressed into more full blown shakes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I then spent the next two hours doing this, some of it shaking pretty hard. I’m reasonably confident I wasn’t having a seizure, but it's hard to describe what happened in a way that doesn't make it sound an awful lot like having a seizure. The main difference is that it felt like I could stop at any moment by just getting out of bed and calming down, although it did feel like that was what it would take - it wasn't uncontrollable, but it certainly wasn't easy to control.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eventually that’s what I did - it didn’t stop because the shaking stopped on its own, it stopped because after about two hours I decided that I was entirely worn out by this and wanted to stop, so we got out of bed, I had a chamomile tea and calmed down.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;During all of this, Lisa did a mix of holding me, telling me I was safe, and telling me to stop making jokes about it and just let it happen. “You can stop any time you want to, but you have to choose to stop, I’m not going to let you deflect.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lisa handled all of this very well. I was and still am impressed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point in all of this I curled up into a ball. “Everything’s fine, I just need to curl up into a ball for a bit, as one does.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was one of the points at which Lisa told me to stop making jokes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how long I was curled up for but eventually I had to uncurl because I’m nearly 40 and not all that flexible. Some time after that I realised that I was apparently not done and needed to curl back up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that I should mention here is that this whole process was &lt;em&gt;boring&lt;/em&gt;. My conscious mind just found the whole thing weird and vaguely confusing and not that interesting. This is almost certainly a deflection. But there was no conceptual content and very little emotional content.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point I mentioned this and Lisa said that I seemed terrified. There was definitely a bit of an emotional response to that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did cry a few times during the whole ordeal, but it still felt very inhibited.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I slept reasonably well after this (I think Lisa slept less well. This was probably more stressful for her than it was for me).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next day I had DOMS (muscle soreness). One interesting thing is that I had it much more in the leg I normally have chronic pain in, but the actual chronic pain was significantly reduced. This didn’t last, and I’m not sure it was real, but it sure was interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;War never changes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Such a dramatic incident should, naturally, result in a period of reflection and exploration and generally integrating the experience and learning from it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead I spent the next two weeks on a war footing, engaged in a major dispute with my landlord, gearing up for a long protracted legal battle.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This then immediately evaporated when I got sufficiently serious that my landlord backed down, leaving a lot of fighty energy with nowhere to go.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This then was followed by about two weeks of depression in which I was basically nonfunctional. Very tired, spent most of the day watching videos and playing games. No ability to read at all except for very trashy fiction. I think of this as being stuck in a Freeze state, although I’m not sure if that’s strictly accurate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also was a period in which I was having really bad insomnia. Lots of physical agitation at night that wouldn’t go away.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did use the big guns (watching Slay the Spire videos and very occasionally sleeping pills) and that helped a bit but the problem kept getting worse, and the mitigations helped less and less.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One night when I was having a particularly bad night I started paying attention to the physical sensations of the agitation and trying to see what sort of actions they “wanted” to do, and the result was more shaking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was watching a Baalorlord slay the spire video at the time and that felt quite helpful. It gave me something to focus on in between shakes and generally felt like it helped make the whole experience feel safer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It felt quite different from the previous incident with Lisa. They weren’t the same motions particularly, and it was much more voluntary (it’s not exactly voluntary, but the previous incident it felt like I had to actively work to stop it, while this it felt more like I had to actively choose to lean into it in order to get anything to happen).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other big difference is roughly... where the motion starts? Before it started from my legs and spread upwards, while this feels very focused on my upper body and sometimes spreads down into my lower. There’s also a lot more almost writhing around feeling out the right motion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing about this is that after every shake that I felt calmer. It was very specifically a place for the physical agitation to go. As a result, after about half an hour of this, I was able to fall asleep despite previously feeling very far from being able to do so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then the next day I was out of my Freeze state. I wasn’t feeling amazing, but I could think and read and generally function for the first time in weeks.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since then I’ve found most nights have at least some of this. Not necessarily a huge amount, but often when I’m in bed there’s a bit of shaking and writhing around as part of getting relaxed enough to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What the fuck is going on?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's talk about Trauma Releasing Exercises.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Trauma releasing exercises (TRE) are a therapy tool the basic idea of which is that the natural response to traumatic events is to shake it off once you’re safe, and that we habitually suppress these shakes because they seem weird, and this causes a build up of trauma stored up in the muscles that we have to shake off. Their evidence for this shaking phenomenon is how people in shock behave and that various cultures do have more common habits of shaking after big events (the former seems true to me, I don't trust amateur anthropology so I'm somewhat reserving judgement on the latter, but it certainly could be true).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m a bit sceptical of this story but it certainly seems more plausible to me now than it did before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do basically subscribe to the theory that emotions are experienced bodily, and that the way to better understand your own emotions is to learn to pay attention to your own body.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think also that muscle tension is often a way to regulate emotions. Certainly when I'm having a strong emotional reaction, I can literally "keep hold of myself", in a way that feels very physical like I'm tensing the appropriate muscles for control.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The "trauma is stored in the body" school of therapy seems to be about habitual patterns of muscle tension like this. If you're always holding yourself very tightly, keeping control of your emotions, then you'll build up habitual patterns of tension in your muscles, and learning to relax that tension is required if you want to have proper access to those emotions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;TRE are exercises designed to tire out your psoas muscle and trigger the shaking response that you see after a triggering event, in an attempt to "release the trauma" that you are storing in these patterns of muscle tension.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve done them before and they’re super weird and interesting, but I didn’t notice much therapeutic effect. That being said, the initial leg shakes in my first night of this seemed a lot like the shakes from doing a TRE. I thought I’d try them again and see what happened.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t feel much like the shaking I’ve been experiencing. There’s definitely a similarity in the leg movements, but it feels more purely physical.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing I did notice doing these is that I could almost feel the shape of things in my body and patterns of muscle tension from where the shakes were. In particular the shakes seemed to avoid my injured knee.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think that having done these in the past was an interesting reference point that made the spontaneous shaking feel safer, and they’re a good work out so I may try them some more, but I’m sortof convinced that these exercises are just coincidentally replicating the shape of something useful without being therapeutically useful themselves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do recommend them giving them a go though. They're interesting and worth trying at least once.
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WZOtBY4RTLo"&gt;This is the guided video I use&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I really don't think they work, except by accident. Possibly they provide a good basis for creating a space in which to do the real thing, but they are not themselves the real thing and can't force it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Interpretation as a barrier to right action&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a principle I tried adhering to for a while. It's very sensible, seems theoretically well grounded, and is all round good advice except for the fact that as far as I can tell it doesn't work. Worse, it's so close to something that does work that it distracts you from the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The principle is this: If you would describe your feelings as "I feel like I want to just curl up into a ball", why not just curl up into a ball?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The answer is because if you do that then now you still feel the same way but also you feel kinda dumb. It doesn't help.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's the corrected version of the principle: If you want to curl up into a ball, why not curl up into a ball?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The difference is annoyingly subtle. It's in the lack of an interpretive layer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me give you an unrelated example. You know the thing where doctors tap your knee to test your reflexes? I was quite bad at it as a kid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How can you be bad at a reflex test?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, the first time the doctor tapped my knee I was like "Ah yes, I know what this test is, I'm supposed to kick" and kicked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as being on a significantly longer delay, the kick was much more exaggerated than the reflexive jerk would be. It was very clear to the doctor that this was Not The Thing. He laughed and told me just to let it happen.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The next time he tapped my knee, I knew I wasn't supposed to kick, so my leg didn't move at all. Turns out, the reflex response is pretty easy to suppress if you try, it just requires holding your muscles tightly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I assume we must have got the exercise working eventually but I don't remember for sure. This was like 30 to 35 years ago now, my memory is a bit fuzzy on the details.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if someone throws a ball at you, and you see it, and you think "Ah, a ball, I should catch it", and move based on that thought, you'll probably fail to catch the ball.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are two different ways you can respond to external events. One goes as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Observe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpret the observational data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Act on that interpretation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other goes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Observe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Act on that observation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The former isn't bad, in that it inserts a great deal of intelligence into the loop that allows you to figure out things you wouldn't otherwise and act beyond your current capabilities, but it's also not exactly good. The results are awkward, and often poorly suited in detail. They tend to be clumsy and unnatural seeming, often poorly timed, overly strong, overly weak, or otherwise not quite fitting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The same holds with acting on internal observations I think.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When doing Focusing, in the Gendlin sense, you are trying to put a description on a "felt sense", a physically felt bundle of sensations that capture some crucial feeling. You follow the felt sense until you find a description that feels right.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The most important sensation to pay attention to in Focusing is "no, that's not quite it". The difference between not quite right and the right thing is, to quote probably-not-Mark-Twain the difference between lightning and lightning bug.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Following through on your interpretation of the felt sense rather than the felt sense itself feels very much like a lightning bug, as do Trauma Releasing Exercises.
Acting on the motion feels like lighting. Based on what actually happens, it probably looks a bit like being struck by lighting too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Is this good?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Having borderline seizure-like episodes and randomly having tic-like symptoms or curling up on the floor in the middle of washing up the dishes seems bad, but I think this is good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Certainly my quality of sleep has massively improved since figuring out how to do this. There's a lot of physical agitation that I sometimes experience on bad nights that this allows me to release that agitation in a way that makes sleep possible on nights when it would previously have been a massive struggle.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It also seems to allow me to get out of Freeze states, in a way that nothing I've previously tried behaviour ever has.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If that was all it did, this would be a huge massive win, but it also feels something like... this is what it's supposed to be like?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think all the random shaking is supposed to be normal, but it feels like I'm clearing out a massive backlog of things that I've been suppressing for years.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also made me far more sensitive to certain sensations I think I've historically ignored. I'm much more aware of certain emotional states that were previously a complete mystery because I couldn't really put words to them. I still can't really, certainly not a good Focusing handle for them, but it turns out that some feelings are better expressed as motions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know where this is going - it feels like I've unlocked a missing piece of how things are supposed to work, and I'm still building out the foundations of that before I can even properly integrate it into the rest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Tracing my steps&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't want this to sound like I know what I'm talking about. I'm just reporting on a bunch of weird-ass experiences and my interpretation of them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But given that I think this is probably good, if you've got similar problems to me it might be worth trying to figure out how to do it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How? Uh... excellent question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The particular mental motion that triggers something like this is something like... notice a particular pattern of muscle tension, and stop stopping it from doing what it wants to do, then do whatever comes naturally next.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I expect that this explanation is completely unhelpful if you can't already do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something that's helpful for triggering it more clearly is to notice the tension, tense it up further, and do a sort of "follow up on the rebound" - when you release the clench, your muscles move in a particular way, just let them keep doing that, and if any sort of movement naturally completes from there, let that happen.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I find this works particularly well for tension in my shoulders, and that often once I've started the motion, it often works downwards from there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another thing I've found helpful is being cold and then warming up. Literally being in a cold room, then covering myself in a fuzzy blanket, seems to be a great way to unblock access to this when in a Freeze state. This is I think consistent with how shock works - people start shivering when you cover them in a warm blanket.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do think that giving the trauma releasing exercises is probably a good starting point for learning what it feels like to just shake uncontrollably. As I say, I don't think it really triggers the same effect, but I do think having done them made all of this more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Probably experimenting with just noticing muscle tension, and trying out movements and seeing which ones feel appropriate, and which ones trigger that "not quite right" sensation, is a good starting point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I expect though the only way to learn to do this is to just do it, and that anything that lets you achieve it makes it easier the next time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you do experiment, please let me know what does and doesn't work for you. I'd also be up for any reading recommendations if you already know about all this and have recommended tools for working with it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-12-08-20:25.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-12-10-14:53.html</id>
    <title>Three key problems with Von-Neumann Morgenstern Utility Theory</title>
    <updated>2022-12-10T16:38:16+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Three key problems with Von-Neumann Morgenstern Utility Theory&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-12-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People semi-routinely argue about Von-Neumann Morgenstern Utility Theory with me.
This rarely goes well - it doesn't change any minds and I don't enjoy it - so I am writing up what I think the core of my objections once and for all so that I can stop having this argument.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't really expect it to convince you, but also I'm not going to argue with you on this subject until you've read it and can tell me a good reason why you disagree.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am not going to argue that VNM theory is never useful, nor that utilities in general are not. I am going to argue that VNM theory is an overly idealised model of agent behaviour that if you try to apply it to a general purpose agent fails in crucial ways.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;A brief recap&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;VNM theory works as follows: You have a finite set of outcomes \(O_1, \ldots, O_n\), you are given lotteries which are some precisely known mixture of these outcomes, and you have the ability to make binary choices between these lotteries, where given any two lotteries you should either strictly prefer one of them or be indifferent between the two.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Under some allegedly reasonable assumptions, for any of these outcomes \(O_i\), you should be indifferent between it and some lottery \(p B + (1 - p) W\), where \(B\) is the (possibly joint) best outcome of the \(O_i\) and \(W\) is the (possibly joint) worst outcome. This \(p\) can then be considered the utility of \(O_i\) and under a bunch more (mostly actually reasonable) assumptions you should be making your choice to maximise the expected utility of lotteries.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Fredkin's paradox, the doom of VNM theory&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've written about two key issues with this setup before:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2018-09-09-21:02.html"&gt;Physical agents can't implement discontinuous functions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-06-07-06:51.html"&gt;You may have to do an infinite amount of computation to get that utility&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Both of these are variations on a key problem with VNM theory: It ignores the cost of decision making, which comes up as &lt;em&gt;Fredkin's paradox&lt;/em&gt; - the difficulty of making a decision between two very similar options is much greater than the difficulty when one is much better than the other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first part is about physical difficulties with measurement - you can only know the probabilities up to some finite precision.
VNM theory handwaves this away by saying that the probabilities are perfectly known, but this doesn't help you because that just moves the problem to be a computational one, and requires you to be able to solve the halting problem.
e.g. choose between \(L_1 = p B + (1-p) W\) and \(L_2 = q B + (1-q) W\) where \(p = 0.0\ldots\) until machine \(M1\) halts and \(1\) after and \(q\) is the same but for machine \(M2\).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second demonstrates that what you get out of the VNM theorem &lt;em&gt;is not a utility function&lt;/em&gt;. It is an algorithm that produces a sequence converging to a utility function, and you cannot recreate even the original decision procedure from that sequence without being able to take the limit (which requires running an infinite computation, again giving you the ability to solve the halting problem) near the boundary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Both of these have the same core problem: In order to be able to identify the decision boundary that is essential for the VNM theory to work, you have to be omniscient. If you accept the flawed premise of knowing the probabilities with perfect knowledge, you can get away with only logical omniscience, but in order to know the probabilities with perfect knowledge you also have to be actually omniscient and not constrained by mere mortal abilities like having to observe the world to acquire knowledge of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is this a nitpicky objection? Kindof, but I think it's important, for two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It does fairly directly demonstrate why the central thing required for VNM theory to work cannot possibly work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It does so in a way that shows that the model of VNM theory fails precisely because it fails to capture the behaviour of actually reasonable agents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The correct thing to do with Fredkin's paradox is to not care about it. An actual agent faced with anything like the VNM setup will choose non-deterministically in the region of indifference, with much of the nondeterminism coming from imprecision in their measurements. When your two alternatives are very close together, your preference will be more or less like a coin toss, when your two alternatives are very far apart it will be close to (or actually deterministic), but the continuity argument shows that you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to have intermediate values - e.g. sometimes you'll pick \(A\) over \(B\) about 60% of the time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Bounded and known preferences&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The VNM setup uses the finite number of options to ensure that there is a best and worst outcome, and calculates your utility in terms of those best and worst options. Additionally it assumes that you know exactly how bad literally the worst thing that can possibly happen is and how good literally the best thing that can possibly happen is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means that VNM theory can only be useful in very well understood bounded domains. Getting to the point where you can even start running the computation for utility of somethign requires \(O(n)\) work to figure out the best and worst thing, you need to be familiar enough with all the options to have real preferences over them, and also there just can't be that many options.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, VNM theory is very poorly suited to dealing with anything to do with money, which has unbounded utility. This is pretty impressive going for a normative utility theory. Good job failing to handle literally the most utility like problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You could argue that there is a maximum amount of money that matters and for many bounded domain cases that's true and reasonable, but if that maximum amount is "literally the entire world economy", I argue that even if you treat this as the best possible thing, you have really very little conception of how good it is, and cannot possibly do so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even if you could have a reasonable opion, it's worth bearing in mind that you are now multiplying very large numbers by very small numbers. This makes the VNM utility extremely impractical, because you've basically reduced choosing what to have for lunch to the problem of Pascal's Wager.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Updating preferences as a result of decisions&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In making its reasonableness assumptions, VNM theory equates two things that are distinct in any real agent: Instantaneous preferences and actual decisions over time. For example, it uses the possibility of being dutch booked as an argument against intransitive preferences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But dutch booking is not a thing you can do to preferences, it's a thing you can do to decisions, and you can only use dutch books to extract infinite money from intransitive decisions if the agent is forced to make the same decision every time, i.e. can't learn from experience.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Dutch booking is more complicated with non-deterministic decisions, but a broadly similar argument applies where instead of requiring transitivity you require certain bounds on sums of cycles. We're not going to worry about that here)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One easy way to learn from experience is to stop accepting offers from people who are trying to dutch book you, but even without that many patterns of intransitive decision making that are exhibited during learning are not susceptible to dutch booking, because they converge over time to transitive ones. e.g. an agent playing a multi-armed bandit problem (this again assumes imperfect knowledge of probabilities which VNM theory assumes away so isn't strictly applicable, but it's a good example) will regularly swap its preferences between arms as it plays, exhibiting many cycles.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One reason these differ is assumed away by VNM theory, which is that you know the probabilities. In actual decision making, you learn the probabilities through making choices which refine your world model. e.g. if you look at a multi-armed bandit algorithm, even though it has a perfectly well defined utility function, it routinely reverses its decisions as it learns more about the distribution of results of pulling a particular lever.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even with known probabilities, real agents will change their mind, because often the only way to know how to value something is to try it. If you offer me a Durian, I'm probably going to say yes. If you offer me a Durian a second time, I'm probably going to say no. This isn't inconsistency, it's just learning from experience.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another way decisions can change is because choices you make have actual consequences. For example, consider a betting agent. Given a choice between two monetary lotteries, one of which satisfies the Kelly criterion and one of which doesn't, they should pick the one that does, or in general the one that maximises the expected logarithm of their bankroll after making it, but then after the lottery is run their bankroll will be different, and so their future preferences will change.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, I already know the objection, VNM theory is about states of the world, not individual decisions, but this objection falls flat for several key reasons:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It justifies the reasonableness of its assumptions based on patterns of decision making, not behaviour of preferences, because without any consequence for preferences anything goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number of possible states of the world is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; large, which runs into the problem that it is poorly suited to large and unbounded domains, so it is also bad for this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Where does VNM theory work?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Basically it doesn't. VNM theory is bad, even in situations where utility theory is good.
It is a poor normative argument that people have taken far more seriously than it deserves, with most of its foundation points failing to actually be viable for real agents.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That doesn't mean utility theory is never useful.
In general, people &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; converge over time to some sort of approximately utility maximising behaviour for some utility function in small domains that can be well understood and that have strong incentives for maximisation. Even there you will tend to run into the Fredkin's paradox problem, with significantly more nondeterminism at the decision margins than VNM theory would suggest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It does mean however that in large unbounded high uncertainty environments with agents who learn their preferences over time and actually impact the state of the world, VNM theory cannot possibly predict their behaviour, and its claims to have normative force over their behaviour don't hold up.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-12-10-14:53.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-12-20-17:21.html</id>
    <title>Action generators</title>
    <updated>2022-12-20T18:13:15+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Action generators&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-12-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Quick, do something.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now do something without leaving your current position. e.g. if you're sitting down stand up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, without leaving your current position, do something with your left hand.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, without leaving your current position, do something with your left hand without touching anything with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, without leaving your current position, do something with your left hand that feels good, without touching anything with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Each of these instructions is an action generator: Something that prompts you to act in the world. These can be instructions, but they can also be observations, thoughts, etc. If a ball comes flying towards your head, you hopefully duck. Action generator!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Any action generator has the default response to it: Do nothing. When I told you to do something, you probably ignored it and kept reading (this is of course doing something). Possibly by the end the instructions were interesting enough that you went "Oh, sure, I'll give that a go.", possibly not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doing nothing isn't always a good idea. If you have a do nothing response to the ball flying towards your head, you get hit. Hope it's not a cricket ball. Those hurt. A lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing about the list of action generators I gave above is that each of them is more specific than the one preceding it, and yet it is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; unlikely that the actions generated by the last are ones you would have thought of in response to the first action generator.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is because the broader the action generator is, the more possibilities there are, the harder it is to navigate to any particular possibility in particular.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also because the more specific action generator gives you permission. The ball coming at your head generates an action of duck, so you duck. You could have ducked even if the ball wasn't coming at your head, but why would you?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Action generators are often useful for doing things that you could have done with a broader action generator but, for one reason or another, didn't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If someone is coming around, that's an action generator to clean your house. You could have done this at any time before, but you didn't. That isn't necessarily bad, but sometimes you &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to do it before and still didn't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This points to the fact that an action generator really has at least two properties:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What actions it &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; generate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What actions it encourages you to take.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Someone coming over doesn't constrain your actions much compared to the default action generator, but it does create a very strong incentive to tidy up, in much the same way that you're free to do whatever you like in the lead up to the ball arriving, but after that if your actions have not taken the ball into account you're going to deal with the consequences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing I'd like to highlight from the hand thing is that to a large degree, making the action generator more specific automatically creates an encouragement to action, because it lowers the activation energy to acting by removing a large class of decisions. "What should I do with my life?" - vast and impossible set of decisions. "What should I do today?" can still be pretty daunting. "What should I eat for breakfast?" - now pretty accessible. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1603792788667207681"&gt;Onward! Towards the abyss&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another thing worth noting is that any theory about the world is an action generator. You create a model of the world, and this gives you a set of actions that makes sense under that model. For example, when we &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/i/53848690/inventing-symbolic-games"&gt;invent symbolic games&lt;/a&gt; to improve our ability at something, we are doing this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly, a theory works as an action generator &lt;em&gt;even if it's wrong&lt;/em&gt;. You can still adopt the theory and act based on it, and often those actions will be perfectly fine, because they're interesting in their own right even if the reasons that lead to them aren't correct. This is akin to the saying that all models are wrong, but some are useful. All models are useful, in that having action generators is useful because it may lead you to things that you wouldn't otherwise have thought of.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think many "bad" theories persist because they're useful action generators. More, though, I think often bad theories are better than good theories, because they generate actions that you would never have thought of if you were constrained to adopting more reasonable theories.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, I think a lot of therapy modalities work like this. My reliably experience reading therapy books is that they explain their theory and I go "lol, sure" and they provide their evidence and I go "an easier explanation of this is that you're lying", and then I do their exercises and... well, most of the time it doesn't work, but it does something interesting often enough that it was worth reading the book.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is often the case: It's worth having a stable of bad theories lying around that generate actions that you wouldn't otherwise have thought of and that are basically harmless in the worst case, and possibly interesting in the best case.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-12-20-17:21.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-02-14-23:37.html</id>
    <title>My current protocol for energy levels</title>
    <updated>2023-02-15T04:39:37+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;My current protocol for energy levels&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2023-02-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People keep asking me questions about my recent miracle increase in mood and energy level, so this is a full write up of what I'm doing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: None of this is medical advice. I'm not competent to give you medical advice. This is a document of what I'm currently doing,
which it may or may not help you to emulate, but also depending on your current health situation some or all of it may not be a good
idea for you, and I'm not competent to tell you which bits.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've recently had a really dramatic increase in mood and mental energy levels, reversing a years long trend of things getting worse
and worse for me over time.
I credit this mostly to taking Inositol, although there are some confounding factors and fears of placebo effect that make me
less confident in that than I'd like to be (I'm still very confident, but it feels obviously true and then I have to add in
a bunch of "OK, but..." caveats).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The theory goes as follows: Inositol is an essential sugar that the brain uses. Its lack causes issues in energy levels and mental health,
among other things, and as a result it can be an effective treatment for those. It is produced by digestion, so if you have digestive
problems you may not be producing enough of it, and supplementing with it can plausibly help.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To the best of my ability to determine the above is pretty established science, though inositol as a medical intervention for these issues
does not seem to be common (it's considered an established treatment for PCOS, and the fact that it can help mood seems to be known but not commonly used).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I started taking inositol after &lt;a href="https://acesounderglass.com/"&gt;Elizabeth Van Nostrand&lt;/a&gt; suggested it in a conversation, and immeditaely felt more like a functioning human being than I had in years. I've mentioned this on Twitter and discord and a bunch of people went "Well I'll give it a go" and some small but non-negligible fraction of them seem to have seen the same results. I think we're up to 5 or 6, but I don't know how many people have tried it. My guess is this corresponds to somewhere in the 1-10% region, in a population probably heavily selected for having these problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Known side effects of inositol which at least one person has reported after this are headaches, tiredness, and stomach problems. I had some stomach problems at the beginning, but not particularly bad ones and frankly I'm used to a bit of stomach pain so I ignord it. It seems to have gone away, but that may be because of other things I'm doing to fix my digestion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In addition, there may be long-term consequences (unclear to me if &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; consequences) to taking inositol. I don't really understand these yet,
but the reason it gets used as a treatment for PCOS is that it has effects on a bunch of hormones. I'm currently ignoring this, but do need to do
some detailed research. I do think at the levels I'm taking it at it's probably pretty safe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What I'm taking&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently taking 1-1.5g of inositol in the morning, and sometimes I take another 0.5-1g in the afternoon. Variation is because I'm doing some not very scientific experiment to find the right amount and timing. I started at 0.5g first thing and even that made a big impact.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently treating 2g as the maximum definitely safe daily dose, but it's likely that it's higher than that. 2g is roughly the amount that your body is supposed to produce per day, PCOS treatment protocols seem to be 4g or even higher. At present I have no plans to go above 2g, and am hoping to reduce that over time if the rest of what I'm doing works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rest of what I'm doing, which is plausibly what made the stomach side effects from inositol go away, is an attempt to actually fix the digestion problems that I think are probably underlying why inositol has such a large benefit for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bioandme.co.uk/"&gt;Bio&amp;amp;Me&lt;/a&gt; "Super seedy and nutty" porridge every morning (I've actually been doing this one for about a year)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://athleticgreens.com/en"&gt;Athletic greens&lt;/a&gt; every morning as an aggressive nutritional supplement for anything I might not be getting properly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strong dose of probiotic every morning. I am currently using three sachets of &lt;a href="https://www.vsl3.co.uk/"&gt;VSL3&lt;/a&gt;. I'm not sold on this being the correct probiotic, but it does seem to help. My plan is to cycle through various brands of plausible probiotics. I will try &lt;a href="https://www.visbiome.com/"&gt;visbiome&lt;/a&gt; next, and possibly &lt;a href="https://seed.com/"&gt;Seed&lt;/a&gt; after that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B01I3O6PJ4/"&gt;Digestive enzymes&lt;/a&gt; with every meal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm also trying to eat a little bit of sauerkraut every day. Fermented vegetables are meant to be good for gut health, and I have problems with digesting brassicas, and some vague notion that eating a little bit of it while also trying to repair my gut microbiome might encourage the sort of bacteria that are good at digesting brassicas. This seems to be at the bare minimum not hurting. Maybe it's also helping, who knows.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've also today started adding a scoop of freeze-dried pineapple to my morning green-stuff-and-bacteria drink. There are a bunch of ultra low confidence reasons why this might be a good idea, but I wouldn't put much faith in this particular suggestion for now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My stomach and digestion seem to be significantly happier as a result of these, although I have no idea at the moment whether this will result in a long term fix or just a short term palliative.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-02-14-23:37.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-06-20-17:00.html</id>
    <title>Larger selves</title>
    <updated>2023-06-21T10:54:55+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Larger selves&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2023-06-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note: This is transcribed verbatim from my physical notebook, so when I refer to a notebook in here I'm talking about an actual book I'm writing in with an actual pen. I just didn't want to inflict my hand writing on you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are subjects I don't know how to write about in a way that communicates why they are important to me, either because they always come out flat, or because they come out disordered in their intensity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the subjects that always comes out flat is that I practice a sort of religion. We're a congregation of one person (me) and not that interested in converts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Whenever I try to explain it, it comes out sounding like either a joke or some very dry philosophy. Honestly it started out that way. But this matters to me, at quite a personal level, even if I don't know how to show it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The joke version goes thus: I believe in a supreme being, in that I think beinghood is closed under union, thus the set of all beings has a superema (a maximal element).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't say it was a funny joke.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Technical nitpick: Beings are actually closed under &lt;em&gt;interaction&lt;/em&gt;, not union. As a result this gets tricky when you bring relativity into the picture. Don't worry about this.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The part of this that actually matters to me is that consciousness, and to some degree personhood, happens at every scale. As I write this, I am not having thoughts and recording them on the page. I am thinking by writing. The thought occurs not in my head, but in the combined head/hand/notebook system. Me plus a notebook behaves like a different, albeit very similar, entity to me without.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The same occurs in conversation. As you and I talk, the pair of us think together. Thoughts are had that we could not have had alone. There is an &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; above any beyond there being a you and separately also a me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is true with action as well as thought of course. I can do things with a knife that I cannot do without. You and I can do things together that we cannot do alone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Less obviously, it is true of feeling too. Empathy is not feeling what another feels, but it is a sort of second-person form of feeling. As we synchronise there is a form of shared feeling that &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; have. This is particularly obvious in sex or dance, but also in e.g. games or pair programming. There is a shared feeling between us.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something that thinks, acts, and feels seems to me to be a legitimate candidate for personhood. It's certainly not a person in exactly the same way that a human is, but it still seems like a person to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You and I together form an us-person distinct from but overlapping with the I-person and the you-person. The same holds for me and my notebook (although I don't think my notebook on its own counts as a person. I sometimes think it's useful to think of personhood as continuous rather than binary. In this view, it is merely not much of a person).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you like, you can substitute "conscious entity" for "person" here, but for me "person" carries more of the right moral and emotional undertones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This extends further upwards of course. A team has personhood. A company. A country. The world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think it requires a human in the mix to be a person. We're not too far off having AI that I'd consider clearly warranted some degree of personhood. A dog seems clearly nearly or wholly a person to me. A forest is at least as much of a person as a dog.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also extends downwards. Any reasonably careful degree of attention to yourself and your experience shows that you are made up of parts. You see this with mixed feelings ("part of me feels X while another part feels Y"). Internal family systems and other types of parts work recommend treating these parts of you as people. Maybe they are.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also see this with aphasia. You can't just recall. The best you can hope for is create a space for the part of you that knows the answer to put it when it's done.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are not a single unitary entity any more than the notebook and I are - we are cooperating modules working together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This starts to sound very "the self is an illusion" but that's bullshit. The self is no more an illusion than a team is. A team is made up of individuals, but the team is created when those individuals work together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The team exists in the connections as well as in the parts, and there is a health and function of the team above and beyond that of the individual parts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Much of why this matters to me is that I want to be a better person, and I want to participate in being a better person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We as people confined to single bodies need to embrace that embodiment, and to learn to self better, but part of how we do that is by learning to participate in larger, better, selves that extend beyond us.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-06-20-17:00.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-07-27-13:03.html</id>
    <title>Adaptive parallel test-case reduction</title>
    <updated>2023-07-28T09:05:39+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Adaptive parallel test-case reduction&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2023-07-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a very simple algorithm I call "adaptive parallel deletion", which I think of as completely standard and thus often forget that literally nobody but me uses.
I haven't written it down anywhere, so here's me finally getting around to doing that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This algorithm is a component of test-case reduction that replaces the classic delta debugging algorithm - that it is, it takes some sequence and produces a subsequence of it satisfying some condition,
such that if you remove any one element from its output the condition is no longer satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The core features of adaptive parallel deletion are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When there are large reductions that can be made, it will usually run in &lt;code&gt;O(log(n))&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When there are no reductions that can be made, it will run in &lt;code&gt;O(n)&lt;/code&gt;, but with the work scaling to as much parallelism as you can give it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will scale fairly gracefully in between the two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here it is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;single_pass_delete&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="sd"&gt;"""Returns a version of `test_case` that satisfies `condition` and&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    is "one-minimal" in the sense that you cannot delete any single&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    member of it and have it still satisfy the condition."""&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;can_delete&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:])&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Scan in parallel for the first location where we can delete&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# a single element of the list. If no more elements are deletable&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# this will run with as much parallelism as we can give it.&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;find_first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;can_delete&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;except&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;NotFound&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="k"&gt;del&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Now that we've found an area where there's at least one deletable&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# element, we hope that it's part of a large chunk of deletable elements.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# This finds an integer k so that we can delete the next k elements&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# and not the next k + 1 elements, running in O(log(k)). This hopefully&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# lets us delete a reasonable large chunk at a time.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;find_integer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;can_delete&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;del&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Because we chose k such that k + 1 elements are not deletable, we know&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# that the element left at i (if any, we might have deleted the whole list)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# is now not deletable, so we increment i to skip past it on the next&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# iteration. This is purely a performance optimisation, but in the worst&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# case might cause us to make twice as many calls to `condition` as we&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# need to if we skip it.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Where the functions this uses are &lt;code&gt;find_integer&lt;/code&gt; that I've &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2019-04-30-13:03.html"&gt;previously written about here&lt;/a&gt; which is just an exponential probe and binary search (so runs in &lt;code&gt;O(log(k))&lt;/code&gt; when it returns &lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt;) and &lt;code&gt;find_first&lt;/code&gt; is defined as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;itertools&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;islice&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;NotFound&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="ne"&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;pass&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;find_first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;predict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="sd"&gt;"""Returns the first element of `target` that satisfies `predicate`,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    or raises `NotFound` if none do."""&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;raise&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;NotFound&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;parallelism&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cpu_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parallelism&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;raise&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;NotFound&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ThreadPoolExecutor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;max_workers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;parallelism&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;executor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;it&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;iter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk_size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;islice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;it&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk_size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class="k"&gt;raise&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;NotFound&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;zip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;executor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk_size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular &lt;code&gt;find_first&lt;/code&gt; is designed so that when it does not find an answer it scales up rapidly to be embarrassingly parallel, but when it finds an answer early on it doesn't do much redundant work (you still have the overhead of the thread pool and such, but it doesn't actually run much extra code).&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-07-27-13:03.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-02-12:48.html</id>
    <title>January is a daily writing month</title>
    <updated>2024-01-02T12:56:38+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;January is a daily writing month&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've long been a disbeliever in new years resolutions, but I'm giving them a go this year. I'm calling them "New Years Aspirations" rather than "resolutions" because that makes me feel better about them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My three aspirations for the year are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See my friends in person more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue to improve my health and exercise levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(3) is a bit of a cliche but in my defence I've been working on it for about four months already, so it's not a fresh start so much as a "that thing I'm already doing but more so".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(2) is the main focus of this though: I've not been writing recently. My &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/why-to-explain-things-you-already"&gt;last newsletter issue&lt;/a&gt; is from September! Literally more than 3 months have passed since I wrote a newsletter issue. I don't like that. I feel bad about it, but not in the sense that I owe it to anyone, I feel bad because writing is an important part of my life and I've not been doing that. So I'd like to fix this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the reasons I haven't been writing are pretty clear: I've been busy, and I've been depressed. Both are still true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Still, it continues to be my belief that the trick to getting out of depression is to do slightly more than depression is telling you is reasonable. Not &lt;em&gt;vastly&lt;/em&gt; more, but a bit more. This helps you relearn what is actually possible and gradually broadens the boundaries of your life-world, helping ease the depression. At least, that's the theory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right now, writing newsletter issues feels intolerable. So instead I'm going to write daily notebook posts and see if that manages to rebuild the habit and thought processes of writing. Maybe I'll write some newsletter issues this month, maybe I won't. We'll see.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The astute observer will note that this is coming out on the &lt;em&gt;second&lt;/em&gt; of January. I'm going to put out a catch up post immediately after this one and count this one as yesterday's post.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Don't expect a high standard of writing this month.
To start with I'm just going to do draft bankruptcy from the newsletter. After that I'll probably do Tarot prompts whenever I don't have a good idea what to write about.
Most of them will be short, and will end whenever I feel done with writing them rather than coming to a tidy conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-02-12:48.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-02-12:56.html</id>
    <title>Is philosophy bad?</title>
    <updated>2024-01-02T13:05:54+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Is philosophy bad?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a draft bankruptcy piece. It contains a few interesting things, but I abandoned it because it fundamentally didn't work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I threatened to write “Contra David Chapman on Philosophy” as a response to David’s repeated insistence that philosophy is bad. This piece isn’t exactly that, but it’s not exactly not that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Chavid Dapman on Philosophy&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Allow me to introduce my correspondent for this piece, Chavid Dapman. Chavid is a fictional character created by Claude to approximate David Chapman’s opinions on the subject. Given real world David Chapman’s opinions on AI, this is probably a very irritating thing of me to do. Sorry, David.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to inform Claude when I think Chavid says something that David wouldn’t, but this is an imperfect process. As Claude would put it, “Chavid Dapman is a fictional character created for narrative purposes. His critical opinions on philosophy should not be taken as precisely representative of thinker David Chapman's more nuanced perspectives.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here is Chavid’s opinion on philosophy:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophy is an intellectual tradition that aims to find absolute answers to questions about life, knowledge, ethics, and existence through logic, thought experiments and reasoning. However, after thousands of years, philosophy has failed to deliver definitive answers, especially compared to the progress of science. Logic and thought experiments have clear limits. And philosophy tends to neglect empirical research and interactive empiricism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the deeper issue is that philosophy pursues misguided questions based on false assumptions, such as: What constitutes a good life? What is the meaning of existence? What is human consciousness? The search for abstract absolute answers presumes these are coherent topics, when they are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophy goes astray in seeking universal essences, rather than understanding experience as an ongoing, embodied process. Contemplating pseudoproblems based on flawed metaphysics cannot elucidate anything. We should reject the search for absolute abstract answers and eternal philosophical truths. Philosophy needs to engage the physical world pragmatically and empirically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Editor's note: I ran this by actual David Chapman and he doesn't think it reflects his views at all and is instead a generic and not terribly well thought out critique. I agree. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;I like philosophy&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let’s just get this out of the way: I like philosophy, and I get a lot out of it. Reading philosophy has been significantly life improving for me, and informed a lot of my thinking. This makes it hard for me to accept a blanket “philosophy is bad” claim when a lot of philosophy is clearly good for me, and I’m writing from that perspective.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s also plenty of philosophy I dislike. Frankly, it’s almost impossible to like a thing without this being true, because almost everything has good and bad examples, and also examples that are and aren’t to your tastes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think one of the differences between Chavids opinions of philosophy and mine are quite straightforwardly that I tend to think of the examples of philosophy that I like as sufficient evidence that philosophy is good, and Chavid tends to think of the examples of philosophy that he doesn’t like as sufficient evidence that philosophy is bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This disagreement is partly what Adam Mastroianni calls a &lt;a href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/science-is-a-strong-link-problem"&gt;strong vs weak link problem&lt;/a&gt;. Some things are as strong as their weakest link, some as their strongest. With science (in Mastroianni’s example), progress doesn’t really depend on the worst science we’re doing but the best. I think the same is true of philosophy: Although there are many bad (both by my standards and theirs) examples of philosophy, there are also many good examples, and you can get value out of the good examples and mostly ignore the bad ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Chavid is basically right in saying that “a good life” is a bad abstraction (although I’m sympathetic to what happens to the question when you verb it, which is “How can you live well?” rather than “What is a good life?” - I think this is hard to answer, but worthwhile engaging with), but also this is almost never the sort of philosophy I read.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, here are two examples of philosophy I’ve got a lot out of:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“Games: Agency as Art” by C Thi Nguyen is a book about games, and what the fact that we play games tells us about humanity, and defending them as a distinctive form of art whose medium is constructing structures of agency. This book isn’t “empirical” in the sense that it gathers a lot of data, but is deeply engaged in the world by basically centring its philosophy on many games Nguyen has played.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“Epistemic Injustice” by Miranda Fricker is a book about ethics that consists of looking at a bunch of examples of things that are bad and saying “these seem to have some sort of shared distinctive character. What is it?”. Many of these examples are fictional, but even those feel like they connect to plausible shared experiences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are examples for me of the sort of thing philosophy really shines at: Pointing at something specific and going “There’s something interesting here. What is it?”. They don’t go astray into big abstract questions, but they use the same sort of methods that philosophers tend to engage with big abstract questions on and focus them on something specific and try to clarify our engagement with them. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Where was this going?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That was the point at which I abandoned this. I would still like to write a pro philosophy piece, but I think arguing against David Chapman's views on it is the wrong way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I like Joe Carlsmith's &lt;a href="https://joecarlsmith.com/2023/02/17/seeing-more-whole"&gt;Seeing More Whole&lt;/a&gt; viewpoint, which is (in very brief summary) that philosophy is about using logical reasoning to discover what sorts of person it is possible to be. This seems an important viewpoint to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've previously ha-ha-only-serious joked that the fundamental philosophical question is "That's weird, right? You get that that's weird?". I think the big thing that I get out of good philosophy is that it forces you to actually look at the details of life and how it works, rather than implicitly skipping over the bits that don't make sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't the first time I've tried to write that piece. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:43.html"&gt;How to use philosophy&lt;/a&gt; is another similarly brief draft bankruptcy piece trying to do much the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/reading-philosophy-for-the-examples"&gt;Reading Philosophy for the Examples&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-use-thought-experiments"&gt;How to use thought experiments&lt;/a&gt; maybe capture this better. Perhaps part of the problem is that I've tried to do too much with this topic and it needs something larger if I'm to write the whole thing. Or maybe just many smaller things.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-02-12:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-03-10:13.html</id>
    <title>Some Philosophy of
Mathematics</title>
    <updated>2024-01-03T12:30:38+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Some Philosophy of
Mathematics&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is another draft bankruptcy piece, pulled out of a random Google
doc. I think what I’ve got here is perfectly reasonable but it was an
overly ambitious project that I lost interest in finishing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s also my first attempt at moving my blog rendering over to
pandoc, so probably a whole bunch of things will break.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m going to be making a few sweeping generalisations about
philosophy of mathematics. I’m sure some of them don’t hold in complete
generality. I’m trying to convey the sense of what mathematics
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Especially modernish mathematics. I think most of what
I’m saying works as a description of historical mathematics, but it
certainly wouldn’t have been the way people thought about it prior to
some time in the 20th century.&lt;/span&gt;
 is typically like rather than
attempting to come up with a grand unifying theory of mathematical
practice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This piece comes out of trying to explain a bit about mathematical
incompleteness to a philosopher and realising that the core problem in
explaining this is that the way we typically
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I don’t know how reliable my sense of how we typically
present axioms is and was worried this might be a &lt;a href="https://www.lisamcnulty.co.uk/essays/phantom-opinions"&gt;phantom
opinion&lt;/a&gt;, so I checked and it’s not. I did some casual googling,
checked Wikipedia, and asked ChatGPT which is usually a pretty good
representation of the sort of the typical but oversimplified vox populi
opinion on things. I also &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1713814331224170566"&gt;did some
polling on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and I think most of the answers are confusing in
the relevant way. I think that my view is probably relatively typical
among working mathematicians, but not of how we talk about mathematics
to non-mathematicians.&lt;/span&gt;

present axioms philosophically is unhelpful for understanding what’s
going on in mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, let’s fix this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="what-are-axioms"&gt;What are axioms?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Axioms are things that we take to be true, but they are things we
take to be true in the sense that “a bachelor is an unmarried man” or “a
bishop moves any number of vacant squares diagonally”. They are not
taken to be true in the sense that they represent deep truths about the
universe that we have no way to prove but wholeheartedly believe
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is one potential source of axioms of course, as the
universe is one of the things we want to reason about, but it is not
what axioms &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
, they are taken to be true in the
sense that they represent defining properties of the class of thing we
are interested in talking about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For this to make sense, we need to realise that mathematics isn’t
really about proofs, it’s about &lt;em&gt;things, &lt;/em&gt;”mathematical objects”.
Proofs are for discovering properties of mathematical objects. They say:
“Suppose I’ve got some object and it has these properties. What else do
I know about it?”. Those properties are the axioms, but you’re not
“assuming” that the object has those properties in the sense that they
are things that might be false but you’re postulating for now, those
properties define the class of object that you are interested in talking
about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, most people think of axioms as things that are “self
evidently true” or, slightly more accurately, “assumptions”, but this
immediately invites the question “But what if your assumptions are
wrong?” or “How do you &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; your axioms are true?”
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;These questions are not meaningless or bad necessarily,
but they’re usually asked in the wrong place.&lt;/span&gt;
. With axioms as picking out objects
of interest, these problems go away - you can argue about whether the
objects in question are interesting or whether any examples of them
exist (“exist” is complicated. More on that later), but not whether the
axioms are true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the easiest places to see how this works is with the
mathematics of games, because there the axioms are just the
&lt;em&gt;constitutive rules&lt;/em&gt; of the game. You can do mathematics around
games of chess (e.g. “From this position, can checkmate be forced in 5
moves?” is implicitly a mathematical sort of question), and in asking
this question you are restricted to the sort of moves that chess allows.
If you were playing with a different rule set, the conclusion might be
different, but that doesn’t mean that the two conclusions are
incompatible, they’re just about different games.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another, more historical, example is the parallel postulate and the
axioms of geometry. Simplified version: Euclid came up with a set of
axioms for geometry, describing how points, lines, and circles worked.
There were a bunch of perfectly sensible axioms, and then there was the
rather awkward &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parallel_postulate"&gt;Parallel
Postulate&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Note: This is all somewhat ahistorical and simplified
for illustrative purposes. Euclid’s account of geometry wasn’t fully
axiomatic, and the version of the parallel postulate stated is not
Euclid’s original and is only equivalent to it given the other axioms.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a plane, given a line and a point not on it, at most one line
parallel to the given line can be drawn through the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People spent ages trying to prove the parallel postulate from the
other axioms, and then someone pointed out that &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spherical_geometry"&gt;Spherical
Geometry&lt;/a&gt; demonstrated that you couldn’t do this: If you take a
sphere and interpret “line” as meaning “great circle” (a circle on the
surface of the sphere whose centre is the centre of the sphere. e.g the
equator, or a line of longitude, but not in general a line of latitude
because those are “off centre” for the sphere), you get something that
satisfies all the basic axioms of geometry but for which the parallel
postulate is false (because there are no parallel lines, because all
great circles intersect at two points on the sphere).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you think of geometry as trying to derive universal truths of
geometry, this information can be very distressing. How do you know
which axioms to use?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If, on the other hand, you instead think of there being such a thing
as &lt;em&gt;a geometry&lt;/em&gt; then all you’re trying to do is figure out
properties of particular geometries of interest, and you can pick
whichever one you want to work on. Sometimes you might want to work with
a Euclidean geometry, sometimes you might want to work with a spherical
geometry. It’s up to you! They’re both equally valid mathematical
objects for doing geometry on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="what-are-mathematical-objects"&gt;What are mathematical
objects?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If axioms pick out which mathematical objects we are talking about,
we need to follow this by answering a much harder question: What are
mathematical objects?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I need to start with a slightly slippery mathematician’s definition:
Mathematical objects are the things you can do proofs about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This definition is actually quite useful, because it highlights an
important point of this conception of axioms: It’s actually slightly
agnostic to foundational questions like this. As long as there is
something called a mathematical object and you can do proofs about it,
this notion of axiom is useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular, consider two
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Slightly strawman versions of these positions, but I
think morally accurate.&lt;/span&gt;
 conceptions of
mathematical foundations:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mathematics is reasoning about real entities that exist in some
sort of abstract platonic realm of ideal forms (&lt;strong&gt;Mathematical
platonism&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mathematics is a purely formal game of manipulating symbols
representing purely formal entities according to agreed upon rules,
which can be put in correspondence with real entities but do not
intrinsically correspond to things that “exist”. (&lt;strong&gt;Mathematical
formalism&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mathematicians often behave liked platonists but fall back on
formalism as a sort of philosophical justification.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A third competing view that I like is Reuben Hersch’s definition of
mathematical objects as “socio-historical objects”. Things that only
exist because we, as people doing mathematics, agree they exist,
similarly to other things like money, rules, games.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is mostly right, but I’d like to propose a slight
refinement: Mathematical objects are things that we agree to &lt;em&gt;behave
as if they existed&lt;/em&gt; because doing so allows us to do mathematics,
and mathematics is useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this makes sense of why, regardless of what they believe
about foundations, mathematicians in practice behave more like
platonists: Regardless of whether mathematical objects “actually exist”,
mathematics is done by behaving &lt;em&gt;as if&lt;/em&gt; mathematical objects
exist, and proceeding from that starting point to reason about what they
should be like.
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In this view, mathematics is a ritual practice in the
sense of Seligman et al’s “Ritual and its Consequences”. It is the
creation of a &lt;em&gt;subjunctive world&lt;/em&gt; in which certain rules and
claims are treated as inviolable properties of the ritual space, because
doing so allows the ritual to occur, which is desirable for its
non-ritual consequences. e.g. politeness norms are viewed as a ritual in
this sense, because maintaining them allows for civil interactions which
everyone enjoys. In practice they are not inviolable, but if everyone
treats them as such they are not violated and thus you get to operate in
a world where you can trust them as if they were inviolable.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I sometimes joke that the formalists are right that mathematics is a
game, but it’s not a purely symbolic one, it’s an RPG set in the
Platonic realm. We are reasoning about some world that we agree to
behave as if it existed, contained certain objects, and was subject to
logical reasoning of the sort that we would expect to hold in the real
world.
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is a nontrivial constraint on a hypothetical world.
e.g. fairy tales have a logic of their own, but it is not a simple if A
then B sort of logical reasoning you can count on. The realm in which
mathematical objects exist is posited to be one that makes sense.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This still leaves us to ask: What sort of mathematical objects do we
posit exist? Fictional worlds are very different depending on the world
building you’ve done for them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Generally mathematical objects are one of two types:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something we’ve built as an abstracted and generalised version of
something in the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something we’ve built out of other mathematical objects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often it’s both: When we build mathematical objects, we’re usually
doing them for some purpose, and that purpose is often to represent
something that in some way looks like the real world. This helps us
avoid positing too many “primitive” mathematical objects - the building
blocks of our mathematical world
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn9"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn9" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Which we want to do because every primitive mathematical
object is a sort of leap of faith as to whether the rules actually make
sense.&lt;/span&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The classic example of something which is purely built as an
abstracted and generalised version of something in the physical world is
a natural (counting) number. The numbers 0, 1, 2, … are mathematical
objects that we just assume exist
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn10"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn10" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In fact, in modern (i.e. dating from the early 20th
century) we construct these too out of other mathematical objects - sets
- but you can do the mathematics of numbers without doing the
mathematics of sets, and numbers are in some sense “more basic” to
mathematics.&lt;/span&gt;
 in our mathematical
world, according to the following rules for constructing them:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a number 0.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If there is a number n, there is a next number immediately after
it (n + 1, although we want to do this before we’ve defined addition so
this is usually written S(n), for successor of n).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We then agree that these mathematical objects satisfy what we think
of as the idealised rules of counting numbers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These counting numbers are abstract in the following sense: There is
no way to point to the number four. You can point to four rocks, four
caling birds, four tally marks. You can point to the arabic number 4, or
the roman numeral IV. These all in some sense “represent” the number
four (as does the word “four”), but they are not the mathematical object
four, they are a real object that in some sense has fourness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These counting numbers are also generalised, in that we posit the
existence of mathematical numbers that have no corresponding real world
counted quantity. Why? Well, it follows from the rules we have for
counting numbers (which I haven’t spelled out, but it does I promise)
that if n exists then so does 10n. But that means that 10 exists, 100
exists, 1,000,000 exists… 10^10000000000 also exists, which is vastly
more things to count than there are atoms in the universe. In the real
world, you can’t count that high. In the mathematical world, no problem
at all.
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn11"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn11" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And there are sometimes reasons to, even if you only
care about real world countable quantities! Sometimes you want to prove
a mathematical result and it requires you to e.g. look at all the
subsets of some set of a reasonable size. Although 1,000,000 is a
perfectly reasonable number, 21,000,000 is again more than the atoms of
the universe. From a mathematical point of view, proving results that
use that number are completely legitimate, even if it has no physical
analogue.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another, more concrete, example of a mathematical object that allows
us to avoid concerns about infinity
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn12"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn12" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And concern ourselves with the merely very large.&lt;/span&gt;
 is the mathematical
objects corresponding to &lt;em&gt;game states&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Consider a game of chess, with the pieces on the board somewhere.
Suppose you nudge a piece slightly, keeping it in the same square but
just shifting it slightly to the left. In one sense, you’ve changed the
state of the board - a piece is in a different location. But, from the
point of view of a game of chess, you have not made a change
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn13"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn13" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In tournament rules you may have committed yourself to
moving this piece, but the point remains: If you moved this piece to
that square prior to nudging it, that makes no difference.&lt;/span&gt;
, because all that matters is which
square the piece is in, not exactly where it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if you were to take another chess board and set and place
the pieces from that set in the same squares as they were in the
original board, this would represent the same game of chess. This is
true even if one board is physical and the other electronic. You could
even copy the chess board position onto paper by hand - either as a
picture, or as a list of positions in a standard chess notation. These
would all represent the same game of chess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although chess is a game whose state is represented by physical
objects (which might be a physical chess board, might be a computer,
might even be solely in the heads of the participants!), chess is played
as the &lt;em&gt;abstract game state &lt;/em&gt;- all that matters is the chess
position, which is represented by the physical object but not synonymous
with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One important feature of this is that not all physical arrangements
of a chess board have a corresponding abstract chess state. e.g. you
could have a piece halfway between two squares. You could have a board
with no kings. These are not valid chess states, they’re just things you
can do with the physical chess board.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, you’ve got the rules of chess which describe how abstract
chess states are transformed into each other. Nothing stops you
physically violating these rules - you can pick someone’s king up and
throw it across the room, you can steal their pawn while they’re not
looking, nothing stops you from doing these things, except the fact that
in doing them you are no longer playing chess. The rules of chess exist
precisely in order to enable you to play chess, and violating the rules
means that this is not a game of chess.
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn14"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn14" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Some games do explicitly allow cheating as part of the
game, but that doesn’t change the basic point, it’s just a more
complicated ruleset.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These abstract chess states and the rules for moving between them are
mathematical objects that exist in the same sort of “mathematical realm”
as numbers. You can also do mathematics to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, the question “Is a checkmate guaranteed for white from
this position?” is a mathematical question. You are trying to reason
about whether white has a strategy that guarantees that all series of
moves from the current chess position result in a checkmate for
white.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although this mathematical question nominally answers a question
about real games of chess being played by the players, it differs in
several ways:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t describe anything about the game other than the
abstract states - you don’t know how the players physically move around
the board, their emotional states, etc. None of these are considered
relevant to or part of the mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has the same sort of unboundedness problem that counting
numbers do. This question actually does have a definite answer, but the
definite answer might require considering 2&lt;sup&gt;2048 &lt;/sup&gt;different
chess positions to reach.
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn15"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn15" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Actually much less than that, because not all of those
chess positions are in fact possible, but even a 100-order of magnitude
reduction makes this an impossibly large number of states.&lt;/span&gt;
 While in theory this
is a finite number with a definite answer, there’s no guarantee we can
calculate it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3 id="detritus"&gt;Detritus&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Editor’s note: This was a section with random cuttings that had been
removed from the text elsewhere because it didn’t fit the flow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the most important features of this explanation is that it
makes much more sense of the social role of axioms. If axioms are
universal truths then they arrive through some sort of deep a priori
knowledge or divine revelation or something, but if axioms just pick out
the objects you’re talking about they arrive in a much more
straightforward way: Someone picks up a mathematical object and goes
“Hey, look at this thing! Interesting, innit?” and then proceeds to try
to describe what’s interesting about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You have to do a bit of fiddling around to figure out which
properties of the object you do and don’t care about, and what a good
set of axioms to represent them are, but that’s just work, it’s not
anything particularly mysterious you just have to come up with a good
design. Once you’ve identified an object, or some objects, of interest,
you can just axiomatise them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This helpfully reduces the question “Where do axioms come from?” to
the much harder question “Where do mathematical objects come from?”,
which in turn first requires us to&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there are roughly two sources for mathematical objects:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We make them out of other mathematical objects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We abstract them from real things (which may be physical objects,
properties of such objects, processes, etc).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can do the first because (I have no idea how I was intending to
continue this sentence).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="reflections"&gt;Reflections&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I often find that there’s a large body of understanding that lives in
my head and that I think is more sensible than how other people seem to
view it, but when it comes time to try to explain it I find it’s all too
interconnected to be worth the effort of explaining unless there’s some
really clear goal to it. This was one of those times.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’d like a solution to this problem, but I’m not sure there is a
solution other than to accept my own mortality and finite energy
reserves and not worry so much about other people being wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-03-10:13.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
