<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2020-05-26T06:09:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-18-09:41.html</id>
    <title>Bug Fixes and Performance Improvements</title>
    <updated>2020-05-18T12:46:52+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Bug Fixes and Performance Improvements&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-18&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today we release Version 37.0 of the DRMacIver software system. We've been working on it for a whole year, and are pretty excited to share the results with you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In reality we of course practice continuous deployment and so have been rolling out releases through the entirety of the last year, and all of our changes are breaking changes so there's no hint of semantic versioning in our release process, but nevertheless bumping the major version number is a good chance to talk about some of the exciting new developments over the last year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The major improvements we've seen since the Version 36.0 release are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We've refactored an awful lot of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;legacy code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Significantly improved write performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modest improvements to read performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We've fixed the bug where the brain randomly crashed in social situations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The system has finally &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/"&gt;evolved to the point where it can send email&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In case you don't get the joke (you probably get the joke) it's my 37th birthday today. Today is, legally speaking, the year where I have to start saying I'm in my mid to late 30s rather than in my mid 30s.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in ancient times, when I were a wee lad in my late 20s, I used to say that I didn't really mind the idea of hitting 30 (back then 30 seemed very old) because the people I knew in their 30s were mostly like the people I knew in their 20s only they had their shit a bit more together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I then spent the first half of my thirties with my shit &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; not together - life went a bit sideways in the dying months of 29 and it took me about five years before I hit rock bottom enough to start doing something about it.
The result was me rather disconnecting from people emotionally, and it didn't have a great impact on my career either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People don't really notice that I'm not a software developer any more, partly because I only became famous as a software developer after I stopped being one. Officially &lt;a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/lp/python-developers-survey-2019/"&gt;4% of Python developers are running my code&lt;/a&gt;. I wrote that code &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/i/status/1194550244496814081"&gt;entirely after burning out&lt;/a&gt;. I haven't actually been employed as a software developer since early 2015, outside of the occasional short term contract for Hypothesis work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something about the software development industry that burns people out. I don't know what it is, but it does it to most people. Maybe every industry is like this and I just mostly see it in the one I know? Maybe it's just &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-12:06.html"&gt;acedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I started to pull myself out of the hole around 2017 I guess - I moved back to London, started a PhD, kinda started seeing people. In late 2018 I started a new relationship, which has been going very well.
It prompted some reflection, and I've spent a lot of the intervening period attempting to sort my shit out in the way that a decade ago I, apparently, naively assumed would come with age.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is it working? I guess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of why I wrote &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-07-07:57.html"&gt;Easy Changes and Uncomfortable Reflections&lt;/a&gt; was that it was what I needed to hear (that's why I write a lot of these posts). It's quite hard to escape the feeling that I could have done all this work seven years ago, or seventeen years ago, or even twenty seven years ago, and life would have gone a lot better for it. I think this is partly true, but mostly false, but it still feels like a wasted opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today's Tarot draw (I've been doing daily draws even when they've not made it into the notebook) is the &lt;a href="http://www.learntarot.com/ca.htm"&gt;Ace of Cups&lt;/a&gt;, which signifies among other things getting in touch with your feelings. Well I've done that. It's got its good points, and there's yet more to do on that front, but also it kinda sucks in that one of the major downsides of becoming more in touch with your own feelings is that you're more aware of your feelings, and sometimes those feelings are bad. I think I've in many ways been less depressed over the last year than I've been... ever, possibly, but it doesn't necessarily &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like that because I'm more aware of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Especially given, as you might have noticed, there's a global pandemic on at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This post was meant to be reasonably optimistic - I do think that the next few years will be quite good for me - but entering my late thirties in the middle of a global pandemic feels weird. I can barely predict what next week is going to look like, let alone the next three years.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All told, I'm doing what I can to lay a solid foundation for whatever comes next. It might even work.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-18-09:41.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-19-09:35.html</id>
    <title>Working with the audience</title>
    <updated>2020-05-19T10:52:04+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Working with the audience&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From Lois McMaster Bujold's "A Civil Campaign", page 137:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Madame Vorsoisson", Mark said with dignity, "is a very sensible woman. When presented with compelling facts, &lt;em&gt;she&lt;/em&gt; doesn't let a thoughtless emotional response overcome her clear reason."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"A Civil Campaign" is probably my favourite book in the Vorkosigan series. The Vorkosigan series is largely an "Adventures! In! Space!" series, but as it goes on there's increasingly fewer adventures in favour of exploring the lives of the characters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Adventures in A Civil Campaign primarily center on a number of things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Planning for the imperial wedding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Miles (the protagonist of the series) attempting to woo the aforementioned Madame Vorsoisson, with a thoroughly inappropriately military approach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mark (Miles's clone/brother) attempting an early stage biotech startup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many exciting politics as a hereditary patriarchal nobility adjusts to things like gene tests and gender changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probably some other things I'm forgetting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This exchange is about the third. Mark has just fed Ekaterin (Madame Vorsoisson) some of his startup's food product. It is a vaguely pleasing but mostly a bit bland product that I imagine as being a bit like cream cheese.
The product is nutritious, flexible, cheap to produce, and has significant environmental benefits.
It should be a miracle product that will make Mark extremely successful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also it comes from bugs. The bugs are particularly disgusting looking. They call it bug butter. The bugs are called butter bugs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, they're trying to sell their product made from genetically engineered bugs on a planet that regards mutations with visceral horror.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ekaterin has, kindly, reacted primarily to the quality of the bug butter as a food product rather than its origins. Miles and everyone else have reacted with horror to the name, the branding, and the general visceral association of the food product with its origins (it's vomited up by horrifying bug creatures).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mark believes that Ekaterin is in the right and that Miles and the others are in the wrong. Mark is wrong. Mark is bad at startups.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Oh, Ekaterin is of course behaving very well. It's &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; to be able to suspend emotional reactions and look at the potential in a situation. However, Mark is conflating how he feels people &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; react to his product with how people are actually going to react to his product. Miles and everyone else are providing him with valuable insight.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mark does eventually turn this around, mostly because of Ekaterin's help on branding, but without her he would have been insisting that people are reacting to his actions &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; and complaining about the unfairness of it all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an easy trap to fall in to, both in startups and in general: If people react badly to your actions that &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be unfair, and it's legitimate to feel aggrieved about it, but ultimately at some point you need to ask whether you want to have an impact or not, and if you want to have an impact it's usually better to ask how you can effectively work with people's reactions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's all very well to demand that people react to your actions differently, but it doesn't usually work. If you want to change the world, if you want people to use your product, you need to start from where you are and work with the audience you have. Even if you do, ultimately, want to change their behaviour, you're not generally going to get there by demanding that they comply - you need to instead work with rather than against their existing reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-19-09:35.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-19-17:31.html</id>
    <title>Parts of you are missing</title>
    <updated>2020-05-19T18:34:29+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Parts of you are missing&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's an article that was going around earlier in The Current Situation: &lt;a href="https://hbr.org/2020/03/that-discomfort-youre-feeling-is-grief"&gt;That Discomfort You’re Feeling Is Grief&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't find the article itself very useful or interesting, but the title stuck with me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's an idea called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transactive_memory"&gt;Transactive Memory&lt;/a&gt; - often we don't remember things, we remember who to ask about them. In a team, or in a relationship, there are many things where we are offloading our memories to the people around us. The group as a whole remembers things, and we are able to rely on that. The group as a whole functions as an extended part of the minds of each person within it - I don't need to know the details of that aspect of the project, because I know who does and I can talk to them about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Couples in particular form complex webs of transactive memory, where they each remember details about their shared lives and responsibilities, and each delegate parts of that memory to the other. Some of these are very practical: One of you knows about the accounts, one of you knows what to do when the boiler breaks. Some of these are more emotional - one of you has a better memory for the places you've been, and when you share stories they fill in the rich details.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And then one of you dies, or leaves, and all of a sudden there are holes in your memory. Every time you reach for the parts of your memory that live outside your body, you find an uncomfortable absence. That discomfort you're feeling is grief.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It goes beyond memory. We are social creatures, and we integrate other people into our lives. Into our selves. We talk to each other, we help each other process our feelings.
When we interact &lt;a href="https://www.brainpickings.org/2015/10/21/telling-is-listening-ursula-k-le-guin-communication/"&gt;we join together&lt;/a&gt;, becoming more than the sum of our parts, and each of us brings part of that whole into ourselves.
Being with others is an opportunity to be different versions of our selves,
letting the whole create an environment that brings out a different aspect of who we are.
Many of our &lt;a href="https://www.rewriting-the-rules.com/self/new-year-new-zine-plural-selves/"&gt;plural selves&lt;/a&gt; only come out in environments that give them the support they need to be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Oh, those other people who bring them out aren't necessarily &lt;em&gt;gone&lt;/em&gt;. Certainly many people have died of COVID-19 or its social fallout, but that is a less complicated and more intense sort of grief. For most of us the people are there, and we're even talking to them, but it's not the same.
We're talking to them over text, or phone, or Zoom, and that's good and it is good that we are doing it, but it isn't the same.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-13-09:56.html"&gt;talked about books&lt;/a&gt; before, and how wrong our ideas of reading are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading is not an act conducted by a pure mind engaging with an idealised platonic flow of information. Reading is an active engagement between a physical body and a physical object. The purpose of reading is to engage with the content, but reading itself is a physical act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If this is true for books, how much more so for people?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Have you ever tried to have a conversation where one of you is typing and the other speaking? It's almost impossibly frustrating for the typist. You're so limited in what you can say - it's slower and less expressive. It's like speaking in a language you understand but are not fluent in. Only a fraction of what you want comes through.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The minds we create together over the internet are interesting and powerful and they have many positive characteristics that it is hard to create in person, but they have many weaknesses over in person communication too. They lack some of the strengths that we need to support ways we could be in person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Can you touch someone over Zoom? Can you dance with them? "Body language" is not just a metaphor - the presence of the other in your world is a key part of how we relate to each other.
Long distance relationships are, of course, possible, but the longer we have been apart, the more our memory of each other's physicality fades, the harder it is to become the person that we allow each other to be. We try to hold on to it as best we can, but memory can only take us so far. The ghosts of our absent selves are a comfort, to be sure, but they are also a reminder of absence.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not even just people. A thing that is especially visible as a mathematician, but is true for most people, is how much of the work of thought lives outside your head. A mathematician without pencil and paper (or a blackboard, or an equivalent) is not a mathematician, they are merely the potential to be one. A swimmer without water cannot swim, cannot become the version of themself that swims.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When we shop, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1248560936102887424"&gt;we become the supermarket&lt;/a&gt;. That part of you is missing too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When we are cut from our environment, we lose the parts of ourself that the environment allowed us to be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of the parts that are missing we will meet again, and it will be a joyous reunion. Some we are glad to be rid of. But they are still missing, and we can feel their absence, and the memory of what it was like to be them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We are all, desperately, trying to find replacements for the parts of us that are missing - new versions of our self that we can be in the environment that we have access to. Some of those versions will be delightful new discoveries that we are happy to meet. Some of them will be mere shadows of the versions we would rather be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But either way, they are parts that we had grown used to, familiar parts that we were able to embody at need, and every time we would want to slip into that way of being, and can't, we are reminded of that absence. Parts of us are missing, and that feeling of discomfort we experience from it is grief.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-19-17:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-09:54.html</id>
    <title>Morality and Emotion</title>
    <updated>2020-05-20T10:45:05+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Morality and Emotion&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3g53ayI"&gt;Voices: The Educational Formation of Conscience&lt;/a&gt;, page 18:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"What is my duty?" is made, by many accounts, the entry question into philosophical ethics. For a philosophy of moral education, however, entry is gained more fully through the Socratic question, "How ought one to live?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The distinction that Green is drawing in this book is between philosophy of ethics, which develops ethical theories of what it is like to behave ethically, and philosophy of moral education, which asks how people learn to behave ethically.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is intimately tied to my point in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-10-08:54.html"&gt;How to become a better person&lt;/a&gt; that as well as a &lt;em&gt;theory&lt;/em&gt; of ethics we need a &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; of ethics.
A philosophy of moral education is not necessarily that practice, but it is at least less far removed from it:
If you ask "What is my duty?", an answer can assume that part of your duty is that you are responsible for figuring out how to uphold your other duties. If you ask "How should I live?", you might quite reasonably object if the answer is a little light on practical details about how, exactly, you are supposed to be able to live in the manner described.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something about the question "How ought one to live?" that feels hopelessly naive and/or oppressive these days. Who are you to tell me what to do?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; in particular feels dangerous. It feels like a question that can only be asked in the presence of a certain amount of coercive power - as if whatever answer you give to the question, that's the answer you're going to impose on others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On top of that, there can be no single &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt;, because are all different people with different desires and constraints. The idea of a one sized fits all "best life" seems both impossible and undesirable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And yet, I still think there's something there. Perhaps not "How ought one to live?" but "How can one figure out how to live?" or "What tools are there to figure out how to live?" or "How can we help people live their best lives?".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think we underestimate the interplay between morality and emotional health. Many of our strongest emotions and feelings have a moral component. Guilt and shame, certainly, but also love and empathy. Emotions and morality interplay strongly as we act in the world, especially with regards to other people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suggested in "How to be a better person" that improving your emotional skills would probably automatically make you a better person, but I think the converse might be true too: Becoming a better person will improve your emotional health (as long as it's paired with good skills for working with emotions - I still think those are the foundations).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-16-12:06.html"&gt;acedia&lt;/a&gt;. I think one of the causes of acedia is living out of line with our values - sometimes because our values are bad, sometimes because we are forced to, and sometimes because it is easier to ignore that dissonance than deal with them. We learn not to care as a defence mechanism, and bringing ourselves more in line with our values allows us to repair some of that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another part is the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety&lt;/a&gt; model. Emotional skills are what provide you with safety to become better, but others are often the spur for that. Certainly much of my current growth came from having people who I wanted to be better for.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my first read of Green &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/08/jiminy-cricket-must-die/"&gt;I was pretty negative about some of this themes&lt;/a&gt;. I still think that's right - a great deal of his work is about how we adopt a community's norms, and my experience is that most communities' norms are very unsafe to internalise. My current read is more sympathetic: I still think moral norms are dangerous tools that are often misused, but I think they also might be a key part of finding our way to better lives as long as we can find the right people to develop them with.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-09:54.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-17:58.html</id>
    <title>How I fix anxiety triggers</title>
    <updated>2020-05-20T19:57:16+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How I fix anxiety triggers&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a sketch of the skillset I use to deal with anxiety. It works well when:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anxiety is at a level that I can deal with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is anxiety &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I currently feel vaguely anxious. Not sure what about. It's not especially hard to deal with, I'm just noticing a certain tension in my shoulders and that I feel slightly on edge. This is undirected anxiety, and I don't currently have a good skillset for dealing with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm currently putting off a whole bunch of accounting stuff because accounting stuff makes me super anxious and I don't &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to deal with it. I should do this, but I haven't, and forcing myself into doing it is probably not helpful for dealing with my anxiety on the subject.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might not be me, and have different sets of problems as a result. I'm reasonably confident that something in this space works for fairly general reasons, but I can't promise that doing exactly what I do will work for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Basic Procedure&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The procedure is very simple:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice that a thing is triggering anxiety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figure out &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it's triggering anxiety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask if the current situation is actually one I need to be anxious about.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If yes, keep being anxious, taking appropriate steps to increase your safety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If no, stop being anxious, and also be less anxious in similar situations in future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All three of these are very simple but they are not easy and require developing some foundational skills that I'll talk about at the end.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does it work? In my experience, pretty reliably, as long as you can actually work through the procedure (which can be both intellectually and emotionally difficult).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Why does this work?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The basic philosophical premises of this are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anxiety is not in and of itself bad. Anxiety is your reaction to being in a dangerous situation, making you aware of it so that you can be prepared. It is good to be aware of when you are in a dangerous situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your brain does not do a perfectly rational threat assessment of the situation, it learns simple pattern matching rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When a rule is active you can change it by better understanding the situation and gently guiding yourself towards understanding why it doesn't apply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(3) is the basic idea behind &lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/i9xyZBS3qzA8nFXNQ/book-summary-unlocking-the-emotional-brain"&gt;coherence therapy&lt;/a&gt;: You can retrain emotions when they are triggered.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've previously explained the idea that your bundle of emotional reactions are a messy complex system that you can debug and refactor in the previous three posts:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;Emotional reactions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-03-09:07.html"&gt;Your emotions are valid but probably wrong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;Alief/Belief Coherence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What doesn't work&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The main thing that people try to do with anxiety is suppress it. This doesn't work, and probably makes your anxiety worse, for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It causes you to ignore anxiety in unsafe situations where it's actually worth being anxious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you can only fix reactions when they're active, if you succeed at suppressing a reaction it'll just come back later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emotions tend to rise to the level that is required to get us to do something about them, so this will tend to make anxiety worse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately because we've got into the habit of treating anxiety itself as the problem, this is the natural thing to do. My instinct is that you are better off palliating to deal with the anxious situation or avoiding it entirely rather than trying to suppress it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Foundational Skills&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although the procedure is simple, it requires some relatively difficult foundational skills:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-compassion, the ability to talk compassionately and without judgement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focusing, the ability to use felt sense and verbalisation to understand your own feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discomfort tolerance, the ability to remain uncomfortable without treating it as an emergency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noticing triggers, the ability to explicitly notice and identify triggered states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I talked about some of these in &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2020/01/a-crash-course-in-having-feelings/"&gt;A Crash Course in Having Feelings&lt;/a&gt;. I don't necessarily have good advice beyond that post on how to develop these skills, but some books that I found helpful in learning about each of these are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-compassion: &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3g52wRL"&gt;Rewriting the Rules&lt;/a&gt; by Meg-John Barker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focusing: &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3cPJEnN"&gt;Focusing&lt;/a&gt; by Eugene Gendlin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discomfort Tolerance: &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2ZlZ2EB"&gt;Conflict is not Abuse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noticing triggers: &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/36ghhg9"&gt;Complex PTSD: From Surviving to Thriving&lt;/a&gt; (I'd probably recommend starting with &lt;a href="https://www.rewriting-the-rules.com/self/trauma-and-cptsd-101/"&gt;Meg-John Barker's Post on this&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But to be honest I think with all of these the real way to get good at them is just to practice. Of these I'd most strongly recommend "A Crash Course in Having Feelings", "Focusing", and MJB's post on trauma. The others were important to my development, but I read a lot of books so that's relatively cheap for me, and was only really a way to get started. The best thing for actually developing these skills was to use them in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-17:58.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-21-09:32.html</id>
    <title>Against the Classification of Books</title>
    <updated>2020-05-21T10:25:24+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Against the Classification of Books&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-21&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2ylGMjz"&gt;How to Read a Book&lt;/a&gt;, p 64:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have already discussed a rough classification of books. The main distinction, we said, was between works of fiction, on the one hand, and works conveying knowledge, or expository works, on the other hand. Among expository works, we can further distinguish history from philosophy, and both from science and mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is part of a general section about how analytical reading should start with the question "What sort of book is this?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On page 60, they list this as the first rule of analytical reading:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must know what kind of book you are reading, and you should know this as early in the process as possible, preferably before you begin to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The authors do not, frankly, justify this very well. At the end of this chapter their argument is this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, just as there is a difference in the art of teaching in different fields, so there is a reciprocal difference in the art of being taught. The activity of the student must somehow be responsive to the activity of the instructor. The relation between books and their readers is the same as that between teachers and their students. Hence, as books differ in the kinds of knowledge they have to communicate, they proceed to instruct us differently; and, if we are to follow them, we must learn to read each kind in an appropriate manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To which I offer the following responses:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A book is not a person, and our relationship is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different to that of a person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The argument is nonsense for people too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can engage with a book however you like. There's no moral obligation to engage with a book as the authors want you to - if you want to read a book of science through a literary criticism lens, or a book of literary criticism through a scientific lens, you can.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even the practical vs theoretical distinction is dubious: I read a lot of philosophy. This philosophy is, for the most part, eminently theoretical, but I am reading it for practical reasons, to help me make sense of things. This requires me to do a lot of translation by doing the active work of framing practical situations using the tools provided.
This is not a style of engagement that a philosopher would generally be receptive to (it depends on the philosopher of course) and they would probably find it quite frustrating. A book can't be frustrated with me, so I'm free to use it however I like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's certainly true that treating a science book as a science book and a piece of literature as a piece of literature will result in results that are more... in line with the intent of the author I guess, and you should probably do that more often than not - it's useful to learn the norms before you violate them - but they don't necessarily produce more &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; outcomes, and different reads will tend to help you
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-24-10:37.html"&gt;bridge the gaps between different areas of knowledge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second problem is that the idea that coarse grained classifications are anything like enough. People have very individual styles and, yes, those are rooted in their communities of practice, but those communities of practice are only loosely defined by disciplines - they're often very different between subdisciplines, departments, individual teacher / student lineages, etc. You need to do at least as much work to identify those individual differences in engagement as you do to identify the genre.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead of asking "What sort of book is this?" I think the questions you should be asking are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can I engage with this book in a way that I want to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If not, where can I learn the skills for doing so?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Knowing what sort of book it is &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be helpful for answering the question, but often it is going to be much more about your relationship to the subject matter than it is about the type of book per se.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-21-09:32.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-22-09:34.html</id>
    <title>Feeling Good About Being Good</title>
    <updated>2020-05-22T10:52:49+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Feeling Good About Being Good&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-22&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently working through a (more or less) full reread of &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3g53ayI"&gt;Voices: The Educational Formation of Conscience&lt;/a&gt;, so you're going to get treated to a lot of extracts from it. Today's extract comes from page 41:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] normation just &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; this structuring of the emotions of self-assessment -shame, guilt, embarassment, pride, and the like-both in our self-assessment and in our judgements of others. It follows, of course, that it structures also the positive emotions companion to these that I have called the emotions of self-assessment. That is to say normation structures also the appearance of elation, pride, self-assurance, and the joy and hope that accompany these. By saying that normation structures these emotions, I mean to refer not to the logic of their composition, whether they presuppose some propositional content, as in one or another version of a cognitive theory of the emotions. I mean to refer rather to their focus or object. Normation gives content to these emotions inasmuch as it provides their object. It tells us &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; things are going to provoke such emotions. In short, normation makes these emotions specific. Structuring them in this way is precisely what mere compliance is powerless to accomplish. Again, absent these emotions and the norms themselves will vanish. Observance will deconstruct into mere compliance, governance into mere behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This continues to explore the theme of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-20-09:54.html"&gt;the connection between morality and emotional health that I highlighted before&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To unpack what Green is saying in this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Normation is the social process by which we acquire norms of behaviour - voices of conscience with which we reflexively judge whether behaviour is good or bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Observance" of a norm is distinguished from mere "compliance" when we feel the force of the norm internally rather than merely adhering to the behaviour it prescribes. e.g. we are observant to a norm of honesty if we feel guilty about lying, but we may still be honest (compliant with the norm of honesty) without internalising that norm if we think that honesty is the best policy for purely practical reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the general point of the quote is that this process of internalising moral norms is about structuring how we &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; about action: When we do something we feel is morally good, we feel good, when we do something we feel is morally bad, we feel bad. Observance to moral norms is defined by part of the structure of our emotional responses.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting things to me about this passage is its emphasis on both the negative &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; positive emotional responses to observing a norms (it also amuses me that he lists "pride" under both). I don't know about you, but I think of morality as primarily experienced through negative emotions - especially guilt and shame - but there are of course positive emotions associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of why I've been interested in &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-virtue/"&gt;Virtue Ethics&lt;/a&gt; recently is that it feels that this is the only one of the currently extant ethical frameworks that get this right (and, interestingly, although Green doesn't make this explicit, his voices of conscience sure sound a lot like virtues to me). If you are striving for excellence, there is a sort of joy in that. If morality is nothing more than a series of duties, or a number you are seeking to make constantly go up, then morality is purely a burden, a stick to beat ourselves with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I previously wrote about the use of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-12:35.html"&gt;fine-grained ethical distinctions&lt;/a&gt; - in particularly the distinction between it being virtuous to do something and being a duty to do something - and I think these track pretty well with emotional reactions. If you fail in your moral duties, it's proper to feel guilty over that. If you have a pattern of failing in your moral duties, it's proper to feel shame over that. But if you exemplify your moral virtues, it's also proper to feel joy in that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This brings the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;safety&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-30-23:12.html"&gt;desire&lt;/a&gt; model into the question of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-10-08:54.html"&gt;how to be a better person&lt;/a&gt; - if we can take joy in our moral successes, then we will want to be better people, and this will drive us to become such.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-22-09:34.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-23-09:31.html</id>
    <title>Feet as a Foundational Skill</title>
    <updated>2020-05-23T10:41:21+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Feet as a Foundational Skill&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Fix a man's feet, and you will make him comfortable for a month. Teach a man to walk properly, and you will make him comfortable for life. Therefore denying people access to good foot education is key to monthly recurring revenue." - Ancient Capitalist Proverb.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently working on being good at feet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being bad at feet sounds ridiculous, right? Almost as ridiculous as &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-11-09:32.html"&gt;being bad at breathing&lt;/a&gt;. I am bad at both feet and breathing, and I'd wager that many of you reading this are too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons you can tell that I am bad at feet is that I've spent the last 10-15 years in semiconstant pain. Not, you know, a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of pain. Just a dull ache in most of the joints of my right leg that waxes and wanes but never really goes away. I've always been a bit reluctant to identify as someone who experiences chronic pain - it doesn't really match the definition of chronic pain, you know, other than being pain and being chronic - other people have it much worse than me (this is a bullshit line of thinking and I know it's a bullshit line of thinking. I have now more or less &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-14-13:55.html"&gt;reconciled the alief&lt;/a&gt; and recognised that, but it took a while).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another way in which I am bad at feet is that standing for long periods of time is painful. Walking is generally fine, but if I stand for more than about half an hour my legs will be very sad and probably hate me the next day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've at various points tried to get medical professionals to take these problems seriously, but it's never worked very well. The best I got is about a year and a half ago I got custom insoles made. They... maybe helped a bit? Not much.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But now, in one of the rare upsides of the world going to hell, my chronic pain is at the lowest it's been since my early 20s - it's not gone, but it's mostly retreated to a vague twinge in my hip (which is where all this started).
I attribute this largely to the almost total lack of wearing shoes, especially as it's accelerated since I've switched to barefoot shoes for running.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Standing for long periods of time is still a bit tricky, so I'm working on arch strength. I've switched to working standing in twenty minute stints recently, and doing a bunch of exercises for strengthening my arches, added a nightly (self) foot massage to my care routine, and I'm looking into toe straightening (one of the structural failings of my feet is that my outer toes curl inwards. I'm pretty sure this is related, because combining arch exercises with toe straightening is excruciating). These might or might not work, but I'm hopeful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this isn't really a post about feet. This is a post about being bad at things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At no point in the more than a decade that I've been dealing with this problem did I consider that the root issue of my chronic pain might be that I was using my feet wrong. I knew that the problem with standing was related to flat feet, but I thought of that as an intrinsic structural issue rather than something that I could work on by changing how I use my feet. At no point did it occur to me that feet were a foundational skill that I could just work on getting better at and that this would significantly improve my life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How much would it improve my life? Hard to say. Not being in constant pain is a pretty good improvement to start with but consider also...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am bad at sleep. Some of that is due to the aforementioned being bad at breathing, but some of it is due to the fact that being in pain makes it hard to sleep!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am bad at socialising in groups, especially parties. How much of that is because group social situations tend to involve a lot of standing, so I tend to be tired and in pain for a lot of them, which gives me fewer opportunities to get good at groups and also gives me negative associations with them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(As an aside, being bad at standing is something I've mentioned before as an &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-23-09:37.html"&gt;illegible marginalisation&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not saying that these are the only causes, because &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-11:43.html"&gt;very little is monocausal&lt;/a&gt;. I'm saying that among the weird and varied landscapes of life, these have exerted consistent pressure in some fairly negative directions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suspect there are a lot of foundational skills like this, and we currently don't have any infrastructure for identifying them, or learning to be better at them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly problematic because being bad at these foundational skills is something you can kinda get away with early on - you have more energy to power through them, and have not been subjected to the constant low-grade degradation of your body (or mind! Much of the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-20-09:31.html"&gt;emotions as legacy code&lt;/a&gt; model plays out this way too) that being bad at these skills causes, so by the time you start to notice the effects you're at the point where you feel like you should have life sorted out and you just treat these as the inevitable consequences of aging, when really they're a sign that you need to relearn a foundational skill.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-23-09:31.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-25-09:18.html</id>
    <title>Identity and Legitimisation of Knowledge</title>
    <updated>2020-05-25T09:55:20+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Identity and Legitimisation of Knowledge&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;PSA: Posts this week are going to be especially short because I need to focus on actual writing for my PhD this week. I'll just be copying out interesting passages from random pages of random books from my "canon" and making very short commentaries on them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/3d3aby7"&gt;Epistemic Injustice: Power and the Ethics of Knowing&lt;/a&gt; by Miranda Fricker, page 9:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see that [a silencing of a woman by a man] involves an exercise of power, of of gender power in particular. But what do we mean by power? And how does gender power relate to the general notion of social power? In order to paint a portrait of testimonial injustice and to home in on its distinctive central case, we need to answer these questions about the nature of social power in general and the particular kind of social power (of which gender power is one instance) that I shall call &lt;em&gt;identity&lt;/em&gt; power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The "testimonial injustice" that Fricker is talking about here is a notion she introduces in this book, and is an injustice done to people in rejecting their testimony based on their identity - e.g. in the case she is talking about, rejecting someone's testimony because she is a woman.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've just finished reading Lyotard's "The Postmodern Condition", an experience which I cannot really recommend, and in it he talks about the role of &lt;em&gt;legitimisation&lt;/em&gt; in knowledge - i.e. if we think of a community of practice as telling each other stories about the world, what are the social practices involved in accepting some of those stories into our canon as legitimate knowledge. He argues that sciences in particular can be thought of as having a set of particularly stringent set of criteria for legitimisation, and tend to reject other modes of legitimisation as hopelessly fuzzy and informal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Read in this light, I think one interesting lens on Fricker's work would be this:
One of the roles of social power is control over the legitimisation process for knowledge. When social power is rooted in identities, this has the particularly pernicious effect of resulting in a community's canon of recognised legitimate knowledge that systemically underrepresents knowledge originating in marginalized groups.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, as has been pointed out before by &lt;a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5250/fronjwomestud.33.1.0024?seq=1"&gt;Kirsty Dotson&lt;/a&gt;, Fricker has badly misunderstood one aspect of the nature of knowledge in a way that this highlights: There is no single canon, but instead many loosely overlapping ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This misunderstanding is also present in her notion of identity power. In fact, identity power does not exist, because social power does not exist in individuals. Social power is a relationship between an individual and a community. The same identity that denies you credibility in one community may gain you credibility in another.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that the problems of testimonial injustice she is pointing out don't exist - they absolutely do - but that they need to be more carefully contextualised. "You're only oppressed by the dominant community who controls most of the economy" is not actually any more reassuring than thinking you're oppressed in some absolute sense, but the fine grained distinction is still useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly significant in another book I've read recently, which is James Scott's &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2yzIMF8"&gt;Domination and the Arts of Resistance&lt;/a&gt;, where he introduces the idea of the &lt;em&gt;hidden transcript&lt;/em&gt; - essentially the canon of knowledge that is present within a marginalised group and is actively concealed (possibly by hiding it in plain sight) from the more dominant group.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Putting these together, one way of looking at Dotson's notion of contributory injustice, which is the refusal of dominant groups to take on the ideas of the marginalised (e.g. white people refusing to acknowledge the idea of racism), is that sometimes the transcripts of marginalised groups are hidden by the marginalised, but equally often they're instead ignored by the powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-25-09:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-26-06:09.html</id>
    <title>2020-05-26-06:09</title>
    <updated>2020-05-26T06:09:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2020-05-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2LU8yqy"&gt;Sherlock Holmes was Wrong&lt;/a&gt; by Pierre Bayard, page 20:&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-26-06:09.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
