<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2025-04-01T21:49:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-23-21:48.html</id>
    <title>How I clean my kitchen at the end of the day</title>
    <updated>2025-03-23T22:46:50+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;How I clean my kitchen at the end of the day&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-03-23&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a guide on how to clean my kitchen. I wrote it up because I
was writing it in my head while cleaning my kitchen and found that
helpful. The audience this post is most useful for is me, and when I say
“you” in it the you in question is mostly me, but some of the general
points might be of broad interest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, many of the specifics of this are only useful if you share a
kitchen with me, and thus have the exact same sets of problems,
constraints, and affordances. If so this post isn’t really intended for
you as that would be massively passive aggressive for me to write a
whole essay telling you how to clean the kitchen. Instead, if you share
a kitchen with me, I refer you to the large poster with helpfully big
letters and clear easy to understand instructions that I have posted on
the kitchen wall.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Ha ha, just kidding. I haven’t really done that. Yet.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, there are some things you should understand before embarking
on cleaning the kitchen:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is that it will, in fact, take about an hour. It might take
a bit less. If it’s a really big dinner or a lot of debris has built up
over the course of the day it might take more. But it will probably take
about an hour, and trying to speed that up massively is going to mostly
stress you out without saving a huge amount of time. You should probably
just let it take an hour. You can resent that, or you can just put up
with it, and you’ll have a better time in that hour if you do the
latter. Put on some music, or a noise track and spend the time in
contemplation, or if you must put on an audiobook. Maybe you can write a
blog post about how to clean the kitchen in your head.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Some of this process can be sped up by having an extra
pair of helping hands but honestly our kitchen is a nightmare to have
multiple people in and it doesn’t speed things up that much so I mostly
just prefer to do it solo.&lt;/span&gt;
Whatever you’re doing though, assume it will take an hour, so make sure
to start at least an hour before bedtime.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second thing to understand is that there is no such thing as
“clean”, there is only “clean enough”. You are not attempting
perfection, you are attempting to achieve a consistent standard of
cleaning. This standard mostly consists of the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no full bins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The dishwasher is running.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The surfaces are clean.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The handwashing has been done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The floor is not covered in debris.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’ve not historically been super reliable about this,
and am trying to add sweeping the kitchen to my cleaning process, but I
don’t yet know if it will stick.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sink should be empty and clean.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The kitchen should pass a “general inspection” for anything that
seems like it really should be done every time and isn’t explicitly on
this list and doesn’t massively increase the workload.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The third thing to understand is that it doesn’t matter if you’re too
tired to clean the kitchen. The kitchen still needs to be cleaned, and
if you don’t do it then tomorrow will go much worse. If you get part way
through the process and you really can’t continue, you can stop, but
you’ll probably be fine, because the process is on your side.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The fourth thing to remember is that the process is on your side.
It’s there to help keep momentum up, make it feel achievable to do more,
and minimise the amount of decision making you have to do, so you can
mostly just autopilot the entire experience, and it’s there so that if
you do give up midway through (you probably won’t), you’ve done the
right things first, and so that you won’t at any point have to go “Oh
fuck, I didn’t do that thing, I can’t be bothered to do that now…”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here is the process.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The process consists of a rolling series of goals. You should always
do the highest priority one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first goal is &lt;em&gt;there should be no full bins&lt;/em&gt;. There is a
recycling bin, a waste bin, and a food scraps bin, and if at any point
(including the start) of the process one fills up, you should stop
whatever you are doing and empty it. If it’s obvious at some point that
it’s going to fill up later, you can prioritise filling it up and then
emptying it, but this isn’t required.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’ve not historically been super reliable about this
making this top priority is a modification that became clearly good as a
result of drafting this post.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second goal is &lt;em&gt;the dishwasher should be running&lt;/em&gt;. Once
the bins are empty, all actions should be directed towards getting
things in the dishwasher and getting it running. If it’s currently got
clean dishes in it, first empty it, then load it, then run it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The third goal is &lt;em&gt;surfaces outside the kitchen should be
cleared&lt;/em&gt;. That means the dining room and living room table need to
have everything taken off them and the tables need to be wiped down.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From here, it’s a process of narrowing the area that still needs to
be cleaned over time, one surface at a time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My kitchen has two counters. Let’s call them sinkside and kettleside.
The next goal is to &lt;em&gt;get the kettleside counter cleaned and wiped
down&lt;/em&gt;. This is partly as a restriction move, and partly because
you’ll need the space to put extra drying up. Once it’s clear, lay some
cloths down to put extra drying up on it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The sinkside counter has two halves, left of stove and right of
stove. Now clean the surface left of stove, corralling all remaining
dirty dishes onto the stove top and right of stove area.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Your priority is now to &lt;em&gt;wash the subset of those dishes that
can’t go in the dishwasher when it’s finished running&lt;/em&gt;. These will
be left to dry, you’re not going to manually dry them up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this point if you’re genuinely exhausted and it’s late, you may
stop, but ideally you would not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Your next goal is to &lt;em&gt;handwash any of the dishes that could go in
the dishwasher tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;, because this enabled the following goal
which is &lt;em&gt;get the right of stove counter completely clean&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you can face it, &lt;em&gt;clean the stove&lt;/em&gt;. Don’t do a proper deep
clean of it, that’s not your job, but do get the worst of debris and the
like off it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;We have a gas stove and I hate it so much. I dislike gas
in general, but I especially hate how gross and hard to clean it is.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, &lt;em&gt;clean the sink&lt;/em&gt;. Throw out any food caught in the food
traps, give it a general wipe down.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;em&gt;sweep the floor&lt;/em&gt;. Doesn’t have to be super thorough,
just get the most obvious debris off the floor.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And, finally, done. Good job.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I said before: Having a process like this really helps, because it
lets you maintain momentum, see clear and visible progress as you go,
and prioritise in a way that makes sure the most important tasks all get
done.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-23-21:48.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-24-21:45.html</id>
    <title>Particularity</title>
    <updated>2025-03-24T23:02:31+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Particularity&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-03-24&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-23-21:48.html"&gt;I
wrote a post about cleaning my kitchen&lt;/a&gt; yesterday. You might have
seen it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I posted it on discord saying “this is probably really boring”. I
shouldn’t have done that, it was just random self-deprecation for the
fact that I’d written about such a “mundane” subject, but really I knew
it was a pretty good piece, and people liked it as expected. More
importantly, this is the sort of thing I think we need more of rather
than less, so I shouldn’t put it down.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things I’ve been worrying about recently is… deskilling I
guess. One of the concerns I have about AI in its current and near
future form is that there are a lot of things where people feel it’s
just no longe rworth doing things pretty well. If you’re bad at art, AI
is probably better at art than you. If you’re bad at writing, an LLM is
probably better at writing than you. Even if you’re pretty good at
these, a lot of the time they can do a good enough job much faster than
you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a new problem. A lot of progress has been devaluing old
skills because they’ve been replaced with something cheaper. e.g. many
things are no longer worth repairing (or can’t be repaired) and you just
replace them when they break.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The big problem with this is that being bad at things is how you get
good at things, so this creates a real difficulty where you’re sortof
discouraged from getting good at things because all the initial steps
are taken away from you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing is… I think this problem is economically real, in that a
lot of demand for this sort of thing &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; sortof fungible and
replacing an expensive human with a machine that can cheaply produce
good enough work &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a win for many use cases, but the problem
is also sortof fake in that a lot of people experience it as “what’s the
point of producing things if you’re not already a genius?” and that’s
really not how it works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The “How I clean my kitchen” essay is, in a real sense, not possible
for an AI to have written. I don’t mean it couldn’t literally put words
like that on a page. An AI can totally write an essay about how it
cleans its kitchen. &lt;a href="https://claude.site/artifacts/6cb6635f-a7d8-4954-8392-d7c17fa7ec39"&gt;Here’s
one&lt;/a&gt;. I got Claude to write it for me in a couple of minutes of
prompting. It’s sortof overwrote and mawkish and you don’t learn much
about cleaning from it, but it is certainly an essay that one could
write about how to clean a kitchen. &lt;a href="https://claude.site/artifacts/baa1d8f0-3163-4b2b-a3a2-6b81c1488134"&gt;Here’s
another one&lt;/a&gt; where I told it to be a bit more useful. It will create
as many essays about cleaning kitchens for you as you like! If you ask
nicely it might even do one by someone who isn’t a woman named Chen with
a charmingly rustic kitchen.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Claude has a major mode collapse problem where it’s not
very creative when comig up with characters.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sufficiently advanced version of Claude might even do this in a
psychologically realistic and practically useful way. We can definitely
imagine a world in which Claude is much better at writing essays about
cleaning its kitchen than I am.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there is one very important difference between Claude’s version
of the essay and mine: Claude doesn’t have a kitchen, and didn’t get any
better at cleaning it as a result of writing about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Claude doesn’t have friends or people who are
interested in its specific ways of relating to the world that can learn
about it and how it is similar and different to them by reading about
its relationship with the kitchen. Claude could have created any
personality you want. &lt;a href="https://claude.site/artifacts/94c552ac-2c51-4b08-9dd6-5fdda565c633"&gt;Here’s
one by a ballerina biker named Magnus “Sledge” Thornton&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;None of these people are real, you can’t have real relationships with
them. As fictional artefacts, they can be interesting,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although honestly all of these have the flavour of slop
to me, and I sortof cringe and my eyes slide off them as I try to read
them, so I’ve only skimmed any of them.&lt;/span&gt; but
they don’t have a particular human at their center.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Creation is relational, and it is particular. When you put yourself
in a situation where the value of what you do is interchangeable with
anyone else doing it, of course you end up being devalued by machines.
Economics can force you to be in that position, but that doesn’t mean
that what you do lacks value in and of itself. The fact that you
produced something gives it a value in how it related you to the world -
it changes you to create it, and in being particular it also matters
more to those who are relationship to you, above the artefact
itself.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-24-21:45.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-25-20:16.html</id>
    <title>Figuring out what hurts</title>
    <updated>2025-03-25T21:29:41+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Figuring out what hurts&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-03-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest reasons why the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-05-30-18:41.html"&gt;victim
of metonymy&lt;/a&gt; concept is important is that it helps you figure out
what you need to vary to fix a problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something interesting that’s happened to me recently is that I’ve had
several work calls that were 2-3 hours long. Part of why this is
interesting is that they didn’t &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; that long, because we were
pair programming on Tuple. This meant we weren’t looking at each other’s
faces (didn’t even have our webcams on).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not that there’s anything wrong with my colleague’s face you
understand. But there’s something about &lt;em&gt;looking at faces on video
calls&lt;/em&gt; that ends up producing something like fatigue&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Your regular reminder that fatigue isn’t a real thing.&lt;/span&gt;. I
have recurring video calls with dear friends and family whose faces I
enjoy seeing very much, and usually my brain is mush an hour in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also have a recurring phone call with a friend, which I usually
take while walking or doing chores, and I have no such mush effect. I’m
reasonably sure the difference is the fact that it’s voice only and my
attention is focused on something rather than someone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In constrast, spending time with someone in person has no such
limitations. Part of that is that you don’t actually spend most of your
in person interactions staring directly at someone’s face, you look
around, you look at things together, your gaze wanders. This is normal.
There’s somethign about the fixity of the face on the screen that is a
real problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Video calls seem particularly prone to being treated as a unitary
thing that just has intrinsic problems, even when those problems are
easily fixed or avoided. e.g. back during the height of the pandemic I
did singing lessons online. I’m glad I did it but it was, frankly, a bit
of a miserable experience to do online. My singing teacher clearly
thought so too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things that was bad about it was that she insisted on
trying to keep time with me as I sung. It took quite some time of me
explaining in detail how latency worked and how what she was asking for
was literally a violation of the laws of physics&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I think this isn’t technically true and we were
physically close enough that a point to point laser comms could have got
latency acceptably low.&lt;/span&gt;
before we figured out better ways to do time keeping using a metronome
app.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I assume she would have figured this out eventually - we’re now at a
point where &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; people have figured out you can’t sing
together on a video call at least - but it was just sortof baffling to
be faced with someone so specifically doing the thing that obviously
wasn’t working and just blaming it on “well video calls suck”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once we’d fixed this and switched to using a local metronome it
worked much better. I still didn’t love doing singing lessons online,
but it was no longer an active exercise in frustration.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is the thing about attending to the specific: When you know
what, precisely, it is about it that hurts, you can fix that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not all my calls with friends and family have moved to the less
painful mode, for one reason or another, but I’ve figured out my own
affordances for them. Sometimes I cook while talking, sometimes I play
Slay the Spire during a call, and both of these engage my eyes in a way
that allows me to maintain the actual conversation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And sometimes I just put up with it. Looking at my friends and family
has its upsides! But knowing the source of the specific problem gives me
options that I wouldn’t have if I just treated the effect as a
mysterious gestalt effect of video calls.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Not that I actually fully understand why the specific
thing causes this problem, but I don’t need to to work aroudn it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-25-20:16.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-26-19:06.html</id>
    <title>Creativity on demand</title>
    <updated>2025-03-26T20:53:13+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Creativity on demand&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-03-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things in my bags of tricks is using random prompts for
things. What should I write about today? IDK, draw a tarot card, flip to
a random page of a book. Write something in response to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another thing in my bag of tricks is making big lists. Can’t think of
anything? Think of 100 things instead! Can’t think how to start the
list? Come up with a bad idea. Or, even worse, a mediocre one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another thing in my bag of tricks is to look at something mundane and
figure out what’s interesting about it. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-23-21:48.html"&gt;Cleaning
the kitchen&lt;/a&gt; is an example of that. &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/using-what-youre-given"&gt;So is
making apples&lt;/a&gt;. To some degree the entire &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/my-no-longer-secret-magical-practice"&gt;spellcraft
thing&lt;/a&gt; is about this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The point that I’m trying to get at is that with all these tools in
my toolkit, it’s pretty easy for me to solve any drying up of the
creative wellspring. Not only &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-09:44.html"&gt;can’t
you run out of ideas&lt;/a&gt;, there are reliable procedures for producing
more ideas.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, here off the top of my head is a spell for writing a
blog post at the end of the day:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Get a sheet of paper. Write down what you did today - not in detail,
just a list of high level things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Pick one. If one of them catches your eye, use that, otherwise pick
semi-randomly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Try to pick out some specific features of it - things that remind you
of other things, or some way it’s unlike other things in that category.
Especially focus on how you made any decisions about it, or how it
felt.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Write about that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway you’ll notice I’m not using this spell right now. I can’t rule
out that I might in future - I did do the first part of listing out
stuff that happened in my day, and for example I thought I might write
something about some work I’m doing on parsing with derivatives, which I
thought was interesting because of a series of pickles I got myself in
and out of, or I thought I might write about the lunch I made for
myself, in which I took some leftovers from our sunday roast and some
vegetables and turned it into a vaguely Chinese meal.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Fun fact: Left over roast potatoes are great when stir
fried with a bit of ginger.&lt;/span&gt;
There’s also something to be said about the experience of waking up, or
&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/losing-yourself-in-an-audiobook"&gt;my
changing relationship with audiobooks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn’t though, partially because I’d already started on this,
partially because I didn’t really feel like it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m reading a recent translation of Max Weber’s “Science ad a
Vocation” right now, and the following passage struck me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both [a laboratory and a factory] it is necessary for somethign,
and the right thing at that, to &lt;em&gt;occur&lt;/em&gt; to people if they are to
achieve anything worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But inspiration cannot be produced to order. And it has nothing in
common with cold calculation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve also recently been reading “The Cult of Information” by Theodore
Roszak, which is surprisingly good, and it has a similar thing in it
about how a computer-focused education with its heavy emphasis on
procedural thinking cannot possibly teach children the full range of
creative and intuitive thought that we need them to develop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the point is that on some level I think they’re wrong.
Intuitively I believe that I really could write a couple of pages of
instructions that you could semi-mechanically follow and produce a
pretty good essay out of. I’m not claiming you could produce
&lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; good essay this way you understand, only that it’s
possible to produce a pretty good generator of essays this way, one that
means that you should never have to suffer the problem of sitting down
in front of the computer and not know what to write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And yet, every time I think about actually doing this, my soul
rebels.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Things like the random book prompt or tarot prompt or the like seem
mostly fine. The above spell for coming up with something interesting
about your day to report on also seems mostly fine - maybe a little over
constraining, and requires me to look at uncomfortable questions like
“What &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; I do today?” sometimes, but it’s actually an
interesting exercise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But if you tell me to, say, roll a die and use it to determine on the
basis of that what to write today, I will fight you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If, on the other hand, you tell me that if I’m not sure which one to
write then I &lt;em&gt;get to&lt;/em&gt; roll a dice to pick one, that’s just &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-make-easy-decisions"&gt;a
spell for making decisions&lt;/a&gt;. Great stuff, no complaints. Big fan,
even.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing about procedures is that they’re great tools and terrible
masters. The kitchen cleaning procedure is very good because I need to
do the thing and I don’t want to have to make decisions about how to do
the thing. A writing procedure that removes all decisions would be
terrible, because the decisions &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; the creative process. I can
be aided in making them, but anything that tries to take the ultimate
authority away from me causes me to bristle.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And this is sortof a problem for the goal of creativity on demand,
because the problem isn’t actually that I can’t produce creativity on
demand - I can - it’s that I &lt;em&gt;don’t want to&lt;/em&gt;. The whole
experience is one of dragging myself kicking and screaming towards some
goal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The idea of a fully mechanized process for writing, even one with
explicitly allowances for breaking out of it and doing your own thing,
is still fundamentally designed to take away the first and most
important decision about creating something: Whether you want to do it
at all. Once that decision is taken away from it, the creative part of
my mind mostly just wants to sit there and sulk and refuse to
participate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And you know what? Too bad. Gonna write anyway. When the dishes gotta
be done, you do the dishes whether you like it or not. When the daily
writing gotta be done, you do the daily writing whether you like it or
not. It’s probably not going to be as bad as you think, and if it is &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/believing-that-you-can-stop"&gt;you
can stop&lt;/a&gt;, but that’s no reason not to start.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-26-19:06.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-27-10:24.html</id>
    <title>Censored solutions</title>
    <updated>2025-03-27T11:42:20+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Censored solutions&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-03-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve got two&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Actually far more than two, but two that are relevant
things here.&lt;/span&gt; big things I care about:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solving problems people have&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saying things that “everybody knows” but nobody says&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which is why it’s particularly interesting to me that there are
certain classes of solution that are broadly known but almost never
mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I first started noticing this because of insomnia advice. I don’t
have &lt;em&gt;major&lt;/em&gt; insomnia, but I do suffer from it a bit, and many
people I know have it about as bad or worse.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here’s &lt;a href="https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/insomnia/"&gt;the NHS’s
advice for what to do about it&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go to bed and wake up at the same time every day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relax at least 1 hour before bed, for example, take a bath or read a
book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make sure your bedroom is dark and quiet – use curtains, blinds, an
eye mask or ear plugs if needed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exercise regularly during the day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make sure your mattress, pillows and covers are comfortable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do not smoke or drink alcohol, tea or coffee at least 6 hours before
going to bed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do not eat a big meal late at night&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do not exercise at least 4 hours before bed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do not watch television or use devices, like smartphones, right
before going to bed, because the blue light makes you more awake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do not nap during the day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do not drive when you feel sleepy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do not sleep in after a bad night’s sleep and stick to your regular
sleeping hours instead&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They then go on to mention that you can get sleep aids, either mild
ones from a pharmacist or stronger ones from a GP.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don’t perfectly agree with all of this, but it’s all perfectly
standard sensible advice, of the sort you’ll get from any reasonable
person when you ask for insomnia advice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s so standard and reasonable that I don’t know if you even noticed
that it omits one of the more widely deployed insomnia solutions.
There’s a reliable, widely known, and commonly used, solution which
helps take your mind off the racing thoughts that cause insomnia and
relax your body, and is very effective and helps you fall asleep:
Masturbating.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Or having sex, but in some ways masturbating is more
effective as a sleep aid than partnered sex. You are, after all, as Kant
would put it, &lt;a href="https://archiveofourown.org/works/15804744?view_adult=true"&gt;using
yourself as an means, not an end&lt;/a&gt;. Also when you’re lying awake
frustrated by insomnia, hopefully your partner is already asleep and
you’re unlikely to be feeling particularly sexy anyway.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am reasonably sure, through various discussions, memes, and general
logical inferences, that this is not news to most people. I’m pretty
sure you’ve heard of masturbating, and most people seem to figure out
that it helps them sleep.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it can still be useful to give advice that most people already
know. It’s remarkably common for people to either not know or forget
common every day knowledge, and also insomnia is often when you’re
feeling least reasonable, so it’s useful to have a reminder. I bet at
least one person with insomnia will read this and go “Oh! I hadn’t
thought of that!”.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And as a result there will be some random person out
there masturbating because I told them to, and that’s &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;/em&gt;,
which is one of the reasons why people don’t casually give advice like
this.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s also not just insomnia. Another of my big things is that if
you’ve got a tool that works in one problem, maybe try it in others?
Someone was asking the other day about tension headaches, and writing
this I belatedly realised that actually if you’ve got a problem caused
by the level of physical stress you’re carrying, maybe doing something
that relaxes your body would be a good idea… I’ve definitely solved
things in the headache / general malaise category this way from time to
time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Still, masturbating is a relatively special purpose tool. You’re both
limited in how often you can use it, and while it’s very useful for a
small category of problems, it certainly can’t solve everything. For
some things you need drugs!&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;To the best of my knowledge, nobody is censoring
themselves from recommending rock and roll as a solution to their
problems.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wrote a while ago about how &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/people-dont-work-as-much-as-you-think"&gt;people
don’t work as much as you think&lt;/a&gt; and one of the common responses is
“OK, but some people &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;. How can I be more like them?”. The
easy answer is amphetamines. Or maybe modafinil if you can’t get a
prescription and would rather something with less legal consequences for
getting caught.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not that stimulants are &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; for working longer. I’ve
actually found my working hours have gone up a bit since quitting
caffeine. Also, many people are just naturally like that because of some
mix of obsession and good health. But, among the people who might need
advice on this subject, the most effective (and widely deployed)
solution to this is that you take strong stimulants and that lets you
work more.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People are a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; more willing to give this category of
advice, because it doesn’t feel so weird, but there are certainly broad
categories of places where it would be inappropriate or unacceptable.
Your boss might give you all sorts of helpful feedback on how to improve
your productivity, but they will (or should) never say “BTW, I know a
guy who can get you some black market ritalin.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I struggle to come up with too many more examples that aren’t
straight up unethical.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;YMMV about whether the drugs one is or not.&lt;/span&gt; Perhaps another example is piracy,
but I think we’re at the stage where the degree to which you don’t tell
people to pirate things is that your university lectures stand up and
very sternly tell you about how piracy is bad and here is a list of the
sites you definitely shouldn’t go to because they might tempt you into
piracy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe one other category is that people prefer to offer advice that
makes them look better than they are. e.g. if you ask how to do
somethign, you’ll often be told how to do it Properly - don’t skip any
steps, make sure you check for problems, etc. - when in reality the
advice giver will often do things far more sloppily. &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/decisions-depend-on-the-decision"&gt;This
isn’t necessarily bad&lt;/a&gt;, but you also can’t necessarily trust their
judgement as to whether it is or not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s also possible that I’m struggling to come up with other examples
because there are other examples that I don’t know about because nobody
talks about them and I’m the one being clueless! That’s the problem with
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-16-14:22.html"&gt;ghost
knowledge&lt;/a&gt;. If you’re not inside the network, you don’t know what’s
going on!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, there are good reasons why people don’t offer this sort of
advice too often. I can’t be bothered to enumerate them, but they do
exist. I’m not making this post to chastise for people for not saying
“Have you tried masturbating about the problem?”, merely to point out
the more general phenomenon:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All advice you get is censored to be the sort of advice that the
advice-giver is comfortable giving, and there are often good solutions
outside of that space. If you’re stuck, and none of the suggestions
people are making are working, it’s worth considering whether there are
things that they wouldn’t suggest but would do, and seeing if any of
those work for you instead.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-27-10:24.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-28-12:43.html</id>
    <title>Behaving as if you were trying to succeed</title>
    <updated>2025-03-28T13:46:09+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Behaving as if you were trying to succeed&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-03-28&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a flat I shared a while back, for some reason we owned a wooden
meat tenderising mallet.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Disgusting object. Can’t recommend.&lt;/span&gt; One of my flatmates was the main
person who used it, so I assume it was hers, but it lived with all of
the other kitchen utensils.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One day I discovered it had been put away still covered in bits of
raw chicken. I politely expressed some disapproval of this fact.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She seemed vaguely baffled by this objection. I don’t remember her
exact words, but it was something to the tune of “I did wash it! But
it’s hard to clean”.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;As a side note, I should observe that this was a long
time ago. I no longer live with her but we’re still in touch and I
believe she has become a vastly cleaner person in more recent years. I
also very much enjoyed living with her at the time despite these
foibles. This is not a story about how terrible she was as a flatmate.&lt;/span&gt; I, in turn, expressed the sentiment
that if something is hard to clean then that means you &lt;em&gt;clean it more
thoroughly&lt;/em&gt;, or don’t use it, but that putting things away with raw
meat stuck to them was not among the acceptable set of outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;She did rewash it, but I’m not sure my point really stuck.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Unlike the chicken.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve thought about this example over and over again since then, in
various shared living situations, because I’ve run into a surprising
number of people who are bad at washing up in a particular way: It’s not
that they’re incompetent at the basic mechanical actions of washing up&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although to some degree they probably are this too,
because they lack a basic feedback mechanism required to get good at
it.&lt;/span&gt;, but that they &lt;em&gt;don’t check if
the thing they’ve washed up is clean afterwards&lt;/em&gt;, and as a result a
substantial fraction of things they wash up still have food stuck to
them. It’s usually not as bad as the raw chicken incident, but it’s bad
enough that I don’t consider the things they washed up to be clean
enough to put away without double checking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, I typically ended up rewashing stuff they’ve washed,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Depending on how bitchy I’m feeling sometimes I’d get
them to do it instead, but that’s often more stressful than doing it
myself. This is not a good strategy and I don’t endorse it, but it is
the one I tend to follow.&lt;/span&gt; which means they’ve put in a bunch
of work for literally zero effect, and made me more annoyed at them than
I would be if they hadn’t done anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, back when I used to work in more end-user-facing software
with an actual web interface and such,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is less necessary with library code because the
code is the user interface and you can see it being used in the tests.&lt;/span&gt;, I
used to deploy this really exciting magical code review technique that
reliably found problems with people’s pull requests: I checked out the
branch, launched the web application, and tried actually using the
feature. Often it had obvious problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This has become something of a bugbear of mine in general: People
doing things as if the thing itself was the point, rather than a tool
you are using to achieve a specific outcome, and not thinking about
whether their actions will actually in any way help them achieve their
goal. The result of this is often that they put in about 90% of the
effort required to do it properly, and get 0% of the actual benefit
because what they did didn’t actually work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to fix this is to &lt;em&gt;check whether what you did
worked&lt;/em&gt; after doing it. Initially, this will slow you down a bit and
add delays, but as you get good at it you will basically internalise the
process and it doesn’t slow you down much.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Except in the sense that sometimes you’ll find problems
and have to fix them.&lt;/span&gt; I
do, however, suspect that in many of these cases the actual thing you
need to do to fix this is to become someone who actually cares about the
end result rather than just wanting to avoid being blamed for not doing
the thing and hoping nobody will notice.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Bad news! I will notice. Yes, including that time you
thought you got away with it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is also important because there are many examples where you
can’t really check if it worked. For example, I still semi-often see
people wearing face masks in public. I rarely do these days, but
consider this a completely reasonable choice. Unless, that is, you’re
wearing your facemask pulled down so it doesn’t cover your nose. In
which case &lt;em&gt;what on earth are you doing?&lt;/em&gt; How have you made it to
2025 without looking up basic mask usage? But you’re never going to
figure out that you did this wrong by checking. What are you going to
check? Did I get a virus Y/N? That’s an incredibly noisy signal, and
tracing it back to the specific error you made is going to be almost
impossible. The only way to get this right is to actually care about
getting things right and then take whatever action is appropriate for
achieving this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, to be clear, I’m not claiming I always succeed. Sometimes I’m
rushing and forget to check something. Sometimes I check something
insufficiently carefully. Sometimes I check something and misinterpret
it, or otherwise make a stupid error. I’m not saying I’m perfect, I’m
not asking you or anyone else to be perfect.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I am asking you to care about succeeding, and when you are
failing, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-25-20:16.html"&gt;try to
figure out why and do better&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-28-12:43.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-29-10:40.html</id>
    <title>Well you gotta</title>
    <updated>2025-03-29T12:10:21+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Well you gotta&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-03-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/for-the-better-right"&gt;The
Anakin/Padme meme&lt;/a&gt; seems to have occupied a useful conceptual shape
in my brain. You’ve probably seen it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The original goes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anakin: “I’m going to change the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Padmé: “For the better, right?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anakin: (gazes in silence)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Padmé: “For the better, right?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For whatever reason, this particular shape appeals to me, so I see
the pattern over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lately I’ve been thinking about it in the context of one of my corner
of the internet’s recurring catch phrases. “You can just do things”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anakin: “You can just do things.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Padmé: “That you want to, right?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anakin: (gazes in silence)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Padmé: “That you want to, right?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of why I think about this particular pattern a lot is parenting.
It’s common interaction with the child that I tell her she needs to do a
thing,&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Such as have a shower, clean her room, do her homework
assignments, all of the incredibly boring mundane cliched tyrannies of
parenting.&lt;/span&gt; and she replies “but I don’t
wanna”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have yet to adequately convey the magnitude of my lack of interest
in whether she wants to or not through anything other than the deeply
nuanced philosophical position: “Well you gotta”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t particularly work for persuading her you understand, but
neither does anything else, and it’s a more accurate, more honest, and,
I think, healthier position than trying to convince her to do it because
she should do it because she wants the end result, because often she
doesn’t care (or claims not to care) about the end result either and I
don’t consider her opinion on whether she’s allowed to be stinky or have
cavities or whatever to be relevant. I would, of course, much rather she
care about those things too, but one of the goals of parenting is that
it’s your job to make sure good decisions are being made.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of things of course where the fact that she doesn’t
want to do them is, in fact, and important and overriding consideration.
I’m not going to force her to play a board game she doesn’t want to play
for example.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Though I will at least discourage her from quitting one
midway through.&lt;/span&gt; The point is very much not that she
should do whatever I (or her other parents) want. It’s the much more
specific and important point that some things need to be done, and it
doesn’t matter if you want to do them, they still need to get done and
you need to be able to do them regardless of whether you wanna.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another meme in my circles is non-coercion, which is the idea that
you shouldn’t force yourself to do things. This also extends into
non-coercive parenting, which is that you shouldn’t force your kids to
do things. I suppose I don’t exactly disagree, but I think the details
are important to get right, and when “doing something because you’re
forced to” is treated as the opposite of “doing something because you
want to”, something has gone very wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you want the ends and not the means. Sometimes you don’t
even want the ends but have an obligation to do them.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;You could argue that you want to fulfill your
obligations, but I would argue in turn that fulfilling an obligation
&lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; very different from a positive motivation to do the thing
most of the time.&lt;/span&gt; In
these circumstances, forcing yourself to have to pretend to want the
means in order to achieve the ends is &lt;em&gt;very bad for you&lt;/em&gt;, because
it forces you to basically lie to yourself about what you want. Being
able to calmly, and without any particular joy in your heart, do the
thing because it needs to be done is a much more valuable attitude to be
able to take.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some of this comes down to parenting for me as well, and this is
definitely an attitude I’ve inherited from my parents. My parents are
both functioning workaholics. My dad, in particular, is in his 70s and
seems absolutely tireless to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Except, in fact, he’s not. He’s tired a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;. He’s got far
worse sleeping problems than me - they run in the family, and he got
them from his mother. So he often wakes up exhausted. And then he goes
out and does a phenomenal amount of hard physical labour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He once passed on a conversation he’d had with his mother about
tiredness. Her advice went something like this: “Yes of course you’re
tired. The trick is to not worry about it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I expect in the original version she sounded less like
Lawrence of Arabia.&lt;/span&gt; You
just have to get on with things anyway.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At the time I hated this advice, but I’ve grown to see the wisdom of
it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When talking about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-23-21:48.html"&gt;cleaning
the kitchen&lt;/a&gt; I made the point that you can choose to resent the fact
that it takes an hour or accept it, and that you’ll have to do the same
amount of work either way but it will be much more pleasant for you if
you don’t spend it resenting the effort.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The same is true with needing to do things. You can resent them, or
you can just do them because they need to get done, and the latter will
be in every way more pleasant for you, and even if you’re not happy
about doing the thing you will be a happier person for being able
to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is, of course, possible to take this too far, and end up burdened
by obligations that you don’t want because you’re the most reliable
person in the room because nobody else takes on this attitude. I’ve
ended up in that situation in past workplaces for example.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The most reliable and viable solution to this is to couple the
ability to do things that are needful with the ability to ask “OK, but
is this actually my problem?”, and a degree of conflict tolerance that
allows you to make it other people’s problem when it should be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, personally, the solution I would most prefer but have never
quite been able to manage is for other people to also adopt this
attitude and stop being goddamn freeloaders.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-29-10:40.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-30-11:41.html</id>
    <title>Necessity creates possibility</title>
    <updated>2025-03-30T15:42:55+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Necessity creates possibility&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-03-30&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the big reasons I’m doing daily writing right now is that I
quit caffeine. I have a very entrenched belief that quitting caffeine
makes it harder for me to think, and my evidence for this is that my
writing habit evaporates every time I quit caffeine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is, as a factual matter, true that I stop writing when I quit
caffeine. That is a thing that happens. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-22-21:54.html"&gt;Writing
feels impossible&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there is, it turns out, a great technique for doing impossible
things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to do the thing and fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-25-20:16.html"&gt;Figure
out the actual specific thing that went wrong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is my proposed default thing that goes wrong when you try to do
something that feels impossible: You think about doing the thing, you
are overcome with despair, you declare that it’s just impossible right
now, and then you flinch away from it and go do some dissociative
activity to self soothe from the aftermath of your terrible encounter
with the impossible.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Ask me how I know…&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of why I’m big on &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-29-10:40.html"&gt;necessity&lt;/a&gt;
is that it is a fix for this problem. If not doing something you find
aversive is an option, not doing thing is likely to be the option you
pick. If you’re definitely going to do the thing, you’re able to have a
genuine encounter with it without much fuss.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is, as a purely factual matter, not the case that it’s impossible
for me to write while not on caffeine. I write on WhatsApp or discord or
Twitter&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Well, not that one any more.&lt;/span&gt; all the time when off caffeine. The
actual mechanical act of writing is not that hard for me, and I often
say perfectly interesting things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could absolutely just open up the notebook, paste a comment from
discord, and write here every day without thinking. I could flip to a
random page of a book and copy out some text on here. I could write “I
am a fish” 500 times.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I am tempted to just do this one day to stop this from
being a hypothetical that I use and make it a real live possibility.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means that the only thing that is preventing me from writing
here every day is that I am &lt;em&gt;choosing not to&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, step one: Choose to. Put daily writing in the category of
necessity. This forces me to admit that it’s not actually impossible -
it’s not actually even terribly difficult - it is just mildly
uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This, in turn, creates encounters with the real problems that you’re
avoiding. Turns out, for me, I was struggling to find things that were
interesting for me to write about. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-26-19:06.html"&gt;It’s
not that I don’t know how to generate things to write about&lt;/a&gt;, but
those don’t feel interesting either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think part of what’s happening here is that there are two major
relevant differences between my brain on caffeine and my brain off
caffeine:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With caffeine, my threshold for something seeming interesting is
much lower.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With caffeine, my thoughts are buzzing all around and generating
many different overlapping ideas all the time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So when I’m caffeinated, sitting down to write is basically just a
matter of waiting for an idea to come along, grabbing it out of the air,
and pulling on it until the thread of an essay comes out. On the rare
occasions I’m stuck, I use a random prompt to lightly prime the process,
but really even with the random prompts it works in part because my
brain is extremely prone to going “AND THAT REMINDS ME OF FIVE OTHER
THINGS”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I’ve actually got something to write about, it’s not actually
that bad to write. It requires dealing with a degree of discomfort and
anxiety about the process, but it’s just a little bit slower and more
halting, it’s not actually a big deal it’s just mildly unpleasant.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is more true for notebook posts than for full
fledged essays that I actually have to think about because of how much
I’m just basically writing down my chain of thought reasoning here
rather than trying to make a clear well-articulated point.&lt;/span&gt;. But sitting down and going “argh
fuck argh what do I write about?” is torture, partly because it’s
intrinsically unpleasant and partly because it triggers a whole “oh god
my brain is broken how can I live without caffeine? Woe is me, for I am
an abject wretch, deprived of that which gives my life meaning!”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway that sounds like a problem, David, have you tried solving
it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yes I have, and it turns out it’s extremely easily solved, and the
magic was inside me all along because I’ve solved this problem before.
&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/using-a-list-to-manage-executive"&gt;The
solution is to make a list of things I could write about&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve now
just got a little pad of paper on my desk with the heading “Things I
could write about”. When something comes to mind during the day that
seems interesting to write about, I jot down some slightly cryptic
phrase or sentence describing it, and when I come to write something I
look at what’s on the page. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-27-10:24.html"&gt;Censored
solutions&lt;/a&gt; was the first post I wrote using this system (partly
because writing &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-26-19:06.html"&gt;Creativity
on demand&lt;/a&gt; is what helped me spot it), and it’s been great since.
There are currenly 20 items on the list (including ones already
written).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The key thing that makes this work is that although it turns out that
I can’t currently generate ideas of what to write about at a rate that
means they just freely appear when I sit down to write, I sure generate
a lot of ideas in a day, the problem is that they don’t reliably stick
in my memory. As long as over the course of a day I generate more than
one idea to write about&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;It looks like right now I generate about five. It’s
likely that that will go down over time, but not necessarily - writing
begets more writing, because it gives you new things to think about.&lt;/span&gt;, the list will always be full.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I haven’t yet decided what to do when the list fills up.
I need to figure that out after finishing writing this post.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the point I’m making is not this specific technique is great
(although it is), it’s that this specific technique was in fact &lt;em&gt;very
easy to create&lt;/em&gt;, and I’ve tried and failed to write through caffeine
withdrawal multiple times before without creating it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I have actually tried a daily writing habit while off
caffeine before and it didn’t stick, but the way it failed was that I
was having a terrible time for other reasons and went back on coffee
before I ran out of backlog of ideas of what to write about.&lt;/span&gt;
Taking the option of not writing off the table and just making it my
problem to figure out how to do it any way forced me to figure out what
the real, specific, problem was, and do something about it rather than
just treating it as impossible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Necessity creates possibility: If you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to do something,
probably you’ll figure out how.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Or, you know, fail horribly and die. But it’s hard to
fuck up a writing habit so hard you die.&lt;/span&gt; If it’s optional, it’s
too easy to make excuses as to why you couldn’t possibly do it.
Frequently those excuses will feel very real and plausible, but
evaporate as soon as confronted with a firm insistence that you try.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-30-11:41.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-31-18:47.html</id>
    <title>Win Streaking and Reliability</title>
    <updated>2025-03-31T19:10:48+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Win Streaking and Reliability&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-03-31&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve been trying to learn to win streak in Slay the Spire recently.
That is, get several wins back to back. I’m only playing on Ascension 1
for this, although I am trying to kill the heart (if you don’t know what
this means: Challenging but not the hardest mode).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty good at Slay the Spire. I’m not the best, not even close,
but I can semi-regularly beat it on the hardest mode, which is a
reasonably difficult achievement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I think one of the things this experiment is very much
demosntrating to me is that I’m playing it wrong. I’m very much engaged
in what you might call “vibe play”&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Get your mind out of the gutter.&lt;/span&gt;, where I’ve got a pretty
well honed intuition as to how to play it, and mostly follow that with a
little bit of tactical reasoning layered on top.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t produce many win streaks. I think on good days I win
maybe… 5-10% of my ascension 20 games, and probably somewhere in 40%
region for ascension 1. This is good for generating lots of wins, but
very bad for win streaking. At 40%, you’ll get some two-streaks,
occasionally three-streaks, and very rarely four-streaks.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, I think, an intrinsic limitation on vibe play, and if I want
to actually win streak I need to start doing some sort of deliberate
play. The problem in slay the spire is that it’s very easy to learn ways
of playing that work very well if the game hands you gimmes. e.g. I
think everyone can beat the heart on A20 most of the time when they get
dead branch/corruption, but you don’t get that very often. If that
happens in, say, 1% of games, you can pretty easily vibe-play your way
to an appreciable win rate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A more general example, one that I think I’m prone to, is that it’s
very easy to take too many risks in Act 1, which will let you either get
very strong early on or die early on. This pretty rapidly gets you up to
a decent win rate where you win a substantial fraction of the time that
you don’t die in Act 1.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is definitely a little bit my problem, although I’m
more likely to die in Act 2 than Act 1 because Act 2 is the hard act.&lt;/span&gt;, but you have a high loss rate in
Act 1, and trying to fix that ends up actually lowering your win rate
because you’re not strong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things I’m trying to point to in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-30-11:41.html"&gt;Necessity
Creates Possibility&lt;/a&gt; is that it’s very easy to end up in this
situation in real life too. It’s very easy to write when you’re in the
mood to write. That gets your win % on writing up to an appreciable
amount above zero. But if you don’t learn to write when you don’t feel
like writing, you end up very limited in how far you can improve.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem with moving off vibe play is that part of how you learn
vibe play is that it’s fun.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Stop snickering.&lt;/span&gt; Learning to step outside
that requires taking a more deliberate perspective on the game. I’ve
talked before about &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/record-yourself"&gt;recording
yourself playing&lt;/a&gt; to do this, but at this point I’m probably better
off actually breaking out pencil and paper and sketching out things
like:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What’s my goal?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do I need to have achieved by floor X?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What probability do I assign to clearing this act?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And having a very slow methodical approach to the problem, where I
actually think about what I’m doing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sounds boring TBH.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is often a problem you get: You can succeed on pure
talent and enjoyment as long as things are going your way, but in order
to get really good you have to become reliable, and in order to do that
you have to figure out how to succeed even when the world isn’t
cooperating with you.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-31-18:47.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-01-21:49.html</id>
    <title>You create rules, rules create you</title>
    <updated>2025-04-01T21:49:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You create rules, rules create you&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2025-04-01&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I used to be a huge &lt;a href="https://www.beeminder.com/"&gt;Beeminder&lt;/a&gt; fan.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In some ways I still am a huge Beeminder fan (certainly
I’m a big fan of the Beeminder team), I just happen to be a
non-practicing one.&lt;/span&gt; For
those who don’t know, Beeminder is a commitment system. You say “I’m
going to do this thing X times a week”, or “I’ll spend at most X hours a
week doing this”, or any other commitment about your life that you can
phrase as a metric.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the features of it I thought was extremely well thought out
was the way changing this commitment worked, which is that you can
change it at any time… and that change will take a week to take effect.
You’re always allowed to let future you off the hook, but the fact that
you don’t want to adhere to your commitment right this very minute
doesn’t get you off the hook.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can, of course, fail to uphold your commitment (“derail”), at
which point you pay Beeminder a previously agreed penalty.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;You can also email them with an excuse as to why you
should be let off the hook and an actual human will read it. Sometimes
they’ll just let you off the hook, sometimes they’ll say “Are you sure
that’s a good enough reason?” and maybe you’ll shuffle your feet and say
“No I guess not” and pay them or maybe you’ll stick to your guns.&lt;/span&gt; It
essentially makes the entire thing a sort of asynchronous negotiation
between your past and future selves. You can decide what commitments you
want to hold your future self to, and you can choose whether to break
your current commitments to your past self, but you cannot
&lt;em&gt;forgive&lt;/em&gt; those commitments. You are forced to either uphold them
or pay the costs of not doing so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is often a good model for trying to choose who to be,
even when it’s not as cleanly mediated by beeminder. When I talk about
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-30-11:41.html"&gt;necessity&lt;/a&gt;
it’s really this sort of commitment made by your past self that I’m
talking about. I don’t pay a financial penalty for failing to write
daily, but I do pay the emotional cost by knowing that I’ve let down
this thing that past me has committed to. At some point I will indeed
decide to stop the daily writing&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Typically I keep it up for 1-3 months before it starts
to lose the appeal, and that’s fine. But also… maybe I won’t. Maybe I’ll
just keep up the daily writing forever, possibly with some
modifications. Who knows?&lt;/span&gt;, but when that happens
it won’t be because one day I’ve just decided I have enough, it will be
because I choose to release future me from his commitments to
writing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Probably at some point in that time I will fail to write some day.
That was nearly today, honestly. It’s not been a great day. This isn’t
the end of the world. Maybe there will be a good reason for it and I
won’t feel bad, maybe there won’t be a good reason and I’ll resolve to
do better, but the important thing is that I will acknowledge that the
rule was broken, and this was an important fact that I should respond
appropriately to, and that I should consider this fact when deciding
whether to break the rule or not - ask myself if I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need
to or if I could in fact do the thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think being able to choose rules that you follow and then stick to
them is very important, and you can use them to shape your emotional
reactions to things, and make aspiring towards be the sort of person you
want to be easier.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One problem with the Beeminder analogy&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And part of why I don’t use Beeminder any more.&lt;/span&gt; is
that it makes it sound like the rules you follow are mostly about
creating negative emotions - they create ways of punishing yourself for
not upholding the ideal. I don’t think this has to be the case. For
example, with the daily writing there’s certainly a sort of “Ugh, I
guess &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-29-10:40.html"&gt;I’ve
gotta&lt;/a&gt;” feeling because I know I’ll feel bad if I don’t do it, but
then I follow the rule it feels &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. There’s something very
satisfying about writing every day, above and beyond the general
satisfaction of writing. It helps elaborate a stream of thinking that
ties thought into life in a way that I very much appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also have rules that are more lightweight or even purely
positive. For example, one rule I live by is that I always say hello to
ducks if I see ducks. Why? Dunno. I started doing it, and I enjoyed it,
so I kept doing it. It’s not a rule I would feel guilty for not
following, but it is a rule I actively try to follow and it pleases me
to do so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think you can also do this by creating your own &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/fragments-intellectual-diy"&gt;idiosyncratic
categories and distinctions&lt;/a&gt; about the world. For example, I have a
mental category of “proper meal” which is basically defined by it having
to have three different vegetables in it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;There is a series of complicated rules and codicils to
this rule. For example: Neither mango, obviously, nor onions are
vegetables, but a dish which combines mangos and onions counts as one
vegetable. I’m aware this is a stupid piece of convoluted Byzantine
logic, but also it’s obviously correct so shut up.&lt;/span&gt; I
try to have at least one proper meal in this sense per day. I don’t
firmly commit to doing this, but a day in which I have at least one
proper meal feels better than a day in which I don’t, because I’ve
decided that this is the sort of meal I should cook.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things I learned with Beeminder is that you can’t add too
many rules at once. It quickly gets overwhelming and you quit the whole
thing in distress as your willingness to engage with the experience
collapses under the burden of it. But for many of the rules we live by,
the actual rule has long dissolved into being just… you. I occasionally
reach for the proper meal rule when I’m trying to figure out what to do
and having some explicit guidance would help, but mostly it’s just baked
in to how I cook and eat. I don’t even think about the ducks rule, I
just see ducks and I say hello. I brush my teeth twice a day, but that’s
not a rule at all at this point it just wouldn’t occur to me not to and
it would feel wrong until I fixed it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But when you’re trying to shift who you are, particularly when you’re
trying to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-03-31-18:47.html"&gt;more
reliably be the sort of person you can only sometimes be&lt;/a&gt;, sometimes
a rule and the ability to commit to it is just what you need. You’ll get
the rules wrong sometimes, and when you do you absolutely need to be
able to change them without guilt, but before you can change them you
need to follow them.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2025-04-01-21:49.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
