<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2022-01-17T09:08:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-08-08:36.html</id>
    <title>Grappling with vastness</title>
    <updated>2022-01-08T10:33:33+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Grappling with vastness&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-08&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out I've written about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-06-12:00.html"&gt;drifting&lt;/a&gt; before, albeit obliquely, in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/why-is-it-hard-to-choose-what-to"&gt;Why is it hard to choose what to do?&lt;/a&gt; where I talked about the difference between proactive and reactive work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One reason why I’m interested in this split is that I’ve found that how proactive I’m able to be is a pretty reliable predictor of my mental health. On a bad day, the ability to be proactive goes long before the ability to be competently reactive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I often find myself having days where if you dropped me in a coaching call I would be perfectly alert and useful and able to do a decent job, and between calls I get nothing done1 - I check Twitter, or I watch YouTube, play a game, or maybe (probably not) I go for a walk or do some cleaning or the like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way this feels internally is that I’m perfectly able to do things, but what I’m unable to do is generate things to do. This is unfortunate, as in theory I have lots of free time and the ability to do quite interesting things, but often they don’t get done anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is, on a bad mental health day, faced with the requirement to choose what to do, I drift.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rereading this piece makes the difference between my newsletter and my current notebook writing fairly clear I think. It's a very intellectual approach to the problem - it's not that I don't talk about the feelings involved, but even there it speculates about them in a very detached way that I'm not sure is entirely helpful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/The_Lagrangian/status/1478122278307041280"&gt;Adam puts it&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what if your cognitivist problems like "akrasia" and "low executive function" are actually emotional problems like "this scares me" or "i don't actually care"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I noted that drifting feels a lot like a freeze response ("I'm too tired to do anything" is a common feeling leading to drifting), and, well, maybe it is. Maybe I encounter the vastness of free choice available to me and Freeze in response to it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not hard to see little versions of this sort of response.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What should I do with my life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What should I do today?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What should I write today?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What should I write on my notebook today?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What should I write on my notebook today about what I've been thinking about recently?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you move down the list the possibilities become more constrained, until it becomes narrower and more tractable.
Towards the beginning of the list, you have to confront the vastness, and that's scary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem isn't just that you have to make a choice from within infinite possibilities. It's that you have to grapple with your agency over those choices, and confront your lack thereof.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I started writing about how the problem was infinite freedom and some part of me rebelled, because it's not, is it? In fact there is very little freedom right now, and dealing with "What should I do today?" causes me to confront that head on, let alone "What should I do with my life?". Given free choice over what to do today I'd probably try to hang out with a group of friends in person, but even in the before times that's hard to organise on short notice, and right now it's all but impossible (or at least feels like a bad idea).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Choosing smaller problems allows me to grapple with things that are my size, and that I know I can handle, but as I expand the scope, I have to grapple with a world of possibilities that is vastly larger than me, and could easily crush me as and when it fights back, and honestly, yeah, this scares me.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-08-08:36.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-09-10:00.html</id>
    <title>Memory and yearning</title>
    <updated>2022-01-09T11:03:17+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Memory and yearning&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-09&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm told normal people remember their childhood. I don't, not really.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At least I say I don't. The memory is clearly there a lot of the time, but it's not always very salient. It takes digging.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know how other people experience memory. I often hear things like "Counter to what you might expect, memory is not recalling a snapshot of what happened from an archive, but is instead a story you reconstruct from pieces" and this sentence sounds a bit like "Counter to what you might expect, water is not a burning sea of flames, but is in fact wet".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Does memory really feel like you're recalling what it was like to be there for you? It certainly doesn't for me. It's more like a puzzle hunt.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm good at remembering facts. Very good. I probably have better access to my mathematics degree 15 years later than most people do after 5.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's because facts fit together. If you don't remember the fact you want, you at least remember something like it. Then you can chain it along - following links of associations until you find the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can do the same thing in a conversation - my superpower is that when you ask "Wait why are we here at this point talking about this thing?" I can generally replay exactly the link of topics that got us here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Memory of events sometimes works like that, but particularly with childhood stuff it all feels like a jumble. There's no organising principle I can follow for most of it - I can construct a timeline, more or less, based on where I lived when, major events, that sort of thing, but when I come to fill in the details it's often a blur.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Adulthood isn't &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better, but it's more recent and thus more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even when I try to sort through the fragments it feels more like an experience report. "Yeah, that happened". There's no real feelings attached to it for the most part. Sometimes the me that is remembering has feelings about it, but trying to recreate how I felt at the time is just a guessing game - the information isn't there as far as I can tell. It's just a list of facts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or at least that's what I tell myself. It doesn't seem likely that it's true though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things I've been noticing recently is that some things that remind me of childhood make me sad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not the things you'd necessarily expect - a lot of things about my childhood sucked (mostly school), but remembering those there's a certain distance from them and most of what I feel about them is rage. At the time I was probably miserable, but these days thinking about it just makes me want to burn the system down.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here's the first time I noticed it recently, and you'll laugh: Watching the premiere of the new Wheel of Time series.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear. There's nothing about the Wheel of Time that should inspire deep emotion, either the books or the TV adaptation. But they were a big part of my childhood - I must have started reading them when I was about eight (this is really too young to have started reading them, but oh well), picking up The Eye of the World in an airport bookstore en route back to Saudi from the UK, and was an avid fan for a while. The books definitely got worse over time, but I kept reading them as long as Robert Jordan kept writing them. Book five in particular (sadly one of the not very good ones) got me through a particularly difficult period where I had nothing else with me to read and needed to hide from an unpleasant situation. I must have read that book at least four times. Unfortunately nothing actually happens in it, so I didn't get much from the experience except a reprieve.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(This is what I mean when I say that my memory is clearly better than I pretend it is. It's not actually hard for me to recall this information, I just treat it as hard).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I found myself on the verge of tears during episode one. No real risk of actual crying, but definitely that feeling around the eyes as if you &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; tear up if you just leant into it. I'm not very good at leaning into it, honestly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know how much other people get this, but it's like when the orchestral score for a movie is &lt;em&gt;clearly&lt;/em&gt; trying to manipulate your feelings to make you more moved by a scene than it actually warrants and it works dammit. You know there's nothing there, but the shadow of the emotion falls over you anyway and you can feel the edge of the tears there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I noticed it again recently watching the YouTube channel &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/BREADSWORD/videos"&gt;BREADSWORD&lt;/a&gt;, and their video about &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=428ZxrW6jhk"&gt;Disney's Robin Hood&lt;/a&gt;. Nothing terribly sad there, although something about their general presentation often triggers a bit of this for me (I think it's that they always seem at least slightly sad themselves), but that movie was definitely something I watched multiple times as a kid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Neither of these are particularly explicable. I'm not sad &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; something, I'm just sad. There's clearly some emotional association they're triggering that leads to sadness, but the feeling isn't revealing anything about what that assocation is. Maybe it's just latching on to some remembered sense of being a kid, and it seems pretty plausible that as a kid I was sad a lot of the time (although I'm not sure I would have expressed it that way).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It feels like maybe the idea that I don't remember feelings from the past is also a lie I tell myself, and that I'm just dissociating from them, holding them at arm's length because they're too much to deal with, so they have to find other ways to sneak around the censor.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last night talking with L I mentioned that I have a long standing "minor" yearning (pro tip: If a yearning keeps coming back to you over and over again over a period of many years, it's not actually minor even if you're pretending it is) for stars. It feels like I never get to see the stars any more. If you look at the sky in London, you'll see almost nothing. There are too many lights everywhere even if there aren't clouds (and there are often clouds). Even outside of London, light pollution is everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This got me to talking a little bit about when I'd really have properly got to see the stars in the past, and my childhood experience of this is camping in the desert. We did this a lot as a family. I don't, if I'm honest, have very fond memories of it - I was not a particularly active kid that I can remember, and being in the desert involves being hot, sandy, far from any shower, and on the look out for scorpions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But the stars must have been glorious. The desert sky has no clouds to speak of, and you're far from any sources of light.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I know I must have looked up at them, but I don't really remember. This is one of the other problems with my memory - I have almost no ability to visualise, and so almost no visual memory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly I might not have even been able to see the stars. I don't remember when I got glasses, but I spent a lot of my childhood unable to see things properly until someone realised that maybe I needed glasses (I had no idea that the world wasn't supposed to be blurry) but I'm not sure when that was. I know it was in the UK, when a friend of the family noticed that I was squinting and handed me her glasses to try on and I went "oh huh so &lt;em&gt;that's&lt;/em&gt; what a tree looks like?", but it must have been before we'd moved here permanently.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But either way, I think the desert is where my yearning for stars comes from, and I find that thinking about the desert very much taps in to this well of sadness that things like remembering favourite childhood media merely sips from. I don't know what it is, but something about trying to remember the desert properly brought me to tears while writing this. Couldn't tell you a thing about why, but it wasn't a subtle effect.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think a lot of my working with feelings has very much started with thoughts and concrete problems. I've taken the feelings seriously, but always in relation to the thing they were about, and so this sort of feeling without an obvious target isn't something I really know how to work with, and childhood memories seem to be something I actively ignore, so never think to work with. As a result, there's clearly a lot there that I've been pretending isn't, and should probably try to figure out how to connect with.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-09-10:00.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-10-10:41.html</id>
    <title>Being unreliable</title>
    <updated>2022-01-10T15:52:30+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Being unreliable&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the worst things about me is that I'm fairly unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Much of it is for reasons beyond my control. It always feels like an exaggeration to describe myself as "chronically ill", but I am on a literal reading of the phrase chronically ill. I get ill a lot. I spent all of December ill, more or less, between one virus or another. Started out with what was either a mild flu or a really bad cold, extended it with a fairly strong reaction to my COVID booster, and then kept daisy chaining new viruses on top of that, getting a new one each time I was feeling better from the last one. It sucked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then there are the days where I just wake up feeling terrible for no obvious reason and it doesn't let up. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1480595949671964674"&gt;Apparently based on polling on Twitter this is not uncommon&lt;/a&gt; which is, I guess... not exactly a relief, but misery loves company. It's certainly concerning that the numbers are that large.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-04-14:48.html"&gt;recent major sleep problems&lt;/a&gt; are also adding to this of course - sometimes I wake up and I've not had nearly enough sleep. Even before that my quality of sleep is highly variable. I used to think of this as a "sleep problem" in that I woke up feeling terrible and attributed that to a result of sleep, and it lingered, but I'm no longer totally sure this is the case. It certainly could be (e.g. one candidate cause is mouth breathing at night).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sort of day to day unreliability makes it very visible to me how bad most work arrangements are for people who can't manage to reliably show up every day for a job. I'm not quite that bad in that I can &lt;em&gt;show up&lt;/em&gt;, but my level of function on a given day may not be meaningfully different from if I didn't. Fortunately I'm good enough at my job that most of my employers have never really noticed - I can just about fake function in a meeting, and my work on the good days tends to be more than enough to make up for the rest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is kinda what I mean by it feeling like an exaggeration to say I'm chronically ill. People with more severe chronic illnesses often can't clear that bar, or need more accommodation. Nevertheless, it sucks and I don't like it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this isn't really intended to be complaining about my health, though maybe I should write about that as well some time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of the basis of my unreliability seems more emotional in nature. Maybe some of the emotions are underwritten by the physical unreliability, I don't know.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm also really unreliable for things at longer time scales. It's very hard for me to commit to things over a long period of time, because over time they acquire this massive... ugh isn't quite right. It's not that they're aversive, it's that the very idea of them feels exhausting.
I've had a few things that haven't gone this way - for example I have managed to maintain a writing habit over a period of decades - but writing feels like more of a skill than a project. I have this problem just as badly with writing projects.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is also, in large part, while I failed to complete my PhD. It hit the point where I just couldn't bear to work on it, so I didn't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It also shows up on a day to day basis - I make a vague plan to do things and then never follow through. I set intentions to e.g. have a habit of cleaning regularly, and don't. A lot of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-06-12:00.html"&gt;drifting&lt;/a&gt; happens when there are plenty of things that I could be doing that past-me intended to do and I intend future-me to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm aware this is yet another post that will cause people to say "David, you have ADHD" but I really don't think so. I'm certainly somewhat in that direction, but the assessment tests think I don't meet the threshold, and stimulants don't seem to help this problem all that much. Also my internal experience doesn't feel like it's all that much like people with ADHD describe theirs as.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was going to claim that I don't feel wracked with guilt over this, and I guess this is true, but there's definitely a certain undercurrent of shame to this, and especially to talking about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular the way we treat reliability as a moral responsibility really adds to that. I do, largely, endorse that. I would like to be reliable, both for myself and other people, and think I would be a better person if I could be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One way of doing that is not trying and just having better support structures. Being more reliable is definitely one of the things I most &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html"&gt;want help&lt;/a&gt; on, but I have no idea how other people can help me on this. Working in a company does that to some degree, but going and working for someone else increasingly doesn't feel like the right fit. Definitely one of my fantasies for once my current business takes off in a big way (hopefully a when not an if) is having a PA to help keep me organised, but that only really scratches the surface of the problem - really I need collaborators. I'm not going to stay remotely on task for as long as I'd like to on a big project without some external assistance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of this is something I feel like there should be pre-existing structures for. Or at least it's something I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; there to be pre-existing structures for me to slot into. Maybe there are, maybe I just slipped through the cracks, but I don't think so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The smart but unreliable person is pretty common, and we're very useful if you can give us the right support, but it increasingly feels taboo to even think about providing that support, let alone asking for it. You're supposed to be reliable on your own, and aren't entitled to anyone else's help in being so. How are you supposed to learn to be reliable if you're not automatically? Well, figuring that out is your responsibility too. Tough luck if you can't manage it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In many ways this would be easier if it were ADHD. As well as being potentially manageable with medication (though truthfully I'm pretty reluctant to consider medication for my problems that feel like they have an emotional underpinning. No judgement to anyone else who does, this just feels like the wrong solution for me), ADHD gives you more of a social license to ask for accommodations - it's not my fault, I have ADHD, so you have to take that into account. Whether people &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; take it into account is another story, but in principle the option is there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't really know that I want accommodations anyway. I don't think of the things I want as accommodations - accommodations are things you give people to help them fit into a place in the world that is fundamentally not designed for them. Often this is much better than the alternative, which is that you &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; help them fit in and just let them suffer, but it's not ideal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Really what I want is some mix of figuring out the underlying issues, both health and emotions, that allow me to be more reliable, and build a part of the world that fits me.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-10-10:41.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-11-03:23.html</id>
    <title>Being fragmented</title>
    <updated>2022-01-11T05:57:21+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Being fragmented&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-11&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being human is weird and I don't really get it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This may be surprising to you, or it may not, given I've probably spilled most of a million words writing about it, but really that's how that works. People aren't good at explaining things they understand easily.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But a lot of that is about being a human among other humans. This is, admittedly, what being human is, and you can't really separate the human condition from the experience of other humans, but nevertheless there's something about the basic n=1 human experience that I feel like I don't get some times.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A while ago I asked &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1085634803381297152"&gt;if people experienced themselves as their body or their body as something they pilot&lt;/a&gt;. I've gotten better at experiencing my body as me since I asked that (though I'm still not perfect at it by any means), but the thing that's increasingly hard is experiencing my brain as me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sounds bad, maybe it is. It's not that I think my brain is anyone else. All of the bits I have ready access to feel like they're doing fine, but it feels like there's so much going on that I don't have access to, and it's very frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't tell how much this is just me and how much is just the human condition. Sometimes when I don't understand something fundamental like this it's because I'm missing something that other people get, but I think a lot of the time other people are also confused about it when it's pointed out them and just ignore it most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But it feels like there's clearly a lot going on under the surface. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-09-10:00.html"&gt;My relationship with memory is very confusing&lt;/a&gt; and there's clearly a lot going on there that I don't have direct access to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not totally clear to me whether I should &lt;em&gt;expect&lt;/em&gt; to be able to directly access these things. All of it feels a bit mysterious. It may well be like feelings, where you have to essentially use something else to "bridge" the parts of your brain that aren't talking to each other directly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing that sometimes works as bridging is some sort of talk aloud protocol. Writing is, in theory, similar but I think doesn't work as well. Hearing yourself speak and noticing what comes out is often a surprisingly good means of finding out things about yourself. If only it didn't feel so weird to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been experimenting a little bit, on and off, with &lt;a href="https://photographyinsider.info/image-streaming-for-photographers/"&gt;image streaming&lt;/a&gt; as a way to learn visualisation. I've had precisely zero success with this method, precisely because speaking out loud seems to be hard for me in a way that disrupts the process. I've had a little more progress with doing the things they say don't work, just paying attention to vague visual impressions I have while half asleep in bed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My working theory about visualisation is that it's basically a user interface to some sort of underlying capability, and I'm definitely not completely lacking that underlying capability, but it feels like I'm communicating with it in semaphore. e.g. I've got a pretty good spatial memory, and there's definitely &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; I can do that is like mentally walking around in a place that I have lived for a while. Or even just spent a reasonable amount of time. There's even a bit of a somatic component to it - I have an experience as if walking around in the place. I could no more really tell you what I'm doing than I could tell you how I left my hand up. I just do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I'm obviously not walking around in the space. It's more like the equivalent of an inner monologue - there's no confusing it for sound, and yet it has a sound like quality. This is what I assume (and have somewhat confirmed) visualisation is like for most people too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But there's clearly still some of the things that visualisation is supposed to access going on. I can, e.g. describe what someone looks like from memory. It just doesn't go via an imagine appearing in my head. &lt;em&gt;Something&lt;/em&gt; is providing the information, in whatever form, I just don't have access to it as anything other than a black box feeding me information.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general, all the capabilities of my mind feel fragmented. Like there are different pieces talking to each other, but large chunks fail to participate in any sort of unitary whole. This isn't plurality - I don't feel like multiple people occupying the same space - it's more like I'm a person with a computer, and some of the capabilities of the human-person computer reside in the computer which the person has to type commands into.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sounds dramatic, but I'm pretty sure some degree of this is normal. Being human is weird, and the more you look at it the weirder it gets, so most people don't look at it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which is fine. It's mostly unproblematic as long as everything is working.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But often not everything is working. When tired, or ill, or half-asleep, capabilities stop working or become slow to respond. It feels like it's unsurprising that &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-04-14:48.html"&gt;I sometimes panic at night&lt;/a&gt; - the capabilities I rely on to function as me are disrupted, and the fragmented nature of thought starts showing.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-11-03:23.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-12-00:46.html</id>
    <title>Coffee as a way of life</title>
    <updated>2022-01-12T05:18:26+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Coffee as a way of life&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-12&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right now I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; want a coffee, and I shouldn't have one, so I'm compromising with a green tea. But this daily writing is about whatever is on my mind, and apparently coffee is what's on my mind today, so let's talk about coffee.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in early December I got the flu. It wasn't much fun, and I spent a couple of days basically unconscious.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result, I took the opportunity to break my caffeine addiction. This made it even less fun, but past a certain intensity it doesn't really matter if it gets a bit worse because I'm basically asleep and full of cocodamol either way.
I had a coffee break scheduled for the week after anyway, so it wasn't bad timing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been a coffee addict for about 20 years at this point - started when I went to university, and have continued ever since.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People look at you funny when you describe it that way. For some reason people don't think that the drug they take every day in order to feel normal is a real addiction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile Pact coffee, who I use(d) for coffee deliveries sent me this email after I started writing this post, and clearly know exactly what they're doing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You took a break from fresh coffee deliveries a while ago. I just wanted to check whether you're stocked up, or it it's time to unpause your plan? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're ready for your next hit of the good stuff, just hit 'Unpause my Plan' below, or you can log in to your Pact Account Page to unpause your Plan whenever you need to. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People's responses when you tell them that you're quitting coffee are often absolutely infuriating. "Why would you ever want to quit?" is common - apparently the fact that they literally can't conceive of life without their drug of choice is evidence that it's &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a big deal...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most users also skip their daily drug dose so rarely that it doesn't even occur to them that the withdrawal symptoms are related. My dad has a story about how he used to get these really mysterious headaches every weekend and he couldn't figure out what was up with them, until he eventually realised that maybe the large quantities of strong coffee he drunk at the office might have something to do with it...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The best piece of advice I've given to people talking to me about this is to imagine I'm saying "cigarettes" instead of "coffee" as a sanity check for whether what they're saying is helpful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, quitting coffee is hard, because you end up building your whole day around it. The first priority in the morning is dealing with caffeine withdrawal (if you wake up feeling like shit every morning, sorry that's probably caffeine withdrawal), which drags you out of bed to make coffee. You drink your coffee, and now you need to go to the bathroom (coffee keeps you regular, although how pronounced this effect is depends on the type of coffee). Now you've got lots of energy (although not necessarily the good kind) and can get on with your day. This gradually wanes throughout the course of the day until by night time you've run out of caffeine, feel sleepy, and fall asleep.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Or at least that's how it is for me. Others differ.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Quitting coffee I have... none of that. This causes all sorts of problems. For example, since quitting I've been &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; struggling to get out of bed in the morning because the cue I've been using has been the caffeine withdrawal, and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-04-14:48.html"&gt;my current sleep problems&lt;/a&gt; seem to partly stem from not being sleepy enough at night due to the lack of caffeine withdrawal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In general it feels like the loss of caffeine has destabilised my entire way of being in the world. I'm much less agitated and fidgetty, which is one of the key reasons why I wanted to quit it, but it turns out I used a lot of that agitated fidgetiness as the basis of getting things done. One of the benefits of the daily writing this month is that it solidly proves to me that I can write without caffeine which is honestly not something I entirely believe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is all of this worth it? Honestly, I don't know. I like not feeling like shit in the morning, and not spending my day either wired, sleepy, or both, is pretty neat. I can read hard nonfiction in the evenings now because my brain hasn't run out of caffeine to fuel it, which is also neat.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But sometimes I have really bad days and I desperately want a coffee because I think, often correctly, that it will help. And this isn't ideal because when my caffeine tolerance is low, caffeine is a hell of a drug (it's about 4 hours since I started writing this post as I had some calls in the middle, and I'm still buzzing off that green tea and a little worried that I won't be able to sleep tonight). Caffeine really helps me plaster over variance, and is one of the tools I've used to be &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-10-10:41.html"&gt;slightly more reliable&lt;/a&gt; over the years. Also it's very easy for one bad day to lead to another, especially if the caffeine I used to fix the first disrupts my sleep, and before long I've got a caffeine addiction again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More than this though, it just feels like being a bit of a stranger to myself. There's the version of David that I was on caffeine, and there's the version I am now, and they're not miles away from each other but they're different enough that the whole thing feels disorienting. It feels like a healthier place to start from, but it also feels like I'm having to relearn basic things. Nothing about my day or my emotions works quite like I expect, because there are subtle shifts in how everything works - the rhythms of my day are different, and the mood I bring to tasks is different. It feels like I'm having to relearn a lot of things from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a pretty decent chance I fall off the wagon and go back to being caffeine David. It's not like this is the first time I've tried to quit coffee, and they usually fail - in my most successful attempts I get a couple months in and go "Wait am I just going to be this depressed forever? That sucks." and go back to drinking coffee.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I'd like to stick with it this time. I like different things about caffeinated and decaffeinated David, but the latter seems like a better foundation for deciding who I want to be, even if I have to learn a lot of the basics of being him from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-12-00:46.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-13-04:16.html</id>
    <title>Regrets and interventions</title>
    <updated>2022-01-13T07:22:30+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Regrets and interventions&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-13&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've seen a number of people write letters to their past selves recently. I keep thinking about doing so, but I have questions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mostly I want to know about what model of time travel we're using.
Do I stop existing when my past self receives the letter, or do I create an alternate timeline?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I, by and large, like existing. I'm not sure what to think about continuity of self in general. I'd probably use a teleporter, but time travel based genocide/suicide in order to birth a new world with a different version of me in it seems like a step too far.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't just pedantic quibbling about the question in which I try to avoid what it's &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; asking. The question is important.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You see, a fantasy of sending a letter to your younger self expresses a very straightforward core belief: If you wished the best for the younger version of yourself, you would make sure they never become you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I struggle to regret being me, mostly for the relationships in my life. I'm probably supposed to not regret being me for intrinsic reasons, but eh. I'm fine I guess. I'll admit to liking many of the other versions better. But those versions had different life paths, and met different people, and I'm sure those people are equally fine, but I like mine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But in the scenario where I get to advise young David on his life path, I would definitely offer him plenty of advice, and if he listened to me it would lead to a very different life. Probably many very different lives.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's difficult to look back at nearly 40 years of life and think how much you'd have done differently, and I think a lot of my memory "problems" probably come from avoiding doing that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It feels like I've essentially meandered my way through a long series of choices that seemed like a good idea at the time but, in retrospect, weren't, or needed to be better thought out. As a result the point in life I've ended up in is... fine? But there's plenty of in-retrospect-obvious paths where a letter from future me would probably have been very life improving.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't feel bad over not having taken those paths exactly. Many of these better paths are ones where I wouldn't really have been able to figure them out at the time. Some of them are ones I'm still struggling with. There are past paths that I wish I'd stuck with, but this would have required a &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-10-10:41.html"&gt;level of reliability with which I'm still struggling&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I'm pretty sure &lt;em&gt;someone&lt;/em&gt; would have been able to figure them out. This is why I have &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html"&gt;such strong feelings about help&lt;/a&gt;. There was no time travelling letter from my future self that could have fixed things, but there was an entire human civilisation in which I was embedded that seems weirdly indifferent to the growth and well-being of the people within it. Probably the people who could have helped existed, and maybe I could even have had access to them if I had sought them out, but I wouldn't have had the first idea how even if I knew that I needed to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I guess, to a large degree, this is why I write much of what I do. I don't have the ability to send it back in time, but my problems are hardly unique, and maybe if they're in a similar position to me, what I write can substitute for someone else's letter from a future self that they're not getting either.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-13-04:16.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-14-16:49.html</id>
    <title>Walls of people</title>
    <updated>2022-01-14T17:54:01+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Walls of people&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's an idea from Jungian psychology that traits that piss you off more than you would endorse often come from traits you reject in yourself - things that you would, on some level, like to be able to do, but feel like it would be bad or not allowed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think this is always true, but the overwhelming majority of the time I treat it as true there's an "Ah... fuck." realisation that comes after.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, one thing that pisses me off to an irrational degree is people in tube stations who just stand around obliviously in the way, dawdling around uselessly in the most inconvenient places as if they didn't have a moral obligation to be constantly anxiously monitoring their environment and themselves in order to avoid inconveniencing other people. Monsters.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm sure there's nothing to look at there and this is a clear case where Jung was wrong. Yes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel similarly about people making too much noise. For example, playing music on your phone speakers while on public transport is, as far as I'm concerned, literally a war crime.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not all of my neuroses are public transport related. I'm also like this about neighbours. A previous neighbour would often deliberately blast loud music into the street out of their flat window, and the lack of subsequent arson charges is a credit to either my self-control or my alibi and I'll never tell you which.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My neighbours are quite loud. Also the sound insulation in this building is garbage, because construction isn't actually designed by people who give a shit about what their flats are like to live in. But definitely the neighbours are also much louder than they should be given that.
Naturally, I resent this bitterly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't even jokingly pretend I don't know where this one comes from. I'm a fairly quiet person, and some part of me really really doesn't want to be. That part wants to scream, long and loudly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"Why scream?", you might reasonably ask. I don't actually know. Anger and frustration are part of it, certainly. Not necessarily at anything in particular (or nothing in particular that I admit to myself), just a lot of that that's built up and been imperfectly dealt with over the years, and the accumulated detritus needs a release.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think that some of it is just that I want to be able to. Some sort of declaration that I'm here, and that I'm allowed to be here, and I'm allowed to take up the space I need.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thing is, I can't. As we've established, no sound insulation. My neighbours will definitely hear me screaming if I do, and no matter how much tolerance you have for your neighbours being inconsiderate with their noise usage, you hear a loud and extended scream you're definitely going to freak out and probably going to call the police. Chances are nothing actually bad will happen to me, but boy would it be a lot of drama.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've thought about going to a park in the middle of the night or something as a place to do this. Throw my head back and scream at &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-09-10:00.html"&gt;the stars&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But sound carries pretty well at night, and if you hear someone screaming in the middle of the night in a park you're &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; calling the police.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are practical solutions to this problem and I've already thought of them. If I really wanted to scream, I could go hire a properly sound proofed music practice room somewhere. Maybe some day I'll do that. But this isn't really about solving the screaming problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Being loud is the easiest way to take up space. Loud people fill the room in a way that doesn't leave space for others, and generally I hate them for it. If you want to be heard when there's a loud person around, you have to be loud in turn, and now everyone's life is worse.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But as a result, a desire to be loud is the easiest way to become aware of the walls of people surrounding your life, and how hemmed in you are by them on every side.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People try not to notice each other, but this only works as long as you don't do something too strange. If you break the norms, they definitely notice. The best case is they judge you for it, the worst case is that there are actual consequences. People don't like it when you break ranks, and the mob is not kind.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The truth is it's not as dangerous as all that, and much of this can be solved by caring less, but caring less has never been my strength.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I like cities, I do. There's a lot to recommend them. But the last few years feel like I've been getting all the downsides of living in London and none of the upsides. On top of that, it's difficult to feel safe leaving on public transport, so there's a deeply claustrophobic feeling of being trapped here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been thinking of getting a car. I'd hoped I'd never need to own a car, but there's a freedom to owning one that it's very hard to replicate with anything else. I'd like to be able to just get in my car and escape London to somewhere that's as close to remote as you get in England.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's nothing wrong with being inside walls, but sometimes you need to go outside.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-14-16:49.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-15-17:03.html</id>
    <title>Being an ideas guy</title>
    <updated>2022-01-15T18:18:11+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Being an ideas guy&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-15&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have a complicated relationship with the fact that I am that much maligned creature, an ideas guy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I'm going to use the gendered term "ideas guy" throughout because a) The stereotype of the ideas guy is very much a guy b) We don't have a good gender neutral term as a result and c) I am a guy)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better at ideas than &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-10-10:41.html"&gt;follow through&lt;/a&gt;. My ideal situation is to be in an environment where my main role is to consult on or suggest problems rather than do the legwork of seeing things through to completion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not a popular archetype. People like me are generally seen as being selfish - wanting to do the fun bits and let other people do the hard work.
It's not entirely unfair. I'm not averse to hard work, but I am averse to &lt;em&gt;sustained&lt;/em&gt; hard work - ideally I'd work hard on a problem until I get bored of it and then hand it over to other people. Sometimes I get bored of things after a couple of days, sometimes they hold my attentionf or months, very rarely they hold my attention for years.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I will say in my defence that I've done my time in the hard work mines. My career has been an endless series of looking for places where I get to go do clever researchy things, I then come in and immediately concluded that what they needed wasn't clever research but responsible engineering and then, reluctantly, admitted that yes I could provide them with that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't mind having done that. I think it's very hard to have any good ideas in a space you've not developed a solid foundation in. But I did it for ten years, and burned out, and enough is enough. This sort of thing is not what I'm for - I can do it, because I'm pretty generically competent, but it doesn't make me happy and burns me out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also a poor use of my abilities, honestly. I am much, much, better at getting other people unstuck than I am at working reliably. As a result, if you add me to a team in this capacity, I probably expand the capacity of the team immensely, but if you add me to the team as one of an interchangeable set of developer roles I still make things better, but I'm just a good developer, nothing very exciting happens. I'm a far better force amplifier for other people than I am a worker on my own.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, I think, a major deficiency in our conception of teamwork. We treat "being a team player" as meaning being part of a homogenous group of people where you're supposed to take on the same responsibilities as everyone else. Sure, maybe you have different skills, but "I'm not able to do that work" is supposed to be the main reason to refuse work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think this really properly respects the strengths of heterogenous work, or the variation in people's individual abilities.
Certainly it's not reasonable to expect to only get to do the fun work, but it's also not reasonable to to ignore your team's individual strengths and weaknesses when planning, and if someone is able to vastly improve the capabilities of others, it's better to have them doing that.
Some of us are smarter than we are reliable, and trying to "fix" that will generally not result in someone who is both smart and reliable, but someone who is miserable and unmotivated and maybe if you're lucky slightly less unreliable than they otherwise would be.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the way out of this is partly to think about what ideas guys are for.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This notion of being a force amplifier for others is not, generally speaking, part of our typical conception of what an ideas guy does, and I think this is because we're confused about a number of things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is that we assign credit too heavily based on who has the idea. The reason the ideas guy is so unpopular is that it's very attractive to people who want credit without doing any work. As a result you get a lot of glory seekers. Most of them also have shit ideas.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ideas don't deserve none of the credit, don't get me wrong, but the people who do the work to actually execute on the idea are typically as or more important than the ideas guy that got them started.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another is where we need ideas. I think your classic stereotypical ideas guy just comes up with an idea for a project then delegates it to other people and sits back and relaxes, or goes on to come up with another project to hand off to someone else. This is how you get &lt;a href="https://archiveofourown.org/works/3673335"&gt;the Stargate program&lt;/a&gt;. This is a bad use of the ideas guy, because they mostly end up creating work ungrounded in the reality of its execution.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been reading a bit about the history of Bell Labs recently, and one of the things that was most interesting about it was the role of AT&amp;amp;T in how effective Bell Labs was. Obviously they were a source of funding, which was important, but more importantly they were a source of &lt;em&gt;problems&lt;/em&gt;. John Gertner's "The Idea Factory" describes Bell Labs as a &lt;em&gt;problem-rich environment&lt;/em&gt;. You had rooms full of smart people, and their job was mostly to be on call when someone wanted to know how to best place telephone poles or reduce noise on a line.
Bell Labs basically invented the entirety of modern computing (e.g. both the transistor and information theory came out of Bell Labs), but the thing that really made it work was that people there were doing research in response to many mundane and practical concerns.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Conveniently, almost every attempt to execute is a problem-rich environment, and it seems like it would be great to have an ideas guy responding to that - someone who you can go to get help when you're stuck, or who can proactively investigate ways to improve. You can think of this as the servant ideas guy, in analogue with servant leadership.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something like this feels like my ideal role, or perhaps that it used to be.
To a degree this is already &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1NyGGU3qDUpvO_7iP66Q8b7L5HjDe6biPiEjau8LJCO0/edit"&gt;what I do with my consulting work&lt;/a&gt;, although that's less embedded in the team than I would like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think what I want these days is some mix of servant ideas guy and classic ideas guy - I do actually want to have ideas for direction (although I need to get out of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-03-14:16.html"&gt;my current malaise&lt;/a&gt; if I'm to do that), but I need other people around and working with me to properly go in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This doesn't necessarily involve me being "in charge" - it works just as well if a bunch of people get together to mutually agree to work on the same problem - but it also doesn't involve entirely working on other people's problems like consulting or normal employment do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Either way though, it's time to get comfortable with this as a key part of who I am, and what I need to thrive. I suspect many others need this too.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-15-17:03.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-16-08:40.html</id>
    <title>Curiosity is a team sport</title>
    <updated>2022-01-16T20:36:10+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Curiosity is a team sport&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-16&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-03-14:16.html"&gt;Relearning curiosity&lt;/a&gt; I talked about the need to talk to others about things I'm interested in. I've been thinking some more about this some more and run into what is, in retrospect, an obvious problem: I don't have the first idea of how to do this, and I think this is because I'm doing something wrong prior to getting to that point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you about the one time I tried to do research level mathematics. The question I was interested in was this: Given a discontinuous function \(f: X \to \mathbb{R}\), where \(X\) is some topological space, how closely can it be approximated by a continuous function in the uniform norm? There is an "obvious" lower bound of \(\delta(f) = \sup\limits_{x \in X} \inf\limits_{U \ni x} \textrm{diam}(f(U)\), where \(U\) ranges over open sets. Is this lower bound tight?
The answer proves to be yes, if \(X\) is paracompact. Is the converse true? i.e. if \(X\) is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; paracompact, are we guaranteed that this bound is not tight?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out, yes, more or less. This question had all been thoroughly explored by some German mathematician back in the 70s, which took me a while to find out because Google Scholar wasn't really a thing I knew about back then (it did exist, but I'm not sure I knew it existed and certainly I wasn't good at using it - this would have been 2005 or so). I can no longer find the reference, which shows how much I still care about the problem. But at the time it was a neat problem to get my teeth into.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This problem has a couple of characteristics of things that are easily interesting to me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the problem statement is relatively accessible. In this case that means it's relatively accessible if you have a certain amount of mathematical knowledge, which I did, but it's not &lt;em&gt;super&lt;/em&gt; off into the weeds. This will not be obvious to you because I've made no attempt to handhold you into it and also my idea of what counts as accessible is weird, but the point is that I could start tackling the problem immediately.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it's pretty niche. Less niche than I thought, clearly, in that it &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; have a niche of people who had worked on it a while ago, it's just that it was unfashionable. Also being unfashionable seems a common theme in my interests.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, it's not all that useful, and if you asked me why it was interesting I wouldn't be able to give you a good answer (certainly not now, but probably even then). It's just neat, in a way that I can't really articulate or defend. It's within arm's length of practical things (for a pure mathematician's notion of practical), but not itself practical. There's no extrinsic reason to be interested in it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unlike most things I tend to get interested in of that nature, I did have the advantage of having a friend who I could interest in the topic. We worked on it together for a bit until we discovered the prior art and got disappointed. That doens't happen to me much these days.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Other things I've been interested in over the years include random voting, test-case reduction, various interesting algorithmic problems, etc. Recently I've been getting into writing Wordle solvers, just for the lulz. There have probably been many others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The crucial feature of all of these is that I noticed something interesting that seemed under-researched, picked it up, and ran with it for a bit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which is to say uh... I appear to be picking my interests in a manner that actively selects for things that other people are not currently interested in, and then being very surprised pikachu when this results in not having people to share my interests.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've tried to get other people interested in these sometimes. If I hadn't flamed out of my PhD, that was ostensibly the point of it - getting other people interested in test-case reduction to the degree that I was. It turns out marketing is hard. Hypothesis was a genuine opportunity to share my interests with people and collaborate on them, but unfortunately I mostly burned out on that by trying to make it do too much for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can explain my interests to lots of people. &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/10/how-to-explain-anything-to-anyone/"&gt;I'm very good at explaining&lt;/a&gt;. 
But as &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-15-17:03.html"&gt;I wrote about yesterday&lt;/a&gt; I'm increasingly feeling like my ideal working environment is working in a team, and I think a lot of the time what I want is not for people to listen to my interests, but to engage with them fully and work with me on them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back in &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/maintaining-niche-interests"&gt;Maintaining niche interests&lt;/a&gt; I talked about how if you've got niche interests you want to maintain, you probably need a community for that interest, but I think I understated the problem there. I tried to fix my increasingly lackluster level of interest in computer science by forming a computer science community, and that was a good thing for me to do but didn't help, because what it got me was an &lt;em&gt;audience&lt;/em&gt; for my interests, which falls very far short of partners.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And, well, if that's actually what I want, why the hell am I working on this as an individual and trying to interest people in what I've done after I've already picked something that makes it hard?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Surely, if you want to have interests you share with people, the thing to do is to start with people you want to share interests with, and then work together with them to find and develop those interests?&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-16-08:40.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-17-09:08.html</id>
    <title>Fulfilling work</title>
    <updated>2022-01-17T09:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Fulfilling work&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's &lt;a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2013/04/23/good-idea/"&gt;almost certainly apocryphal&lt;/a&gt;, but there's a supposed quote by Gandhi that goes as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journalist: What do you think of Western civilization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gandhi: I think it would be a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is what I feel about the enobling power of work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a thing I've noticed on and off which is that people who have never worked, in some generalisable sense, are &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;/em&gt;, in a way that I do not intend to be as complimentary as I often do when I describe someone as weird.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't necessarily mean "had a proper job", and there's all sorts of other things that count as "work" in my book here. My central example of someone like this is not someone on unemployment benefits, but a trust fund kid. People who are rich enough that their life hasn't ever really required them to work for things. They may still have had a hard life in other ways, and I'm sure they have myriad &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-07-15-09:33.html"&gt;nice problems to have&lt;/a&gt;, but there's something that feels very dysfunctional about them - a sort of purposelessness and failure to engage with the actual reality of the world, or their relations with other people, because they have never really had to test themselves against the former and have always had the resources to avoid relying on the latter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a problem that, to some degree, I can relate to, and feel like I'm struggling with a bit myself. To the degree that I have not fallen into this trap, my history of actually working seems to be a large chunk of the character I rely on to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've not really had a "proper" job for the last 6 years - I've had projects, and I tried doing a PhD, and I've picked up freelance work on and off (which I'm properly taking seriously now so will be more on than it has been), so it's not like I've been idle or had no money coming in, but it's definitely felt more like being a NEET than like being in employment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And there are aspects of employemnt I miss a great deal, even if there are other aspects that I do not miss at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To me it feels like there's some sort of central human experience which has all of the following components:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A group of people, working together on a problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problem has an actual (even if small) impact on the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problem is difficult and without working hard on it they will fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All (or most) of the people in the group actually care about the problem and want to succeed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No member of the group could succeed at the problem on their own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each member of the group is an active participant in the process, and the end result depends on how well they fulfill their role.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Possibly this list isn't sufficient, but it all seems necessary to be an example of the thing I'm pointing to, which one might as well call something like "fulfilling work".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For me the optimal examples of such things are research and development, but they don't have to be. Renovating a house or working in a garden, for example. Hosting an event to some degree counts (it depends a lot on the event - certainly running something like a conference does. Throwing a party seems to be lacking something, probably the impact aspect).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think many people have roughly zero experiences like this in their life, but their job is the thing that comes closest. Some people even have this in their jobs, although I think it's not the norm.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Certainly, jobs being fulfilling work is not my experience - my jobs have all failed on (4), in that I think roughly nothing I have ever been paid to work on as a software developer has felt like something I cared about for its own sake. Some have reached the heady heights of "Oh yes I guess that might be good to exist", some of them have been intellectually neat problems to work on (which I then reluctantly went and worked on the boring engineering they obviously actually needed rather than the neat problems they hired me for), but none of them have been things I would have considered worth my effort if, well, they weren't paying me a lot of money for it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was also a bit lacking in (6) - generally the end result wasn't bottlenecked on how well I fulfilled my role because the nature of working at startups is that the thing that will kill you is whether or not the people with power are competent to run a company and choose a product direction. Spoiler: They usually aren't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It does, however, have all of the other characteristics, to a much larger degree than really anything else in my life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Hypothesis is a close second, but I sortof failed at working on it around the point it was starting to become truly collaborative, for unrelated reasons)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-16-08:40.html"&gt;Yesterday's post&lt;/a&gt; was partly me coming to terms with the fact that hobbies and personal interests &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; don't fill this role, and the other people are a necessary part of it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of discourse that one could handwavily frame as "work vs leisure". Obviously you need both and the strawman versions of both of these positions are idiots, but I feel like the thing that is missing from both the pro and anti work discourse is that the sort of work you need is not just any work but &lt;em&gt;fulfilling&lt;/em&gt; work, and that much of what people experience at work is a cruel caricature of that experience.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And I do think that we need something of this nature, not just leisure. People create themselves in concern with other people, and test themselves against reality, and this sort of shared project that actually matters is our best tool for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-17-09:08.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
