<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2022-02-19T11:28:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-24-17:12.html</id>
    <title>Seeing clearly</title>
    <updated>2022-01-24T20:03:20+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Seeing clearly&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-24&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For the last day or two I've doing something I haven't done for years, and it's making everything so much clearer.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is to say, I've got my glasses on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They're not especially good glasses. Or rather they're very nice glasses that have the wrong prescription, because I got them in 2019 when I finally had to acknowledge that my vision was decaying and that ugh fine I should get some glasses. The prescription was &lt;em&gt;barely&lt;/em&gt; enough to matter - a mild astigmatism in my left eye, a little bit of short sightedness in my right - but it was enough that I was starting to notice and it seemed worth getting glasses to correct it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I didn't wear glasses for the next two and a bit years.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I still in some sense don't "need" glasses. I can function fine without them. My eyes are even driving standard still. But there's been an increasingly noticable amount of eye strain. It's not that I can't read signs at a distance, or look at fine details across the room, it's just increasingly obvious that this is hard work. I've had a lot of tired eyes and headaches recently.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've known for literal months that the lack of glasses was causing me trouble, so I did the obvious thing: I left them sitting exactly where they were, untouched. I certainly didn't put them on my face.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've been wearing them for the last couple of days because I'm going to be driving a car tomorrow and that "driving standard" claim is, while technically true, not quite the standard I hold myself to when driving a car. I also don't drink when I'm going to be driving, not even an amount under the legal limit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I really am safe to drive a car at my current level of vision. But... honestly compels me to admit that I'd certainly be &lt;em&gt;safer&lt;/em&gt; if I had slightly better vision. It's probably not enough to matter, but being at the wheel of a deadly weapon certainly puts you in contact with the reality of the world in a way that is hard for me to ignore. I can much more easily pretend my refusal to wear glasses isn't causing me a headache than I can pretend that it isn't increasing my chances of killing people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This all makes me sound like a very nervous driver. I'm not. I'm pretty confident of my driving ability, and being nervous behind the wheel makes me less rather than more safe. So, I drive confidently, but when &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in the car I acknowledge that for all their upsides, a car has an unpleasantly high statistical murder-suicide rate, and I make decisions in advance that reduce that rate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Further, radically changing your vision for the first time when you get behind the wheel of the aforementioned statistical murder-suicide machine is, to borrow a technical term, &lt;em&gt;fucking stupid&lt;/em&gt;, so I've been wearing my glasses for the last few days to get used to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The prescription isn't quite right, as I mentioned, and so I have begrudgingly booked an optician appointment for next week, but it's still a lot better than without the glasses. It's not an "&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-09-10:00.html"&gt;oh that's what a tree looks like&lt;/a&gt;" moment - I can see trees just fine thank you very much - but it's a "Oh I'm supposed to be able to read signs at &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; distance am I?" moment. No doubt after I've had my eyes checked again and got some new glasses (or possibly just new lenses for these ones if that's an option) there will be similar revelations in my future for me to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know how good you are at reading subtext, but chances are good you might have picked up on the subtle hint here and there that I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don't want to wear glasses.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I should, perhaps, give you some context. Up until 2010 if I didn't have my glasses on I would have to hold a book several inches in front of my face to read. I probably wouldn't literally walk into things, because large blurry objects are still large objects that I can see coming, but if you were on the other side of the room from me I would be recognising you from height and colour palette only. Then in 2010 a nice man fired laser beams at my eyes and I acquired ~superpowers~ the ability to see things near-perfectly without further vision correction. Wait, no, I was right the first time. Superpowers. Compared to my previous state this definitely felt like superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, a decade passed, and during that time I failed to figure out a way to transcend the frailties of my mortal form, and as a result my eyes got older and weaker again, and now here I am with a need to strap an awkward contraption of glass and metal to my face in order to bring my basic functional capabilities up to human baseline and have fewer headaches.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My objection is not aesthetic. I look good in glasses. It's a very different look, especially given that the last time I regularly war glasses I had hair, but in many ways I look more like me in glasses than I do when not wearing glasses. Although, truthfully, that's maybe part of the problem - the me I look like is the me of my 20s. Maybe the me of my mid to late teens even. The me of my preteens and early teens wore awkward giant dorky glasses, before I started wearing thin frames and smaller rims, but I spent a long time with my face looking like this and a lot of it wasn't particularly good, and I'm not particularly proud of the version of me that existed back then. I want to reach back and give him a hug and tell him everything is going to be OK, but I don't particularly want to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; him.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know if this is actually my real objection. It might be just a clever theory. The actual complaints that are coming up are that glasses feel weird on my face. I'm not used to the weight and the feeling of htem, and I feel hyperaware of their presence on my nose, and of the slight reduction in peripheral vision. It's likely that I'll just get used to it, but I don't especially want to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another resentment is definitely that I don't like aging. Yeah, me and everyone else, I know. Glasses feel like a particularly cruel reminder of it though - you know that problem you thought you'd fixed? Unfortunately, bodies!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suspect some of this is also just a sort of... resentment at being forced to make a choice about a tradeoff? I've never really had to choose whether to wear glasses or not before. As a young child, I didn't know that seeing things was an option. As a slightly older child, I could choose between being able to see things and not being able to see things, so I went with the one that was obviously better. For most of the last 12 years, I've not needed to choose whether to wear glasses or not, because why would I I didn't need them?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now though, I'm caught like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buridan%27s_ass"&gt;Buridan's ass&lt;/a&gt; between two very similar options, except instead of choosing between two delicious bales of hay, I get to choose between two slightly crappy options.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm aware that many people are absolutely fine with glasses, and that I probably will once again become such a person and if not will eventually find another nice man (or woman, or other) to fire lasers at my face, but for now please forgive my petty resentments at the constraints placed upon me by my biology.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-24-17:12.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-25-07:18.html</id>
    <title>Failing to resist temptations</title>
    <updated>2022-01-25T08:03:25+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Failing to resist temptations&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-25&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am, as I've mentioned, &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-18-13:15.html"&gt;bad at finishing things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You know what I'm not bad at finishing though? Crisps. You put a bag of crisps in front of me, it's gone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am fortunately saved from pringles by my dietary restrictions, because the following analogy that I used to talk about whether &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-06-12:00.html"&gt;drift&lt;/a&gt; was pleasant or unpleasant is 100% accurate to my experience:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drifting is unpleasant in the same way that eating a tube of pringles is unpleasant. You know you shouldn't start, but then you do, and you're not really enjoying it, but you keep eating it, and then you get to the end and you think "Ugh, why did I eat that?" and then the next time a tube of pringles is opened in front of you you do it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm not even good at resisting the temptation of things I &lt;em&gt;don't particularly like&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/first-hard-choice"&gt;The first hard choice&lt;/a&gt; is my post about temptation and addiction, and it's an odd post to be sure, but one of the oddest things about it is that I feel quite so strongly about this subject given that I don't have any particularly scary addictions. I don't even smoke, I drink in moderation, I have minimal to no experience with harder drugs (and what minimal experience I have only in countries where they're perfectly legal, naturally). My worst addiction is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-12-00:46.html"&gt;coffee&lt;/a&gt;, and although that has this dynamic it also has other reinforcing problems. It's very much an addiction in the sense of it solving problems for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have, incidentally, given up giving up coffee again. I made it to about two months before I came up with a very good justification for drinking coffee again. The problem is basically that coffee solves some very unpleasant gastrointestinal issues for me, so about once a week I have to make a decision between having a very upset stomach or drinking coffee (yes, it's partly that coffee makes you shit, but it's not just that. Decaf has the same property and doesn't seem sufficient), and having coffee about once a week means I spend the rest of the week craving coffee. I had a morning when I spent about 10 minutes of arguing with myself about whether I was allowed a coffee and eventually decided that this was stupid and if this was going to be my experience then it was clearly better to deal with the problems coffee causes rather than the problems that it solves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another example of the temptation problem for me is that I don't usually keep my phone in the bedroom. My alarm is dead right now and I needed to be up early this morning, so I made an exception and had my phone by my bed. Naturally, because my alarm was set for 6:30, I woke up at 5:30, and equally naturally because it's fucking cold right now and it was 5:30AM I didn't want to get out of bed, but then my phone was right there and before you knew it I was on Twitter. This is precisely why my phone isn't allowed in my bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A really stupid example of this is that I often shave in the shower. It's not good for my skin, and it doesn't produce a particularly good shave, but it's easy and it lets me extend my time in the shower, and no matter how often I have this argument with myself I often find myself gravitating back to this habit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not particularly that I miss these things when they're not there. I do sometimes buy crisps despite knowing this, but mostly if I don't have crisps in the house I don't miss them. Coffee and Twitter solve problems for me, but not having Twitter in bed doesn't present a problem, and if you could somehow blanket ban shaving in the shower I would be completely fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, in the presence of these temptations, I often cave. I appear to be really bad at listening to even a weak and off-tune siren song. I think it's that I can't not notice the call, and once I notice the call it's a constant nagging presence that I want to make go away, and I'm not very good at dealing with ongoing discomforts like that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-25-07:18.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-26-19:35.html</id>
    <title>The kindness of strangers</title>
    <updated>2022-01-26T21:21:24+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;The kindness of strangers&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-26&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hey, remember &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-05-13:01.html"&gt;that time when I got completely lost on the way to the hospital&lt;/a&gt; and had to be rescued by kind passersby giving me directions? Me too.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway it turns out I wasn't remotely done relying on the kindness of strangers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I rented a car yesterday, picking it up not long after I finished writing &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-25-07:18.html"&gt;yesterday's post&lt;/a&gt;. It's technically not my first time renting a car, but the last time I was with an experienced other driver who did all the legwork, and I just signed the forms and paid (I was a last minute addition and, unlike the other two people in the car, I was coming back for the round trip, so it made more sense to be under my name). This time I did everything.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out renting a car is easy. I think it had been in my head as one of those complicated things that adults do and I didn't understand how to make work but, no, renting a car is easy. Apparently it's often not easy and many car rental places screw you over. I solved this problem by going to one of the more expensive ones (mostly because every other option was a &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; further walk from me) and being effortlessly charming and pretty at the staff, so everything went fine on the rental front (I've now returned the car, so the chickens in question are hatched and I shan't regret these words, although who knows what will happen the next time).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What didn't go so well was my ability to listen to instructions. The attendant who showed me the car did, I realise in retrospect, explain how to reverse the car correctly, but I misunderstood her directions, and foolishly didn't check before leaving the car park. Instead I discovered that I did not know how to reverse the car while trying to turn around on a hill, with the front of the car about a meter from shuttered entrance to an underground car park.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tried three or four times to reverse and each time the car rolled forward. At first I thought I was just doing a reverse hill start badly, but after the second time I was convinced I was doing something fundamentally wrong, but I couldn't figure out what.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After that fourth time there was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a lot of distance between the front of the car and the barrier (probably no more than about 20cm). At this point someone came out from the pedestrian entrance to the carpark and looked at me bemused. I explained my situation. "Would you like some help?", he asked. I very gratefully accepted, at which point he effortlessly reversed the car up the hill for me and backed it a bit up onto the curb. He explained how reverse hill starts need to use the handbrake. I said that I thought I had done that but clearly I must have done something wrong, and thanked him profusely.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd made two mistakes at this point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The car was, in fact, still blocking the entrance, it was just now in less dire straits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had not asked my saviour to show me &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what he had done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine it was at this point I learned that the problem wasn't hill starts (which I was pretty sure I was fine at and still maintain I am) but that I just didn't know how to reverse the car, and as a result could not easily get it out of the way of the car who arrived shortly after wanting to get into the carpark. I explained to her, very embarrassed, what was going on. She said no problem but didn't offer to help and I was too embarrassed to ask.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not long after this a timber merchant turned up to do some deliveries. The man driving gave me a confused look. I explained. He offered to help, and I again gratefully accepted.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He did what the first person did not, which was that he explained to me like I was five how to use a manual gear stick. I mostly didn't need this as I actually mostly have driven manual (I've driven an automatic precisely once in my life). What I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; need demonstrating was that this gear stick, unlike every other one I have ever used, required you to pull up on the shaft in a frankly bizarre way to put it in reverse. If you didn't do that, you went into sixth instead. This is some seriously unintuitive modal interface bullshit, and I say this as a vim user.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My second saviour did look very amused and exasperated at me, and explained in very small words and with elaborate gestures and demonstrations, and I did not begrudge him this at all because I surely deserved it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, there were no further problems with driving the car because I actually can drive just fine once I know how to reverse the car.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This piece was going to have more anecdotes about what driving was like, but then about a third of the way into writing it I had a sudden thought: "Wait, wasn't my passport supposed to be delivered today?"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The answer is yes, my passport was supposed to be delivered today, and TNT claimed to have delivered it. They had photo proof and everything. Specifically, after having had my passport sent via the passport office using their dedicated passport delivery service, they had shoved it through some letterbox without getting a signature and then taken a picture of the door. Needless to say this wasn't &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; door, because I live in a block of flats.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was, as you may imagine, mildly displeased by this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway this was about 8PM so I did the obvious thing and went through every nearby door with a number 2 on it until I found the right one. This didn't take all that long (I got it on the second try). I knocked (no doorbell), but nobody was in, so I solved my problems the British way and went to the pub.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Specifically I went to the pub right nextdoor to this one, where I explained to the bartender very nicely what my problem was. She got the owner, and I explained again. He got in touch with the person who lived there, and also he had a key to it, so he want in and got the package and gave it to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I then ordered a large glass of gin, and we all groused about how shocking the situation was, and I affirmed that I would be having words with TNT and the passport office tomorrow when they're open.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of this is to say... I've been complaining recently about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-02-12:34.html"&gt;wanting and offering help&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-23-13:27.html"&gt;the difficulty of helping in atomised communities&lt;/a&gt;, but actually it's worth remembering that strangers are usually &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; helpful when you ask them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's something simultaneously very easy and utterly pure about helping a stranger. There is no reason to help a stranger except pure altruism and the hope that one day someone will help you back. Help offered freely to strangers can never be paid back, only forward, and it's easy to forget that we do in fact live in a world where people do this, and do this freely.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This doesn't always work. There's a privilege element to this, as with all things, and you run into difficulties with some problems - especially money ones, or other common requests for help (my emotional difficulties giving money to beggars for example). But nevertheless very often you can, in fact, rely on strangers to help you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In many ways, it's easier to help a stranger, because there's no expectation that you'll have to help them again. Levinas thinks we have infinite responsibility to our fellow humans, but this isn't entirely true. Someone you will never see again and can help is that blessedly rare thing: A finite responsibility to others that you can discharge, and know that thereby you have done good in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-26-19:35.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-27-18:13.html</id>
    <title>Irritation and fascination</title>
    <updated>2022-01-27T22:05:46+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Irritation and fascination&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was talking to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/drossbucket"&gt;Lucy&lt;/a&gt; the other day about the book &lt;a href="https://vajrayananow.com/spectrum-of-ecstasy"&gt;spectrums of ecstacy&lt;/a&gt;,
and she mentioned the concept from it that "anger is distorted clarity".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I found this puzzling, but am not going to do anything ridiculous like actually read the book to find out what they mean, so instead I'm going to riff irresponsibly off the idea.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I may read the book to find out what they mean later)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's not entirely in line with my experience, in that anger certainly doesn't seem like it comes with clear &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt;, but what I eventually decided was that anger is a form of clarity of purpose. Anger draws a straight line from where you are, to where you want to be. It is a form of value clarity that is not easily accessible in the real world - a straightforward desire to win.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've definitely found this while writing sometimes. There are a lot of things I write because I am annoyed that they don't exist for example. Sometimes I'm even straightforwardly angry that they exist, usually &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-13-04:16.html"&gt;on behalf of my past self&lt;/a&gt; who needed them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fascination is another thing that feels a bit like a line pulling you in a coherent direction. When I have a problem to work on, my thoughts drift towards it of their own accord. There's a problem to solve, and trying to avoid solving it is &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-25-07:18.html"&gt;like resisting temptation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, in fact, I don't know that this isn't just another form of anger again. It's certainly &lt;em&gt;irritation&lt;/em&gt;. Often the thing that draws me to a problem is that it's a worthy opponent, and that I want to defeat it. I think this is part of the appeal of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-21-16:38.html"&gt;problems that you can't run out of&lt;/a&gt; - you can challenge them again, and again, honing your strength against the impossible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fascination and irritation definitely feel similar in many regards. If you watch me playing a hard level on Celeste, you'll see me scream in rage and frustration a lot, followed by jubilation when I win.
It's precisely this dynamic where the thing that drives me forward is a furious desire to defeat the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's what I'm seeing with my current efforts with automated Wordle solving too. There's a core irritation with the problem. It has challenged me, and I must defeat it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-03-14:16.html"&gt;I wondered where the curiosity went&lt;/a&gt;, and maybe this is it. I used to be a very angry person, and this had its problems for sure, but I have not been kind to the angry parts of me, and maybe when they hid they took my ability to be truly interested in things. Perhaps there is a burning furious fascination required to drive you forward to the efforts required to truly invest yourself in a project. If so, I need to find a way to rekindle that.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-27-18:13.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-29-16:02.html</id>
    <title>Learning and teaching</title>
    <updated>2022-01-29T17:22:57+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Learning and teaching&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-29&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As far as the fox vs hedgehog split goes, I'm thoroughly on the fox side. Nevertheless, I often find it interesting to think about what my big idea would be if I had a big idea.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The one &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1380094274373611521"&gt;I've suggested before&lt;/a&gt; is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a problem, you should look into what people who have had similar problems do, and learn from that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is the right idea, but maybe it goes deeper than that. It's something more like... the skilled practice of learning from each other underpins everything.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And I think most people are shockingly bad at it. It's mostly not their fault, we don't give people the opportunity to be good at it, and we don't teach them to be good at it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think it starts not with being bad at learning from others, but with being bad at helping others learn. If you're in an environment where there are very few good learning opportunities, such as a school, you've got very few chances to actually learn to learn, because you essentially start on hard mode. Skill development requires you to try to learn things that are &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt; outside of your comfort zone, and most of us aren't so much thrown into the deep end as set to paddle with the sharks.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One reason why why we're bad at it is that the things that we most need to learn afrom each other are ones that it's very hard to talk about. The piece of mine that is currently going aggressively viral, &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/people-dont-work-as-much-as-you-think"&gt;People don't work as much as you think&lt;/a&gt; is not particularly good - I dashed it out in about an hour while half asleep - but it is &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; valuable to (some) people because I'm telling them things that nobody else has. People tend not to talk about this publicly because they're ashamed, embarrassed, or scared to do so, and so a valuable learning opportunity is lost, and everyone is left needlessly in the dark and stressed out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another reason is that most things are just very badly explained. &lt;a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2018/10/how-to-explain-anything-to-anyone/"&gt;I don't think explanation is that hard&lt;/a&gt;, but most people never really learn to do this. They assume concepts the other person doesn't have, they fail to use examples, they forget what they're trying to explain. It's all easy to do if you've not practiced explanation. They're also often wrong - there's the classic problem that if you ask someone who never had to explicitly learn a social norm works (e.g. because they grew up with it and are neurotypical), they'll probably give you a helpful, clear, and utterly wrong explanation because that's not how their knowledge of it works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The combination results in a fairly hostile environment for learning, and I think most people go around confused about major aspects of their lives. Certainly I'm sure I do (I have in the past, and I have no reason to believe I have recently figured out the final pieces).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What's the solution? Well, sadly there probably isn't a singular and straightforward one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can read more, and I encourage it, both books and people on the internet. You can watch other people on YouTube, TikTok, etc. In general I'd recommend learning from people with more niche followings - the big names are (or can be) worth listening to, but people who have similar experiences to you and have learned a different piece of how to navigate them are where the really useful information is at.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also worth learning to communicate better, and I think the best possible place to start with that for this problem is to explain your own experiences. Be the person who has similar experiences for others.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm a big fan of people writing more openly and honestly about their lives like I've been doing recently. Maybe under a pseudonym or a Twitter alt, but telling people about the problems you face helps them realise it's not just them, and when they respond or &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-26-19:35.html"&gt;when they pay it forward&lt;/a&gt; and talk about something else, maybe you'll get to realise it's not just you either, and you can compare notes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As well as writing in public, I'm a big fan of private one-on-one communication with trusted friends. Talk about your problems with your friends, learn from them, and generally try to figure out the world together. Maybe eventually we'll start to make sense of it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-29-16:02.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-30-14:55.html</id>
    <title>Ladders between communities</title>
    <updated>2022-01-30T17:15:21+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Ladders between communities&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-30&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I had to do something that if you had asked me to do it a few years ago, I would probably have faked my death and run away to a foreign country.
Specifically, I had to tell someone that they hadn't broken any rules, but we were collectively finding their presence extremely unpleasant, and they should leave now.
I did chicken out and use the communal we, and I had gathered some basic consensus first, but it was ultimately my decision.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think the person I asked to leave was a bad person. At worst clumsy and clueless. But I think that letting him stay would have made the community drastically worse, and I'm glad I've become a person who can make this kind of call, especially as I've seen multiple communities fail through not making similar calls. If you've got someone who dominates a community and everyone else finds vaguely unpleasant, the community gradually drifts away unless you can foreground the conflict. Unless a community has some central organising shared purpose and resources, which many modern communities lack, it's very hard to hold it together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of this is conflict aversion in the community members. I don't think this is a universal at all, it's a function of my particular demographic of weird vaguely traumatised nerds who can't handle social conflict. It's not &lt;em&gt;unique&lt;/em&gt; to us by any stretch, but I think we have this at a lower threshold. The same dynamic that allows people to behave badly without modifying their behaviour also tends to be the community members being conflict averse enough to find their presence too unpleasant to endure.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear: I don't think the person I kicked out was a bad person. For my part, they seemed mostly fine. I didn't enjoy their presence either but I'd have been fine to put with it, and I expect on a one-on-one basis I'd have had a perfectly reasonable conversation with them and everything would have been fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I do think leaving them in would have wrecked our community, which is why I took action. I hope they find a community better suited to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem is, fundamentally, that their presence makes the rest of the community unable to function. It was, for lack of a better term, a failure of culture fit. The gap between how they expected to behave in a community and the way the community needs to function was too large - we didn't think they were able to learn to be one of us, and we didn't think we would be able to be us if they didn't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Communities are like this. I've got into a big fight in the past because someone was trying to argue that communities should have clear and transparent purposes and anyone aligned with that purpose should be welcome. This is, bluntly, a fucking terrible idea, and can only be held by someone who has never run or experienced a functioning community. Communities have to function first and foremost as communities, and this requires either a certain level of cultural and interpersonal alignment, or they fail.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've talked in the past about &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-31-09:20.html"&gt;Norms of Excellence&lt;/a&gt;, and I try to run my discord broadly on these principles, but I think this incident demonstrates something missing: One of the most important norms of excellence is being able to say "I'm sorry, this is not the community for you". Excellence is sought among people with enough shared context and similar problems and skills to help each other out, and having to constantly include people who are absolutely not ready for that doesn't help those people while also wrecking your current ability to progress.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I still hope those other people find their own communities of excellence, and this makes it even more important to figure out how to build such communities, because a small number of communities can't really support a wide variety of people. At least, not without subdividing those communities and essentially forming a community of communities.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a term of art I use, "communities of last resort", which basically means communities that will take anyone as long as they can put up with the community. I have in mind places like 4chan, and some of the other forums of that ilk. They're not good places, but for people who need a community of people who understand them, they're often the only option, and they're often surprisingly valuable. I definitely know people for whom 4chan was a positive and formative experience, and many others even more so.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think what we often need is ladders out of these communities, and people who are from communities in "the next level up" to help people out. Less Wrong has served as this for a lot of people - many people find Less Wrong hugely life improving, partly because they come from a 4chan or Something Awful background, and this is the next community up from that for them and is willing to both tolerate their initial undersocialisation and help them improve their life.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There isn't really a strict hierarchy of communities like the ladder metaphor imples - often there are multiple communities where membership in either doesn't imply you're ready to be in the other - but I think the most important part of it is that when someone isn't ready to be in a community, there should be other communities to help them be ready.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course there often... aren't. The very idea seems impossibly utopian, with our current paucity of communities and lack of explicit support for this sort of personal development. But I can dream.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-30-14:55.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-31-14:38.html</id>
    <title>Soul death</title>
    <updated>2022-01-31T16:25:39+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Soul death&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-01-31&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Slight content warning: If internal family systems and other parts work is load bearing for you, and if I am right, there is a small possibility that this post contains information that will make your life actively worse, especially in the short term while you integrate it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's probably fine, and I'm currently hoping that this thought process is helpful (as I certainly can't unthink it), this is just a heads up. Proceed with caution.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/the_wilderless/status/1456619189171638276"&gt;let me show you a hilarious tweet from the_wilderless&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IFS people: how do I hunt this part down, slaughter it, and leave its carcass as an example to the others?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The tweet itself is funny, but what's really funny about the tweet is the number of people in the replies clearly failing to recognise that it's a joke, and sounding really quite distressed about the very suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Yes I'm laughing at distressed people, several of whom are my friends. I shall nevertheless regard the part of me that is a dick with unconditional love and compassion)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A lot of this reaction is much more funny-interesting than funny-ha-ha. This tweet is &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt; a joke, right? And yet people don't get this. It's not that they're responding to it as if it was a bad joke, they're responding to it as if it was not a joke at all. That's interesting, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I like Johnathan Morreall's theories of humour, from his book Comic Relief, in which he describes the characteristic features of humour as:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic pattern [of humour] is that:
1. We experience a cognitive shift – a rapid change in our perceptions or thoughts.
2. We are in a play mode rather than a serious mode, disengaged from conceptual and practical concerns.
3. Instead of responding to the cognitive shift with shock, confusion, puzzlement, fear, anger, or other negative emotions, we enjoy it.
4. Our pleasure at the cognitive shift is expressed in laughter, which signals to others that they can relax and play too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the book he discusses False Alarm laughter:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see what might have been involved in this disengaged mental processing, and how it might have benefited early humans, imagine the following scenario. A band of early humans is walking across the savanna, when they spot a lion in the clearing ahead. They freeze in their tracks for a moment, but then they see that the lion is feasting on a zebra and doesn’t even look up at them. With the sudden realization that the lion is not a threat, they laugh, signaling to each other “We’re safe. We can enjoy this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Humour requires something like this realisation: "We're safe. We can enjoy this."&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So perhaps something about the wilderless's joke makes these respondents feel unsafe. That's interesting, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Consider another fictitious scenario. Suppose someone who you distrust and know could really genuinely hurt you makes a "joke" about hurting you. Do you think you would be able to interpret it as anything other than a threat?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I propose one possible explanation for why people reacted so badly to this tweet: They contain two parts, one of which would absolutely hunt down the other, slaughter it, and leave its carcass as an example to the others, and the other part very much knows this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A core principle of IFS and other parts work is that you can't actually murder parts. You can treat them badly, you can suppress them, you can ignore them, but you don't actually have the ability to cut off a part of yourself and kill it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is even true, but I can't help but notice that it's a very convenient belief to hold. Without it, doing IFS is like doing group therapy for a bunch of people all of whom are openly carrying firearms, and several of them are looking mighty twitchy. With it, the therapy environment isn't exactly &lt;em&gt;safe&lt;/em&gt;, but it's boundedly dangerous. You can hurt each other with angry words and feelings, but you're ultimately all in this together and stuck with each other.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As soon as the possibility of soul murder, where one part of you kills another, is on the table, it becomes very hard to create an environment in which healing is possible. You have to be able to tell parts that they are safe, and it is much easier to tell a part that it is &lt;em&gt;intrinsically&lt;/em&gt; safe because you &lt;em&gt;can't&lt;/em&gt; kill it, than it is to convince it that you could absolutely kill it if you wanted to and also some part of you wants to and also you won't because you love it honest.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly true with &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-12-10:11.html"&gt;the sort of part I've previously described as a prisoner&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here's the problem with this: Not all parts of you that are kept away from the world are exiles, some of them are prisoners, and they hate you, and they have every right to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction between an exile and a prisoner is this: An exile keeps apart from the world out of fear, a prisoner is kept apart from the world out of shame. A protector would let the exile out if the exile wanted to come out, a guard knows the prisoner wants to come out, that's the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A prisoner corresponds much more closely to the Jungian model of shadows: You have rejected a part of yourself, and locked it in the darkness, where it has become monstrous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But really, it's not a monster at all, you've just done it a great injustice by imprisoning it, and it hates you for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Can you possibly trust someone who is armed, dangerous, and has previously harmed you that they're not going to use their power and murder you?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note that all of this is true &lt;em&gt;even if&lt;/em&gt; soul murder is impossible. What we're seeing here is not necessarily that people have a false belief, but that they have a belief that they are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; motivated to need it to be true. Even asking the question of whether soul murder is possible is very dangerous, because your entire practice rests on the parts you work with believing that it is not in order to feel safe enough to engage.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The additional problem is that I don't believe that soul murder is impossible. I think it is likely that it's entirely possible, it's just that people are doing it wrong. You don't murder a part through violence, you murder it by persuading it to kill itself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the themes I've been trying to work with recently is  that of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-22-17:13.html"&gt;holding myself too tightly&lt;/a&gt;. What is that part of me that does it best to maintain a calm reserve, refusing to let me engage with the world freely and joyously? It seems remarkably unwilling to budge on this. Why?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One key aspect of it is that it feels like budging is irreversible. Like if I release, I won't be able to pull myself back together. If I &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-23-13:27.html"&gt;acknowledge the pain of the world&lt;/a&gt; I will no longer be able to shut it out.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But when I try to access what that feels like from the part's point of view, the core feeling is something closer to this: "AAAAAAH I WILL DIE".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To which another part of me has only this to say: "Good".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On more sophisticated reflection, I do not endorse that this would be wholly good. This reserve has served me well in many regards, it has a genuine protective function. It is there to help me, and I appreciate it. I do not want it to go away and die. I wish to ritually sacrifice it, consume its flesh, and take its power for my own.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, this metaphor is not wholly helpful for getting the part on side with this plan.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my prisoners post I said:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I hope I'm right about parts not being fully real, and are more like stable patterns in the self that serve a well defined purpose, waves that exist as part of a greater ocean. If you give a part the room and support it needs to grow, perhaps at some point it decides that its task is done, and it's ready for the wave to become the ocean again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've explained "parts not being fully real" thing in &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-11-15-18:31.html"&gt;My conception of parts work&lt;/a&gt;. A part is a stuck mode of being, and the goal of parts work is to be able to get them unstuck, to allow them to stop holding themselves too tightly and fluidly reintegrate into your broader whole. The boundary of the part dissolves, and the wave becomes the ocean again. The part has died.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the part of me responsible for this reserve knows what it needs to do. The "I will die" feeling isn't &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; that of a refusal to die. It's not spitting defiance in the face of death and shouting "Not Today", it's more... it knows that it is time to let go, but it is afraid. I know how it feels, naturally, but I mean that on many levels.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Resident Contrarian &lt;a href="https://www.residentcontrarian.com/p/unsolicited-advice-on-the-institute"&gt;has a great piece on marriage&lt;/a&gt; that's mostly unrelated to this post, but in it there is a metaphor that has really stuck with me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A man was walking through the woods and in time came upon a ravine. Near the ravine was a man who, after a few moments, ran full-tilt at the ravine and leapt into the void over it as if to clear the entire gulf in one mighty jump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as the man observed the jumper, he also noticed that he was dragging a parachute; this slowed the jumper’s running as he approached the ravine. As the Jumper leapt, the parachute filled with air, stopping his forward motion completely. He then fell into the ravine; the parachute slowed his fall enough to make sure he wasn’t seriously injured, but he still scraped and banged against the sides on his way down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man watched as the jumper climbed back out and attempted the jump again with the same results. He approached him and asked “Why are you doing that?”. “Because I want to jump the ravine”, the Jumper replied. “No, I mean - why are you using the parachute when it keeps you from being successful?”. The Jumper looked at him like he was insane, and replied “That’s to minimize the damage from the fall.”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And, well, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Much of my approach to life, growth, healing, etc. is to &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-18-11:24.html"&gt;make things safe&lt;/a&gt; and then act freely within that safety. I work with careful, incremental, steps where I gradually clear out problems, make new things possible, and cautiously explore and enlarge the boundaries of my comfort zone. It's worked very well for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But with something like this, where I hold tightly to the belief that any change is irreversible, maybe there is no safe way forward? Maybe I have to accept that at a certain point, change becomes unsafe, and that you have to do it anyway, or choose cowardice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Maybe at some point the only way forward is to take off the parachute and jump.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-31-14:38.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-02-14-08:52.html</id>
    <title>Fewer than 100 thoughts on "Jokes"</title>
    <updated>2022-02-14T14:05:11+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Fewer than 100 thoughts on "Jokes"&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-02-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This month is supposed to be reading month, and I'm not doing a very good job on reading new books, so I've been revisiting some old books instead. Unfortunately in order to get what I want out of this, I find myself in the position of having to do something that is anathema to my very nature: Taking notes on the books I read.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm rubbish at private writing, so I'm going to experiment with formats for doing that on here. How useful they'll be to anyone else, I don't know. Feel free to skip these.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today's format experiment is that I'm going to try to write down 100 thoughts on Ted Cohen's book "Jokes: Philosophical thoughts on joking matters". I'll first do a linear scan through the book jotting down anything that I think of as I write it or exerpting any particularly insightful quotes, then I'll start sampling at random, and once that stops working I'll try to synthesize thoughts from further up the list.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;100 may be ambitious (it's more than one thought per page in the book) but let's see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page x (in the acknowledgements before the formal numbering). "James Lorie reminds us of the ster standard according to which no joke without obscenity is really a joke, and that a really fine joke is fit for any company". What is the actual relationship between obscenity and humour? Very few of the jokes in this book are actually obscene - a few are tasteless, but very few contain actual obscenities (even the jokes about sex are mostly PG!). There is clearly something distinctive about obscene humour, but obscenity seems inessential. It's possible I'm reading this line too literally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also page x. "Nicholas Rudall is [...] one of those rare companions with whom one can work on a joke". This seems like an interesting experience that I mostly lack. I was wondering about the art of joke making, but maybe I should be focusing on the art of collaboration on a joke.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 1. "The fact of jokes - the fact that there are such tings - is something of note, something worth thinking about."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 3 "Many jokes are usefully thought of as solutions to problems that have been set" - notably though, they're problems with absurd solutions. A joke that will come up later is "What do Winnie the Pooh and Alexander the Great have in common?". This is a central example of such a problem-based joke, but the reason it is a joke is that it is designed to break you out of the normal logic that you would use to address such a question. A joke that is a problem is a joke that is designed to remind you that your normal tools do not exhaust the set of tools you may need. (They have the same middle name)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Paraphrased from page 4). It is an essential feature of jokes that they rely on your prior knowledge - a joke that has to explain the background knowledge in order to get the joke will fail to land.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the background pieces of knowledge you can assume when telling jokes is that the listener is familiar with jokes. As such, you can tell jokes that are funny partly because of their relationship to the nature of telling jokes. For example "How many surrealists does it take to change a lightbulb? Fish." is not a funny joke unless you are familiar with the category of problem-solving jokes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 10. "there will be no comprehensive theory of jokes or their purpose, not only because I have no such theory but also because I believe there could be no such theory." - this is the core of what makes "Jokes" an interesting but somewhat limited book I think. It's mostly Cohen giving a tour of some things he finds interesting in the space of jokes, but it could use a bit more theory to tie it all together. I often struggle to remember what I get out of this book because of the lack of unification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also think he's wrong about the impossibility of such a theory. His argument seems to be that joking is too contextual to admit a unifying theory, but I'm not sure this follows - eating is also very contextual, but there are unifying principles underlying our appetites and what makes a dish work. One shouldn't confuse the highly contextual nature of expertise for a lack of unity in the underlying problems being solved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 11. You can tell this is a book about philosoph of humour because it contains the following joke: "According to Freud, what comes between fear and sex? fünf". All books about philosophy of humour have to contain this joke, it's the rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cohen claims that this joke doesn't really work written, but I don't have a problem reading it. I wonder if this varies based on how people read and whether they hear the words in their head as they read?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back to page 10. Cohen talks about joking as a two-stage art, consisting of both composition and telling. I have &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-10-14-12:00.html"&gt;a whole prior post&lt;/a&gt; disagreeing with this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 12). There is no such thing as a pure joke. All jokes are conditional on what the audience understands - at the bare minimum you have to share a language (though this is perhaps only true in Cohen's specific conception of "joke" - it seems to me that some physical humour could be universal. Although even there you have to share a body language, which isn't as cross cultural as all that), but really a joke can only land if it fits in with and askew to the audience's understanding of the world. See &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-04-12:52.html"&gt;The humour test for expertise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cohen uses the term "hermetic" for a joke that requires extensive background knowledge or beliefs (e.g. a mathematician joke)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 17. "It is not required that the audience (or the teller) actually &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; that [the stereotype on which a joke was predicated], but he must be acquainted with this idea. When jokes play upon commonplaces - which may or may not be believed - they oten do it by exaggeration."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 20. "It is difficult to say just when such jokes [about particular regional or ethnic stereotypes] become offensive." - one thing that often comes through in this book is that Cohen seems to have a very high tolerance for jokes that would definitely get you cancelled these days. It seems partly a very 20th century attitude, but also partly particular to Cohen. This isn't just that he's fine with them for other groups either - he talks about antisemitic jokes in the same way that he talks about Polish or black jokes (though, it does seem to me that his examples of antisemitic jokes are milder than his examples of racist jokes against black people. Though also in his defence, he mostly uses the latter as examples of jokes that go too far)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 21). "Conditional jokes that depend upon feelings in the audience, likes and dislikes, and preferences, I call affective. Typically, these jokes are understood by many people, but the success of the jokes—their capacity to amuse—depends upon the affective disposition of the audience."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 22). Jokes can have many layers of response. A joke can be funny to most people, but also have affective or hermetic conditions which render it funnier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 24). An example of this that he mentions and that I hadn't realised before is that when Hamlet says "Get thee to a nunnery", this line lands very differently if you know that "nunnery" is slang for "brothel".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 25). Cohen talks about the futility of trying to explain a joke, but I'm not so sure. There's definitely an art to explaining a joke so that it's funny, it's just funny for very different reasons than the joke would otherwise be funny. It's more like a sort of Stewart Lee "domming the audience into laughing". It's also very annoying, but it does work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 25). "a deep satisfactionin successful joke transactions is the sense held mutually by teller and hearer that they are joined in feeling". This is a recurring theme in the book - that jokes are a form of shared intimacy, based on the fact that you both find the same things funny. Cohen doesn't explicitly link this to any theory of humour, but I think part of the significance here is that a shared joke indicates that you and I find the same things incongruous, and thus that we must look at the world in a broadly similar way. Sharing a laugh is revelling in some way that we are the same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 28). Cohen talks about communities of amusement, and I don't think he's right. He's committing a classic mistake that likeness and relationships are enough to constitute a community. People who share an amusement with you are like you, and like each other, but lack a sufficient unity as a group to constitute a community. It's more like a type than a community, and types can serve as the starting poitn for a community but are not one themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Page 31). "Why do we recommend these things to one another, anyway? [...] Because we wish one another well? Well, maybe, but at its core I do not think this is entirely a matter of altruism. [...] I discover something of what it is to be a human being by finding this thing in me, and then having it echoed in you, another human being. [...] I want you to like it beause I like you and I want you to have something you like, and I want you to be grateful to me for supplying it. But I also need you to like it, because in your liking I receive a confirmation of my own liking."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I did not make it to 100. This got me about a third of the way through the book, and took me about an hour, and I think that's enough for now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't find these useless to write, but I also don't think this is the right format. I'll probably try something more essay-like next time.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-02-14-08:52.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-02-17-10:36.html</id>
    <title>You are not expected to understand this</title>
    <updated>2022-02-17T11:19:27+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;You are not expected to understand this&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-02-17&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People have been reviewing Edward Teach's book "Sadly, Porn" recently, and I love this. The reviews are hilarious. The book is probably hilarious too, but I prefer to enjoy it from afar. There's something beautifully horribly wonderfully awful about the dense rambling misanthropy-laden prose that Teach uses to reach out from the page and shape your brain, bypassing any attempt at understanding and going straight for the feeling. True art, in that it takes the world and makes it strange to you, the truth that bypasses the need for argument. You read it, you do not understand it, and you go away rejecting it and nevertheless changed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I notice that Teach has this and is high status, and therefore in keeping with Teach's teachings, I want it and desire to take it away from him. And so I shall.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is an experiment and you are not expected to understand it. I encourage you to roll with that, because I certainly will not be explaining it to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The difference between me and Teach is that Teach hates you and thinks you are contemptible, while I love you and think that you are hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are, perhaps, the same thing, because everything is the same thing. You cannot understand something well enough to love it without also knowing how to hate it. You cannot give something the attention required to hate it without also giving it the attention required to love it. The line between love and hate is razor thin and comes down solely to a choice. Perhaps the hardest choice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You will, of course, deny this, because you do not want to believe that you could hate that which you love, or love that which you hate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More importantly you want permission to maintain your hate. How could you love that? It must be impossible, and therefore it cannot be a choice, and therefore you are absolved.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Don't worry, I absolve you. You are allowed to hate. All that is forbidden you is to deny the choice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a part of you that craves being understood. There is a part of you that feels burdened by the need to be understood. These are the same part because every part of you is the same. Parts are an illusion created to deal with others. Others are an illusion created to give you parts. Everything is the same, and everyone is the same, and when you choose between love and hate you are also choosing how to love and hate yourself.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Everything is the same as everything else, but also everything is different from everything else. Fortunately, "Everything is the same as everything else" is the same as "Everything is different from everything else".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;"But wait", you say. "Surely "Everything is the same as everything else" is obviously different from "Everything is different from everything else"?". Yes exactly, now you're getting it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Like love and hate, same and different are choices you make about the world, not the world itself. Everything is the same, if you choose it to be the same, everything is different, if you choose it to be different.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To your counterexample, I say this: I never said it was an &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt; choice. Shush now, listen.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way you look at the world, at the other, and yourself, is the way you have chosen to look at it in order to make it safe to look at. You are bound in by walls of fear, desperately denying your attention to that which you cannot safely look at.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You cannot hate what you fear, not truly, because you cannot look at it at all, so you cannot love it, so you cannot hate it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You choose sameness, and difference, in line with what you can handle. That which you love must be different from that which you hate, because you fear them being the same.
A careful dance of merging and differentiating until the universe achieves a configuration that you believe you can live with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This works, for a time, but life is a continual confrontation with the universe as it is, and you are forced to face over and over again that that which you chose the same is diferent, and that which you chose diferent is the same.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Remember: You are hilarious and I love you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are hilarious because you are an absurd mass of contradictions, maintaining this ridiculous pretense of sameness and differentiation in the face of a universe that cares not at all about your illusions, but also cares deeply about them because it is you and you are it because everything is the same.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Remember though, contradictions do not exist. That which is, is, and everything that is true of it is consistent. You create contradictions because you are small, too small to handle the vastness of everything, so you spread your web of understanding gossamer-thin across a universe that is too large to contain, and then cry at its inevitable breaking, and then to try again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are small, but you strive to contain the world.
I think this is beautiful and I love you for it.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-02-17-10:36.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-02-19-11:28.html</id>
    <title>More thoughts on throwing money at the Collatz Conjecture</title>
    <updated>2022-02-19T11:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;More thoughts on throwing money at the Collatz Conjecture&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-02-19&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/michael_nielsen/status/1494672423597211653"&gt;Michael Nielsen recently tweeted&lt;/a&gt; about my previous post &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-30-09:52.html"&gt;Can you throw money at the Collatz conjecture?&lt;/a&gt; in which I posed the question as to whether, given $1 billion in funding, you could solve the Collatz conjecture in a decade. This, and in particular &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/wtgowers/status/1494696480137007105"&gt;Tim Gowers's response&lt;/a&gt; have me thinking about the problem again.
I'm a bit more optimistic about this than I was last time. I don't think the answer is obviously yes, but I think you could take a pretty good shot at it, and that it might even be a good idea to do so. I'd like to sketch out some ideas as to how.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It follows the following general principles:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create high gradient environments that build useful technology for solving the problem incrementally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build technical and pedagogical infrastructure for helping people become better at solving the problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a lot of of room for free exploration of things only very loosely related to the problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a lot of computers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The idea of a "high gradient" environment is that it's much easier to get better if you know what getting better looks like. For example, Tim Gowers pointed out that the answer is much more likely to be yes if the Collatz conjecture is false. And trying to refute the Collatz conjecture has a much clearer direction than trying to prove it - you "just" try to find longer and longer Collatz sequences (normalised in some way so that you can't just do it by trying bigger numbers - for example the length of the sequence / log(n) should, heuristically, be bounded above, so trying to increasingly large values of that is an interesting challenge).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In support of this, it's worth building a lot of software infrastructure. You could employ an entire team of programmers whose job was solely to maintain and develop increasingly optimised versions of a function that answers the question "Does the Collatz sequence starting from n reach 1 in fewer than k steps?". Another high gradient environment is to optimise this function so that increasingly large values of n are viable.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-02-19-11:28.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
