<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/</id>
  <title>DRMacIver's notebook</title>
  <updated>2024-01-06T08:31:48+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David R. MacIver</name>
    <email>david@drmaciver.com</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-12-20-17:21.html</id>
    <title>Action generators</title>
    <updated>2022-12-20T18:13:15+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Action generators&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2022-12-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Quick, do something.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now do something without leaving your current position. e.g. if you're sitting down stand up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, without leaving your current position, do something with your left hand.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, without leaving your current position, do something with your left hand without touching anything with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, without leaving your current position, do something with your left hand that feels good, without touching anything with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Each of these instructions is an action generator: Something that prompts you to act in the world. These can be instructions, but they can also be observations, thoughts, etc. If a ball comes flying towards your head, you hopefully duck. Action generator!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Any action generator has the default response to it: Do nothing. When I told you to do something, you probably ignored it and kept reading (this is of course doing something). Possibly by the end the instructions were interesting enough that you went "Oh, sure, I'll give that a go.", possibly not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doing nothing isn't always a good idea. If you have a do nothing response to the ball flying towards your head, you get hit. Hope it's not a cricket ball. Those hurt. A lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing about the list of action generators I gave above is that each of them is more specific than the one preceding it, and yet it is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; unlikely that the actions generated by the last are ones you would have thought of in response to the first action generator.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is because the broader the action generator is, the more possibilities there are, the harder it is to navigate to any particular possibility in particular.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's also because the more specific action generator gives you permission. The ball coming at your head generates an action of duck, so you duck. You could have ducked even if the ball wasn't coming at your head, but why would you?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Action generators are often useful for doing things that you could have done with a broader action generator but, for one reason or another, didn't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If someone is coming around, that's an action generator to clean your house. You could have done this at any time before, but you didn't. That isn't necessarily bad, but sometimes you &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to do it before and still didn't.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This points to the fact that an action generator really has at least two properties:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What actions it &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; generate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What actions it encourages you to take.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Someone coming over doesn't constrain your actions much compared to the default action generator, but it does create a very strong incentive to tidy up, in much the same way that you're free to do whatever you like in the lead up to the ball arriving, but after that if your actions have not taken the ball into account you're going to deal with the consequences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing I'd like to highlight from the hand thing is that to a large degree, making the action generator more specific automatically creates an encouragement to action, because it lowers the activation energy to acting by removing a large class of decisions. "What should I do with my life?" - vast and impossible set of decisions. "What should I do today?" can still be pretty daunting. "What should I eat for breakfast?" - now pretty accessible. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1603792788667207681"&gt;Onward! Towards the abyss&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another thing worth noting is that any theory about the world is an action generator. You create a model of the world, and this gives you a set of actions that makes sense under that model. For example, when we &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/i/53848690/inventing-symbolic-games"&gt;invent symbolic games&lt;/a&gt; to improve our ability at something, we are doing this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly, a theory works as an action generator &lt;em&gt;even if it's wrong&lt;/em&gt;. You can still adopt the theory and act based on it, and often those actions will be perfectly fine, because they're interesting in their own right even if the reasons that lead to them aren't correct. This is akin to the saying that all models are wrong, but some are useful. All models are useful, in that having action generators is useful because it may lead you to things that you wouldn't otherwise have thought of.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think many "bad" theories persist because they're useful action generators. More, though, I think often bad theories are better than good theories, because they generate actions that you would never have thought of if you were constrained to adopting more reasonable theories.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, I think a lot of therapy modalities work like this. My reliably experience reading therapy books is that they explain their theory and I go "lol, sure" and they provide their evidence and I go "an easier explanation of this is that you're lying", and then I do their exercises and... well, most of the time it doesn't work, but it does something interesting often enough that it was worth reading the book.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is often the case: It's worth having a stable of bad theories lying around that generate actions that you wouldn't otherwise have thought of and that are basically harmless in the worst case, and possibly interesting in the best case.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-12-20-17:21.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-02-14-23:37.html</id>
    <title>My current protocol for energy levels</title>
    <updated>2023-02-15T04:39:37+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;My current protocol for energy levels&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2023-02-14&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People keep asking me questions about my recent miracle increase in mood and energy level, so this is a full write up of what I'm doing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: None of this is medical advice. I'm not competent to give you medical advice. This is a document of what I'm currently doing,
which it may or may not help you to emulate, but also depending on your current health situation some or all of it may not be a good
idea for you, and I'm not competent to tell you which bits.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've recently had a really dramatic increase in mood and mental energy levels, reversing a years long trend of things getting worse
and worse for me over time.
I credit this mostly to taking Inositol, although there are some confounding factors and fears of placebo effect that make me
less confident in that than I'd like to be (I'm still very confident, but it feels obviously true and then I have to add in
a bunch of "OK, but..." caveats).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The theory goes as follows: Inositol is an essential sugar that the brain uses. Its lack causes issues in energy levels and mental health,
among other things, and as a result it can be an effective treatment for those. It is produced by digestion, so if you have digestive
problems you may not be producing enough of it, and supplementing with it can plausibly help.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To the best of my ability to determine the above is pretty established science, though inositol as a medical intervention for these issues
does not seem to be common (it's considered an established treatment for PCOS, and the fact that it can help mood seems to be known but not commonly used).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I started taking inositol after &lt;a href="https://acesounderglass.com/"&gt;Elizabeth Van Nostrand&lt;/a&gt; suggested it in a conversation, and immeditaely felt more like a functioning human being than I had in years. I've mentioned this on Twitter and discord and a bunch of people went "Well I'll give it a go" and some small but non-negligible fraction of them seem to have seen the same results. I think we're up to 5 or 6, but I don't know how many people have tried it. My guess is this corresponds to somewhere in the 1-10% region, in a population probably heavily selected for having these problems.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Known side effects of inositol which at least one person has reported after this are headaches, tiredness, and stomach problems. I had some stomach problems at the beginning, but not particularly bad ones and frankly I'm used to a bit of stomach pain so I ignord it. It seems to have gone away, but that may be because of other things I'm doing to fix my digestion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In addition, there may be long-term consequences (unclear to me if &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; consequences) to taking inositol. I don't really understand these yet,
but the reason it gets used as a treatment for PCOS is that it has effects on a bunch of hormones. I'm currently ignoring this, but do need to do
some detailed research. I do think at the levels I'm taking it at it's probably pretty safe.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What I'm taking&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently taking 1-1.5g of inositol in the morning, and sometimes I take another 0.5-1g in the afternoon. Variation is because I'm doing some not very scientific experiment to find the right amount and timing. I started at 0.5g first thing and even that made a big impact.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently treating 2g as the maximum definitely safe daily dose, but it's likely that it's higher than that. 2g is roughly the amount that your body is supposed to produce per day, PCOS treatment protocols seem to be 4g or even higher. At present I have no plans to go above 2g, and am hoping to reduce that over time if the rest of what I'm doing works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rest of what I'm doing, which is plausibly what made the stomach side effects from inositol go away, is an attempt to actually fix the digestion problems that I think are probably underlying why inositol has such a large benefit for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bioandme.co.uk/"&gt;Bio&amp;amp;Me&lt;/a&gt; "Super seedy and nutty" porridge every morning (I've actually been doing this one for about a year)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://athleticgreens.com/en"&gt;Athletic greens&lt;/a&gt; every morning as an aggressive nutritional supplement for anything I might not be getting properly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strong dose of probiotic every morning. I am currently using three sachets of &lt;a href="https://www.vsl3.co.uk/"&gt;VSL3&lt;/a&gt;. I'm not sold on this being the correct probiotic, but it does seem to help. My plan is to cycle through various brands of plausible probiotics. I will try &lt;a href="https://www.visbiome.com/"&gt;visbiome&lt;/a&gt; next, and possibly &lt;a href="https://seed.com/"&gt;Seed&lt;/a&gt; after that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B01I3O6PJ4/"&gt;Digestive enzymes&lt;/a&gt; with every meal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm also trying to eat a little bit of sauerkraut every day. Fermented vegetables are meant to be good for gut health, and I have problems with digesting brassicas, and some vague notion that eating a little bit of it while also trying to repair my gut microbiome might encourage the sort of bacteria that are good at digesting brassicas. This seems to be at the bare minimum not hurting. Maybe it's also helping, who knows.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've also today started adding a scoop of freeze-dried pineapple to my morning green-stuff-and-bacteria drink. There are a bunch of ultra low confidence reasons why this might be a good idea, but I wouldn't put much faith in this particular suggestion for now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My stomach and digestion seem to be significantly happier as a result of these, although I have no idea at the moment whether this will result in a long term fix or just a short term palliative.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-02-14-23:37.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-06-20-17:00.html</id>
    <title>Larger selves</title>
    <updated>2023-06-21T10:54:55+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Larger selves&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2023-06-20&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note: This is transcribed verbatim from my physical notebook, so when I refer to a notebook in here I'm talking about an actual book I'm writing in with an actual pen. I just didn't want to inflict my hand writing on you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are subjects I don't know how to write about in a way that communicates why they are important to me, either because they always come out flat, or because they come out disordered in their intensity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the subjects that always comes out flat is that I practice a sort of religion. We're a congregation of one person (me) and not that interested in converts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Whenever I try to explain it, it comes out sounding like either a joke or some very dry philosophy. Honestly it started out that way. But this matters to me, at quite a personal level, even if I don't know how to show it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The joke version goes thus: I believe in a supreme being, in that I think beinghood is closed under union, thus the set of all beings has a superema (a maximal element).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't say it was a funny joke.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Technical nitpick: Beings are actually closed under &lt;em&gt;interaction&lt;/em&gt;, not union. As a result this gets tricky when you bring relativity into the picture. Don't worry about this.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The part of this that actually matters to me is that consciousness, and to some degree personhood, happens at every scale. As I write this, I am not having thoughts and recording them on the page. I am thinking by writing. The thought occurs not in my head, but in the combined head/hand/notebook system. Me plus a notebook behaves like a different, albeit very similar, entity to me without.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The same occurs in conversation. As you and I talk, the pair of us think together. Thoughts are had that we could not have had alone. There is an &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; above any beyond there being a you and separately also a me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is true with action as well as thought of course. I can do things with a knife that I cannot do without. You and I can do things together that we cannot do alone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Less obviously, it is true of feeling too. Empathy is not feeling what another feels, but it is a sort of second-person form of feeling. As we synchronise there is a form of shared feeling that &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; have. This is particularly obvious in sex or dance, but also in e.g. games or pair programming. There is a shared feeling between us.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Something that thinks, acts, and feels seems to me to be a legitimate candidate for personhood. It's certainly not a person in exactly the same way that a human is, but it still seems like a person to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You and I together form an us-person distinct from but overlapping with the I-person and the you-person. The same holds for me and my notebook (although I don't think my notebook on its own counts as a person. I sometimes think it's useful to think of personhood as continuous rather than binary. In this view, it is merely not much of a person).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you like, you can substitute "conscious entity" for "person" here, but for me "person" carries more of the right moral and emotional undertones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This extends further upwards of course. A team has personhood. A company. A country. The world.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't think it requires a human in the mix to be a person. We're not too far off having AI that I'd consider clearly warranted some degree of personhood. A dog seems clearly nearly or wholly a person to me. A forest is at least as much of a person as a dog.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also extends downwards. Any reasonably careful degree of attention to yourself and your experience shows that you are made up of parts. You see this with mixed feelings ("part of me feels X while another part feels Y"). Internal family systems and other types of parts work recommend treating these parts of you as people. Maybe they are.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can also see this with aphasia. You can't just recall. The best you can hope for is create a space for the part of you that knows the answer to put it when it's done.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You are not a single unitary entity any more than the notebook and I are - we are cooperating modules working together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This starts to sound very "the self is an illusion" but that's bullshit. The self is no more an illusion than a team is. A team is made up of individuals, but the team is created when those individuals work together.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The team exists in the connections as well as in the parts, and there is a health and function of the team above and beyond that of the individual parts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Much of why this matters to me is that I want to be a better person, and I want to participate in being a better person.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We as people confined to single bodies need to embrace that embodiment, and to learn to self better, but part of how we do that is by learning to participate in larger, better, selves that extend beyond us.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-06-20-17:00.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-07-27-13:03.html</id>
    <title>Adaptive parallel test-case reduction</title>
    <updated>2023-07-28T09:05:39+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Adaptive parallel test-case reduction&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2023-07-27&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's a very simple algorithm I call "adaptive parallel deletion", which I think of as completely standard and thus often forget that literally nobody but me uses.
I haven't written it down anywhere, so here's me finally getting around to doing that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This algorithm is a component of test-case reduction that replaces the classic delta debugging algorithm - that it is, it takes some sequence and produces a subsequence of it satisfying some condition,
such that if you remove any one element from its output the condition is no longer satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The core features of adaptive parallel deletion are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When there are large reductions that can be made, it will usually run in &lt;code&gt;O(log(n))&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When there are no reductions that can be made, it will run in &lt;code&gt;O(n)&lt;/code&gt;, but with the work scaling to as much parallelism as you can give it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will scale fairly gracefully in between the two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here it is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;single_pass_delete&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="sd"&gt;"""Returns a version of `test_case` that satisfies `condition` and&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    is "one-minimal" in the sense that you cannot delete any single&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    member of it and have it still satisfy the condition."""&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;can_delete&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:])&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Scan in parallel for the first location where we can delete&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# a single element of the list. If no more elements are deletable&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# this will run with as much parallelism as we can give it.&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;find_first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;can_delete&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;except&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;NotFound&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="k"&gt;del&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Now that we've found an area where there's at least one deletable&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# element, we hope that it's part of a large chunk of deletable elements.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# This finds an integer k so that we can delete the next k elements&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# and not the next k + 1 elements, running in O(log(k)). This hopefully&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# lets us delete a reasonable large chunk at a time.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;find_integer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;can_delete&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;del&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Because we chose k such that k + 1 elements are not deletable, we know&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# that the element left at i (if any, we might have deleted the whole list)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# is now not deletable, so we increment i to skip past it on the next&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# iteration. This is purely a performance optimisation, but in the worst&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# case might cause us to make twice as many calls to `condition` as we&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# need to if we skip it.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_case&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Where the functions this uses are &lt;code&gt;find_integer&lt;/code&gt; that I've &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2019-04-30-13:03.html"&gt;previously written about here&lt;/a&gt; which is just an exponential probe and binary search (so runs in &lt;code&gt;O(log(k))&lt;/code&gt; when it returns &lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt;) and &lt;code&gt;find_first&lt;/code&gt; is defined as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;itertools&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;islice&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;NotFound&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="ne"&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;pass&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;find_first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;predict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="sd"&gt;"""Returns the first element of `target` that satisfies `predicate`,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    or raises `NotFound` if none do."""&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;raise&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;NotFound&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;parallelism&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cpu_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parallelism&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;raise&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;NotFound&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ThreadPoolExecutor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;max_workers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;parallelism&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;executor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;it&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;iter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk_size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;islice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;it&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk_size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class="k"&gt;raise&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;NotFound&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;zip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;executor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;chunk_size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular &lt;code&gt;find_first&lt;/code&gt; is designed so that when it does not find an answer it scales up rapidly to be embarrassingly parallel, but when it finds an answer early on it doesn't do much redundant work (you still have the overhead of the thread pool and such, but it doesn't actually run much extra code).&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2023-07-27-13:03.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-02-12:48.html</id>
    <title>January is a daily writing month</title>
    <updated>2024-01-02T12:56:38+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;January is a daily writing month&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've long been a disbeliever in new years resolutions, but I'm giving them a go this year. I'm calling them "New Years Aspirations" rather than "resolutions" because that makes me feel better about them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My three aspirations for the year are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See my friends in person more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue to improve my health and exercise levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(3) is a bit of a cliche but in my defence I've been working on it for about four months already, so it's not a fresh start so much as a "that thing I'm already doing but more so".&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(2) is the main focus of this though: I've not been writing recently. My &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/why-to-explain-things-you-already"&gt;last newsletter issue&lt;/a&gt; is from September! Literally more than 3 months have passed since I wrote a newsletter issue. I don't like that. I feel bad about it, but not in the sense that I owe it to anyone, I feel bad because writing is an important part of my life and I've not been doing that. So I'd like to fix this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the reasons I haven't been writing are pretty clear: I've been busy, and I've been depressed. Both are still true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Still, it continues to be my belief that the trick to getting out of depression is to do slightly more than depression is telling you is reasonable. Not &lt;em&gt;vastly&lt;/em&gt; more, but a bit more. This helps you relearn what is actually possible and gradually broadens the boundaries of your life-world, helping ease the depression. At least, that's the theory.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right now, writing newsletter issues feels intolerable. So instead I'm going to write daily notebook posts and see if that manages to rebuild the habit and thought processes of writing. Maybe I'll write some newsletter issues this month, maybe I won't. We'll see.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The astute observer will note that this is coming out on the &lt;em&gt;second&lt;/em&gt; of January. I'm going to put out a catch up post immediately after this one and count this one as yesterday's post.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Don't expect a high standard of writing this month.
To start with I'm just going to do draft bankruptcy from the newsletter. After that I'll probably do Tarot prompts whenever I don't have a good idea what to write about.
Most of them will be short, and will end whenever I feel done with writing them rather than coming to a tidy conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-02-12:48.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-02-12:56.html</id>
    <title>Is philosophy bad?</title>
    <updated>2024-01-02T13:05:54+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Is philosophy bad?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-02&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a draft bankruptcy piece. It contains a few interesting things, but I abandoned it because it fundamentally didn't work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I threatened to write “Contra David Chapman on Philosophy” as a response to David’s repeated insistence that philosophy is bad. This piece isn’t exactly that, but it’s not exactly not that.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Chavid Dapman on Philosophy&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Allow me to introduce my correspondent for this piece, Chavid Dapman. Chavid is a fictional character created by Claude to approximate David Chapman’s opinions on the subject. Given real world David Chapman’s opinions on AI, this is probably a very irritating thing of me to do. Sorry, David.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to inform Claude when I think Chavid says something that David wouldn’t, but this is an imperfect process. As Claude would put it, “Chavid Dapman is a fictional character created for narrative purposes. His critical opinions on philosophy should not be taken as precisely representative of thinker David Chapman's more nuanced perspectives.”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here is Chavid’s opinion on philosophy:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophy is an intellectual tradition that aims to find absolute answers to questions about life, knowledge, ethics, and existence through logic, thought experiments and reasoning. However, after thousands of years, philosophy has failed to deliver definitive answers, especially compared to the progress of science. Logic and thought experiments have clear limits. And philosophy tends to neglect empirical research and interactive empiricism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the deeper issue is that philosophy pursues misguided questions based on false assumptions, such as: What constitutes a good life? What is the meaning of existence? What is human consciousness? The search for abstract absolute answers presumes these are coherent topics, when they are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophy goes astray in seeking universal essences, rather than understanding experience as an ongoing, embodied process. Contemplating pseudoproblems based on flawed metaphysics cannot elucidate anything. We should reject the search for absolute abstract answers and eternal philosophical truths. Philosophy needs to engage the physical world pragmatically and empirically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Editor's note: I ran this by actual David Chapman and he doesn't think it reflects his views at all and is instead a generic and not terribly well thought out critique. I agree. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;I like philosophy&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let’s just get this out of the way: I like philosophy, and I get a lot out of it. Reading philosophy has been significantly life improving for me, and informed a lot of my thinking. This makes it hard for me to accept a blanket “philosophy is bad” claim when a lot of philosophy is clearly good for me, and I’m writing from that perspective.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There’s also plenty of philosophy I dislike. Frankly, it’s almost impossible to like a thing without this being true, because almost everything has good and bad examples, and also examples that are and aren’t to your tastes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think one of the differences between Chavids opinions of philosophy and mine are quite straightforwardly that I tend to think of the examples of philosophy that I like as sufficient evidence that philosophy is good, and Chavid tends to think of the examples of philosophy that he doesn’t like as sufficient evidence that philosophy is bad.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This disagreement is partly what Adam Mastroianni calls a &lt;a href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/science-is-a-strong-link-problem"&gt;strong vs weak link problem&lt;/a&gt;. Some things are as strong as their weakest link, some as their strongest. With science (in Mastroianni’s example), progress doesn’t really depend on the worst science we’re doing but the best. I think the same is true of philosophy: Although there are many bad (both by my standards and theirs) examples of philosophy, there are also many good examples, and you can get value out of the good examples and mostly ignore the bad ones.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Chavid is basically right in saying that “a good life” is a bad abstraction (although I’m sympathetic to what happens to the question when you verb it, which is “How can you live well?” rather than “What is a good life?” - I think this is hard to answer, but worthwhile engaging with), but also this is almost never the sort of philosophy I read.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, here are two examples of philosophy I’ve got a lot out of:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“Games: Agency as Art” by C Thi Nguyen is a book about games, and what the fact that we play games tells us about humanity, and defending them as a distinctive form of art whose medium is constructing structures of agency. This book isn’t “empirical” in the sense that it gathers a lot of data, but is deeply engaged in the world by basically centring its philosophy on many games Nguyen has played.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“Epistemic Injustice” by Miranda Fricker is a book about ethics that consists of looking at a bunch of examples of things that are bad and saying “these seem to have some sort of shared distinctive character. What is it?”. Many of these examples are fictional, but even those feel like they connect to plausible shared experiences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are examples for me of the sort of thing philosophy really shines at: Pointing at something specific and going “There’s something interesting here. What is it?”. They don’t go astray into big abstract questions, but they use the same sort of methods that philosophers tend to engage with big abstract questions on and focus them on something specific and try to clarify our engagement with them. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Where was this going?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That was the point at which I abandoned this. I would still like to write a pro philosophy piece, but I think arguing against David Chapman's views on it is the wrong way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I like Joe Carlsmith's &lt;a href="https://joecarlsmith.com/2023/02/17/seeing-more-whole"&gt;Seeing More Whole&lt;/a&gt; viewpoint, which is (in very brief summary) that philosophy is about using logical reasoning to discover what sorts of person it is possible to be. This seems an important viewpoint to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've previously ha-ha-only-serious joked that the fundamental philosophical question is "That's weird, right? You get that that's weird?". I think the big thing that I get out of good philosophy is that it forces you to actually look at the details of life and how it works, rather than implicitly skipping over the bits that don't make sense.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't the first time I've tried to write that piece. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-06-05-14:43.html"&gt;How to use philosophy&lt;/a&gt; is another similarly brief draft bankruptcy piece trying to do much the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/reading-philosophy-for-the-examples"&gt;Reading Philosophy for the Examples&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-use-thought-experiments"&gt;How to use thought experiments&lt;/a&gt; maybe capture this better. Perhaps part of the problem is that I've tried to do too much with this topic and it needs something larger if I'm to write the whole thing. Or maybe just many smaller things.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-02-12:56.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-03-10:13.html</id>
    <title>Some Philosophy of
Mathematics</title>
    <updated>2024-01-03T13:26:05+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Some Philosophy of
Mathematics&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-03&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is another draft bankruptcy piece, pulled out of a random Google
doc. I think what I’ve got here is perfectly reasonable but it was an
overly ambitious project that I lost interest in finishing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s also my first attempt at moving my blog rendering over to
pandoc, so probably a whole bunch of things will break.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m going to be making a few sweeping generalisations about
philosophy of mathematics. I’m sure some of them don’t hold in complete
generality. I’m trying to convey the sense of what mathematics
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Especially modernish mathematics. I think most of what
I’m saying works as a description of historical mathematics, but it
certainly wouldn’t have been the way people thought about it prior to
some time in the 20th century.&lt;/span&gt;
 is typically like rather than
attempting to come up with a grand unifying theory of mathematical
practice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This piece comes out of trying to explain a bit about mathematical
incompleteness to a philosopher and realising that the core problem in
explaining this is that the way we typically
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I don’t know how reliable my sense of how we typically
present axioms is and was worried this might be a &lt;a href="https://www.lisamcnulty.co.uk/essays/phantom-opinions"&gt;phantom
opinion&lt;/a&gt;, so I checked and it’s not. I did some casual googling,
checked Wikipedia, and asked ChatGPT which is usually a pretty good
representation of the sort of the typical but oversimplified vox populi
opinion on things. I also &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DRMacIver/status/1713814331224170566"&gt;did some
polling on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and I think most of the answers are confusing in
the relevant way. I think that my view is probably relatively typical
among working mathematicians, but not of how we talk about mathematics
to non-mathematicians.&lt;/span&gt;

present axioms philosophically is unhelpful for understanding what’s
going on in mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, let’s fix this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="what-are-axioms"&gt;What are axioms?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Axioms are things that we take to be true, but they are things we
take to be true in the sense that “a bachelor is an unmarried man” or “a
bishop moves any number of vacant squares diagonally”. They are not
taken to be true in the sense that they represent deep truths about the
universe that we have no way to prove but wholeheartedly believe
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is one potential source of axioms of course, as the
universe is one of the things we want to reason about, but it is not
what axioms &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
, they are taken to be true in the
sense that they represent defining properties of the class of thing we
are interested in talking about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For this to make sense, we need to realise that mathematics isn’t
really about proofs, it’s about &lt;em&gt;things&lt;/em&gt;, “mathematical objects”.
Proofs are for discovering properties of mathematical objects. They say:
“Suppose I’ve got some object and it has these properties. What else do
I know about it?”. Those properties are the axioms, but you’re not
“assuming” that the object has those properties in the sense that they
are things that might be false but you’re postulating for now, those
properties define the class of object that you are interested in talking
about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In contrast, most people think of axioms as things that are “self
evidently true” or, slightly more accurately, “assumptions”, but this
immediately invites the question “But what if your assumptions are
wrong?” or “How do you &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; your axioms are true?”
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;These questions are not meaningless or bad necessarily,
but they’re usually asked in the wrong place.&lt;/span&gt;
. With axioms as picking out objects
of interest, these problems go away - you can argue about whether the
objects in question are interesting or whether any examples of them
exist (“exist” is complicated. More on that later), but not whether the
axioms are true.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the easiest places to see how this works is with the
mathematics of games, because there the axioms are just the
&lt;em&gt;constitutive rules&lt;/em&gt; of the game. You can do mathematics around
games of chess (e.g. “From this position, can checkmate be forced in 5
moves?” is implicitly a mathematical sort of question), and in asking
this question you are restricted to the sort of moves that chess allows.
If you were playing with a different rule set, the conclusion might be
different, but that doesn’t mean that the two conclusions are
incompatible, they’re just about different games.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another, more historical, example is the parallel postulate and the
axioms of geometry. Simplified version: Euclid came up with a set of
axioms for geometry, describing how points, lines, and circles worked.
There were a bunch of perfectly sensible axioms, and then there was the
rather awkward &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parallel_postulate"&gt;Parallel
Postulate&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Note: This is all somewhat ahistorical and simplified
for illustrative purposes. Euclid’s account of geometry wasn’t fully
axiomatic, and the version of the parallel postulate stated is not
Euclid’s original and is only equivalent to it given the other axioms.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a plane, given a line and a point not on it, at most one line
parallel to the given line can be drawn through the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;People spent ages trying to prove the parallel postulate from the
other axioms, and then someone pointed out that &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spherical_geometry"&gt;Spherical
Geometry&lt;/a&gt; demonstrated that you couldn’t do this: If you take a
sphere and interpret “line” as meaning “great circle” (a circle on the
surface of the sphere whose centre is the centre of the sphere. e.g the
equator, or a line of longitude, but not in general a line of latitude
because those are “off centre” for the sphere), you get something that
satisfies all the basic axioms of geometry but for which the parallel
postulate is false (because there are no parallel lines, because all
great circles intersect at two points on the sphere).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you think of geometry as trying to derive universal truths of
geometry, this information can be very distressing. How do you know
which axioms to use?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If, on the other hand, you instead think of there being such a thing
as &lt;em&gt;a geometry&lt;/em&gt; then all you’re trying to do is figure out
properties of particular geometries of interest, and you can pick
whichever one you want to work on. Sometimes you might want to work with
a Euclidean geometry, sometimes you might want to work with a spherical
geometry. It’s up to you! They’re both equally valid mathematical
objects for doing geometry on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="what-are-mathematical-objects"&gt;What are mathematical
objects?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If axioms pick out which mathematical objects we are talking about,
we need to follow this by answering a much harder question: What are
mathematical objects?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I need to start with a slightly slippery mathematician’s definition:
Mathematical objects are the things you can do proofs about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This definition is actually quite useful, because it highlights an
important point of this conception of axioms: It’s actually slightly
agnostic to foundational questions like this. As long as there is
something called a mathematical object and you can do proofs about it,
this notion of axiom is useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular, consider two
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Slightly strawman versions of these positions, but I
think morally accurate.&lt;/span&gt;
 conceptions of
mathematical foundations:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mathematics is reasoning about real entities that exist in some
sort of abstract platonic realm of ideal forms (&lt;strong&gt;Mathematical
platonism&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mathematics is a purely formal game of manipulating symbols
representing purely formal entities according to agreed upon rules,
which can be put in correspondence with real entities but do not
intrinsically correspond to things that “exist”. (&lt;strong&gt;Mathematical
formalism&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mathematicians often behave liked platonists but fall back on
formalism as a sort of philosophical justification.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A third competing view that I like is Reuben Hersch’s definition of
mathematical objects as “socio-historical objects”. Things that only
exist because we, as people doing mathematics, agree they exist,
similarly to other things like money, rules, games.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this is mostly right, but I’d like to propose a slight
refinement: Mathematical objects are things that we agree to &lt;em&gt;behave
as if they existed&lt;/em&gt; because doing so allows us to do mathematics,
and mathematics is useful.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think this makes sense of why, regardless of what they believe
about foundations, mathematicians in practice behave more like
platonists: Regardless of whether mathematical objects “actually exist”,
mathematics is done by behaving &lt;em&gt;as if&lt;/em&gt; mathematical objects
exist, and proceeding from that starting point to reason about what they
should be like.
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In this view, mathematics is a ritual practice in the
sense of Seligman et al’s “Ritual and its Consequences”. It is the
creation of a &lt;em&gt;subjunctive world&lt;/em&gt; in which certain rules and
claims are treated as inviolable properties of the ritual space, because
doing so allows the ritual to occur, which is desirable for its
non-ritual consequences. e.g. politeness norms are viewed as a ritual in
this sense, because maintaining them allows for civil interactions which
everyone enjoys. In practice they are not inviolable, but if everyone
treats them as such they are not violated and thus you get to operate in
a world where you can trust them as if they were inviolable.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I sometimes joke that the formalists are right that mathematics is a
game, but it’s not a purely symbolic one, it’s an RPG set in the
Platonic realm. We are reasoning about some world that we agree to
behave as if it existed, contained certain objects, and was subject to
logical reasoning of the sort that we would expect to hold in the real
world.
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;This is a nontrivial constraint on a hypothetical world.
e.g. fairy tales have a logic of their own, but it is not a simple if A
then B sort of logical reasoning you can count on. The realm in which
mathematical objects exist is posited to be one that makes sense.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This still leaves us to ask: What sort of mathematical objects do we
posit exist? Fictional worlds are very different depending on the world
building you’ve done for them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Generally mathematical objects are one of two types:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something we’ve built as an abstracted and generalised version of
something in the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something we’ve built out of other mathematical objects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Often it’s both: When we build mathematical objects, we’re usually
doing them for some purpose, and that purpose is often to represent
something that in some way looks like the real world. This helps us
avoid positing too many “primitive” mathematical objects - the building
blocks of our mathematical world
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn9"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn9" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Which we want to do because every primitive mathematical
object is a sort of leap of faith as to whether the rules actually make
sense.&lt;/span&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The classic example of something which is purely built as an
abstracted and generalised version of something in the physical world is
a natural (counting) number. The numbers 0, 1, 2, … are mathematical
objects that we just assume exist
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn10"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn10" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In fact, in modern (i.e. dating from the early 20th
century) we construct these too out of other mathematical objects - sets
- but you can do the mathematics of numbers without doing the
mathematics of sets, and numbers are in some sense “more basic” to
mathematics.&lt;/span&gt;
 in our mathematical
world, according to the following rules for constructing them:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a number 0.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If there is a number n, there is a next number immediately after
it (n + 1, although we want to do this before we’ve defined addition so
this is usually written S(n), for successor of n).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We then agree that these mathematical objects satisfy what we think
of as the idealised rules of counting numbers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These counting numbers are abstract in the following sense: There is
no way to point to the number four. You can point to four rocks, four
caling birds, four tally marks. You can point to the arabic number 4, or
the roman numeral IV. These all in some sense “represent” the number
four (as does the word “four”), but they are not the mathematical object
four, they are a real object that in some sense has fourness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These counting numbers are also generalised, in that we posit the
existence of mathematical numbers that have no corresponding real world
counted quantity. Why? Well, it follows from the rules we have for
counting numbers (which I haven’t spelled out, but it does I promise)
that if n exists then so does 10n. But that means that 10 exists, 100
exists, 1,000,000 exists… &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(10^{10000000000}\)&lt;/span&gt; also exists, which is
vastly more things to count than there are atoms in the universe. In the
real world, you can’t count that high. In the mathematical world, no
problem at all.
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn11"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn11" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And there are sometimes reasons to, even if you only
care about real world countable quantities! Sometimes you want to prove
a mathematical result and it requires you to e.g. look at all the
subsets of some set of a reasonable size. Although 1,000,000 is a
perfectly reasonable number, &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(2^{1000000}\)&lt;/span&gt; is again more than the atoms
of the universe. From a mathematical point of view, proving results that
use that number are completely legitimate, even if it has no physical
analogue.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another, more concrete, example of a mathematical object that allows
us to avoid concerns about infinity
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn12"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn12" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And concern ourselves with the merely very large.&lt;/span&gt;
 is the mathematical
objects corresponding to &lt;em&gt;game states&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Consider a game of chess, with the pieces on the board somewhere.
Suppose you nudge a piece slightly, keeping it in the same square but
just shifting it slightly to the left. In one sense, you’ve changed the
state of the board - a piece is in a different location. But, from the
point of view of a game of chess, you have not made a change
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn13"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn13" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In tournament rules you may have committed yourself to
moving this piece, but the point remains: If you moved this piece to
that square prior to nudging it, that makes no difference.&lt;/span&gt;
, because all that matters is which
square the piece is in, not exactly where it is.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if you were to take another chess board and set and place
the pieces from that set in the same squares as they were in the
original board, this would represent the same game of chess. This is
true even if one board is physical and the other electronic. You could
even copy the chess board position onto paper by hand - either as a
picture, or as a list of positions in a standard chess notation. These
would all represent the same game of chess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although chess is a game whose state is represented by physical
objects (which might be a physical chess board, might be a computer,
might even be solely in the heads of the participants!), chess is played
as the &lt;em&gt;abstract game state &lt;/em&gt;- all that matters is the chess
position, which is represented by the physical object but not synonymous
with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One important feature of this is that not all physical arrangements
of a chess board have a corresponding abstract chess state. e.g. you
could have a piece halfway between two squares. You could have a board
with no kings. These are not valid chess states, they’re just things you
can do with the physical chess board.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Similarly, you’ve got the rules of chess which describe how abstract
chess states are transformed into each other. Nothing stops you
physically violating these rules - you can pick someone’s king up and
throw it across the room, you can steal their pawn while they’re not
looking, nothing stops you from doing these things, except the fact that
in doing them you are no longer playing chess. The rules of chess exist
precisely in order to enable you to play chess, and violating the rules
means that this is not a game of chess.
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn14"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn14" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Some games do explicitly allow cheating as part of the
game, but that doesn’t change the basic point, it’s just a more
complicated ruleset.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These abstract chess states and the rules for moving between them are
mathematical objects that exist in the same sort of “mathematical realm”
as numbers. You can also do mathematics to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For example, the question “Is a checkmate guaranteed for white from
this position?” is a mathematical question. You are trying to reason
about whether white has a strategy that guarantees that all series of
moves from the current chess position result in a checkmate for
white.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Although this mathematical question nominally answers a question
about real games of chess being played by the players, it differs in
several ways:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t describe anything about the game other than the
abstract states - you don’t know how the players physically move around
the board, their emotional states, etc. None of these are considered
relevant to or part of the mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has the same sort of unboundedness problem that counting
numbers do. This question actually does have a definite answer, but the
definite answer might require considering &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;\(2^{2048}\)&lt;/span&gt; different chess positions to
reach.
&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn15"&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn15" type="checkbox"/&gt;
&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Actually much less than that, because not all of those
chess positions are in fact possible, but even a 100-order of magnitude
reduction makes this an impossibly large number of states.&lt;/span&gt;
 While in theory this is a finite
number with a definite answer, there’s no guarantee we can calculate
it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3 id="detritus"&gt;Detritus&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Editor’s note: This was a section with random cuttings that had been
removed from the text elsewhere because it didn’t fit the flow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the most important features of this explanation is that it
makes much more sense of the social role of axioms. If axioms are
universal truths then they arrive through some sort of deep a priori
knowledge or divine revelation or something, but if axioms just pick out
the objects you’re talking about they arrive in a much more
straightforward way: Someone picks up a mathematical object and goes
“Hey, look at this thing! Interesting, innit?” and then proceeds to try
to describe what’s interesting about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You have to do a bit of fiddling around to figure out which
properties of the object you do and don’t care about, and what a good
set of axioms to represent them are, but that’s just work, it’s not
anything particularly mysterious you just have to come up with a good
design. Once you’ve identified an object, or some objects, of interest,
you can just axiomatise them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This helpfully reduces the question “Where do axioms come from?” to
the much harder question “Where do mathematical objects come from?”,
which in turn first requires us to&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think there are roughly two sources for mathematical objects:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We make them out of other mathematical objects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We abstract them from real things (which may be physical objects,
properties of such objects, processes, etc).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can do the first because (I have no idea how I was intending to
continue this sentence).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="reflections"&gt;Reflections&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I often find that there’s a large body of understanding that lives in
my head and that I think is more sensible than how other people seem to
view it, but when it comes time to try to explain it I find it’s all too
interconnected to be worth the effort of explaining unless there’s some
really clear goal to it. This was one of those times.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’d like a solution to this problem, but I’m not sure there is a
solution other than to accept my own mortality and finite energy
reserves and not worry so much about other people being wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-03-10:13.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-04-10:02.html</id>
    <title>Honesty is kinder than lying</title>
    <updated>2024-01-04T11:26:13+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Honesty is kinder than lying&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-04&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another draft bankruptcy post. This is one of those posts that I
started writing because I was annoyed about something (I forget what, I
don’t think it’s present anywhere in the text), and stopped writing when
I lost steam on that annoyance. I still think it’s important and worth
saying, but I lost the impetus to keep saying it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Advance warning: I am not pulling any punches in this post.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="do-you-want-impostor-syndrome-because-thats-how-you-get-impostor-syndrome."&gt;Do
you want impostor syndrome? Because that’s how you get impostor
syndrome.&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For various reasons I’ve been thinking recently about something I
helped a client with a while ago.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Details slightly altered and kept vague for
confidentiality reasons.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Roughly the scenario they found themselves in was this: Someone new
had joined their staff, and this person wasn’t &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; at their
job, but they were very slow at it, taking much longer to complete basic
tasks than seemed reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More, this person knew it, and was clearly very bothered by it, and
kept apologising for it. My client kept reassuring them that this was
fine and it was normal to take a while to get started. This didn’t seem
to help, and they kept being anxious about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, a couple of months of this had passed and my client now had a
problem: Their staff member was &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; too slow at their job. It
could no longer be written off as just slowness getting up to speed,
they actually weren’t fast enough at the job to keep up with the needed
workload, and weren’t showing any signs of improvement.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m reasonably confident that the problem isn’t that the client’s
expectations were unreasonable. We talked a bit about it and it was a
set of requirements that it was perfectly normal to expect a person to
be able to do, nothing terribly out of the ordinary.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I’m &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; sure about is whether in an alternate history
their subordinate could have been capable of doing the job at that
point. Certainly in this history they weren’t.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Unfortunately I also don’t know if they became so. Due
to a mix of funding changes at the client’s company and me winding down
that part of my business, this was only a month or two before my last
session with that client, so I don’t know how the story ends. It doesn’t
matter for the point I’m making though.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And part of why they weren’t is that my client had, bluntly&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Somewhat more bluntly than I put it at the time,
although I think I was at least clear about what they’d done wrong.&lt;/span&gt; spent the last couple of months
lying to them about their performance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t the client’s fault. It’s what we’re all trained to do.
When someone is expressing anxiety, you reassure them that the thing
they’re anxious about couldn’t possibly happen and everything will be
fine. When someone is expressing guilt about how they fucked up, you
tell them that it’s not their fault and there’s nothing they could have
done. There’s this deep seated cultural assumption that the way to be
kind to people is that you lie to them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I hate this and think it’s a travesty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of honesty, I will admit that I do this sometimes. Much
much less than most people do, I think, but it’s hard not to. There are
a lot of forces pushing you to do it. When I find myself doing it, I try
to learn from that and do better in future.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a similar spirit of honesty, I know that you probably do this too,
and I’m &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/just-disappointed"&gt;disappointed&lt;/a&gt;
in you for doing so. I would like you to do better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason we all lie to each other like this is often framed as
kindness. I don’t think it is. I think it’s a form of cowardice. Honesty
has consequences that we have to own in a way that dishonesty would not.
If we speak the truth, we are responsible for any hurt inflicted, and
might have to face the other’s negative reaction to our words. If we
tell a nice lie we are not responsible when the problem we are lying
about inevitably has consequences.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doing better requires both the courage to face those consequences,
and a sense of responsibility for events that are not our “fault” that
everyone is keen to disavow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The correct way to handle something like my client’s situation is, in
my opinion, to say something along the lines of: Yes, you’re
underperforming compared to what I’d hope for. It’s not a problem yet,
but if it continues it will become one. I’ve got your back in trying to
prevent that. Let’s figure out together what you need to solve this
problem and do our best to get it for you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, taking on a lot of work, and it’s also taking on
a lot of responsibility. Now in the quite likely&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;A sad reality is that many people are in fact not good
enough at the jobs they’ve been hired to do, for reasons that are
outside of anyone’s power to fix, or at least to fix fast enough to be
viable. When this happens it’s important to treat them well, but it’s
also important to not retain them in that role.&lt;/span&gt;
event that their subordinate failed to perform and had to be let go at
the end of their probation period, it would be in part be because they
had failed to help them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Depending on how much capacity is available, that might not be an
option. I was talking to a friend recently about their company’s
situation and he was in a similar position but absolutely didn’t have
the capacity spare to help the person in question learn to perform at
the level he needed (and suspected that they couldn’t or wouldn’t
anyway).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In such a circumstance I honestly think the kindest thing to say to
someone is something along the lines of: Look, this is what we need, and
the fact that you can’t give it is a problem. If you’re willing to take
responsibility for stepping up, we’re happy to give you the space you
need to do that, and can make some changes to support that but cannot
commit a lot of resources. What do you want to do?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This sucks to hear and it sucks to say. This is not going to be an
easy conversation&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And in this particular example and depending on where
you are can run into employment law complications. Not legal advice
etc.&lt;/span&gt;, but it is necessary, and the
results of not having it are worse. Again, this is why I think avoiding
conversations like this is a form of moral cowardice. Not having these
conversations allows you to pretend that the failure is not your
responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="you-shouldnt-lie-to-your-friends"&gt;You shouldn’t lie to your
friends&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I don’t care that much about the employment example right
now. It’s important, but it’s not why this has been on my mind.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was talking to some friends recently about the advice “when you
find yourself beating yourself up over something, imagine you’re talking
to a friend or loved one and ask if you would talk to them that
way”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the objections to this advice raised is that when talking to a
friend or loved one you will tend to lie to them in the ways I’ve been
discussing. You diminish the degree to which the situation is their
fault, you downplay the possibility of bad consequences. This feels fine
to do to a friend, but bad to do to yourself because you can see through
the ruse.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This objection is a commendable level of self honesty&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn6"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn6" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Although I think self honesty of this form is often too
“brutal honesty”.&lt;/span&gt;,
but also reveals how much we let our friends down.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because here’s the thing: Your friends can see through the ruse too.
The thing about having a social norm of lying to people is that
&lt;em&gt;everybody knows you lie to people in this way&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recall the example of my client. One of the problems with lying to
his subordinate is that it didn’t give them the support they needed to
improve. But it &lt;em&gt;also didn’t make them less anxious&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And of course it didn’t. If people are going to tell you that
something isn’t a problem even when it’s a problem, you can’t trust that
reassurance at all, so why would it help?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you want to be able to reassure people that something isn’t a
problem when it’s not a problem, they need to be able to believe that
you would tell them that it’s a problem if it were one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can achieve this belief in one of three ways:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be true.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They can have poor judgement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They can lie to themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That is, when you lie to people, you either fail to help them, or you
make them complicit in the lie, and at some level that’s hard to
maintain, and it’s bad for them and it’s bad for the relationship.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="the-problem-of-brutal-honesty"&gt;The problem of brutal
honesty&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honesty has &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-28-10:26.html"&gt;a
differing thresholds problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I often get accused of being brutally honest. It’s certainly
sometimes true - I think this post is erring on the side of brutal
honesty, partly because I’m fed up and partly because I don’t think a
softer version would land - but I think actually most of the time I’m
&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; brutally honest, I’m just honest in situations where other
people wouldn’t be, and this rounds to brutal honesty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But my primary association with people who self describe as “brutally
honest” is that they tend to care more about the brutal part than the
honest part, and that when you are being “brutally honest” with someone
it tends to be more because you don’t care about their feelings&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn7"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn7" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Or do care about their feelings, in that you want them
to feel bad.&lt;/span&gt; than it is because you care about
telling them the truth.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn8"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn8" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;That doesn’t mean you’re necessarily &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;
telling them the truth, but it does usually mean that you’re telling
them only the bits of the truth that hurt the most.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think brutal honesty has a missing mood. Something along the lines
of “It is regrettable that I must hurt this person but the truth is in
this instance more important than their feelings”. Instead, the attitude
seems to be much more “truth hurts, suck it up”. This is not an attitude
I want to encourage.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="you-probably-shouldnt-lie-to-yourself-either"&gt;You probably
shouldn’t lie to yourself either&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why I’ve been thinking about this recently is that
I was talking about self-help books the other day, and realising that
there’s really one fundamental message that underlies the vast majority
of self help books.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s this: You know that problem you’ve been having? It’s not your
fault. You don’t have to feel bad about having it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes this is a useful message for people to hear, because it
lets them get a bit of emotional distance from the problem that they
need to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And if it helps them achieve that, and they then solve the problem,
(Editor’s note: I apparently stopped writing this post mid sentence
here).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="postscript"&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I should revisit this theme at some point as honesty is
somewhere where my moral intuitions seem to sharply differ from other
people’s, in a way that causes frictions when ~I’m right and they’re
wrong~ we have differing intuitions about how to e.g. answer a
question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do honestly think that my way is better. I’m not blind to its
downsides, and it requires skill to do well&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn9"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn9" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;And sometimes I even have that skill!&lt;/span&gt;,
but I think the downsides of the status quo are much worse, and choosing
them feels like a sort of collective cowardice to me.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-04-10:02.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-05-11:11.html</id>
    <title>Reason as a moral mechanism</title>
    <updated>2024-01-05T11:19:55+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Reason as a moral mechanism&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-05&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another draft bankruptcy post. This ended up being another
overambitious philosophy piece of the sort I haven’t really figured a
time or place to write.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve since learned that these go better in a google doc. Maybe they’d
go better yet if I expanded my notebook site to have an essays section
now that I’ve got sidenotes and full pandoc support for references and
such.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Attention conservation notice: This piece is quite inside baseball. I
think it’s of interest to a general audience in where it ends up, which
is why it’s on the newsletter rather than the &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/"&gt;notebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Editor’s note: lol never mind.&lt;/span&gt;,
but it &lt;em&gt;starts&lt;/em&gt; by arguing about the logical underpinnings of
Kantian ethics. You should not however require much philosophy
background to read it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m currently doing a read through of Velleman’s “Self to Self”. You
can follow along with my increasingly frustrated noises I make as I try
to decode it on &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLxO1bY9tS9Kr1gkHMPa0kaJtIIIKxJgzH"&gt;my
YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; (Editor’s note: I also abandoned this series and
project), but be warned the production quality is approximately zero
these are very much notes I am taking in my reading.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m mostly still stuck on chapter 1, which is his introduction to
Kantian ethics. I find the content a frustrating mix of tantalisingly
close to pointing at something important I’m missing and just wildly
wrong. This post is an attempt to explain some of my frustrations with
it, try to make sense of what it might mean, and reconstruct something
that I think actually works and is pointing roughly in the same
direction, but definitely isn’t what Kant or Velleman mean.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="why-should-i-act-according-to-reasons"&gt;Why should I act
according to reasons?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the core premises of Velleman’s account of Kantian ethics is
that we have a basic obligation to “act according to reasons”. He
justifies this as such:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where we previously asked “Why should I act on my desire?” let us now
ask “Why should I act for reasons?” Shouldn’t this question open up a
route of escape from &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; requirements?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as we ask why we should act for reasons, however, we can hear
something odd in our question. To ask “Why should I?” is to demand a
reason; and so to ask “Why should I act for reasons?” is to demand a
reason for acting for reasons. This demand implicitly concedes the very
authority that it purports to question – namely, the authority of
reasons. Why would we demand a reason if we didn’t envision acting for
it? If we really didn’t feel required to act for reasons, then a reason
for doing so certainly wouldn’t help. So there is something
self-defeating about asking for a reason to act for reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you’re like me, your response to this is something along the lines
of “What? No.” or possibly “What on earth are you talking about?”&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This argument is too clever by half and relies in a fundamental way
on an ambiguity in the term “reason” that, once you resolve, causes the
argument to dissolve into uselessness.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The ambiguity is this: When you ask “Why should I do the thing?” the
answer to this is an &lt;em&gt;explanation&lt;/em&gt; of why you should do the
thing&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; which may or may not itself be present prior to your
doing the thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An answer to the question “Why should I act according to reasons?” is
not necessarily providing the sort of reason that compels action,
because the answer is intrinsically descriptive.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The core problem in all of this is that it is attempting to weasel
out of the normative content of a “should” resting on you actually
caring about something by trying to figure something that you logically
must care about. But you can just not do that - I don’t need a logical
argument to care about not being hurt for example, I can do things to
avoid pain without needing a compelling logical justification for this.
“Because if you don’t the reason fairy will appear and hit you with a
big stick” is a &lt;em&gt;perfectly logically consistent&lt;/em&gt; answer to “Why
should I act according to reasons?” that does not have any
circularity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It grounds out the authority of reasons in the authority of pain, but
that’s fine if you’re willing to accept an ethics for human beings who
don’t like pain rather than an ethics for perfectly spherical ethicists
in a vacuum. It is only circular if you think “Why should I act to
minimise pain?” roots the authority of pain in the authority of reasons,
but that’s not what that question means - it is asking for an
explanation, not delegating authority, because the avoidance of pain
already has authority over you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rest of the chapter tacitly acknowledges all of this by basically
trying to work through a set of reasons for acting for reasons, it just
can’t say out loud because it’s built on this premise that reasons are
an inescapable&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;In general the idea of escapability of authority in
Velleman’s account of Kantian ethics seems (Editor’s note: What does it
seem?? I apparently left this sentence hanging)&lt;/span&gt; source of authority.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a shame, because I think the actual source of the authority
of reasons is much more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="what-does-any-of-this-even-mean"&gt;What does any of this even
mean?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think Velleman considers the meaning of “act according to reasons”
self-explanatory, but I think it’s not just not self-explanatory but
borders on meaningless given the ambiguity of the word “reasons”. If a
“reason” is a thing that causes something, then the obligation is
tautologically satisfied - all your actions are caused by something. If
a “reason” is a verbal explanation of why things happened as they did,
then it will generally come after the fact rather than prior to it -
almost everything we do well, we do without a significant amount of
verbal reasoning prior to it.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn3"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn3" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;For an elaboration on this last point, I recommend “The
Enigma of Reason” by Dan Sperber and Hugo Mercier, and “Sources of
Power” by Gary Klein&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Throughout, I will use “&lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt;” to mean something
like “verbal causal explanation” - i.e. something you would say in
answer to a “Why?” question. I will use &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt; to
refer to something like… the state of the world that lead to a
particular outcome, a set of conditions which would lead to the same
outcome reliably. A &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; is a &lt;em&gt;necessarily
incomplete&lt;/em&gt; description of the &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn4"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn4" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I’m using bold here to indicate that I intend these to
be precise terms which are compatible with but more specific than
colloquial meanings. When I use a bolded term without bolding I will
usually be referring to someone else using the colloquial word. Or I
forgot.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly, &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; are not normally present in our
mind at the point of action (they can be, but not necessarily). So when
you are acting “according” to a &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt;, in that the
reason accurately describes the &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt;, that
reason is not itself &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of the &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt;.
This is what I mean by the argument resting on an ambiguity: If you are
asking for a &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; to act in accordance with
&lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;, the fact that you can answer the question does
not create a circularity because your answer need not be part of the
&lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt; for acting for reasons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One easy way to see this is that often the &lt;strong&gt;actual
cause&lt;/strong&gt; exists prior to it being possible to give an explanation
for it. This is especially true for causes that are in some sense
physical. e.g. if you ask me why I’m not working my best today and I
have a low grade virus that is sapping my energy, that is part of the
&lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt; regardless of whether I know I have a
virus, or even have the concept of virus. Both “I have a virus” and “I
don’t know, I’m just not feeling it today” count as
&lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;. I could even answer “I’m lazy”, which would
arguably count as an incorrect &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, there is often far more &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; than
you are aware of in the moment, so you &lt;em&gt;could not&lt;/em&gt; have thought
of all the reasons in the time you had prior to action. Suppose you see
someone who has injured themself. You help them get to a safe place, and
then call the emergency services. Why did you do this? Because they were
hurt. Why is “because they were hurt” a sufficient
&lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt;? Because it’s morally the right thing to do. Why
must you do the morally right thing? Because I want to, and will feel
guilty if I don’t. Why would you feel guilty if you didn’t? Because I
was raised proper… etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a long chain of verbal &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; you can give
for this and &lt;em&gt;almost none of them went through your head when you
helped&lt;/em&gt;. You might have verbalised something like “Oh they’re
injured, I should help them”. Maybe you considered a couple arguments
and counter-arguments. But there was not a long chain of verbal
reasoning for why you should help them, the helping comes with an
immediacy of its own as the thing for you to do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt; is thus not the reasons you give
for it, because those reasons were not present at the point of action.
The &lt;strong&gt;actual cause&lt;/strong&gt; is necessarily something like “because
I am the kind of person who in these kinds of circumstances performs
these kinds of actions”, with the &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; attempting to
define some boundaries on all of those “kind of”s.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This should, I think, still be considered acting &lt;em&gt;according&lt;/em&gt;
to &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;, in that “I helped them because they were
hurt” is a &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; that accurately describes your
actions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is, however, now a very weak requirement. All it demands is that
your actions be in some way comprehensible. “I helped him because his
shirt was yellow”, or “I helped him because I felt like it” are both
also potential &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;. This weakness is not a failing
of the Kantian account, which is in many ways all about deciding what
counts as a good &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; (although I think it is
incorrect in how it goes about doing this), it’s just important to point
out because we’re also going to need to strengthen it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two directions that I think are reasonable to strengthen it are as
follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You should be able to provide &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; for your
actions to peers (that it’s to peers will be significant later) who want
them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; should remain relatively stable,
in the sense that if they would apply in future then they should contain
to describe your actions, or you should be able to provide a
&lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; why they don’t.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What does “should” mean here? i.e. why should you act according to
&lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; in this sense? Kant and Velleman want this to
be through logical necessity, but I don’t think that’s valid, and I
think the weaker form that I am aiming at here is in many ways better.
It allows for more empirically accurate descriptions of how ethics
works, and in many cases by being weaker allows for stronger norms.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, my answer is that you should because life will go better for
you if you do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="norming-and-consequences"&gt;Norming and consequences&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things we do in our groups of peers is we create norms of
behaviour. What is, and isn’t, an acceptable to behave. We do this by
imposing consequences for that behaviour - we might chastise each other
for bad behaviour, withdraw future opportunities, etc. e.g. you might
not get a promotion if you behave badly at work, or you might just get
reprimanded the first time, in an extreme case you might get fired.
Similarly if you behave like a dick at a party I invited you to, you’re
not going to get invited back. Extreme cases might also include e.g.
physical violence, but most norming tends to be at least slightly more
subtle than this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Evaluating reasons is part of how we do this. When someone does
something, especially something we disapprove of, we will often ask why
they did it, and this factors in to our evaluation of their
behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;e.g. suppose we’re going to the movies together. I’m waiting for you
at the cinema and you never show, even by the time the movie was
supposed to have &lt;em&gt;ended&lt;/em&gt; let alone started. You’ve not sent me a
text, you’re not responding to mine. By default, I’m likely to be pretty
pissed off at you.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn5"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn5" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;There’s likely some cultural variation in this,
especially if you’re merely late - I’m a stickler for punctuality, but
know people from places where turning up an hour late is considered
completely normal. Regardless though, I’m not making a universal claim
that it is &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; to be pissed off about this, I’m saying that I
would be. Feel free to substitute your own example of someone letting
you down.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is likely that when we finally make contact, my first question is
going to be some variant on “What happened?” - I expect you to provide a
&lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; for the fact that you didn’t show when we’d
previously agreed to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Consider how I might respond differently to the following three
answers:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“I don’t know, no reason really, I just didn’t feel like it.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“I got the day wrong, was caught up in work, and didn’t hear the
notification and completely forgot.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“I was on my way here and there was someone in a terrible accident
and I had to stop and help and keep them conscious while waiting for the
ambulance.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These would change my response significantly. (1) would probably make
me &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; angry at you. (2) would probably reduce my anger a bit,
with how sorry you seemed about it and how many times you’d made this
sort of error error mattering more than the actual
&lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt;. (3) on the other hand my anger would probably
instantly evaporate, because I would agree that under these
circumstances that was completely the right thing to do. Indeed, if
instead you’d turned up and told me that there was such an accident but
you didn’t stop to help because it would make you late to the cinema,
I’d probably be angry at you for an entire different reason - of course
you shouldn’t prioritise going to the movies with me over helping
someone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Part of this judgement is that we now have more context for the
action, and we can now ask not just how we feel about this particular
outcome, but how we feel about the process that lead to it. i.e. if
similar circumstances were to occur again, and you were to behave in the
same way in them, how would I feel about that?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a very lightened version of Kant’s categorical imperative.
Instead of asking whether you are acting according to
&lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; that constitute &lt;em&gt;universal&lt;/em&gt; law, we are
asking wether in our particular relational context your
&lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt; are ones I would consider acceptable if they
consistently described your behaviour. Your behaviour is judged not
based on its consequences, but on what the &lt;em&gt;generalisation&lt;/em&gt; of it
(as described by your provided &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;) looks like. By
requesting &lt;strong&gt;reasons&lt;/strong&gt;, we can judge you (positively as
well as negatively) not just by your one-off actions but by &lt;em&gt;how you
tend to behave -&lt;/em&gt; i.e. what sort of person you are.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="trusting-our-peers"&gt;Trusting our peers&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, I can only judge what sort of person you are based on your
reasons for action if the &lt;strong&gt;reason&lt;/strong&gt; you provide is one
that you are likely to act in accord with in future.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am a big fan of C. Thi Nguyen’s paper “Trust as an unquestioning
attitude”. My light generalisation of it is that you
&lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; that X to the degree that you do not really have
to entertain the possibility of not X. e.g. you &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt;
that the sun will come up tomorrow, because even if you think about
whether or not it will the possibility that it will not seems neither
plausible nor emotionally relevant. You &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; that your
partner is not secretly a serial killer because if you think about the
possibility it doesn’t seem remotely plausible. You also
&lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; to a lesser extent that your long-term business
partner isn’t going to betray you, your friends don’t secretly hate you,
etc. - it’s not that there is zero concern here, and you may worry about
it a bit, but it’s not a major part of your day to day experience.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Importantly, you &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; that something will or won’t
happen. You might &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; totally that someone won’t
betray you, but that doesn’t necessarily mean that you
&lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; them to fly a plane.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can still &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; someone in a more generalised
sense, in that the better you know them the more you
&lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; about them. When I first meet someone I can’t
&lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; that they won’t be a dick to me, or that they’re
reliable, or that they are fun to be around, but as I get to know them
better I learn the ways in which I can &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; them (and
the ways I cannot).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3 id="afterword"&gt;Afterword&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I actually still think that there’s something important here and I’d
like to try to revisit it at some point, but I think this kind of
dissecting of someone else’s arguments isn’t really for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In particular the role of trust and reason in constituting our moral
behaviour is something that I’ve been thinking about since and would
like to try to articulate more at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-05-11:11.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-06-07:04.html</id>
    <title>Disingenuous Advice</title>
    <updated>2024-01-06T08:31:48+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">

&lt;p class="subtitle"&gt;Disingenuous Advice&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;dl class="metadata"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Published&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd class="post-date"&gt;2024-01-06&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m a big fan of giving advice. You should give more advice. &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2021-07-17-14:20.html"&gt;Appropriately&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/p/how-to-give-good-advice"&gt;effectively&lt;/a&gt;,
but helping people is good and advice, done well, is one of the easiest
ways to help people.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But a thing I’ve been noticing for a while is that a lot of advice
isn’t really designed to help people. It’s designed to discharge your
responsibility, real or imagined, for helping them, in a way that makes
having the problem their problem rather than yours.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The characteristic features of this sort of disingenuous advice
are:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s not exactly &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; advice. It’s important that it could,
in theory, solve the problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It tends to be quite one-size-fits-all. It shows very little
engagement with the actual problem - if you were going to put in enough
effort to tailor your advice, you’d probably make at least some effort
to give reasonable advice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It tends to be quite simple, so as to make it seem easy. It’s the
sort of thing that you could very naturally use the word “just” in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It seems to encourage closing off further conversation until you’ve
tried to follow the advice. Reasons why the advice won’t work sound like
excuses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is, in fact, very hard to follow this advice and even following
the advice isn’t guaranteed to work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The prompt for me to start noticing this pattern is how often “go to
therapy” is this. Therapy is a perfectly valuable tool that, if you can
afford it, can help with many categories of emotional problems. It also
tends to be suggested very blindly, for large categories of problems
that it’s not especially suited for, and to people who are probably not
well set up to benefit from it (e.g. because they can’t afford it, or
because the real problem is that their life sucks in very tangible ways
and their negative emotions mostly stem from that). But by suggesting
going to therapy you make it very clear that their problems aren’t
yours, you’ve suggested a solution now, they should go make it a
therapist’s problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“Learn to code” as a response to career problems is another common
one. It’s not necessarily bad advice - software is a pretty good career
option for some people. But it’s not a catch all solution to career
problems - not everyone is actually well suited to work in software,
retraining is hard, getting your first software job is hard, and there
may be many better lateral transfers for most people that actually get
to use their current experience.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn1"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn1" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;Also not all jobs can be software jobs you do actually
have to move atoms as well as bits.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another example that came up on discord recently was students having
to ask permission to go to the bathroom in class, and how bad this is
(especially given that it can be refused). The advice “you should have
gone to the bathroom between classes” absolves your responsibility to
them by making it the student’s fault for their lack of forethought.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of these very effectively discharge your responsibility without
being in any way helpful. They are, at best, &lt;a href="https://drmaciver.substack.com/i/39151933/checklist-advice"&gt;checklist
advice&lt;/a&gt;, without any suggestion that you’re willing to do the rest of
the checklist or, heaven forbid, actually offer real advice once the
checklist is completed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, often it’s perfectly reasonable not to want their problem to be
yours. If it’s some stranger on the internet asking you to feel bad for
them and care about their problems then… I don’t know, I probably think
&lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2022-01-23-13:27.html"&gt;you
should feel bad for them&lt;/a&gt;. Certainly it’s not fard, but it might be
mustahabb.&lt;label class="margin-toggle sidenote-number" for="fn2"&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input class="margin-toggle" id="fn2" type="checkbox"/&gt;&lt;span class="sidenote"&gt;I got the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fard"&gt;Islamic tiers of moral
obligation&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="/images/islamic-moral-tiers.webp"&gt;some
random Tumblr post that no longer seems to exist on the internet&lt;/a&gt; but
it’s very useful and somewhat better grain than most of the equivalent
English words. The point I’m making here is that this is a morally good
act that you are not required to do.&lt;/span&gt; But this is hard, and most people
don’t want to do it. What they do want, however, is to feel good about
themselves, so giving a plausible appearance of caring is helpful. Or,
even better, being able to credibly suggest that in fact the speaker is
bad for having this problem and it’s their fault for not having solved
it already, thus not only discharging your obligations but making it
clear that you didn’t have any obligations to discharge in the first
place.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is particularly bad behaviour when you’re not in the “strangers
on the internet” scenario and it’s someone who you do have some sort of
responsibility to - a personal relationship, one of your reports at
work, a student of yours, etc. There it is not just a disavowal of
responsibility that you don’t want to have, it’s a refusal to accept the
responsibility that you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even when you don’t have any responsibility to the person, I do think
it is your responsibility not to give this sort of disingenuous advice.
As well as being &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-04-10:02.html"&gt;dishonest&lt;/a&gt;,
the sheer ubiquity of this behaviour is a failure of &lt;a href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-07-14:34.html"&gt;collective
responsibility&lt;/a&gt;, and while you might have no individual
responsibility to the advice recipient, I do think you have an
individual responsibility not to make these collective problems
worse.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2024-01-06-07:04.html" rel="alternate"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
